import{_ as g,o as i,c as o,a as n,m as h,t as l,C as y,M as b,U as c,F as w,p,e as f,f as j,q as v}from"./chunks/framework.B1z0IdBH.js";const q={name:"PoemCard",props:{poem:{type:Object,required:!0}}},A={class:"poem-container"},z={class:"review"},N={class:"review-title"},x={class:"review-content"};function T(e,a,s,m,t,u){return i(),o("div",A,[n("div",z,[n("div",N,[a[0]||(a[0]=n("span",{class:"icon"},"question:",-1)),h(l(s.poem.question),1)]),a[2]||(a[2]=n("div",{class:"divider"},null,-1)),n("p",x,[a[1]||(a[1]=n("span",{class:"icon"},"answer:",-1)),h(l(s.poem.answer),1)])])])}const B=g(q,[["render",T],["__scopeId","data-v-0cc2b795"]]),M=JSON.parse(`[{"question":"请回答这个问题：地球上最大的湖泊是哪個？","answer":"答案：裏海 (Caspian Sea)，位於歐洲和亞洲之間。"},{"question":"LIBIA","answer":"Libya is a country located in North Africa. It is bordered by the Mediterranean Sea to the north, Egypt to the east, Sudan to the southeast, Chad and Niger to the south, and Algeria and Tunisia to the west.The capital of Libya is Tripoli, which is also the largest city in the country. Other major cities include Benghazi, Misrata, and Sabha. Libya is the fourth-largest country in Africa by land area, and the 16th-largest country in the world. The country is home to a variety of landscapes, including the Sahara Desert, the Mediterranean coast, and the Jebel Nafusa mountains."},{"question":"Византия империясынын борбору болуп турганда Түркиядагы азыркы Стамбул кандай аталды?","answer":"Азыркы Стамбул ал убактарда Константинополь деп аталды."},{"question":"Kí ni dídi ọ̀be ìfárí mọ́ òkú l'ọ́wọ́ sínú sàréè tọ́ka sí?","answer":"Òkú ríró ni."},{"question":"ਕੁੜੀ ਨੇ ਮੁੰਡੇ ’ਤੇ ਪਾਣੀ ਦਾ ਗੁਬਾਰਾ ਸੁੱਟਿਆ। | ਨਤੀਜੇ ਵਜੋਂ ਕੀ ਹੋਇਆ? ਚੋਣ 1 : ਮੁੰਡੇ ਦੇ ਥਪਾਕ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਵੱਜਾ। ਚੋਣ 2 : ਮੁੰਡਾ ਭਿੱਜ ਗਿਆ। ","answer":"ਚੋਣ 2 : ਮੁੰਡਾ ਭਿੱਜ ਗਿਆ।"},{"question":"క్రింద ఇచ్చిన పద్యానికి ప్రతిపదార్ధం మరియు తాత్పర్యం ఇవ్వండి:ఉ|| ఆ సమయంబునందు దివిజాపగ వేగము దుస్సహంబుగాఁజేసి మహాఘనధ్వనివిజి న్నిజనిస్వనముల్ జగత్రయత్రాసకరంబులై మొరయ దారుణలీల హిమాచలాభమైభాసీలు శంభుమస్తకముపైఁ బడియెం గడు నద్భుతంబుగాన్.","answer":"ప్రతిపదార్థం :ఆ సమయంబునందు = ఆ సమయంలోదివిజ + ఆపగ = దేవలోకంలో ప్రవహించే నదిదుస్సహంబుగా = సహింప రానివేగము = వేగంతోమహాఘనధ్వని = పెద్ద శబ్దంజేసి = చేసివిజిన్ + నిజ = గెలవాలనే కోరికతోనిస్వనముల్ = మ్రోతజగత్రయ = మూడు లోకాలకుత్రాసకరంబులై = భయం కలిగించేవిగామొరయు = మోగగాదారుణలీల = భయంకరముగాహిమాచలాభమై సిలు = హిమాలయ పర్వతము లాగభాసిలు = ప్రకాశిస్తున్నశంభు = శంకరునిమస్తకము పైఁ = తలపైకడున్ అద్భుతంబుగాన్ = మిక్కిలి అద్భుతముగాబడియెన్ = పడిందితాత్పర్యం : ఆ సమయంలో దేవలోకంలో ప్రవహించే గంగా నది సహింపరాని వేగంతో, గెలవాలనే కోరికతో, పెద్ద శబ్దం చేస్తూ, మూడులోకాలకు భయాన్ని కలిగించే విధంగా మ్రోగుతూ హిమాలయ పర్వతంలాగా ప్రకాశిస్తున్న శివుని తలపై మిక్కిలి అద్భుతంగా పడింది."},{"question":"Sheeg magaca saddexan ee halgame Xalane, meesha uu ku geeriyooday iyo            sanadkii  uu geeriyooday? ","answer":" Waxaa hidisay Axmed Shire Jaamac.Sheeg magacyada laba dawladood oo ku yaal qaaradda Afrika colaadna ay u          dhaxeysay, hase yeeshee dawladdii kacaanku ay heshiis dhex dhigtay? "},{"question":"Dee ekpere Ekele Marịa","answer":"Nke a bụ ederede ekpere Ekele Marịa:Ekene Marịa, ị jupụtara na grasịa,Oseburụwa nọnyere gị. Ị dị ngọzị n'etiti   ikporo nile, Ọ dịkwazị ngọzị bụ nwa afọ gị bụ Jesu. Marịa dị asọ, nne nke Chukwu, rịọbara anyị bụ ndị njọ arịrịọ, kịta ma n'ọnwụ anyị. Amen."},{"question":"Грузиндер өз өлкөсүн эмне деп аташат?","answer":"Грузиндер өз өлкөсүн - Сакартвело деп аташат."},{"question":"Wax iga Sheeg Dhiiri gelin ?","answer":"Haddii aad raadinayso qofkii noloshaada beddeli lahaa, eeg muraayadda hortaada!"},{"question":"క్రింద ఇచ్చిన కాంటెక్స్ట్ ప్రకారం ౩౩౩ హెక్టార్ల సమాధానం కలిగిన ప్రశ్నని ఇవ్వండి. అగరమంగళం అన్నది చిత్తూరు జిల్లాకు చెందిన గంగాదర నెల్లూరు మండలం   లోని గ్రామం, ఇది 2011 జనగణన ప్రకారం 432 ఇళ్లతో మొత్తం 1772 జనాభాతో 333 హెక్టార్లలో విస్తరించి ఉంది. సమీప పట్టణమైన చిత్తూరు కి 15 కి.మీ. దూరంలో ఉంది. గ్రామంలో మగవారి సంఖ్య 871, ఆడవారి సంఖ్య 901గా ఉంది. షెడ్యూల్డ్ కులాల సంఖ్య 672 కాగా షెడ్యూల్డ్ తెగల సంఖ్య 0. గ్రామం యొక్క జనగణన లొకేషన్ కోడ్ 596670[1].","answer":"అగరమంగళం గ్రామ విస్తీర్ణం ఎంత ?"},{"question":"Question: గార్లదిన్నె మండలం లో ఎన్ని గ్రామాలు ఉన్నాయి?Answer the question with Yes or No. If it is not possible then answer None.Hint: గార్లదిన్నె, ఆంధ్ర ప్రదేశ్ రాష్ట్రములోని అనంతపురం జిల్లా, గార్లదిన్నె మండలం లోని గ్రామం, మండల కేంద్రం.. పిన్ కోడ్ నం. 515731.ఇది సమీప పట్టణమైన అనంతపురం నుండి 18 కి. మీ. దూరంలో ఉంది. 2011 భారత జనగణన గణాంకాల ప్రకారం ఈ గ్రామం 1904 ఇళ్లతో, 7766 జనాభాతో 2250 హెక్టార్లలో విస్తరించి ఉంది. గ్రామంలో మగవారి సంఖ్య 3947, ఆడవారి సంఖ్య 3819. షెడ్యూల్డ్ కులాల సంఖ్య 865 కాగా షెడ్యూల్డ్ తెగల సంఖ్య 237. గ్రామం యొక్క జనగణన లొకేషన్ కోడ్ 594993[1].పిన్ కోడ్: 515731.విద్యా సౌకర్యాలుగ్రామంలో రెండుప్రైవేటు బాలబడులు ఉన్నాయి. ప్రభుత్వ ప్రాథమిక పాఠశాలలు ఐదు, ప్రైవేటు ప్రాథమిక పాఠశాలలు రెండు, ప్రభుత్వ ప్రాథమికోన్నత పాఠశాల ఒకటి , ప్రభుత్వ మాధ్యమిక పాఠశాల ఒకటి ఉన్నాయి. ఒక ప్రభుత్వ జూనియర్ కళాశాల ఉంది. ఒక ప్రైవేటు వృత్తి విద్యా శిక్షణ పాఠశాల ఉంది. ఇంజనీరింగ్ కళాశాల లోలూరు లోనూ ఉన్నాయి. సమీప వైద్య కళాశాల, మేనేజిమెంటు కళాశాల, పాలీటెక్నిక్ , సమీప అనియత విద్యా కేంద్రం, దివ్యాంగుల ప్రత్యేక పాఠశాల, సమీప ప్రభుత్వ ఆర్ట్స్ / సైన్స్ డిగ్రీ కళాశాల,  అనంతపురం లో ఉన్నాయి.వైద్య సౌకర్యంప్రభుత్వ వైద్య సౌకర్యంగార్లదిన్నెలో ఉన్న ఒకప్రాథమిక ఆరోగ్య కేంద్రంలో ఒక డాక్టరు, 10 మంది పారామెడికల్ సిబ్బందీ ఉన్నారు. ఒక ప్రాథమిక ఆరోగ్య ఉప కేంద్రంలో డాక్టర్లు లేరు. ఇద్దరు పారామెడికల్ సిబ్బంది ఉన్నారు. ఒక పశు వైద్యశాలలో ఒక డాక్టరు, ఇద్దరు పారామెడికల్ సిబ్బందీ ఉన్నారు. ఒక సంచార వైద్య శాలలో డాక్టర్లు లేరు. ముగ్గురు పారామెడికల్ సిబ్బంది ఉన్నారు. ఒక కుటుంబ సంక్షేమ కేంద్రంలో ఇద్దరు డాక్టర్లు , ముగ్గురు పారామెడికల్ సిబ్బందీ ఉన్నారు. సమీప సామాజిక ఆరోగ్య కేంద్రం, మాతా శిశు సంరక్షణ కేంద్రం, టి. బి వైద్యశాల గ్రామం నుండి 10 కి.మీ. కంటే ఎక్కువ దూరంలో ఉన్నాయి. అలోపతి ఆసుపత్రి, ప్రత్యామ్నాయ ఔషధ ఆసుపత్రి, డిస్పెన్సరీ గ్రామం నుండి 10 కి.మీ. కంటే ఎక్కువ దూరంలో ఉన్నాయి.ప్రైవేటు వైద్య సౌకర్యంగ్రామంలో 7 ప్రైవేటు వైద్య సౌకర్యాలున్నాయి. ఎమ్బీబీయెస్ కాకుండా ఇతర డిగ్రీలు చదివిన డాక్టర్లు ఆరుగురు, డిగ్రీ లేని డాక్టరు ఒకరు ఉన్నారు. ఆరు మందుల దుకాణాలు ఉన్నాయి.తాగు నీరుగ్రామంలో కుళాయిల ద్వారా శుద్ధి చేయని నీరు సరఫరా అవుతోంది. బోరుబావుల ద్వారా కూడా ఏడాది పొడుగునా నీరు అందుతుంది.పారిశుధ్యంమురుగునీరు బహిరంగ కాలువల ద్వారా . మురుగునీరు బహిరంగంగా, కచ్చా కాలువల ద్వారా... ప్రవహిస్తుంది","answer":"None"},{"question":"అసలు చిట్టా అంటే ఏమిటి?","answer":"సహాయక చిట్టాలలో రాయడానికి వీలులేని వ్యవహారములు ఏవైతే ఉన్నాయో వాటిని అసలు చిట్టాలో వ్రాస్తారు. ఉదా: అరువుపై యంత్రాన్ని కొనుగోలు చేస్తే దీనిని కొనుగోలు చిట్టాలో రాసే వీలులేదు. ఇది అరువు వ్యవహారం అయినా సరుకు కాదు. కాబట్టి దీనిని అసలు చిట్టాలో వ్రాస్తారు."},{"question":"inona ilay teny malaza fampiasa miaraka amin'ny angano?","answer":"arira ilay teny malaza fampiasa amin'ny angano"},{"question":"Кантип ийгиликке жетсе болот?","answer":"Мээнеткеч адам мүмкүнчүлүктөрдү, маселени чечүүнүн жол жобосун издейт. Ал эми жалкоо адам шылтоо жана улам тоскоолдуктарды таба баштайт.Буга мисал катары акча каражатынын тартыштыгын алалы. Мээнеткеч адам акча табуунун жол жобосун издештирип, билим алат. Тапкан акчасын туура колдонууну ойлонот. Жалкоо адам бул өлкөдө акча табууга мүмкүн эместигинин себептерин таап чыгат."},{"question":"Hãy chọn đáp án đúng cho câu hỏi sau:Điểm cực Bắc của Việt Nam nằm tỉnh nào?a. Hà Giangb. Lào Caic. Cao Bằng","answer":"đáp án là Hà GiangHà Giang là một tỉnh thuộc vùng Đông Bắc, rộng hơn 7.884 km2. Phía Đông giáp Cao Bằng, phía Tây giáp tỉnh Yên Bái và Lào Cai, phía Nam giáp tỉnh Tuyên Quang, phía Bắc giáp Trung Quốc. Nơi rộng nhất của Hà Giang từ Tây sang Đông dài 115 km, từ Bắc xuống Nam dài 137 km.Điểm cực Bắc của Hà Giang cũng là điểm cực Bắc của Việt Nam nằm tại xã Lũng Cú, huyện Đồng Văn. Cột cờ Lũng Cú nằm ở đỉnh Lũng Cú hay còn gọi là đỉnh núi Rồng (Long Sơn) với độ cao khoảng 1.470 m so với mực nước biển. Đây là điểm du lịch được nhiều yêu thích.Với nhiều dân tộc cùng sinh sống trong quá trình lịch sử lâu dài, Hà Giang có sự đa dạng về bản sắc văn hóa dân tộc thiểu số, thể hiện qua ẩm thực, trang phục, lễ hội, tập quán."},{"question":"ጥያቄ፦ በ2022 ዓ.ም ከፍተኛ ደመወዝ የተከፈለለት አትሌት ማን ነበር","answer":"መልስ፦ ሊዮኔል ሜሲ"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai anjing tiada bercawat ekor\\"?","answer":"Maksudnya adalah hina dan tidak berguna."},{"question":"ചോദ്യം: കേരളത്തിൽ നിന്നുള്ള ഇന്ത്യയുടെ ആദ്യ രാഷ്ട്രപതി ആരായിരുന്നു? ഉത്തരം:","answer":"കെ.ആർ. നാരായണൻ (4 ഫെബ്രുവരി 1921 - 9 നവംബർ 2005) ഇന്ത്യയുടെ പത്താമത്തെ രാഷ്ട്രപതിയായിരുന്നു. കേരളത്തിൽ നിന്നുള്ള ആദ്യത്തെ ഇന്ത്യൻ പ്രസിഡന്റുമായിരുന്നു അദ്ദേഹം."},{"question":"السؤال: متى استلمت لجنة الاتحاد والترقي الحكم ؟","answer":"الإجابة: بعد تحويل السلطنة إلى ملكية دستورية وتقليص سلطات السلطان آنذاك عبد الحميد الثاني في انقلاب 27 أبريل 1909."},{"question":"\\"ताजमहल कहाँ स्थित है? ताजमहल एक __________ का प्रसिद्ध स्मारक है, जिसे मुग़ल सम्राट शाहजहाँ ने अपनी पत्नी मुमताज़ महल की __________ के रूप में बनवाया था।\\"","answer":"ताजमहल कहाँ स्थित है? ताजमहल एक आगरा का प्रसिद्ध स्मारक है, जिसे मुग़ल सम्राट शाहजहाँ ने अपनी पत्नी मुमताज़ महल की याद में बनवाया था।"},{"question":"Ọwọ tẹ awọn gende meji to feẹ ji ọmọ gbe ni Supare Akoko","answer":"Diẹ lo ku ki wọn lu awọn gende meji kan pa lọsan-an ọjọ Aiku, Sannde, ọsẹ yii, niluu Supare Akoko, nijọba ibilẹ Guusu Iwọ-Oorun Akoko, lẹyin tọwọ tẹ wọn níbi ti wọn n gbiyanju ati ji ọmọ ọlọmọ gbe.ALAROYE gbọ pe ṣe lawọn afurasi ajọmọgbe mejeeji dibọn bii awọn to maa n ṣa aloku irin lagboole kan ti wọn n pe ni Ajakaye Sadiku Muraina, ni Supare.Obinrin kan lati agboole ọhun lo deede fariwo ta, to si ke sawọn eeyan nigba to ri awọn afurasi naa lasiko ti wọn ku giri wọle wọn, ti wọn si n gbiyanju ati ji ọmọ rẹ gbe sinu apo nla kan ti wọn fa lọwọ.Kiakia lawọn araalu ti su bo wọn, ti wọn si n lu wọn lalubami ki wọn too tun fa wọn le ọlọpaa ilu Supare lọwọ."},{"question":"Gudo hono inonzichii","answer":"horomba"},{"question":"Đoạn văn sau đang nói về vấn đề gì? Từng là hộ nghèo ở địa phương, \\"nuôi gì cũng lỗ\\" nhưng nhiều năm nay ông Mai Lam Phương (60 tuổi, ngụ tại thị trấn Cái Nước, huyện Cái Nước, Cà Mau) khiến ngành nông nghiệp Việt Nam bất ngờ với mô hình trồng \\"thanh long ôm gốc mắm\\" cực kỳ sáng tạo. Ông Phương cho biết, trước đây ông nuôi tôm nhưng sau nhiều năm sản xuất không hiệu quả, ông chuyển sang trồng mãng cầu, nuôi gà ta, gà sao... nhưng cũng không mang lại thu nhập. Trong một lần tình cờ bắt gặp cây thanh long sống ở vùng nước mặn cho trái ông đã nảy sinh ý tưởng trồng thanh long trên chính bờ ao tôm của gia đình. Khoảng năm 2012, ông Phương bắt tay vào thực hiện mô hình, trong đó, thanh long giống được ông đem về từ quê vợ ở Bình Thuận. Do không đủ kinh phí để đặt trụ nên ông buộc thanh long vào các cây tạp trong ao tôm như cây mắm, cây đước... Thanh long có giá thể bám vào nên phát triển rất nhanh. Đến năm 2014, ông đã sở hữu 400 gốc thanh long. \\"Ai cũng tưởng trồng thanh long ở nước mặn thì trái sẽ nhỏ, vị mặn chát... nhưng hoàn toàn ngược lại, thanh long tôi trồng ngọt hơn các vùng khác, vỏ mỏng, tai ít, hạt thưa. Đặc biệt, trái thanh long có mùi thơm của nhãn đọng lại cổ họng nên bán được giá rất cao, từ 15.000 đến 45.000 đồng/kg\\", ông Phương cho hay. Nhận thấy diện tích giữa ao tôm còn trống, lão nông Cà Mau tiếp tục trồng cây mắm, đợi cây lớn thì cho thanh long \\"nương tựa\\". Từ đó, mô hình \\"thanh long ôm gốc mắm\\" ra đời. Ban đầu, ông Phương ươm giống thanh long trong những chậu nhỏ, sau đó mang treo vào gốc cây mắm dưới ao tôm. Cây thanh long ôm gốc mắm ngay dưới mực nước mặn, vẫn phát triển bình thường. \\"Nếu ghim thanh long xuống nước mặn, cây sẽ chết ngay nhưng ký gửi trên thân mắm lại khác, thanh long hút nước và dinh dưỡng để sống, cây mắm cũng không bị hư hại gì. Tôi trồng đến nay đã 3 năm nhưng chưa thấy gốc mắm nào chết cả\\", ông Phương tiết lộ. Được biết, thanh long trồng khoảng 2,5 năm bắt đầu cho trái, riêng số thanh long trồng dưới ao tôm hơn 600 gốc đã cho trái 30%, ông đang thu hoạch khoảng 1 tháng nay. Nhờ sự sáng tạo và mạnh dạn thay đổi hướng sản xuất, chỉ với 1ha ao tôm, ông Phương đã trồng thành công hơn 1.000 gốc thanh long cho năng suất 2-3 tấn/năm, bình quân mỗi tấn ông lãi 20 triệu đồng. \\"Có khách ở ven biển miền Trung thấy mô hình của tôi hiệu quả đã gọi điện đặt mua cây mắm và thanh long về trồng. Tôi không nghĩ mô hình này được mọi người đón nhận đến thế\\", lão nông U70 nói như khoe. Ông Phạm Văn Dẻn - Phó Chủ tịch Hội Nông dân thị trấn Cái Nước cho biết, cách trồng \\"thanh long ôm gốc mắm\\" do ông Phương nghĩ ra và làm đầu tiên ở địa phương. Thông thường trồng thanh long phải đặt trụ nhưng ông Phương muốn tiết kiệm chi phí nên đã cho thanh long bám vào thân cây mắm sinh trưởng. Cách làm này giúp ông Phương đạt hiệu quả kinh tế cao. \\"Nhiều năm qua, ông Phương là nông dân giỏi của địa phương, được tỉnh chú ý. Mô hình thanh long của ông đã được quảng bá rộng rãi, nhiều hộ đến học hỏi\\", ông Dẻn cho hay. Dưới đây là một số hình ảnh về quy trình trồng thanh long \\"nương tựa\\" trên thân cây mắm của lão nông Mai Lam Phương:","answer":"Lão nông sống khỏe nhờ mô hình sáng tạo \\"thanh long ôm mắm\\""},{"question":"తటస్థ అణువులు ప్లాస్మాత్వచం ద్వారా ఎలా చలిస్తాయి ? ధృవ అణువులు కూడా వాటివలెనే చలిస్తాయా? కానిచో అవి త్వచంలో ఏ పద్ధతిలో రవాణా చెందుతాయి?","answer":"తటస్థ ద్రావితాలు కణ పొర ద్వారా సామాన్య విసరణ పద్ధతిలో గాఢతా ప్రవణతను అనుసరించి అంటే అధిక గాఢత నుంచి అల్ప గాఢత దిశలో ప్రయాణిస్తాయి. ధృవ ధర్మంగల అణువులు అధృవ స్వభావం ఉన్న ద్విపటలికాయుత లిపిడ్ పొర ద్వారా ప్రయాణించలేవు. కనుక వాటికి త్వచం గుండా రవాణా చెయ్యటానికి వాహక ప్రోటీన్ల సాయం కావాలి. కొద్ది అయానులు లేదా అణువులు వాహక ప్రోటీన్ల సహాయంతో వాటి గాఢతా ప్రవణతకు వ్యతిరేకదిశలో అంటే అల్పగాఢతనుంచి అధికగాఢతలవైపు త్వచం గుండా రవాణా చెందుతాయి."},{"question":"பிரெட்ரிக் எங்கெல்ஸ்சின் மேற்கோள் ஒன்றை தரவும்.","answer":"மனிதனைத் தவிர மற்ற விலங்குகள் இயற்கையைத் தனது சுற்றுச் சார்புக்காக மட்டுமே பயன்படுத்துகின்றன. ஆனால் மனிதன் மட்டுமே தனது தேவைக்கு ஏற்றவாறு இயற்கையை மாற்றி அமைக்க முயற்சிக்கிறான். மணிதன் இயற்கையின் மீது ஆதிக்கம் செலுத்தி அதை மாற்றி அமைக்க முயற்சிக்கும் போது, மனிதனை இயற்கை திருப்பி அடிக்கிறது."},{"question":" د مقررې طی مراحل بیان کړئ ؟","answer":"په حقوقي او تنظیمي چوکاټونو کې، د قانون جوړونې پروسه معمولا څو مرحلې لري. پروسه اکثرا د مسلې پیژندنې سره پیل کیږي ، چیرې چې د نوي مقرراتو اړتیا یا د موجوده قانون تعدیل پیژندل کیږي. له دې وروسته، د قواعدو د پراختیا یوه مرحله ده، چې په ترڅ کې یې اړونده چارواکي او شریکان د قانون د ژبې او مشخصاتو د مسودې په جوړولو کې همکاري کوي. پدې مرحله کې کیدای شي عامه مشورې، د متخصصینو معلومات، او د اغیزو ارزونه شامل وي ترڅو د حاکمیت د احتمالي پایلو هر اړخیز پوهاوی یقیني کړي.وروسته، وړاندیز شوی قاعده د عامه خبرتیا او تبصرو څخه تیریږي، چې اغیزمنو اړخونو او عامو خلکو ته اجازه ورکوي چې خپل نظر وړاندې کړي. دا مرحله د حاکمیت په پروسه کې روڼتیا او حساب ورکونې ته وده ورکوي. د ترلاسه شویو نظرونو په پام کې نیولو وروسته، وروستی قاعده بیا اعلان او پلي کیږي. دا ټوله پروسه د عامه معلوماتو او تفتیش اړتیا سره د مقرراتو اړتیا انډول کولو لپاره ډیزاین شوې."},{"question":"Burun ameliyatından sonra ne zaman güneşe çıkmak?","answer":"Genel olarak burun ameliyatları sonrasında doktorlar en az iki hafta süreyle güneş ışınlarından korunmayı öneriyorlar. Güneş ışınlarının zararlı ışınlarından korunmak özellikle burun bölgesinin iyileşme sürecinde olumlu yönde etki ediyor."},{"question":"Su’aal: Sheeg Wadanka Qaarada Yurub Ku Yaal Oo Hal Wadan Oo Keliya Xuduud La Leh?","answer":"Jawaab: Waa Wadanka Portugal."},{"question":"Izihlabathi ziyaqibana ngempela uma ubheka ngasohlangothinilezimfashini. Phambilini uma ukhuluma ngemfashini ubusukeubhekise ezingutsheni zokugqoka kuphela. Nokho-ke isikhathisesiguqukile ngoba sekukuningi kakhulu okubizwa ngemfashiningaphandle kwezingubo zokugqoka. Indlela yokulungisa izinwele,uhlobo lwezimoto olungajwayelekile, omakhalekhukhwini konkelokhu kuyaba imfashini. Uma imfashini ethile isangenisile baningiabantu ababa nesiqiniseko sokuthi ayibedluli. Abanye bancamelaukutsheleka imadlana okukanye bayintshontshe ukuze bazibusisengemfashini.Akuve kudabukisa nokho-ke ukufica umuntuesezimpintshe kabuhlungu ngesiketi noma ngebhulukwe egamenilokuthi imfashini. Imfashini phela nayo iyabhekelelwa. Kwesinyeisikhathi kuhle nje ukuthi uyiyeke imfashini yedlule ungazangeuzihluphe ngayo. Abantu abaningi bazithola sebengonomafashiningenxa yokuthi bafuna ukwamukeleka kubangani babo. Basukebefuna ukusika ukhasi emiphakathini abahlala kuyo. Imisakazonamaphephandaba iyazama ukunqanda lesi sihlava ngokuthi kubenezinhlelo ezithize ezikhuluma ngobubi nobuhle bezimfashini. 1. Qalisa umusho ngala magama abhalwe ngokugqamile kulo mushoolandelayo:Imisakazo namaphephandaba iyazama ukunqanda lesi sihlava","answer":"Lesi sihlava siyazanywa ukunqandwa imisakazo namaphephandaba. "},{"question":"P(E) + P (E కాదు) = ………(A) 1(B) 2(C) 3(D) ఏదీకాదు","answer":"(A) 1"},{"question":"¿Qué colombianos han ganado premios Nobel?","answer":"En 1982 Gabriel García Márquez gana el Nobel de literatura y en 2016 el entonces presidente de Colombia, Juan Manuel Santos, ganó el Nobel de la paz."},{"question":"கேள்வி:தஞ்சையில் பொறிக்கப்பட்டுள்ள அரசாணையால் அறியப்படும் செய்தி யாது?","answer":"பதில்:தஞ்சாவூரில் வாழ்ந்த ஆகம சாஸ்திர பண்டிதராகிய சர்வசிவ பண்டிதரிடத்தில் பல நாட்டைச் சார்ந்த மாணாக்கர்கள் கல்விக் கற்க வந்திருந்தார்கள் என்ற செய்தி, முதலாம் இராசராச சோழன் காலத்தில் தஞ்சையில் பொறிக்கப்பட்டுள்ளது. ஆழ்ந்த சிவபக்தனான இராசராசன் இந்தியாவின் பெரும் இராசதந்திரிகளைப் போன்று, எல்லா சமயங்களிடத்தும் பொது நோக்குடையவனாய் அவற்றை ஆதரித்து வந்தான். தஞ்சைப் பெருங் கோயிற் சுவர்களில் காணப்படும் அழகிய சிற்பங்களிலிருந்து இம்மன்னன் கல்வெட்டுகளில் இவனால் கட்டப்பட்டதாகக் கூறப்படும் விட்டுணு ஆலயங்களிலிருந்தும் இராசராசன் தனது சமயக் கொள்கைகளில் தாராள மனப்பான்மை உடையவனாகவே இருந்தான் என்று தெரியவருகிறது."},{"question":"Тыныстан Айданага жаза албады эмнеге?","answer":"Кулжанын он бири. Жекшемби. Мокоп кеттим. Сүйлөсөм сөзүм, ойлосом оюм мокок болуп калды. Турмуштун ташына чапкылай берсең, араңжан акылыңдын да, көртешик көөдөнүңдүн да мизи майтарылары турган иш. Мен азыр майтарылып турам. Мококтун орусчасы “тупой” болот. Мен азыр тупой болуп турам. Денемде жашабай калдым. Ойгоно калып эле ачык турган терезеден асман аралап учуп кетем. Сөөктөрү аркайган денем үйдө жаткан бойдон калат. Келечекке барам – кыялдар тосуп алат, өткөнгө барам – өкүнүч өпкөгө, өкүт өзөккө, сагыныч санга жабышат. Денем болсо сөөктөрү оркоюп үйдө жатат.Сүйгөнүмдүн жанына барам, чачтарынан жыттайм, колун байкатпай кармап алып чогуу басам, кучактайм, кээде кумарга берилебиз, денемди өзүм менен ала келбегениме өкүнүп алам. Тиктоктун коштоосунда күлкү агымы менен ажайып дүйнөгө сапар алам, бир аздан кийин катарга Instagram, YouTube кошулат. Анан оргия башталат. Сөөктөрү аркайган денем үйдө жаткан бойдон калат. Дем албай, абаны сезбей калдым. Мен оргияда, денем үйдө. Өпкөм гана вазыйпасын жең учунан жасап жүрөт.Мокогон балтаны ташка чапсаң деле убал эмес. Мокогон ойлорду туш келди чапкылап, мокогон сөздөрдү туш келди чачкылап жүрө берсең түгөнбөйт экен, убалы жок да. Ошо мокоду деген сөздөрүң анча-мынча камышты, чырпыкты кыйып өткөнгө жарай берсе, аны көргөндөр курч экен дешип, сага түзөнүп кайрагын кайрап калышса, ичиңден түтөп, ичиңден быкшыйсың. Мында да мокок ойлорду курчута жазып жаткан өзүмдөн уялам. Денемден чыга калып, сырттан өзүмдү карап, испанча уялам. Курчтук жөнүндө сүйлөгөн башка мококтордон уялам. Мокок адамдан эмнени күттүңөр, мокок ойлордон эмнени күттүм, билбейм. Курчуш керек. *Бул кечээги текст. Мындайдын канчасы жазылып, кара тешикке ыргыды. Ушундай, Айдана. Сен “жаз” дейсиң. Мокоп жатсам, эмнени жазам"},{"question":"Quais são os idiomas oficiais da Bélgica?","answer":"A Bélgica é um país multilíngue e possui três idiomas oficiais reconhecidos em diferentes regiões do país. Esses idiomas são:Neerlandês: Também conhecido como flamengo, o neerlandês é a língua oficial na região de Flandres, que abrange a parte norte da Bélgica, incluindo cidades como Antuérpia, Bruxelas (onde é cooficial com o francês) e Gent.Francês: O francês é a língua oficial na região da Valônia, que abrange a parte sul da Bélgica, bem como na Região de Bruxelas-Capital. Na capital, Bruxelas, tanto o francês quanto o neerlandês têm status oficial.Alemão: O alemão é o terceiro idioma oficial da Bélgica e é falado em algumas áreas da região de língua alemã, localizada no leste do país, perto da fronteira com a Alemanha. Esta é uma comunidade minoritária, e o alemão é cooficial nessas áreas.Essa diversidade linguística reflete a complexa composição cultural e política da Bélgica, que é composta por várias comunidades linguísticas. Cada região tem seu próprio governo e administração, o que reflete a importância dos idiomas em diferentes partes do país."},{"question":"文中の主な言葉を見つけて、その内容を説明しなさい。 「フォーミュラE」は、排気ガスを出さない電気自動車のレースです。今までにアメリカのニューヨークやイギリスのロンドンなどで開いています。20日、このレースを東京で来年3月30日に開くことが決まりました。日本で開くのは初めてです。コースは東京都江東区にある東京ビッグサイトの周りで、日本の車の会社など10ぐらいのチームが出る予定です。東京都は、二酸化炭素を出さない社会にするために、このレースを開きたいと考えていました。小池知事は「このレースは電気自動車の時代の象徴です。もっと多くの人が電気自動車に乗るようにしていきたいです」と話しました。","answer":"文にある主な言葉とその内容はこちらです。- 排気ガス: 1）自動車などのエンジンからはき出される、不用になったガス。有害な物質を含み、大気汚染の原因になる。- レース: 1）競走・競泳などの競技。2）競争。- コース: 1）進んで行く道。進路。2）競走で、そこを通るように決められた道。3）学習の内容や順序。課程。4）料理を出す、決まった順序。- チーム: 1）競技や仕事をするときの、組や団体。- 二酸化炭素: 1）炭素と酸素の化合物で、色もにおいもない気体。炭火の燃えるときなどに発生し、人のはく息の中にもふくまれている。ドライアイス・ソーダ水などに使われる。炭酸ガス。記号は「CO₂」。- 知事: 1）都・道・府・県などの政治をとる、いちばん上の役目。また、その人。- 象徴: 1）考え・気持ちなど、目に見えないものを、色や音・形などにたとえて表すこと。また、表したもの。シンボル。"},{"question":"Сынган кылыч романдагы 📚 Казый ким болгон?","answer":"Казый — Нүзүпкө шарияттын жолун айтып, Кокон хандыгында \\"аталык\\" мансабын негиздеген адам. Ушул мансапка ээ болгондон кийин Нүзүп диванханага шамшар бычак менен Шералинин чокоюн илдирген ким экенинди унутпа деп."},{"question":"ఇచ్చిన గద్యానికి కొనసాగింపుగా ఒక పేరా రాయండి:యువకుడు విప్లవకారుడని తెలుసుకుని ఉపచారాలు చేస్తుంది. ఆమె మనస్థితి కాయకల్పమైంది. “ఇదేం గతిరానీకు! గిట్లెందుకైనవు కొడకా! అంది. వెళ్ళిపోతానన్న యువకుని “ఆ మాపోతా! మా పోతా… ఒక్కటే పోకడ! చక్కంగ స్వర్గమే పోతా! హు పోతడండ యాడికో” అని నిలువరించింది.","answer":"రాజోలిగే ఉన్నవు కొడకా! నీవెందుకొచ్చెరా ఈకట్టం? పండుపండు గొంగల్లపండు” అని అతనిపై గాఢనిద్రలోని వెళ్ళేట్లు ఓదార్చింది. మనవరాలిని పిలిచి దీపం వెలిగించి ఆ యువకుని శరీరంపై గుచ్చుకున్న ముళ్ళను తీసేయమని చెప్పింది. “మా చేత్తవులే సంసారం! ఇక కూకోవాని పక్క, ముండ్లు తీసెయి ఉల్లుల్లుగ అయ్యో సిగ్గయితాందా వాని ముట్టుకుంటే, ఏం మానవతివి గదవే! నీ సిగ్గు అగ్గిలబడ! వాని పానం దీత్తవా యేం సిగ్గు సిగ్గను కుంట! ఊ చెయ్యి చెప్పినపని. పాపం పీనుగోలె పడున్నడు గాదె! వాని జూత్తే జాలి పుడుతలేదె నీకు! ఆ! గట్ల! నొప్పించకు పాపం” అమ్మ సంభాషన తీరిది."},{"question":"Toлкoвaниe и знaчeниe cлoвa \\"Бyдyчи\\"","answer":"Бyдyчи, дeeпpичacтиe нecoвepшeннoгo видa, oбpaзoвaннoe oт глaгoлa «быть». Oбoзнaчaeт cвязи мeждy coбытиями и oпpeдeляeт иx пocлeдoвaтeльнocть. Moжeт yпoтpeблятьcя в кaчecтвe зaмeны cлoв «являяcь», «нaxoдяcь», и т.п. нaпp.: «He бyдyчи aнaлoгиeй жизни, иcкyccтвo нe имeeт бытия впoлнe пoдoбнoгo нaшeмy»."},{"question":"Ao anatin'ny kontinentan'i Afrika ve i Ejipta?","answer":"Eny, firenena any Afrika Avaratra i Ejipta, any amin’ny faritra avaratratsinanan’ny kaontinanta afrikanina indrindra no misy azy."},{"question":"Sheeg salaada aan aadaan iyo aqim midna lahayn?","answer":"Salaada aan aadan iyo aqim midna lahen waa salaada Ciida."},{"question":"TAMBAYA: Rubuta ɗari biyu da arba'in da takwas a matsayin lamba?","answer":"Amsa: 248"},{"question":"Completa la siguiente frase : En virtud de un contrato con el Ejército de los EE. UU. Colt Arms fabrica la ametralladora rotativa M1895 de diez cañones, variante de la ametralladora Gatling, con una cadencia de 800-900 disparos/minuto y que empleaba el cartucho .30 Army, siendo utilizada con gran efectividad en la... ","answer":"Batalla de las Colinas de San Juan. La ametralladora Colt-Browning M1895, o \\"Potato Digger\\", fue fabricada por Colt. La Colt-Browning fue una de las primeras ametralladoras en emplear el sistema de recarga accionada por gas, originalmente inventado por John Browning. Se convirtió en la primera ametralladora automática adoptada por los Estados Unidos y tuvo un uso limitado por el Cuerpo de Marines de EE. UU. en la Batalla de la Bahía de Guantánamo y por los Regimiento de Caballería Voluntaria de Estados Unidos en la campaña de Santiago durante la Guerra hispano-estadounidense. En el año 1901 Elizabeth Jarvis Colt vendió la compañía a un grupo de inversionistas externos con sede en Nueva York y Boston."},{"question":"Dame un ejemplo de trivia en está categoría : Música. ","answer":"¿Cuál es la canción más corta en el álbum Plastic Hearts de Miley Cyrus? Gimme What I Want. "},{"question":"أين يوجد أكبر سوق للتمور؟","answer":"بريدة"},{"question":"السؤال: كم مرة اعتلى ليبرون جيمس منصة التتويج؟","answer":"4الإجابة:"},{"question":"இந்த உரை என்ன முக்கியமான நிகழ்வைப் பற்றியது: ஜஹனாரா இமாம் (Jahanara Imam) (3 மே 1929 - 26 சூன் 1994) ஒரு வங்காளதேச எழுத்தாளரும் அரசியல் ஆர்வலரும் ஆவார். வங்காளதேச விடுதலைப் போரில் போர்க்குற்றங்கள் செய்ததாகக் குற்றம் சாட்டப்பட்டவர்களை விசாரணைக்கு உட்படுத்துவதற்கான முயற்சிகளுக்காக இவர் அறியப்படுகிறார். இவர் \\"ஷாஹீத் ஜனானி\\" (தியாகிகளின் தாய்) என்று அழைக்கப்படுகிறார்.","answer":"வங்காளதேச விடுதலைப் போரில்"},{"question":"Indro misy toe-javatra :\\"Ny alika, io namana mahatoky sy mahatoky io, dia lazaina matetika ho \\"sakaizan'ny olona\\". Nandritra ny an'arivony taona maro, ireo zavaboary alika ireo dia nijoro teo anilan'ny olombelona, ​​nanolotra firaiketam-po tsy misy fepetra, namana mahafaly, ary indraindray aza fanampiana sarobidy.\\" Raha ohatra ka \\"Ny alika\\" no valiny dia inona no fanontaniana mety napetraka?","answer":"Biby inona no heverina ho naman’ny olombelona matetika?"},{"question":"మధుర కళ గురించి సంక్లిప్తంగా వివరించండి.","answer":"జైన మతం స్ఫూర్తితో ధ్యానంలో ఉన్న దిగంబర తీర్థంకరుల శిల్పాలను మధుర శిల్పులు నిర్మించారు. మొదట్లో బుద్ధుని, బోధిసత్వుని ప్రతిమలు నిర్మించారు. తర్వాత కాలంలో, మత భావనలు ప్రదర్శితమయ్యేటట్లు నిర్మించారు. బుద్ధుని ప్రతిమలు బిగుతు కండరాలు, బలమైన శరీరంతో హుందాగా, భక్తి భావంతో ఉండే విగ్రహాలను మధుర శిల్పులు నిర్మించారు. వైదిక దేవతలైన శివుడు, విష్ణువు, పార్వతి, లక్ష్మీ ప్రతిమలు కూడా ఈ శిల్ప శైలిలో నిర్మించడం జరిగింది."},{"question":"O ma ṣe o, ọkọ ajagbe tẹ obinrin to n lọ jẹẹjẹ ẹ pa l’Ekoo","answer":"Obinrin kan tẹnikẹni ko ti i mọ orukọ ẹ titi di ba a ṣe n sọ yii lo ti kagbako iku airotẹlẹ latari ijamba ọkọ tanka kan to waye ni agbegbe Mile 2, nitosi Nigeria Army Signal Barracks, ni nnkan bii aago mẹwaa aabọ owurọ ọjọ Ẹti, Furaidee yii, lọna marosẹ Apapa si Oshodi, nipinlẹ Eko.Niṣe ni tirela ọhun ti epo bẹntiroo kun inu rẹ temutemu ṣubu yakata, to si dabuu ọna marosẹ ọhun, bẹẹ lobinrin agbalagba naa wa labẹ taya rẹ, aṣọ ankara buluu lo wọ, o ti ku fin-in fin-in.Alukoro fun Ajọ to n ri si iṣẹlẹ pajawiri nipinlẹ Eko, (LASEMA) Ọgbẹni Nosa Igiebor, fidi iṣẹlẹ naa mulẹ, o lawọn oṣiṣẹ ajọ naa pẹlu irinṣẹ to le wọ mọto ti wa nibi ijamba naa, mọto panapana si ti debẹ pẹlu, nitori ewu ijamba ina to le ṣẹlẹ.Nosa ni o ṣee ṣe ko jẹ ere asapajude lo ṣokunfa iṣẹlẹ yii, paapaa bi ọkọ naa ṣe ti loodu epo ẹgbẹrun lọna marundinlọgọta lita, ti eyi si le maa fi i sọtun-un sosi. O fi kun un pe afaimọ ko ma jẹ pe niṣe lọkọ naa lọọ subu lu obinrin to n rin lọ jẹẹjẹ tirẹ mọlẹ.O jọ pe dirẹba ọkọ ọhun ti sa lọ, tori ko sẹnikan to kofiri rẹ, ṣugbọn iṣẹ ti n lọ lati yọ oku obinrin naa labẹ ọkọ ọhun.Nosa si ti ṣeleri pe awọn yoo wadii ohun to ṣokunfa ijamba yii."},{"question":"एमिनेम को हो?","answer":"एमिनेम, जसलाई मार्शल माथर्स वा स्लिम श्याडी पनि भनिन्छ, एक अमेरिकी र्‍यापर, गीतकार, र रेकर्ड निर्माता हो जुन उनको गीतात्मक कौशल, उत्तेजक सामग्री, र र्याप संगीत उद्योगमा उनको प्रभावको लागि व्यापक रूपमा मान्यता प्राप्त छ।"},{"question":"Orchestrator in Web Frameworks","answer":"Orchestrator component ကို Laravel မှာ HTTP Kernel အနေနဲ့ မြင်ရပါတယ်။ request-response pipeline တခုလုံးကို တာဝန်ယူ စီမံပေးတဲ့ ဗဟိုချက်အနေနဲ့ တည်ဆောက်ထားပြီး request/response model တည်ဆောက်တာ၊ middleware stack တာနဲ့ route assisting စတဲ့ တာဝန်တွေကို လုပ်ဆောင်ပါတယ်။ Application intelligence ရှိတာဖြစ်လို့ အပိုဆောင်းအနေနဲ့ path နဲ့ query parameter တွေကိုဖတ်ပြီး dynamic routing နဲ့ conditional middleware တွေကိုပါ လုပ်ပေးနိုင်ပါတယ်။ExpressJS မှာ HTTP Kernel နဲ့ တိုက်ရိုက်နှိုင်းပြစရာ မရှိပေမယ့် App object က Orchestrator ရဲ့ တာဝန်တွေဖြစ်တဲ့ res နဲ့ resp object တွေတည်ဆောက်တာ၊ routing လုပ်တာ အစရှိတဲ့ လုပ်ဆောင်ချက်တွေကို တာဝန်ယူပါတယ်။ ဒါပေမယ့် Application intelligence ရှိတာဖြစ်လို့ အပိုဆောင်းအနေနဲ့ path နဲ့ query parameter တွေကိုဖတ်ပြီး dynamic routing နဲ့ conditional middleware တွေကိုပါ လုပ်ပေးနိုင်ပါတယ်။ExpressJS မှာ HTTP Kernel နဲ့ တိုက်ရိုက်နှိုင်းပြစရာ မရှိပေမယ့် App object က Orchestrator ရဲ့ တာဝန်တွေဖြစ်တဲ့ res နဲ့ resp object တွေတည်ဆောက်တာ၊ routing လုပ်တာ အစရှိတဲ့ လုပ်ဆောင်ချက်တွေကို တာဝန်ယူပါတယ်။ ဒါပေမယ့် Application intelligence မပါဝင်တဲ့အတွက် Laravel လို feature တွေအသင့်သုံး မရနိုင်ပါဘူး။"},{"question":"Responde la siguiente pregunta :¿Quién es el mánager general de los Broncos?, write a text that explains this. The answer should start at char number 280. Text:","answer":"Peyton Manning se convirtió en el primer mariscal de campo de la historia en llevar a dos equipos diferentes a participar en múltiples Super Bowls. Ademas, es con 39 años, el mariscal de campo más longevo de la historia en jugar ese partido. El récord anterior estaba en manos de John Elway ―mánager general y actual vicepresidente ejecutivo para operaciones futbolísticas de Denver― que condujo a los Broncos a la victoria en la Super Bowl XXXIII a los 38 años de edad."},{"question":"Trên hòn đảo phép thuật có 2021 tắc kè xanh, 2022 tắc kè đỏ và 2023 tắc kè vàng. Biết rằng cứ sau một phút, khi hai con tắc kè khác màu gặp nhau thì chúng sẽ cùng biến đổi sang màu còn lại. Hỏi sau ít nhất bao lâu thì tất cả tắc kè biến đổi thành cùng một màu?","answer":"Lời giải: Ban đầu, số lượng của ba loại tắc kè là ba số tự nhiên liên tiếp, nên khi chia cho 3 có ba số dư là bộ (0, 1, 2).Sau mỗi lần có hai con tắc kè đổi sang màu còn lại thì có hai loại tắc kè giảm 1 và loại tắc kè còn lại tăng 2. Do đó, kết quả số lượng của ba loại tắc kè nhận được vẫn luôn là bộ ba số dư (0, 1, 2) khi chia cho 3.Từ đó suy ra: ở mọi thời điểm, số lượng của mỗi loại tắc kè luôn là bộ ba số chia cho 3 dư (0,1,2) nên không bao giờ có thể biến tất cả các con tắc kè thành cùng một màu vì khi đó số lượng tắc kè sẽ là (0,0, 6066), tức là bộ ba số cùng chia hết cho 3"},{"question":"Hãy giải thích về tình trạng \\"High-functioning anxiety\\"","answer":"Theo bác sĩ tâm thần Sasha Hamdani, high-functioning anxiety là hiện tượng một người bị lo âu song vẫn có thể “vận hành” bình thường. Họ vẫn học tập và làm việc hiệu quả, trò chuyện vui vẻ với người khác dù bên trong không ổn chút nào.Hiện tại, high-functioning anxiety không được ghi nhận chính thức trong Cẩm nang Chẩn đoán và Thống kê Rối loạn tâm thần (DSM-5). Dù vậy theo bác sĩ Hamdani, nó có thể kích thích các rối loạn tâm lý khác ở mức độ nghiêm trọng, mà phổ biến nhất là trầm cảm do sự thờ ơ với cảm xúc bên trong."},{"question":"ما هي أطول سورة من سور القرآن الكريم؟","answer":"\\tسورة البقرة."},{"question":"السؤال: ما هو اسم الملك الذي يقف خازناً على جهنم؟","answer":"الإجابة: مالك."},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'rajin bekerja mudah belanja'? Berilah satu contoh ayat untuknya.","answer":"Ia bermaksud jika rajin bekerja akan mendapat hasil yang banyak untuk dibelanjakan. Contoh ayat: Kita selalu diingatkan supaya rajin bekerja kerana rajin bekerja mudah belanja."},{"question":"Ƙirƙiri labarin don kanun labarai mai zuwa:Atiku Abubakar: Tarihin mutumin da aka tsayar takarar shugaban Najeriya karo na uku","answer":"A daren Lahadin nan ne babbar jam'iyyar hamayya a Najeriya, PDP, ta ayyana tsohon mataimakin shugaban ƙasar Atiku Abubakar a matsayin wanda ya lashe zaɓen fitar da gwani na ɗan takarar shugaban Najeriya. Atiku ya lashe zaɓen ne bayan da ya samu ƙuri'a 371, inda ya kayar da gwamnan Jihar Rivers Nyesom Wike wanda ya zo na biyu da ƙuri'a 237. Tsohon shugaban majalisar dattawan Najeriya, kuma shugaban kwamitin ya gudanar da zaben, David Mark, ne ya bayyana sakamakon zaben wanda aka gudanar a Abuja, babban birnin kasar. Kafin fara zaɓen ne gwamnan jihar Sokoto Aminu Waziri Tambuwal da tsohon fitaccen ma'aikacin banki Hayatu-Deen sun janye wa Atiku, tare da umartar magoya bayansu su zaɓi Atiku Abubakar. Atiku Abubakar gogaggen dan siyasa ne da ya shafe shekaru da dama yana jan zaren. Hasalima yana daga cikin jiga-jigan mutanen da suka kafa jam'iyyar PDP. An haifi Atiku Abubakar ranar 25 ga Nuwamban 1946 a Jihar Adamawa da ke Arewa Maso Gabas, kuma ya kasance jigon dan siyasa kuma hamshakin attajiri a Najeriya. Tun bayan da Najeriya  ta dawo mulkin dimokuradiyya a shekarar 1999, Atiku Abubakar ya kasance mataimakin shugaban kasar Najeriya na 11, a mulkin Shugaba Olusegun Obasanjo a tsakanin 1999 zuwa 2007. Ya mallaki katafariyar Jami'ar ABTI, wato American University of Nigeria a Jiharsa ta Adamawa. Kamfaninsa na hada-hadar man fetur, mai suna Intels Nigeria Limited na hada-hada a kasashen Afirka da suka hada da Angola da Equatorial Guinea da Gabon da Sao Tome and Principe. Atiku Abubakar ya tsunduma harkokin sisaya a 1989, kuma yana cikin makusantan tsohon mataimakin shugaban kasa na mulkin soji, Janar Shehu Musa Yar'adua. Ya shiga jam'iyyu daban-daban tun da ya shiga harkokin siyasa. An zabi Atiku Abubakar a matsayin gwamnan gwamnan Jihar Adamawa a 1998, ko da yake daga bisani Cif Obasanjo ya zabe shi domin kasancewa mataimakinsa. Daga wancan lokacin zuwa yanzu, wannan ne karo na uku da Atiku Abubakar ke tsayawa takarar shugaban kasa, ko da yake ya tsaya zaben fitar da gwani sau da dama. A shekarar 2007, jam'iyyar Action Congress of Nigeria (ACN) ta tsayar da shi takara inda ya sha kaye a hannun dan takarar PDP, Umaru Musa Yar'adua. Kazalika a shekarar 2019 ya fafata da Muhammadu Buhari na jam'iyyar APC amma bai yi nasara ba. Sai kuma yanzu da PDP ta saye tsayar da shi takara domin fafatawa a zaben shekarar 2023. Atiku yana da mata hudu da 'ya'ya 28 da jikoki da dama. Haka kuma yana goyon bayan kungiyar kwallon kafa ta  Arsenal."},{"question":"Hoàn thiện đoạn văn sau: Sau sự sụp đổ của Liên Xô, các lực lượng Spetsnaz của các nước cộng hòa mới thành lập của Liên Xô đã tham gia vào nhiều cuộc xung đột trong nước như Nội chiến Tajikistan, Chiến tranh Chechen, Chiến tranh Nga-Gruzia","answer":"và Khủng hoảng Crimea. Spetsnaz cũng đã chịu trách nhiệm giải quyết một số tình huống bắt giữ con tin cấp cao như cuộc khủng hoảng con tin tại nhà hát Moscow và cuộc khủng hoảng con tin ở trường Beslan (vụ thảm sát trường Beslan)."},{"question":"السؤال: كم تبلغ ثروة مؤسس شركة أمازون؟","answer":"الإجابة:  تقدر بنحو 177 مليار دولار."},{"question":"ලෝක සෞඛ්‍ය සංවිධානයේ (WHO) භූගෝලීය වියාප්තිය කෙබදුද?","answer":"ලෝක සෞඛ්‍ය සංවිධානය ස්විට්සර්ලන්තයේ ජිනීවා හි මූලස්ථානය ඇතුලුව ප්‍රාදේශීය කාර්යාල 6 ක්, සහ විවිධ රටවල කාර්යාල 150 කින් සමන්විත වේ"},{"question":"प्रश्न : दिइएका शब्दको अर्थ लेख्नुहोस् :यश, रैती ,अकलुषित ","answer":"उत्तर  :यश ➡ राम्रो काम गर्नेले पाउने इज्जतरैती ➡ अरूको जग्गा कमाउने व्यक्तिअकलुषित ➡ सफा हृदयको"},{"question":"ටෙස්ට් ක්‍රිකට් දිවියක පන්දු යවන්නෙක් වැඩිම කඩුලු සංඛ්‍යාවක් දවාගෙන ලෝක වාර්තාවක් පිහිටවූ ශ්‍රී ලංකා දඟ පන්දු යවන්නා  කවුද? ඔහු මෙම දස්කම ලබා ගත්තේ කුමන වසරවලදීද?","answer":"ටෙස්ට් ක්‍රිකට් දිවියක පන්දු යවන්නෙකු ලබාගත් වැඩිම කඩුලු සංඛ්‍යාවට හිමි ලෝක වාර්තාව පිහිටවූ ශ්‍රී ලංකා දඟ පන්දු යවන්නා  මුත්තයියා මුරලිදරන් වේ. මුරලිදරන් ක්‍රීඩා ඉතිහාසයේ විශිෂ්ටතම පන්දු යවන්නෙකු ලෙස සැලකේ. ඔහුගේ කීර්තිමත් දිවිය පුරාවට ඔහු ටෙස්ට් කඩුලු 800ක් දවා ගනිමින් වාර්තාගත මුලු ලකුණු සංඛ්‍යාවක් ලබා ගත්තේය.2007 දෙසැම්බර් 3 වැනිදා එංගලන්තයට එරෙහිව පැවැති තරගයකදී ඔස්ට්‍රේලියානු පා දඟ පන්දු යවන ක්‍රීඩක ෂේන් වෝන් විසින් තබා තිබූ කඩුලු 708ක වාර්තාව මුරලිදරන් බිඳ දැමීය. ඔහු 2010 ජූලි 22 වැනිදා ඉන්දියාවට එරෙහිව ඔහුගේ අවසන් ටෙස්ට් තරගයේදී ඔහුගේ 800 වැනි කඩුල්ල ලබා ගත්තේය. මෙම ජයග්‍රහණය ටෙස්ට් ක්‍රිකට් ඉතිහාසයේ වැඩිම කඩුලු ලාභියා ලෙස ඔහුගේ ස්ථානය තහවුරු කළේය."},{"question":"Setiap hari, Akmal menulis _________ tentang pengalamannya sepanjang percutian itu.","answer":"catatan"},{"question":"दाङमा रहेको घोरही उपमहानगरपलिकाको बारेमा केही भन्नुहोस् ","answer":"घोराही उपमहानगरपलिका नेपालको दाङ जिल्लामा स्थित एक नगरपालिका हो। यस उपमहानगरपलिका चौधेरी, बाहुन, छेत्री  आदि जातीय व सांस्कृतिक समृद्धता पाइएका विभिन्न जनजातिहरूका निवासीहरू बस्छन्। यो नगरपालिकामा जनसंख्या, कृषि, वाणिज्य, उद्योग, पर्यटन, शिक्षा र स्वास्थ्य सेवाहरूको विकास र व्यवस्थापनमा माथी हेरचाह गरिएको छ।घोराही नगरपालिका सहरमा विकासीकृत आवासीय, वाणिज्यिक, विनोदी र धार्मिक स्थलहरू छन्। यहाँमा संचार, विद्युत, पानी, निर्माण सामग्री, पेशा व्यवसाय आदि तथा विभिन्न सार्वजनिक सुविधाहरू उपलब्ध छन्।घोराही नगरपालिका राष्ट्रिय तथा अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय यातायात जीवनमा प्रमुख महत्त्वका सडक जोडिएको छ। यस नगरपालिकामा स्थापित स्थानीय सरकारी कार्यालयहरू, विद्यालय, कलेज, बैंक, अस्पताल, औषधालय, हड्टेल, ठेक्का भवनहरू, खेलकूद क्षेत्र, पार्क आदि सार्वजनिक सुविधाहरू रहेका छन्।"},{"question":"السؤال: من هو أول نبي قال في رسائله: (أمّا بعد)؟","answer":"الجواب: هو نبي الله داود عليه السَّلام."},{"question":"pick me a random number","answer":"Okay, how about this random number : 42 ?"},{"question":"sir nacaybka iyo habyb sooca ","answer":"soomaalida ayaa caan ku ah labadaas waxyaalood waxaana keenaya diin yarida iyo ka fogaanshaha ku dhaqanka Dinta islaamka runta ah, canuga yar meeshii lagu tarbiyayn lahaa barashada diinta iyo jacaylka wixii la mabda' ah waxaa loo sheegayaa reer hebel waa cadowgeenna, waan necebnahay, waligaa iska jir iskana ilaali, ilmihii yaraa wuxuu ku korayaa qolo nacayb uusan fasiri karin waxa dhaliyay, iyo waxa ku kalifay midna, markuu u yaraado wuxuu dhihi karaa colaad baa na dhex martay waa' hore, oo colaada qof baad ka tahaye maxaa u wada nacday cidaas oo dhan?, dad aan raali ka ahayn colaadaas sow ma jiri karaan? oo bal ka waran hadii reerkiin dulmiga lahaa, waa wax aan la sheegi karin, gabyaa carbeed oo joogay waqtigii jaahiliga ayaa laga sheegay inuu yiri (anigu \\"ghazya' uun baan ka mid ahay, haday lunta iyo haday hanuunto ayaga uun baan la jiraa) ghazya waa reerkiisa, waa indho la'aanta qabyaalada iyo mabda' la'aanta.. carabta waxaa astaan u ahaa waagaas (u gargaar walaalkaa haduu gardaran yahay iyo hadii laga gardaranyahayba) waana tabta soomaali ku sifaysantahay soomaalida maanta joogta."},{"question":"Hãy viết một bài báo có thể sử dụng tiêu đề này: 1 tỷ người có nguy cơ chết do biến đổi khí hậu","answer":"Các chuyên gia dự đoán số ca tử vong đáng báo động liên quan đến biến đổi khí hậu dựa theo một số quy luật, bao gồm \\"quy luật 1.000 tấn\\".Bản đánh giá mới công bố trên tạp chí Energies, dựa trên 180 bài viết về tỷ lệ tử vong của người do biến đổi khí hậu, đưa ra một con số đáng lo ngại, Science Alert hôm 30/8 đưa tin. Vào khoảng thế kỷ tới, một tỷ người, thậm chí nhiều hơn, có thể thiệt mạng do thảm họa khí hậu.Giống như đa số dự đoán, dự đoán này dựa trên một số giả định và quy luật, trong đó có \\"quy luật 1.000 tấn\\". Theo đó, mỗi 1.000 tấn carbon mà nhân loại đốt cháy có thể gián tiếp kết án tử cho một người trong tương lai.Nếu thế giới đạt mức nhiệt cao hơn 2 độ C so với nhiệt độ trung bình toàn cầu thời tiền công nghiệp - điều có khả năng xảy ra trong những thập kỷ tới - thì sẽ có nhiều sinh mạng mất đi. Tình từ thời điểm hiện tại, cứ mỗi 0,1 độ C nóng lên, thế giới có thể hứng chịu khoảng 100 triệu ca tử vong.Tỷ lệ tử vong của con người do biến đổi khí hậu rất khó tính toán, kể cả trong thời hiện đại. Theo Liên Hợp Quốc, hàng năm, các yếu tố môi trường lấy mạng khoảng 13 triệu người, nhưng chưa rõ bao nhiêu trong số đó do biến đổi khí hậu tác động trực tiếp hoặc gián tiếp. Một số chuyên gia cho rằng nhiệt độ bất thường giết chết khoảng 5 triệu người mỗi năm, nhưng số khác lại đưa ra ước tính thấp hơn.Một trong những lý do khiến việc tính toán trở nên khó khăn là ảnh hưởng của biến đổi khí hậu rất đa dạng. Mất mùa, hạn hán, lũ lụt, thời tiết khắc nghiệt, cháy rừng và nước biển dâng đều có thể tác động đến cuộc sống con người theo những cách phức tạp.Dự đoán số người chết trong tương lai do những thảm họa khí hậu này vốn là việc cực kỳ khó, nhưng chuyên gia năng lượng Joshua Pearce tại Đại học Western Ontario (Canada) và Richard Parncutt tại Đại học Graz (Áo), hai tác giả của bản đánh giá, cho rằng rất đáng để nghiên cứu. Theo hai chuyên gia, việc đo lượng khí thải theo các khía cạnh liên quan đến con người giúp công chúng dễ dàng tiếp nhận số liệu hơn, đồng thời nhấn mạnh mức độ cần thiết phải hành động ngay."},{"question":"現在の福井県中北部に相当する日本の旧国名である、「テニスの王子様」の主人公の苗字は何でしょう。","answer":"越前です。"},{"question":"قصة رائعه ","answer":"قـــصـــــة رائـعــة 🩷🥺سمعوا هاذ القصة لأنها من أجمل ما سمعت.... يروى ان الرسول صلى الله عليه وسلم هداوه عباءه حافظات عليها السيده عائشه رضي الله عنها هو يدق الباب واحد الشخص كيتسول على صدقه فقال الرسول لعائشه رضي الله عنها اعطي لهاذ السائل ذيك العباءه فخذاها هاذ السائل ومشى للسوق تايبيع فيها وتيقول شكون اللي يشري العباءه ديال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم. تجمعوا الناس عليه كل شيء بغا يشري العباءه. واحد الراجل عمى سمع ها النداء وهو يقول للغلام ديالو سير وجيب ذيك العباءه كيف ما كان الثمن ديالها والا درتيها فانت حر لوجه الله. فعلا, هذاك الغلام مشى جابها لذاك العمى. العمى هو يدير واحد الدعاء هذه وهو يقول 'بحق رسول الله عليك وبركه عباءته الطاهره بين يديه اعد الي بصري' فاذا بالبصر ديالو كيرجع. خرج فرحان عند الرسول صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو يقول ليه الحمد لله رجع لي البصر ديالي وها هي هذه العباءه مني فحكى لي القصه وبدا الرسول صلى الله عليه وسلم وسلم يضحك حتى بانوا الاسنان ديالو, هو يدور عند السيده عائشه رضي الله عنها وقال ليها بمعنى هذه العباءه رجعات واحد الفقير غني وشفات واحد المريض واعتقت واحد العبد وها هي رجعات لنا🩷🌸..."},{"question":"ඔබේ ආහාර නිශ්පාදන වලින් උපයන්න්න","answer":"මෙය තවමත් එතරම් ප්‍රචලිත ක්‍රමයක් නොවුනත්, නගරබදව නම් මෙම ක්‍රමය ඕනෑ තරම් දැක ගත හැකියි. එනම් වෙබ් අඩවියක් හරහා ආහාර සපයන්නන් සහ ආහාර ඉල්ලුම් කරුවන් එකිනෙක සම්භන්ධ කරන සහ, එම ආහාර බෙදාහරින ජාලයක, ආහාර සපයන්නෙකු වීමයි. මේ සඳහා දැනට ශ්‍රී ලංකාව තුල Pick me foods සහ Uber eats යන සේවාවන් ක්‍රියත්මකයි. ඉතින්, එම ආයතන ලබා දෙන කොන්දේසි සපුරාලමින්, ආහාර සපයන්නෙකු ලෙස ඔබට ලියාපදිංචි විය හැකිනම් එය විශාල අවස්ථාවක් වනවා."},{"question":"“రెండు సరూప త్రిభుజాల వైశాల్యాలు సమానం అయిన అవి సర్వసమానాలు”. (సత్యం/అసత్యం)","answer":"సత్యం"},{"question":"次の段落は何について話しているのか？ お菓子などの袋のプラスチックを少なくするために、外側を紙にする技術ができました。袋の中は、お菓子の油や水分がつくため、プラスチックを使っています。袋に使うプラスチックが40%ぐらい少なくなります。外から中が見える紙で作った封筒もあります。この封筒の中に、住所や名前を書いた紙を入れると、封筒の外から読むことができます。今までは、中が見えるように一部にプラスチックを使っていました。荷物を箱に入れて送るとき、中の物が壊れないように、空気が入った袋を一緒に入れることがあります。この袋の材料の75%を紙に変える技術もあります。去年4月、プラスチックのごみを少なくするための法律が始まりました。新しい技術で作った紙が、これからもっと広がりそうです。","answer":"プラスチックの代わりに新しい技術で作った紙を使う"},{"question":"ජෛනාගම යනු කුමක්ද?","answer":"16 වන ශතවර්ශයේදී හින්දු ආගම තුළ ඇතිවූ ප්‍රතිසංස්කරණ පියවරක් ලෙස ජෛනාගම බිහිවිය. එය පදනම් වී ඇත්තේ එහි නිර්මාතෘවරයා වන මහවීරාගේ ඉගැන්වීම මතය. තමකම ප්‍රතික්ෂේප කරන ජීවිතයක් තුළින් \\"සර්වඥ බවට\\" පත්විය හැකි බව විශ්වාස කරමින් මහවීරා වසර 12 ඉන්දියාවේ සෑම තැනකම නිර්වස්ත්‍රව සහ ගොළුවතින් සැරිසැරූ අතර ඒ හේතුවෙන් ඔහුට බොහෝ දුෂ්කරතා සහ ගැරහීම් වලට ලක්වීමට සිදුවිය. ඉන්පසු ඔහු තම ගෝලයන් හට තමා අළුතින් සොයාගත් විශ්වාස් ගැන දේශනා කළේය. අති උසස් තැනැත්තෙකු පිළිගැනීම් හෝ ඔහුට වැද නමස්කාර කිරීම ගැන ඔහු තුළ තිබූ අදහස කෙරෙහි බලවත් ලෙස විරෝධතාවයන් පැන නැගුනි. වැද නමස්කාර කිරීම ලැබීමට තරම් දෙවිවරයෙකු හෝ දෙවිවරුන් සිටින බව මහවීරා ප්‍රතික්ෂේප කළ නමුත් වෙනත් ආගමික නායකයන් මෙන්ම ඔහුද තමන්ගේ පසුකාලීන අනුගාමිකයන් විසින් කෙළසනු ලැබීය. ඔහු 24 වන තීර්නාත්කර එනම් අවසාන හා ශ්‍රේෂ්ඨතම ගැළවුම්කරු යනුවෙන් නම් කරනු ලැබීය. ජෛන භක්තික ලියවිලි අනුව මහවිරා ස්වර්ගයෙන් බැසවිත් කිසිම පාපයක් නොකර භාවනා උපයෝගි කරගෙන මෙලොව ඇති සියලූම ආශාවලින් තමාව නිදහස් කරනු ලැබීය.ජෛනාගම වූ කලී අතීශයින් නීතිරීති වලට ගැතිවූ ආගමක් වනුයේ යම් කෙනෙකුට තමන්ගේ ගැළවීමේ මාර්ගයට පිවිසිය හැකි එකම මග නම් තාපස (තදින්ම තමකම අත්හැරීම) තුළින් බව එයින් දැක්වෙන බැවිනි. මෙම ආගම තුළ කිසිම නිදහසක් නැත. එහි ඇත්තේ නීතිරීතී පමණක්ය. මූලිකව පොරොන්දු 5 ඇත. එනමි,ජීවින් මරා දැමීමබොරු කීමකෑදරකමලිංගික ආශ්වාදය සහලෞකික බැදීම්යන දේවල් අතහැර දැමීමය. මෙහිදී ස්ත්‍රී පක්ෂය සමිපූර්ණයෙන්ම බැහැර කළ යුතුවේ. මන්දයත් සෑම පාපිෂ්ඨ ක්‍රියාවකටම හේතුවන්නේ ස්ත්‍රීන් බැවින්ය."},{"question":"Inona avy ny fitaovana ilaina amin'ny \\"ala volon-jaza\\"?","answer":"Ny fitaovana ilaina amin'ny \\"ala volon-jaza\\" dia:- Fary raiki-bololona,- Akondro velon-dreny,- Sahafa vita amin'ny hazo famelona, Vary masaka Trafon-kena,- Saonjo masaka, Akondro,- Tantely,- Hety"},{"question":"አፈወርቅ ተክሌ ለከፍተኛ ትምህርት በስንት አመታቸው ተመረጡ?","answer":"በአሥራ አምስት ዓመታቸው"},{"question":"中国の思想家で、「性善説」を唱えたのは孟子ですが、「性悪説」を唱えたのは誰でしょう?","answer":"荀子です。"},{"question":"السؤال: شنو هو اطول عظم فجسم الإنسان ؟","answer":"الإجابة: العظم ديال الفخذ"},{"question":"அக்காலத்திய மணிப்பிரவாள நடைக்கு எடுத்துக்காட்டாக விளங்குவது எது?","answer":"இரத்தினம்-பவளம் என்ற நேரடிப் பொருளுடைய மணிப்பிரவாளம் என்னும் சொல், தென்னிந்தியாவில் சமஸ்கிருதமும், திராவிட மொழியொன்றும் கலந்து எழுதப்பட்ட ஒரு இலக்கிய நடையைக் குறிக்கும். மணியும், பவளமும் சேர்த்து உருவாக்கப்பட்ட மாலை போல இரண்டு மொழிகள் கலந்து உருவான இலக்கிய நடை என்பது இதன் பொருளாகும்.சோழப் பேரரசுக் காலத்திலும் அதன் பின்னரும், இன்றைய கேரளத்தையும் உள்ளடக்கியிருந்த தமிழ் நாட்டில் ஒருசில வட்டாரங்களில் சமஸ்கிருதச் செல்வாக்கு மிகுந்திருந்தது. சமஸ்கிருத மொழி உயர்வானதாகவும், இறைவனுடைய மொழியாகவும் கற்பிக்கப்பட்ட காலம் அது. தமிழில் சமஸ்கிருதத்தைக் கலந்து எழுதுவது உயர் நடையாக அவ்வட்டாரங்களில் எண்ணப்பட்டது. ஆழ்வார்களுக்குப் பின்னர், அவர்களுடைய நூல்களுக்கு உரை எழுதிய இராமானுஜருடைய ஆக்கங்கள் [மேற்கோள் தேவை] மணிப்பிரவாள நடையிலேயே அமைந்திருந்தன. சோழர்காலத்தில் சமஸ்கிருதத்தின் வழி புகுந்த சமயக் கருத்துருக்களும், தமிழில் எழுந்த சமஸ்கிருதத் தழுவல் நூல்களும் இத்தகைய போக்குக்கு வாய்ப்பாக அமைந்தன.அன்றைய சேர நாட்டில், மணிப்பிரவாளத்தின் தாக்கம் கடுமையாக இருந்ததால் சேர நாட்டுத் தமிழ், இன்று மலையாளம் என அழைக்கப்படும் புதிய மொழியாக மாறிவிட்டது.எடுத்துக்காட்டுஅக்காலத்திய மணிப்பிரவாள நடைக்கு எடுத்துக்காட்டாக \\"உபதேசரத்னமாலை\\" என்னும் நூலிலிருந்து ஒர் பகுதியைக் கீழே காணலாம்.மணவாளமாமுனிகள் தமக்காசார்யரான பிள்ளையுடைய ப்ரசாதத்தாலே, க்ரமாசுதமாய் வந்த அர்த்த விசேஷங்களைப் பின்பற்றாருமறிந்து உஜ்ஜீலிக்கும் படி, ப்ரபந்தரூபேன உபதேசித்து ப்ரகாசிப்பிக்கிறோமென்று ச்ரோத்ரு புத்தி ஸமாதாநார்த்தமாக ப்ரதிஞ்ஞை பண்ணி யருளுகிறார்.சமஸ்கிருத ஒலிகளை குறிக்க கிரந்த எழுத்துக்கள் பயன்படுத்தப்பட்டன. தமிழ் மணிப்பிரவாள நடையில் தமிழ் எழுத்துக்களும், கிரந்த எழுத்துக்களும் கலந்து எழுத்தப்பட்டன. கீழே மேற்கூறிய பகுதி எவ்வாறு கிரந்தம் கலந்து எழுதப்பட்டது என்பதை காணலாம்."},{"question":"வினா : தனித்தமிழ் இயக்கத் தந்தை என அழைக்கப்பட்டவர் யார்?A. பரிதிமாற் கலைஞர்B. உ.வே.சாC. மறைமலை அடிகள்D. தந்தை பெரியார்","answer":"விடை : C. மறைமலை அடிகள்"},{"question":" ¿Quiénes fueron los Incas y cuál fue su imperio?","answer":"Los Incas fueron una civilización indígena que fundó el Imperio Incaico en el siglo XV en la región andina de Perú. Este imperio se convirtió en uno de los imperios más grandes y poderosos de América precolombina."},{"question":"این متن به چه رویداد مهمی اشاره دارد؟ در دسامبر ۱۹۳۴، وی با درجه ستوانی به عنوان خلبان بمب افکن سبک مشغول به کار شد. وی از ژانویه ۱۹۳۶ تا آوریل ۱۹۳۸ در اسکادران ۱۴ منطقه نظامی خارکوف خدمت کرد و پس از آن به هنگ ۴ بمب افکن منتقل و از فوریه تا مارس ۱۹۴۰ به عنوان خلبان پلیکارپو آر-زد در جنگ زمستان شرکت کرد. وی به دلیل هشت مأموریت موفق هوایی نشان پرچم سرخ دریافت کرد. در آستانه حمله آلمان به اتحاد جماهیر شوروی، زلنکو در آموزش مجدد پرسنل به عنوان خلبان سوخو-۲ شرکت می‌کرد.","answer":"این متن به جنگ زمستان و جنگ جهانی دوم اشاره دارد."},{"question":"桜が満開の季節には、まだ寒い日もありますが、そんな日に特有の冷え方を何と言うでしょうか。","answer":"それは「花冷え」と呼ばれています。"},{"question":" sheeg suurada halmar soo wada degatay iyadoo dhameystiran","answer":" jawab. waa suuradda ancaam."},{"question":"أي هي عاصمة مصر؟","answer":"القاهرة"},{"question":"次のタイトルに基づいて、最大500語の段落を書いてください： ズワイガニの漁が始まる　福井県の港では1匹310万円","answer":"ズワイガニの漁が始まりました。福井県越前町では6日、漁に行った船が港に戻ってきました。福井県のズワイガニは「越前がに」と呼ばれています。港では「越前がに」の黄色い札を付けたたくさんのカニの競りを行いました。そして、重さ2.2kgのカニが1匹310万円になりました。この港では今まででいちばん高くなりました。鳥取県鳥取市の港でも7日、漁に行った船が戻ってきました。鳥取県のズワイガニは「松葉がに」と呼ばれています。港ではまず、形や大きさが特にすばらしい8匹の競りを行いました。そして、重さ1.35kg、甲羅の長さ15cmのカニが1匹100万円になりました。"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai air digenggam tak tiris\\"?","answer":"Kedekut"},{"question":"ஈ. வெ. இராமசாமி மேற்கோள் ஒன்றை தரவும்.","answer":"தமிழ்நாட்டு மாணவர்கள், பட்டதாரிகள் செக்குமாடாக இருத்தல் வேண்டாம்; பந்தயக் குதிரைகளாக இருத்தல் வேண்டும்."},{"question":"Title: సింగపూర్ ఇతర దేశాలకన్నా ఎందుకు ముందుంది?nGiven the above title of an imaginary article, imagine the article.nకియాసువిజం'ను గురి0చితెలప0డి. ","answer":"కియాసు పదానికి అర్థం 'ఏదైనా కోల్పోతామనే భయం'ఓ శనివారం ఆర్కార్డ్ రోడ్డులో షాపింగ్ చేశాక, నేను ఎమ్‌ఆర్‌టీ (రైలు) స్టేషన్‌కు వెళ్లాను. అక్కడ స్టేషన్ నిండా జనం ఉన్నారు. అయితే అక్కడ రెండు ఎస్కలేటర్లు ఉన్నా, అందరూ లిఫ్టు వద్దే నిలబడ్డం నాకు ఆశ్చర్యం కలిగించింది. లిఫ్టు రాగానే అందరూ దానిలో చొరబడ్డారు. దీనికి వ్యతిరేకమైన అనుభవాలు కూడా నాకు తారసపడ్డాయి. ఒకసారి నేను మా పాపతో వెళుతుండగా, పాప నిద్ర లేస్తుందేమో అన్న భయంతో నిర్మాణ కార్మికులందరూ కొద్దిసేపు తమ పని నిలిపేశారు. వర్షం కురిసేటప్పుడు నేను బస్సు దిగుతుంటే, తడిచిపోతానని నాకు తమ గొడుగులు ఇచ్చిన వాళ్లున్నారు. మరి అలాంటప్పుడు లిఫ్ట్‌లో ఎక్కడానికి మాత్రం ఎందుకంత పోటీ పడ్డారు? నాకు తొందరలోనే దీనినే 'కియాసు' అని అంటారని తెలిసింది. చైనాలోని హొక్కెయిన్ మాండలికంలో 'కియా' అంటే భయం, 'సు' అంటే కోల్పోవడం - అంటే 'కోల్పోతామనే భయం'. 2007లో దీనిని ఆక్స్‌ఫర్డ్ ఇంగ్లీష్ డిక్షనరీలో చేర్చడం జరిగింది. దానికి అర్థం - 'గుంజుకునే, తమకే చెందాలనే ధోరణి' అని పేర్కొన్నారు. మనుగడ కోసం పోరాటమే దీనికి కారణమని నేషనల్ యూనివర్సిటీ ఆఫ్ సింగపూర్‌కు చెందిన డాక్టర్ లియాంగ్ చాన్ హూంగ్ తెలిపారు. కేవలం 53 ఏళ్ల వయసున్న ఈ ఆగ్నేయాసియా దేశం, సాంస్కృతికంగా భిన్నమైన దేశాల మధ్య ఉంటూ, నిరంతరం ఒత్తిడిని ఎదుర్కొంటుంటుంది. ''సింగపూర్ ప్రజల మెదళ్లలోకి స్వయం సమృద్ధి సాధించాలనే భావనను చొప్పించారు. ఎప్పుడూ అవకాశాల కోసం చూడాలి, అందరికన్నా ముందుండాలి, ఇది సమాజంలో భాగమైపోయింది.'' అని హూంగ్ అన్నారు.  క్లుప్తంగా చెప్పాలంటే, ఏదైనా కోల్పోవడాన్ని సింగపూర్ వాసులు భరించలేరు. అంతే కాదు, ఆఫర్లన్నా వాళ్లకు చాలా ఇష్టం. లేటెస్ట్ మోడల్ ఫోన్ కోసం వాళ్లు ఎంత సేపైనా క్యూల్లో నిలబడగలరు. 2015లో నిర్వహించిన ఒక సర్వేలో సింగపూర్ ప్రజల ముఖ్యమైన 10 నమ్మకాలలో పోటీతత్వం, వ్యక్తిగత స్వార్థంతో పాటు 'కియాసు' కూడా ఒకటని తేలింది. అదే సమయంలో కుటుంబ సంబంధాలు, స్నేహం, నిజాయితీలు కూడా ఆ జాబితాలో చోటు చేసుకున్నాయి. సమస్య ఏమిటంటే, సింగపూర్ వాసులు ఆ రెండింటి మధ్య సమతుల్యత సాధించడానికి ఇబ్బంది పడుతున్నారు. కానీ సింగపూర్‌లోనే 'కియాసువిజం'ను తీసిపారేసేవారూ ఉన్నారు. జానీ లావ్ అనే కళాకారుడు 1990ల నుంచి 'మిస్టర్ కియాసు' అనే కామిక్ పాత్ర ద్వారా దాన్ని ఎగతాళి చేస్తున్నారు. మొదట దానికి మిశ్రమ ప్రతిస్పందన లభించింది. ''60 శాతం మంది దానిని చూసి..."},{"question":"Chọn đáp án đúng cho câu hỏi sau:Giải Nobel Hóa học đầu tiên được trao cho ai?A. Marie CurieB. Louis PasteurC. Jacobus Henricus van 't HoffD. Alfred Nobel","answer":"C. Jacobus Henricus van 't HoffNăm 1901 là năm đầu tiên giải thưởng Nobel đầu tiên được trao ở Stockholm, Thụy Điển, trong các lĩnh vực Vật lý, Hóa học, Y học, Văn học và Hòa bình. Theo Nobelprize, giải Nobel Hóa học đầu tiên được trao cho Jacobus Henricus van 't Hoff với công trình khám phá ra các định luật về động lực học hóa học và áp suất thẩm thấu trong các dung dịch.Jacobus Henricus van 't Hoff (30/8/1852 - 1/3/1911) là một nhà Vật lý học và Hóa học người Hà Lan. Nghiên cứu về động lực học hoá học, cân bằng hóa học, áp suất thẩm thấu và hóa học lập thể là các thành tựu nổi bật của ông. Qua các thành tựu này, Van 't Hoff giúp tìm ra hệ thống môn học hóa lý đang được học tập hiện nay."},{"question":"السؤال: من هم أولاد فاطمة بنت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ؟","answer":"الإجابة: الحسن، الحسين، أم كلثوم"},{"question":"Dựa trên tiêu đề sau, hãy viết một bài báo nói về chủ đề này: 6 mẹo giảm mỡ bụng giúp bạn lấy lại vòng eo thon gọn","answer":"‏Duy trì vòng eo chuẩn chỉnh không chỉ khiến diện mạo của bạn thu hút hơn mà còn giúp bạn sống vui khỏe mỗi ngày. Hãy dừng ngay những thói quen xấu và áp dụng 6 mẹo giảm mỡ bụng được gợi ý qua bài viết dưới đây. 1. Hạn chế carbs giúp giảm mỡ bụng hiệu quả ‏Trong một nghiên cứu so sánh tác động giữa việc giảm cân thông qua chế độ ăn ít carbohydrate và chế độ ăn ít chất béo tại đại học Johns Hopkins, Mỹ, các nhà khoa học đã phát hiện ra rằng, mặc dù mỗi chế độ ăn chứa cùng một lượng calo, nhưng những người theo chế độ ăn ít carbs đã giảm trung bình 10 pound (xấp xỉ 5kg) trong 6 tháng, nhiều hơn những người ăn kiêng ít chất béo. Vì vậy, hãy hạn chế ăn các thực phẩm giàu carbs, đặc biệt là carbs tinh chế để vòng eo thon gọn hơn.‏ ‏Ngoài hiệu quả giảm cân, chế độ ăn ít carbohydrate mang lại nhiều lợi ích sức khỏe cho người bệnh tiểu đường, giúp ổn định đường huyết và ngăn ngừa biến chứng nguy hiểm do căn bệnh này gây ra.  ‏Hạn chế carbs có nhiều lợi ích cho sức khỏe.‏ ‏2. Tăng cường protein Protein đóng vai trò quan trọng trong quá trình giảm cân. Nhiều bằng chứng đã cho thấy rằng ăn đầy đủ protein giúp giảm 60% cảm giác thèm ăn, tăng cường trao đổi chất 80-100 calo và giúp bạn ăn ít hơn tới 441 calo mỗi ngày. ‏‏Bạn có thể tham khảo các nguồn protein tốt từ:‏ ‏Thịt bò, thịt lợn, thịt gà‏‏Các loại cá béo (cá hồi, cá ngừ, cá thu…) và hải sản (tôm…)‏‏Trứng‏‏Thực vật như các loại đậu (đậu lăng, đậu gà, đậu Hà Lan…) ‏Bên cạnh đó, đạm whey là một lựa chọn không tồi giúp tăng lượng hấp thụ protein một cách lành mạnh. Bạn có kết hợp đạm whey cùng trái cây, rau, các loại hạt… để có món sinh tố protein vừa thơm ngon, vừa giàu dinh dưỡng.  ‏Tăng cường protein. ‏3. Kết thân với rau xanh và trái cây‏ ‏Trong rau xanh và trái cây chứa nhiều chất xơ, vitamin và khoáng chất nhưng lượng calo lại khá thấp. Bổ sung rau xanh cùng trái cây vào các bữa ăn sẽ giúp bạn no lâu hơn. Nhờ vậy thói quen ăn vặt không lành mạnh cũng được hạn chế.‏ ‏Bạn có thể lựa chọn bông cải xanh, súp lơ, rau chân vịt, cải xoăn, bắp cải, rau xà lách, cà chua, dưa chuột… Các loại đậu cũng là một nguồn rất tốt mà bạn không nên bỏ qua bên cạnh một số loại ngũ cốc, chẳng hạn như yến mạch nguyên hạt. Tất cả đều là những lựa chọn lý tưởng hỗ trợ đốt mỡ thừa hiệu quả.  Kết thân với rau xanh và trái cây.‏ 4. Tránh tiêu thụ đường và đồ uống có đường‏ Ăn các loại thực phẩm có thêm đường có thể gây tăng cân, không tốt cho sức khỏe. Các nghiên cứu đã chỉ ra rằng, lượng đường dư thừa có thể dẫn đến tích tụ chất béo xung quanh bụng và gan. Bởi vậy, giảm các đồ ăn và thức uống chứa đường trong khẩu phần ăn hàng ngày sẽ giúp bạn tránh xa mỡ bụng và duy trì một vóc dáng khỏe đẹp. ‏ ‏Tuy nhiên, điều này không áp dụng đối với các loại trái cây, chúng rất tốt cho sức khỏe và chứa nhiều chất xơ giúp giảm thiểu tác động tiêu cực của đường fructose.‏ ‏5. Giảm khẩu phần ăn và tăng số lượng bữa ăn‏ Ngoài ba bữa chính, hãy bổ sung thêm 2 – 3 bữa ăn phụ trước và sau khi tập thể thao (hoặc trước khi đi ngủ). Các bữa ăn phụ này sẽ giúp bạn không cảm thấy đói và thèm ăn vặt. Nhờ vậy, khẩu phần ăn trong những bữa ăn chính cũng giảm đi. Lượng calo nạp vào vì thế cũng được kiểm soát hiệu quả.‏ ‏6. Tập thể dục thường xuyên để giảm mỡ bụng‏ Hoạt động thể chất giúp đốt cháy mỡ bụng hiệu quả. Theo Kerry Stewart, giám đốc Sinh lý học Lâm sàng tại đại học Johns Hopkins: \\"Một trong những lợi ích lớn nhất của việc vận động là thúc đẩy quá trình trao đổi chất. Tập thể dục có tác dụng giảm mỡ bụng bởi nó làm giảm lượng insulin lưu thông trong máu và khiến gan sử dụng hết acid béo, đặc biệt là những vùng mỡ nội tạng tích tụ gần đó\\".‏ ‏Thay vì chỉ tập riêng các bài tập bụng, nên kết hợp với các bài tập toàn thân để đạt được kết quả như mong muốn. Hãy dành từ 30 đến 60 phút mỗi ngày để tập luyện, bắt đầu từ vận động nhẹ nhàng như đi bộ hay tập yoga, sau đó thử các bài tập nặng hơn như tập tạ hoặc chạy bộ, cardio…‏ Nguồn: https://suckhoedoisong.vn/6-meo-giam-mo-bung-giup-ban-lay-lai-vong-eo-thon-gon-16922072517081651...Nguồn: https://suckhoedoisong.vn/6-meo-giam-mo-bung-giup-ban-lay-lai-vong-eo-thon-gon-169220725170816518.htm "},{"question":"ਸੰਪਾਦਕ ਨੇ ਮਸੌਦੇ ਵਿੱਚ ਇੱਕ ਵਾਕ ਦੁਬਾਰਾ ਲਿਖਿਆ। | ਇਸ ਦਾ ਕਾਰਨ ਕੀ ਸੀ? ਚੋਣ 1 : ਉਸਨੂੰ ਮਸੌਦਾ ਪ੍ਰਭਾਵਸ਼ਾਲੀ ਲੱਗਾ। ਚੋਣ 2 : ਉਸਨੇ ਵਾਕ ਅਸਪਸ਼ਟ ਮੰਨਿਆ। ","answer":"ਚੋਣ 2 : ਉਸਨੇ ਵਾਕ ਅਸਪਸ਼ਟ ਮੰਨਿਆ।"},{"question":"అభాగ్యులను, అనాథలను చూస్తే మీకేమనిపిస్తుందో రాయండి.","answer":"అభాగ్యులను, అనాథలను చూస్తే, నాకు బాధ కలుగుతుంది. నా మిత్రులతో, నా తల్లిదండ్రులతో చెప్పి, వారికి సాయం చేద్దామనిపిస్తుంది. అభాగ్యులకు, అనాథలకు ప్రభుత్వం ఆశ్రయం కల్పిస్తే బాగుండుననిపిస్తుంది. స్వచ్ఛంద సంస్థలు కూడా ఈ విషయంలో చొరవ చూపితే మేలనిపిస్తుంది. ధనవంతులు అభాగ్యులు, అనాథల కన్నీళ్ళు తుడవాలనీ, వారికి అండగా నిలిచి ఆదుకోవాలని అనిపిస్తుంది."},{"question":"請回答這個問題：地球上最大的濕地是哪個？","answer":"答案：帕米爾高原濕地"},{"question":"ඔබට AI ඉතිහාසයේ ප්‍රධාන චරිත සහ ඔවුන්ගේ දායකත්වය නම් කළ හැකිද?","answer":"AI ඉතිහාසයේ අනෙකුත් කැපී පෙනෙන පුද්ගලයින් අතර 20 වැනි සියවසේ මැද භාගයේදී AI සඳහා සැලකිය යුතු දායකත්වයක් ලබා දුන් Alan Mathison Turing සහ සැලකෙන \\"Logic Theorist\\" නිර්මාණය කළ ඇලන් නිව්වෙල් සහ හර්බට් A. සයිමන් ඇතුළත් වේ. Yann André LeCun, Geoffrey Everest Hinton සහ Yoshua Bengio ගැඹුරු ඉගෙනීම (Deep Learning) පිළිබඳ ඔවුන්ගේ දායකත්වය සඳහා ප්‍රසිද්ධ වී ඇති අතර ඔවුන් \\"AI හි ගෝඩ් ෆාදර්ස්\\" හෝ \\"ගැඹුරු ඉගෙනීමේ ගොඩ් ෆාදර්ස්\\" ලෙස හැඳින්වේ."},{"question":"Apakah jawapan untuk teka-teki berikut: Saya berdiri di tepi jalan, sesiapa pun boleh bercakap dengan saya hanya dengan membayar saya, siapakah saya?","answer":"Jawapannya ialah telefon awam. Telefon awam ialah sejenis telefon yang diletakkan di sepanjang jalan atau di tempat awam, dan sesiapa sahaja membayar untuk perkhidmatan telefon boleh menggunakannya untuk bercakap dengan orang lain."},{"question":"Apakah kontroversi yang wujud dalam musim kedua untuk Malaysian Idol? Siapakah yang terlibat dalam kontroversi ini? Apakah sebab kontroversi ini berlaku dalam Malaysian Idol?","answer":"Walaupun berjaya meningkatkan bilangan penonton berbanding musim pertama (mengikut kajian media), musim kedua Malaysian Idol menerima pelbagai kritikan mengenai mutu para pesertanya, terutamanya juaranya Daniel Lee Chee Hun yang dikutuk oleh sebilangan orang sebagai tidak berbakat dalam nyanyian dan bergantung kepada paras rupanya yang \\"comel\\" untuk meraih undian oleh gadis muda. Bagaimanapun, Daniel dan peminatnya menghadapi cabaran tersebut dengan jualan album yang laris.Kontroversi yang menyelubungi MI tidak bermula di situ. Antara pertikaian yang terawal ialah penyingkiran Lee Kar Wei, seorang peserta perempuan yang terpuji kerana \\"nyanyiannya yang sangat bagus\\", di pusingan saringan sebelum bermulanya pertandingan, menyebabkan sebilangan penonton mempersoal kredibiliti dan profesionalisme para juri.Di pertandingan meraih undian pula, timbulnya keresahan antara sebahagian penonton setia yang mendapati bukan sahaja para peserta mempersembahkan lagu-lagu secara tidak konsisten, malah penyertaan peserta seperti Faizull dan Daniel kuat tercabar oleh orang awan yang meninggalkan pesanan di laman Internet, tambahan pula terjadinya penyingkiran awal peserta yang dianggap mereka sebagai paling bermutu, seperti Atilia, Trish dan Xerra.Yang sebenarnya ramai yang tidak berpuas hati dengan kemenangan Daniel Lee boleh disebabkan undian perkauman. Tambahan pula Malaysian Idol disiarkan di saluran Cina, itu menjadi penyebab adalah mustahil peserta bukan berbangsa Cina yang menang pertandingan ini. Sesiapa yang aktif dengan forummer di krees.com tahu bahawa pada malam penyingkiran Faizul Rock Orang Kampung, undian untuk Faizul tersekat. Ini diberitahu oleh orang dalam belakang tabir Malaysian Idol sendiri yang keluar memberitahu kepada forummer yang lain. Ramai yang tidak puas hati dengan keadaan itu, dan itulah yang menyebabkan Malaysian Idol jatuh standardnya yang tersendiri. Malah admin krees.com juga seperti berat sebelah dengan mengatakan Faizul kononnya diberikan hak untuk tidak menyanyikan lagu English. Ini adalah perbuatan yang tidak profesional. Jika Faizul adalah pilihan rakyat Malaysia untuk jadi pemenang, seharusnya tidak perlu sebarang komplot untuk buat mana-mana peserta tersingkir."},{"question":"Bahasa rasmi di Malaysia","answer":"Bahasa Melayu merupakan bahasa rasmi di Malaysia dan telah ditetapkan menjadi bahasa untuk berkomunikasi dalam segala bidang pentadbiran di Malaysia. Perkara 152 Perlembagaan Malaysia menyatakan bahawa bahasa rasmi ini digunakan untuk semua urusan rasmi di peringkat kerajaan persekutuan, kerajaan negeri dan juga badan berkanun."},{"question":"Apakah latar belakang Menara Berkembar Petronas? ","answer":"Menara Berkembar PETRONAS di Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia ialah sepasang menara berkembar yang pernah menjadi bangunan tertinggi di dunia sebelum diatasi oleh Burj Khalifa dan Taipei 101. Sungguhpun begitu, kedua-dua menara ini masih merupakan menara berkembar tertinggi di dunia dan juga merupakan bangunan tertinggi pada abad ke-20. Kini, Menara Berkembar Petronas merupakan bangunan ke-11 tertinggi di dunia. Menara Berkembar Petronas memegang gelaran bangunan tertinggi dari tahun 1998 hingga 2004 dari segi ukuran dari aras pintu masuk utama hingga atas struktur, iaitu rujukan ketinggian asli yang digunakan oleh pertubuhan antarabangsa Majlis Bangunan Tinggi dan Habitat Bandar sejak tahun 1969 (tiga kategori ketinggian tambahan diperkenalkan ketika menara ini hampir disiapkan pada tahun 1996). Menara berkembar ini merupakan mercu tanda dan ikon Kuala Lumpur, bersama-sama Menara Kuala Lumpur yang terletak berdekatan. Menara Berkembar Petronas telah majlis pembukaan secara rasminya oleh Perdana Menteri Malaysia ke-4, Mahathir bin Mohamad sempena ulang tahun Petronas ke-25 dengan tajuk pesta perak dan Hari Kemerdekaan Malaysia ke-42 pada 31 Ogos 1999.Menara Petronas yang direka oleh jurubina César Pelli dari Argentina ini, siap dibina pada tahun 1998 setelah menelan masa tujuh tahun sehingga menjadi bangunan tertinggi di dunia sewaktu disiapkan. Menara ini dibina di atas tapak lumba kuda Kuala Lumpur. Kedalaman batuan dasar menjadikan bangunan ini dibina pada tapak yang paling dalam di dunia. Tapak sedalam 120 meter itu memerlukan sejumlah konkrit yang berlebihan untuk dibina dalam masa 12 bulan oleh Bachy Soletanche.Menara setinggi 88 tingkat ini banyak dibuat daripada konkrit bertetulang dengan muka bangunan buatan keluli dan kaca yang direka untuk menyerupai motif kesenian Islam untuk mencerminkan agama Islam di Malaysia. Satu lagi pengaruh seni Islam dalam bangunan ini ialah keratan rentas kedua-dua menara yang berbentuk Rub el Hizb, ditambah dengan bahagian bundar untuk memenuhi keperluan ruang pejabat. Menara 1 dibina oleh konsortium Jepun yang dipimpin oleh Hazama Corporation manakala Menara 2 dibina oleh dua kontraktor Korea Selatan, iaitu Samsung C&T dan Kukdong Engineering & Construction. Jejantasnya pula disiapkan oleh Kukdong.Disebabkan kekurangan keluli serta kos pengimportan keluli yang mahal, menara berkembar ini didirikan atas konkrit bertetulang teramat kukuh bereka bentuk radikal yang murah sekali. Konkrit yang amat kukuh dikenali ramai kontraktor Asia dan dua kali lebih berkesan mengurangkan gegaran berbanding keluli; namun, oleh itu bangunan ini dua kali beratnya pada tapak berbanding bangunan keluli yang seumpamanya. Disokong oleh teras konkrit 23-kali-23 meter dan segelang luar tiang super yang beruang legar, menara-menara ini menggunakan sistem struktur canggih yang menampung profilnya yang langsing serta menyediakan ruang pejabat tanpa tiang seluas 560,000 meter persegi (669,754 ela2). Di bawah menara berkembar ini ialah pusat beli-belah Suria KLCC dan Dewan Filharmonik Petronas."},{"question":"Sheeg shinida Imisa in dhod aye ledahay?","answer":"Waxay ledahay shan indhood."},{"question":"ما هو الحدث المهم في النص التالي: بعد استسلام باريس، ذهب درويت مع فيلق جيشه وراء لوار . هو أحد الشخصيات الخاضعة للاعتقال الفوري بموجب المرسوم المؤرخ 24 يوليو 1815 (المادة 1) ، ونجح في مغادرة البلاد ولجأ إلى بروسيا في بايرويت . حُكم عليه بالإعدام غيابياً عام 1816 . في وقت لاحق، أسس مصنع الجعة في جميع أنحاء ميونيخ . برسم تشارلز العاشر أثناء التتويج، عاد إلى فرنسا في عام 1825 وعاش في التقاعد حتى ثورة 1830 .","answer":"يتحدث النص عن درويت."},{"question":"Como é que Saramago abordou questões sociais e políticas através da escrita?","answer":"José Saramago utilizou elementos literários para debater questões sociais e políticas. Na sua obra \\"Ensaio sobre a Cegueira\\", ele metaforicamente examina a decadência da moral na sociedade. As suas obras não só contam histórias, também provocam reflexões profundas sobre a condição humana."},{"question":"Kokia yra gyvenimo prasmė? ","answer":"Gyvenimo prasmė – vienas esminių filosofinių, teologinių klausimų, kuriuo bandoma nusakyti atskiro individo, žmonijos, gyvybės, visatos egzistavimo priežastį, paskirtį, tikslą. Į gyvenimo prasmės klausimą vienareikšmių atsakymų nėra, įvairios filosofijos kryptys, religijos ir tikėjimai pateikia labai skirtingus atsakymus į šį klausimą. Atsakymų į šį klausimą ieškoma per tokias sąvokas ir išeities taškus kaip Dievas, siela, laisva valia, etika, gėris ir blogis, pomirtinis gyvenimas, laimė ir kt."},{"question":"Apakah maksud peribahasa 'gigi dengan lidah ada kalanya tergigit juga'?","answer":"Ianya bermaksud kerap kali juga timbul perselisihan antara suami isteri, sanak saudara dan sahabat handai."},{"question":"Skriv en fortsättning till detta stycke - Den största framgången för landslaget under 1960-talet blev kvartsfinalen i Europacupen för landslag 1964","answer":", en turnering som startat 1960 utan svenskt deltagande. I ett turneringsformat som spelades över tre år med både hemma- och bortamöten besegrade man Norge i första omgången och därefter Jugoslavien innan laget föll mot Sovjetunionen i kvartsfinalen. Turneringen ersattes från 1968 av Europamästerskapet i fotboll vartill Sverige dock inte lyckades att kvalificera sig efter att ha hamnat trea i sin grupp efter Bulgarien och Portugal."},{"question":"Harga daging hayam geus turun.Antonim tina kecap turun nyaéta ...A. MahalB. NaékC. Murah","answer":"Jawabanana: B. Naék"},{"question":"Generate a more complex version of this sentence: \\"His mother is of Kuwaiti origin.\\"","answer":"Of course, a more complex version of the sentence is: \\"His mother is of Kuwaiti origin, and he is full-brother of Nasser bin Hamad.\\""},{"question":"Kto otrzymał Nagrodę Nobla z Literatury w 2011 roku?","answer":"W 2011. roku Nagrodę Nobla z dziedziny literatury otrzymał: Tomas Tranströmer (Szwecja) za „zwięzłe, przejrzyste obrazy, które dają nam świeży dostęp do rzeczywistości”."},{"question":"नेपाली लोक संगीतमा प्रयोग हुने परम्परागत वाद्य यन्त्रहरू के के हुन्?","answer":"परम्परागत नेपाली वाद्ययन्त्रहरूमा मादल, सारंगी र बाँसुरी समावेश छन्। लोक संगीतका रुपमा पन्चे बाजा पनि प्रचलित छ। पन्चे बाजामा झ्याली, ढोलक, दमाहा, सहनाई, कर्णाल र नर्सिङ्घ पर्दछन।"},{"question":"ताज महल कहाँ स्थित है?","answer":"ताज महल आगरा में स्थित है।"},{"question":"¿Cómo ir al desierto de la Tatacoa en el departamento del Huila en Colombia?","answer":"1. Desde el municipio de Neiva tomar un bus hasta el municipio de Aipe.2. Al llegar a Aipe, dirigirse hacia la salida del Ferry o embarcación que recorre el rio Magdalena, el cual se dirige a Villavieja.3. Villavieja es el pueblo más cercano al desierto de la Tatacoa"},{"question":"Kurio iš dešimties didžiausių Lietuvos miestų pavadinimas yra kildinamas iš vienuolių ordino pavadinimo?","answer":"Marijampolės. Miestas buvo pavadintas: Švč. Mergelės Marijos Nekaltojo Prasidėjimo kongregacija arba Marijonų ordino garbei."},{"question":"駕駛時應與前方車輛保持一個安全車距，如果後方車輛與你的車輛跟車距離太近，你應?","answer":"如果有可能應保持其他車道行駛，讓其超越輕微減速，切忌急煞車與前方車輛保持一個安全距離，避免因前方車輛急煞車而被後方車輛追尾"},{"question":"कोरोना विषाणूचा मानवी शरीरावर थेट परिणाम कुठे होतो?","answer":"कोरोना विषाणूचा मानवी शरीरावर, त्यातही  थेट परिणाम श्वसन प्रणालीवर होतो."},{"question":"次の文章に書かれている内容に基づいて、少なくとも200語の段落を書いてください。： 東京都　性的マイノリティーのカップルのための制度が始まった","answer":"自分と同じ性別の人を好きになる人など性的マイノリティーのカップルがいます。東京都は、このようなカップルが生活しやすい社会にしようと考えました。そして11月1日から「パートナーシップ宣誓制度」を始めました。2人が一緒に生きていくパートナーの関係だという証明書を出します。この制度には、18歳以上のカップルで、どちらかが東京都に住んでいるか、会社や学校に通っている人が申し込むことができます。証明書をもらうと、東京都がつくったアパートに2人で住む資格をもらうことができます。携帯電話の「家族割引」を受けることもできます。証明書をもらったカップルは「社会に家族だとわかってもらえるのでうれしいです」と話していました。東京都によると、1日の朝までに177のカップルが申し込みました。"},{"question":"Мага кызыктуу факты жазып берчи!","answer":"Албетте, мына сизге кызыктуу факты : Эласмотерий - байыркы Сибирдеги керик. Бул байыркы кериктердин көлөмү өтө чоң болгон.  Бул тукум курут болгон жаныбарлардын узундугу 6 метр, бийиктиги 3 метрге чейин жана массасы 5 тонна болгон.  Эласмотерийдин негизги айырмалоочу өзгөчөлүгү чекесиндеги чоң томпок проекция болгон.  Окумуштуулар анын узундугу 1,5 метр болгон коюу мүйүзү болгон деп божомолдошот."},{"question":"What are the different parts of speech in English grammar, and can you provide examples for each?","answer":"The parts of speech are categories of words based on their function within a sentence. There are traditionally eight parts of speech in English grammar:Nouns: Words that name people, places, things, or ideas. Examples include \\"dog,\\" \\"city,\\" and \\"happiness.\\"Pronouns: Words that take the place of nouns. Examples include \\"he,\\" \\"they,\\" and \\"which.\\"Verbs: Words that express actions or states of being. Examples include \\"run,\\" \\"is,\\" and \\"think.\\"Adjectives: Words that describe or modify nouns or pronouns. Examples include \\"happy,\\" \\"blue,\\" and \\"tall.\\"Adverbs: Words that modify verbs, adjectives, or other adverbs. They often end in \\"-ly\\" but not always. Examples include \\"quickly,\\" \\"very,\\" and \\"well.\\"Prepositions: Words that show relationships between a noun or pronoun and another word in the sentence. Examples include \\"in,\\" \\"on,\\" and \\"by.\\"Conjunctions: Words that join words, phrases, or clauses. Examples include \\"and,\\" \\"but,\\" and \\"because.\\"Interjections: Words or phrases that express strong emotion or sudden utterance. Examples include \\"Oh!,\\" \\"Wow!,\\" and \\"Hey!\\"Each part of speech plays a crucial role in sentence construction and conveys specific types of information. Understanding the parts of speech helps in analyzing sentence structure and improving language skills."},{"question":"Ci ban kembaar la réwum Papouasie-Nouvelle-Guinée nékk","answer":"Réwum Papouasie-Nouvelle-Guinée mu ngi nékk ci kembaar bi ñuy wakh Oceanie"},{"question":"TAMBAYA: Shin yaya za a rubuta ɗari biyu da goma sha-tara a matsayin lamba?","answer":"Amsa: 219"},{"question":"س169- كم دامت خلافة علي بن أبي طالب؟","answer":"ج169- 5 سنوات"},{"question":"खालील म्हणीचा मराठीत सुलभ अर्थ सांगा .--हिरा तो हिरा गार तो गार","answer":"गुणी माणसाचे गुण प्रकट झाल्यावाचून राहत नाहीत"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai apabila patah tumbuh nyiur itu, tumbuh nyiur jua akan gantinya\\"?","answer":"Ia bermaksud yang hilang mesti diganti dengan yang serupa."},{"question":"ਨਵੀਂ ਦਿੱਲੀ, 7 ਮਾਰਚਇਥੇ ਮੇਜਰ ਧਿਆਨ ਚੰਦ ਨੈਸ਼ਨਲ ਹਾਕੀ ਸਟੇਡੀਅਮ ਵਿੱਚ ਖੇਡੇ ਜਾ ਰਹੇ ਵਿਸ਼ਵ ਕੱਪ ਦੇ ਪੂਲ ਏ ਦੇ ਇਕ ਮੈਚ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਖਣੀ ਕੋਰੀਆ ਦੀ ਟੀਮ ਨੇ ਕੈਨੇਡਾ ਨੂੰ 9-2 ਨਾਲ ਹਰਾ ਦਿੱਤਾ।ਏਸ਼ਿਆਈ ਚੈਂਪੀਅਨ ਕੋਰੀਆ ਦੀ ਟੀਮ ਨੇ ਹੁਣ ਤੱਕ ਪੂਲ ਲੀਗ ਦੇ ਤਿੰਨ ਮੈਚ ਖੇਡੇ ਹਨ, ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਟੀਮ ਨੇ ਅਰਜਨਟੀਨਾ ਨੂੰ ਹਰਾਇਆ, ਓਲੰਪਿਕ ਤੇ ਵਿਸ਼ਵ ਚੈਂਪੀਅਨ ਜਰਮਨੀ ਨਾਲ ਬਰਾਬਰੀ ਕੀਤੀ ਅਤੇ ਨਿਊਜ਼ੀਲੈਂਡ ਤੋਂ ਹਾਰ ਖਾਧੀ। ਉਧਰ ਟੂਰਨਾਮੈਂਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਕੈਨੇਡਾ ਦੀ ਚੌਥੀ ਹਾਰ ਸੀ। ਹੁਣ ਉਸ ਦਾ ਆਖਰੀ ਤੇ ਪੰਜਵਾਂ ਪੂਲ ਮੈਚ 9 ਮਾਰਚ ਨੂੰ ਅਰਜਨਟੀਨਾ ਨਾਲ ਹੋਵੇਗਾ।ਇਸ ਜਿੱਤ ਨਾਲ ਕੋਰੀਆ ਲਈ ਸੈਮੀਫਾਈਨਲ ਦੇ ਦਰਵਾਜ਼ੇ ਅਜੇ ਵੀ ਖੁੱਲ੍ਹੇ ਹਨ। ਕੋਰੀਆ ਲਈ ਪਹਿਲਾ ਗੋਲ 22ਵੇਂ ਮਿੰਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਨਾਮ ਵੂ ਹਯੂਨ ਨੇ ਪਹਿਲੇ ਪੈਨਲਟੀ ਕਾਰਨਰ ਉਤੇ ਕੀਤਾ। 35ਵੇਂ ਮਿੰਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਟੀਮ ਨੂੰ ਤੀਜਾ ਪੈਨਲਟੀ ਕਾਰਨਰ ਮਿਲਿਆ ਪਰ ਬਾਲ ਰੋਕਣ ਲਈ ਕੈਨੇਡਾ ਦੇ ਖਿਡਾਰੀ ਵੱਲੋਂ ਕੀਤੇ ਫਾਊਲ ਕਾਰਨ ਮੈਚ ਰੈਫਰੀ ਐਚ. ਕੋਲੀਨ ਨੇ ਪੈਨਲਟੀ ਸਟਰੋਕ ਦੇ ਦਿੱਤਾ। ਕੈਨੇਡਾ ਦੀ ਟੀਮ ਨੇ ਇਸ ਦਾ ਵਿਰੋਧ ਕੀਤਾ ਤੇ ਫੈਸਲਾ ਵੀਡੀਓ ਰੈਫਰੀ ਨੂੰ ਭੇਜ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਪਰ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਵੀ ਇਸ ਫੈਸਲੇ ਨੂੰ ਬਰਕਰਾਰ ਰੱਖਿਆ। ਪੈਨਲਟੀ ਸਟਰੋਕ ਉਤੇ ਜੰਗ ਜੋਂਗ ਹਯੂਨ ਨੇ ਗੋਲ ਕਰਕੇ ਲੀਡ ਨੂੰ 2-0 ਕਰ ਦਿੱਤਾ।ਦੂਜੇ ਅੱਧ ਦੀ ਖੇਡ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਹੋਣ ਦੇ ਦਸ ਮਿੰਟਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਹੀ ਕੋਰੀਆਈ ਖਿਡਾਰੀਆਂ ਨੇ ਉਪਰੋਥਲੀ ਚਾਰ ਗੋਲ ਕਰਕੇ ਟੀਮ ਨੂੰ 6-1 ਦੀ ਲੀਡ ਦਿਵਾ ਦਿੱਤੀ। ਕੈਨੇਡਾ ਦੀ ਟੀਮ ਵੱਲੋਂ 42ਵੇਂ ਮਿੰਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਰਾਈਟ ਫਲਿੱਪ ਨੇ ਖਾਤਾ ਖੋਲਿ੍ਹਆ। ਫਲਿੱਪ ਨੇ 51ਵੇਂ ਮਿੰਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਟੀਮ ਲਈ ਦੂਜਾ ਗੋਲ ਕੀਤਾ। 60ਵੇਂ ਮਿੰਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਕੋਰੀਆ ਨੂੰ ਮੈਚ ਦਾ ਪੰਜਵਾਂ ਪੈਨਲਟੀ ਕਾਰਨਰ ਮਿਲਿਆ, ਜਿਸ ਉਤੇ ਜੰਗ ਜੋਂਗ ਹਯੂਨ ਨੇ ਟੀਮ ਲਈ ਸੱਤਵਾਂ ਗੋਲ ਕੀਤਾ। 63ਵੇਂ ਮਿੰਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਗੋਲ ਕਰਕੇ ਯੂ. ਸਿਕ ਹਯੂ ਨੇ ਹੈਟ੍ਰਿਕ ਬਣਾਈ। ਕੋਰੀਆ ਵੱਲੋਂ 67ਵੇਂ ਮਿੰਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਵੂ ਨਾਮ ਹਯੂਨ ਨੇ ਨੌਂਵਾ ਗੋਲ ਕੀਤਾ। ਕੋਰੀਆ ਦੇ ਲੀ ਸੇ ਯੁੰਗ ਨੂੰ ‘ਮੈਨ ਆਫ ਦਿ ਸਟੀਲ’ ਅਤੇ ਹਯੂ ਸਿਕ ਨੂੰ ‘ਮੈਨ ਆਫ ਦਿ ਮੈਚ’ ਦਾ ਖਿਤਾਬ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਗਿਆ।ਇਸ ਦੌਰਾਨ ਫਾਕੁੰਡੋ ਕਾਲਿਯੋਨੀ ਦੇ ਗੋਲ ਸਦਕਾ ਅਰਜਨਟੀਨਾ ਨੇ ਅੱਜ ਨਿਊਜ਼ੀਲੈਂਡ ਉਤੇ 1-0 ਨਾਲ ਜਿੱਤ ਦਰਜ ਕਰਕੇ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਸੈਮੀਫਾਈਨਲ ਦੀ ਦੌੜ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਬਾਹਰ ਕਰ ਦਿੱਤਾ।ਪਿਛਲੇ ਮੈਚ ਵਿੱਚ ਜਰਮਨੀ ਨੂੰ ਸਖ਼ਤ ਟੱਕਰ ਦੇਣ ਤੋਂ ਬਾਅਦ 4-3 ਨਾਲ ਹਾਰੀ ਅਰਜਨਟੀਨਾ ਦੀ ਟੀਮ ਨੇ ਆਖਰਕਾਰ ਅੱਜ ਟੂਰਨਾਮੈਂਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਪਹਿਲੀ ਜਿੱਤ ਦਰਜ ਕੀਤੀ। ਉਸ ਲਈ ਇਕੋ ਇਕ ਗੋਲ 55ਵੇਂ ਮਿੰਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਕਾਲਿਯੋਨੀ ਨੇ ਕੀਤਾ। ਪੂਲ ਏ ਵਿੱਚ ਨਿਊਜ਼ੀਲੈਂਡ ਨੇ ਚਾਰ ਮੈਚ ਖੇਡ ਕੇ ਛੇ ਅੰਕ ਬਣਾਏ ਹਨ। ਉਸ ਦਾ ਆਖਰੀ ਮੈਚ 9 ਮਾਰਚ ਨੂੰ ਵਿਸ਼ਵ ਅਤੇ ਓਲੰਪਿਕ ਚੈਂਪੀਅਨ ਜਰਮਨੀ ਨਾਲ ਹੋਵੇਗਾ।ਅਰਜਨਟੀਨਾ ਦੀ ਟੀਮ ਮੈਚ ਵਿੱਚ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਤੋਂ ਜੇਤੂਆਂ ਵਾਂਗ ਖੇਡੀ। ਉਸ ਦੀ ਫਾਰਵਰਡ ਲਾਈਨ ਖਾਸ ਕਰਕੇ ਤਜਰਬੇਕਾਰ ਪੈਡਰੋ ਇਬਾਰਾ ਅਤੇ ਕਾਲਿਯੋਨੀ ਨੇ ਜ਼ਬਰਦਸਤ ਖੇਡ ਦਿਖਾਇਆ। ਪਹਿਲੇ ਅੱਧ ਵਿੱਚ ਨਿਊਜ਼ੀਲੈਂਡ ਨੂੰ ਇਕ ਪੈਨਲਟੀ ਸਟਰੋਕ ਵੀ ਮਿਲਿਆ ਪਰ ਰਿਆਨ ਆਚਿਬਾਲਡ ਦਾ ਸ਼ਾਰਟ ਜੁਆਨ ਥਾਮਸ ਐਸਿਪਨੋਸਾ ਨੇ ਬਚਾ ਲਿਆ।ਦੂਜੇ ਅੱਧ ਵਿੱਚ ਅਰਜਨਟੀਨਾ ਨੇ ਕੀਵੀ ਗੋਲ ਉਤੇ ਲਗਾਤਾਰ ਹਮਲੇ ਕੀਤੇ ਅਤੇ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ 53ਵੇਂ ਅਤੇ 54ਵੇਂ ਮਿੰਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਪੈਨਲਟੀ ਕਾਰਨਰ ਮਿਲੇ ਪਰ ਕਾਮਯਾਬੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਮਿਲ ਸਕੀ। ਇਸ ਤੋਂ ਅਗਲੇ ਹੀ ਮਿੰਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਕਾਲਿਯੋਨੀ ਨੇ ਇਬਾਰਾ ਦੇ ਕਰਾਸ ਉਤੇ ਗੇਂਦ ਨੂੰ ਗੋਲ ਵੱਲ ਦਿਸ਼ਾ ਦੇ ਦਿੱਤੀ। ਕੀਵੀ ਟੀਮ ਦਾ ਪ੍ਰਦਰਸ਼ਨ ਚੰਗਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੀ ਅਤੇ ਉਸ ਦੇ ਫਾਰਵਰਡਾਂ ਨੇ ਕਈ ਗਲਤੀਆਂ ਕੀਤੀਆਂ। ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪੂਰੇ ਮੈਚ ਵਿੱਚ ਇਕ ਪੈਨਲਟੀ ਕਾਰਨਰ ਅਤੇ ਇਕ ਪੈਨਲਟੀ ਸਟਰੋਕ ਮਿਲਿਆ ਪਰ ਅਰਜਨਟੀਨਾ ਦੇ ਗੋਲਕੀਪਰ ਦੇ ਵਧੀਆ ਪ੍ਰਦਰਸ਼ਨ ਅੱਗੇ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੀ ਇਕ ਨਹੀਂ ਚੱਲੀ।ਹਾਕੀ ਵਿਸ਼ਵ ਕੱਪ ਦੇ ਅੱਜ ਦੇ ਆਖਰੀ ਮੈਚ ਵਿਚ ਜਰਮਨੀ ਅਤੇ ਹਾਲੈਂਡ ਦੇ ਖਿਡਾਰੀਆਂ ਵਿਚਕਾਰ ਗਹਿ-ਗੱਚ  ਟੱਕਰ ਹੋਈ। ਹਾਲੈਂਡ ਦੀ ਟੀਮ ਤਿੰਨ ਜਿੱਤਾਂ ਕਰਨ ਤੋਂ ਬਾਅਦ ਜਰਮਨੀ ਟੀਮ ਨਾਲ ਮੈਚ ਬਰਾਬਰ ਕਰਨ ‘ਚ ਕਾਮਯਾਬ ਜ਼ਰੂਰ ਹੋਈ। ਦੂਜੇ ਪਾਸੇ ਦੋ ਜਿੱਤਾਂ ਅਤੇ ਹਾਲੈਂਡ ਤੋਂ ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਦੱਖਣੀ ਕੋਰੀਆ ਨਾਲ ਮੈਚ ਬਰਾਬਰ ਰੱਖਣ ਕਰਕੇ ਜਰਮਨੀ ਦੀ ਟੀਮ ਦੇ ਅੰਕਾਂ ਦੀ ਗਿਣਤੀ ਅੱਠ ਹੈ ਜਦੋਂ ਕਿ ਹਾਲੈਂਡ ਟੀਮ ਦੇ ਦਸ ਅੰਕ ਹਨ। ਦੋਵਾਂ ਟੀਮਾਂ ਵਿਚਕਾਰ ਅੱਜ ਦਾ ਮੁਕਾਬਲਾ 2-2 ਦੀ ਬਰਾਬਰੀ ‘ਤੇ ਮੁੱਕਿਆ।ਜਰਮਨੀ ਅਤੇ ਹਾਲੈਂਡ ਵਿਚਾਲੇ ਮੈਚ ਦਾ ਨਤੀਜਾ ਕੀ ਰਿਹਾ?","answer":"ਜਰਮਨੀ ਅਤੇ ਹਾਲੈਂਡ ਵਿਚਾਲੇ ਮੈਚ ਡਰਾਅ ਰਿਹਾ।"},{"question":"หายไม่สบายรึยัง ?","answer":"ดีขึ้นแล้วแต่ยังไม่หาย"},{"question":"Uunku maxaa uu ka samaysan yahay?","answer":"Aqoonteennu inta ay gaadhsiisan tahay uunku waxa uu ka samaysan yahay maatar iyo tamar. Wax kasta oo cuf iyo culays leh, meel bannaana buuxin kara ayaa maatar (matter) lagu magacaabaa. Si kale haddii aan u dhigno, wax kasta oo aad taaban kartid waxaa la dhihi karaa waa maatar. Sidaas awgeed, dhagaxa, ciidda, geedka, dadka, xoolaha, hawada, biyaha iyo wixii la mid ah ba waa maatar. Maatarka waxaa u dhigma, ka na soo horjeeda tamar (energy; enerji). Tamartu ma laha culays meel bannaanna ma buuxin karto. Tusaale ahaan, ilayska iyo codku waa tamar, ma na laha cuf ay meel bannaan ku buuxiyaan iyo culays toona."},{"question":"இந்தியாவில் மத்திய உணவு தொழில்நுட்ப ஆராய்ச்சி நிறுவனம் எங்கு உள்ளது?","answer":"மத்திய உணவு தொழில்நுட்ப ஆராய்ச்சி நிறுவனம்  என்பது இந்தியாவின் மைசூரை தலைமையிடமாகக் கொண்ட ஒரு இந்திய உணவு ஆராய்ச்சி நிறுவனம் மற்றும் ஆய்வகமாகும்."},{"question":"Est-ce que tu peux me raconter une blague ?","answer":"D'accord, voici une blague :Question: Un astronaute qui commet un crime dans l’espace sera-t-il puni ?Réponse: Non car il s’agit d’un crime sans gravité."},{"question":"Ọmọ Ọlọ́run","answer":"Nínú ìtàn, ọ̀pọ̀lọpọ̀ àwọn olórí ni wọ́n ti fún ara wọn ní orúkọ bíi \\"ọmọ Ọlọ́run\\", tàbí ọmọ ọ̀run.Ọ̀rọ̀ yìí, \\"Ọmọ Ọlọ́run\\", ni wọ́n ti kọ́kọ́ lò nínú Bíbélì èdè Hébérù, gẹ́gẹ́ bí orúkọ mìíràn tí wọ́n fi ń pe ènìyàn tí ó bá súnmọ́ Ọlọ́run tàbí ẹni tí ó bá ní ìbáṣepọ̀ tó dán mánrán pẹ̀lú Ọlọ́run. Nínú ìwé Ẹ́ksódù, wọ́n máa ń pe àwọn ọmọ Ísírẹ́lì ní àkọ́bí Ọmọkùnrin Ọlọ́run. Kódà, Bíbélì pé Sólómọ́nì ní \\"Ọmọ Ọlọ́run\\". Bákan náà, wọ́n máa ń pe àwọn Áńgẹ́lì, àwọn ènìyàn mímọ́ àti àwọn ọba Ísrẹ́lì ní \\"Ọmọ Ọlọ́run\\"Nínú ìwé Májẹ̀mú Tuntun tí Bíbélì mímọ́ àwọn ẹlẹ́sìn ọmọ lẹ́yìn Jésù, Jésù ni wọ́n ń pè ní \\"Ọmọ Ọlọ́run\\" ní ọ̀pọ̀ ìgbà. Níbi ìṣẹ̀lẹ̀ méjì nínú Bíbélì, a gbọ́ wípé ohùn kan ti ọ̀run wá, tí ó pe Jésù ní \\"Ọmọ Ọlọ́run\\". Jésù pàápàá fúnra rẹ̀ pe ara rẹ̀ ni \\"ọmọ Ọlọ́run\\", bákan náà ọ̀pọ̀ ènìyàn pè é ní \\"Ọmọ Ọlọ́run\\" nínú Májẹ̀mú Tuntun inú Bíbélì. Wọ́n pe Jésù ni Ọmọ Ọlọ́run, tí wọ́n sì pe àwọn ọmọ ẹ̀yìn rẹ̀ ní \\"Àwọn Ọmọ Ọlọ́run\\".\\" Ní ti Jésù, wọ́n ń pè é ní Ọmọ Ọlọ́run nítorí ipa tí ó kó gẹ́gẹ́ bí Mẹ̀sáyà, (Olùgbàlà Aráyé) tàbí Christ, Ọba ti Olódùmarè yàn. (Matthew 26:63 KJV). Ni ọ̀pọ̀lọpọ̀ ọ̀nà, pípe Jésù ní Ọmọ Ọlọ́run tàbí Messiah ju bẹ́ẹ̀ lọ fún ọ̀pọ̀ àwọn ọ̀jọ̀gbọ́n tí wọ́n ṣì ń ṣe àkàwé àti ìwádìí rẹ̀ lọ́wọ́lọ́wọ́.Ẹ má ṣe jẹ́ kí a ṣe àṣìlò ọ̀rọ̀ yìí, \\"Ọmọ Ọlọ́run\\" pẹ̀lú \\"Ọlọ́run Ọmọ\\", èyí ẹnikejì nínú Mẹ́talọ́kan nínú ẹ̀kọ́ ẹ̀sìn Christianity, àwọn atẹ̀lé Jésú. Ẹ̀kọ́ nípa Mẹ́talọ́kan ṣàlàyé pé Jésù ní \\"Ọlọ́run Ọmọ\\", ẹ̀kọ́ náà ṣàlàyé pé Ọlọ́run àti Ọlọ́run Ọmọ jẹ́ ẹni kan náà ṣùgbọ́n pẹ̀lú àlàyé pé ọkàn jẹ́ Ọlọ́run Baba ti èkejì sì jẹ́ Ọlọ́run Ọmọ. Ẹni kẹta wọn ní Ọlọ́run Ẹ̀mí Mímọ́. Bákan náà, àwọn ẹlẹ́sìn Kìrìsìtẹ́nì tí wọn kò gbàgbọ́ nínú Mẹ́talọ́kan gbàgbọ́ pé Jésù jẹ́ Ọmọ Ọlọ́run, bí ó ṣe wà nínú Májẹ̀mú Tuntun tí Bíbélì."},{"question":"شنو هي اول دوله استعملات الطابع البريدي ؟","answer":"بريطانيا اول دوله استعملات الطابع البردي سنه 1837 من شهر ديسمبر اللي نشر فيها المدير ديال البريد البريطاني السير رولاند هيل واحد الكتاب صغير بعنوان 'اصلاحات البريد أهميتها وقابليتها للتطبيق' واقترح فيه تخفيض الرسوم البريديه للحد الادنى واقترح نظام جديد ديال الرسوم البريديه مقابل الخدمات البريديه"},{"question":"Gumi lawọn ologun n lẹdi apo pọ pẹlu awọn agbebọn, lawọn ṣọja ba ni irọ lo n pa","answer":"Latari awọn ọrọ ti wọn lo n tẹnu gbajugbaja olori ẹsin Musulumi l’Oke-Ọya nni, Sheik Abubakar Ahmad Gumi, jade laipẹ yii, ileeṣẹ ologun ilẹ wa ti ṣekilọ fun un pe ko ṣọ ẹnu ẹ, tori niṣe lawọn ọrọ to n sọ tubọ n ki awọn janduku agbebọn laya, awọn o si fara mọ ẹnikẹni to ba naka abuku sileeṣẹ ologun.Gumi ba awọn oniroyin sọrọ l’Ọjọruu, Wesidee yii, ninu ifọrọwanilẹnuwo tileeṣẹ tẹlifiṣan Arise ṣe fun un, o fẹsun kan ileeṣẹ ologun pe iwakiwa awọn janduku agbebọn to n gogo si i lojoojumọ lọwọ awọn kan nileeṣẹ ologun ninu, wọn mọ nipa bi awọn janduku ṣe n ri ibọn ko wọle, ti wọn si sọ iwa janduku di okoowo nla, tori bi ina ko ba l’awo, ko le jo goke odo.O ni: “Awọn agbebọn wọnyi n ṣiṣẹ pẹlu ọpọ awọn oṣiṣẹ ileeṣẹ ologun ati awọn agbofinro ilẹ wa ni. Okoowo ni wọn jọ n ṣe, bi ko ba jẹ bẹẹ, bawo lawọn nnkan ija oloro to lagbaraṣe maa gba ẹnubode ilẹ wa kọja bi ki i ba ṣe pe owo ti bọ sapo awọn kan?“Niṣe la n fọrọ to wuwo yii pa mi-in-din, ko si daa bẹẹ, eyi n mu idarudapọ wa. Ija ẹlẹyamẹya n lọ ni Naijiria, kaka ki ijọba wa lai fi sibi kan, niṣe nijọba kọyin sawọn janduku agbebọn, ti wọn bẹrẹ si i ran ṣọja si wọn lati pa wọn. Ohun ti mo ri to n ṣẹlẹ nipinlẹ Zamfara ati Niger lo jẹ ki n sọ bẹẹ.Nigba tawọn eeyan ba n sọ pe awọn agbebọn wọnyi n huwa laabi, bẹẹ ni, mo gba, wọn n huwa ọdaran loootọ, wọn n paayan, wọn n jiiyan gbe, wọn n fipa ba obirin laṣepọ, wọn n ṣe oriṣiiriṣii. Ṣugbọn njẹ ẹ tiẹ ti lọ sọdọ wọn wo lati ri ohun toju awọn naa n ri ati laabi ti wọn n ṣe sawọn naa?Tori naa, dipo tijọba fi maa mura kankan lodi si wọn, ti wọn maa doju awọn ọmọ ogun kọ wọn, ohun tijọba apapọ le ṣe to le mu ki ilu rọgbọ ni ki wọn ba wọn sọrọ, ki wọn jọ wo nnkan sọtun-un sosi, ki wọn si lo awọn ti wọn ba ri i pe wọn lẹmii alaafia laarin wọn lati ṣẹgun wọn.”"},{"question":"Resuma o seguinte artigo:  Um jogador da AFL foi acusado de deixar o local de um acidente depois de bater num carro estacionado e não parar. O atacante do Geelong, Brad Hartman, de 20 anos, estava dirigindo para casa no domingo à tarde quando bateu no veículo em St Peter's, na Austrália do Sul, mas continuou a dirigir, de acordo com um comunicado do clube. Na segunda-feira, ele relatou o incidente à polícia depois de discutir o assunto com seu pai. Brad Hartman jogou o seu primeiro jogo para os Cats em 15 de Junho deste ano. Ele foi acusado de deixar o local de um acidente e de não parar no sinal de \\"Pare\\". O CEO da Geelong, Brian Cook, disse que o clube estava desapontado e frustrado pelo envolvimento de Hartman no incidente. \\"Tem havido muitos problemas relacionados com o automobilismo com os nossos jogadores nos últimos anos\\", disse o Sr. Cook. O Brad devia ter lidado com isto de forma diferente, parando e dando os detalhes do ocorrido. O clube ficou \\"frustrado e desapontado\\" com o incidente. O Sr. Cook disse que o clube precisava reavaliar a forma como trabalha com os seus jogadores no que diz respeito às suas responsabilidades enquanto representantes do clube. \\"Vamos nos reunir no próximo ano, quando as pessoas-chave regressarem ao clube, para desenvolver uma forma de avançar neste domínio\\", afirmou o Sr. Cook. O Hartman irá ao tribunal numa data a ser definida.","answer":"O atacante de Geelong, Brad Hartman, ia para casa quando bateu em outro veículo. Ele não parou e continuou a dirigir, de acordo com um comunicado do clube, que disse que estava frustrado e desapontado com tal comportamento."},{"question":"Inona no mahasamihafa hy aolo sy haolo?","answer":"Ny aolo dia entina ilazana tanana tsy misy mponina ela nilaozana elany haolo kosa dia mirenireny na kaodikaody"},{"question":"Jéggal ma","answer":"excuse me\\t"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਉੜੀ ਭੀ ਸੋਰਠਿ ਭੀ ॥ਰੇ ਜੀਅ ਨਿਲਜ ਲਾਜ ਤੋੁਹਿ ਨਾਹੀ ॥ਹਰਿ ਤਜਿ ਕਤ ਕਾਹੂ ਕੇ ਜਾਂਹੀ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਜਾ ਕੋ ਠਾਕੁਰੁ ਊਚਾ ਹੋਈ ॥ਸੋ ਜਨੁ ਪਰ ਘਰ ਜਾਤ ਨ ਸੋਹੀ ॥੧॥ਸੋ ਸਾਹਿਬੁ ਰਹਿਆ ਭਰਪੂਰਿ ॥ਸਦਾ ਸੰਗਿ ਨਾਹੀ ਹਰਿ ਦੂਰਿ ॥੨॥ਕਵਲਾ ਚਰਨ ਸਰਨ ਹੈ ਜਾ ਕੇ ॥ਕਹੁ ਜਨ ਕਾ ਨਾਹੀ ਘਰ ਤਾ ਕੇ ॥੩॥ਸਭੁ ਕੋਊ ਕਹੈ ਜਾਸੁ ਕੀ ਬਾਤਾ ॥ਸੋ ਸੰਮ੍ਰਥੁ ਨਿਜ ਪਤਿ ਹੈ ਦਾਤਾ ॥੪॥ਕਹੈ ਕਬੀਰੁ ਪੂਰਨ ਜਗ ਸੋਈ ॥ਜਾ ਕੇ ਹਿਰਦੈ ਅਵਰੁ ਨ ਹੋਈ ॥੫॥੩੮॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 330 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਭਗਤ ਕਬੀਰ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਵਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਸਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਹੇ ਬੇਸ਼ਰਮ ਮਨ! ਤੈਨੂੰ ਸ਼ਰਮ ਨਹੀਂ ਆਉਂਦੀ?ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਛੱਡ ਕੇ ਕਿੱਥੇ ਤੇ ਕਿਸ ਦੇ ਪਾਸ ਤੂੰ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈਂ? (ਭਾਵ, ਕਿਉਂ ਹੋਰ ਆਸਰੇ ਤੂੰ ਤੱਕਦਾ ਹੈਂ?) ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦਾ ਮਾਲਕ ਵੱਡਾ ਹੋਵੇ, ਉਹ ਪਰਾਏ ਘਰੀਂ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਚੰਗਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਲੱਗਦਾ ।੧।(ਹੇ ਮਨ!) ਉਹ ਮਾਲਕ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਸਭ ਥਾਈਂ ਮੌਜੂਦ ਹੈ, ਸਦਾ (ਤੇਰੇ) ਨਾਲ ਹੈ, (ਤੈਥੋਂ) ਦੂਰ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੈ ।੨।ਲੱਛਮੀ (ਭੀ) ਜਿਸ ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਦਾ ਆਸਰਾ ਲਈ ਬੈਠੀ ਹੈ, ਹੇ ਭਾਈ! ਦੱਸ, ਉਸ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਘਰ ਕਿਸ ਸ਼ੈ ਦੀ ਕਮੀ ਹੈ? ।੩।ਜਿਸ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀਆਂ (ਵਡਿਆਈਆਂ ਦੀਆਂ) ਗੱਲਾਂ ਹਰੇਕ ਜੀਵ ਕਰ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਸਭ ਤਾਕਤਾਂ ਦਾ ਮਾਲਕ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਸਾਡਾ (ਸਭਨਾਂ ਦਾ) ਖਸਮ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਸਭ ਪਦਾਰਥ ਦੇਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈ ।੪।ਕਬੀਰ ਆਖਦਾ ਹੈ—ਸੰਸਾਰ ਵਿਚ ਕੇਵਲ ਉਹੀ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਗੁਣਾਂ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈ ਜਿਸ ਦੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ (ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ) ਕੋਈ ਹੋਰ (ਦਾਤਾ ਜਚਦਾ) ਨਹੀਂ ।੫।੩੮।\\""},{"question":"‘एक चिहान’ उपन्यासका आधारमा दिइएका पात्रको चरित्र चित्रण गर्नुहोस् : रञ्जनादेवी ","answer":"रञ्जनादेवी सहायक स्त्री पात्र हुन् । उनि प्रोफ्रेसर कि छोरी र डाक्टरकी श्रीमती, शिक्षित् एवम् सचेत नारि पात्र, स्वार्थी प्रेमको विरोध, सकारात्मक चरित्र र नारि पुरुषबिच समन्वय हुनुपर्छ भन्ने आदर्श चिन्तन भएकी नारि पत्र हुन् । "},{"question":"Waxaad sheegtaa cuntooyinka miisaanka dhima iyo talooyin muhiim ah?","answer":"Dunida maanta oo waxa ugu badan ee caafimaad ahaan laga cawdaa uu yahay korodhka miisaanka oo la socda qaab nololeedka casriga ah iyo caadooyin cunto qaadasho oo aad loo isticmaalo ayaa ay khubaradu si joogto ah u soo jeediyeen farsamooyin iyo qaab nololeedyo kala duwan oo ay ku talinayaan in uu raaco ruuxa doonaya in uu miisaanka dhimo.Qormadan oo aynu ka soo xiganay Shabakadda Al-Carabiya ayaa Dr. Liza Sason oo ah bare-sare oo jaamacadda New York ka dhigta culuumta nafaqada, waxa soo jeedinaysaa talooyin dhinaca cuntada la xidhiidha oo qofka ka caawinaya iin uu miisaanka dhimo, isla markaana ilaashado miisaanka saxda ah ee caafimaad ahaan ku haboon:1. Cuntada aad jeceshay:Dadka qaar ayaa aaminsan in qofka miisaanka dhimaya laga rabo in uu cuntada aanu nafsadda u ahayn uu cuno, laakiin dhakhaatiir baadhitaanno cilmiya ku sameeyey ayaa ogaaday in qofka oo cuna cuntada uu xiisaynayaa ay ku abuurto farxad, taasina ay ka caawinayso in miisaanka dheeraadka ahi ka dhaco. Sason waxa ay tidhi, “Haddii aad marto nidaam ah in aad cunto cunto aanad jeclayn, natiijadu waa in aad fashilmayso”2. Xaddiga aad cunayso:Xaddiga cunto iyo inta uu le’eg yahay bilaaydhka aad wax ku cunaysaa waxa ay ka mid yihiin aasaaska nafsiga ah ee ay tahay in qofku uu raaco marka u udoonayo in uu miisaanka dhimo. Waxaa waajib ku ah in uu bilaydh yar wax ku ruto si nafsiyan aanu u qawadin, cunto dheregga uun bi’isana uu cuno xilli-cunto oo kasta.3. Ha isku kallifin in aad hudheel cunto tagto:Inteenna badani waxa aynu jecel nahay cuntada hudheellada oo lagu yaqaanno, dhadhan wacan, xaddi badni iyo dufan badnaan, waxa aanay taasi keenaysaa in qofku uu cunto inta caadiga ah ka badan cuno.Khubaradu waxa ay ku talinayaan ruuxa miisaan dhimis ku jiraa in aanu cunin cunto ka badan inta sacabkiisu qaadi karo. Waayo intaas ayaa ku filan in ay jidhka siiso tamarta iyo Kalaris ka ay u baahan tahay. Ruuxa miisaan dhimista ku jira waxaa u fiican in uu cuntada guriga cuno si uu u xakamayn karo dufanka iyo macaanka lagu darayo.Cuntada leh ganka iyo barootiinta:Cuntooyinka ganka iyo barootiinta badan lihi waxa ay sababaan in qofku uu dhaqso u dhargo, muddo ugu yarana 5 saac ahna aanu gaajo dareemin. Sida ay Dr. Sason sheegaysana cuntooyinka qaar barootiintooda ama gankoodu waxa uu ku xidhan yahay kolba sida loo sameeyo, tusaale ahaan baradhada shiilan lagama dhargo, waana ay dufan badan tahay, halka baradhada karsan ay gan badan leedahay, dhaqsana looga dhergo.Cuntada u diyaarsan qaabka loo yaqaanno miisaan ridista Badda 4.Sirtu waa Biyaha:Iska jir in cunista cuntada aad la sugto illaa aad gaajoonayso, wayo haddii aad gaajooto cunto badan ayaa aad cunaysaa. Sida ugu fiican ee aad gaajada u yarayn karto si aanad cunto badan u cunin, waa in aad cabto illaa litir badhkii oo biyo ah cuntada ka hor. Waayo litir badhkii oo biyo ah oo aad soddon daqiiqo cuntada ka horreysiisaa, waxa ay caawisaa in miisaanku dhaco.Hurdo kugu filan seexo:Sida ay caddeeyeen khubaro caafimaad iyo culimi ku xeeldheer cilminafsigu, qofka oo habeenkii waqti aad u dambeeya seexdaa, subaxdiina goor hore toosa, ama qofka oo seexda saacado ka yar intii uu jidhkiisu u baahnaa, waxa ay keentaa cirweyni iyo in qofku uu gaajoodo, waxa aanay taasi keenaysaa in dufan badani jidhkiisa galo iyo in miisaankiisu aad u kordho.Midhitereeniyaanka:Waa cunto samayskeeda ay ku jiraan, Saliid Saytuun, Shumburo, Saladhyo, Tamaandho, Khiyaar iyo khudraddo kala duwan. Waxaana la aaminsan yahay in cuntooyinka walxan ka samaysani ay yareeyaan khatarta wadne xanuunka, una fiican yihiin xoojinta xusuusta, isla markaana ay yareeyaan u nuglaanshiyaha kansarka naaska ku dhaca."},{"question":"Sheeg wabiga shabeelle mesha uu ku dhamaado?","answer":"Wabiga shabeelle waxa uu ku dhamaada mesha la yiraahdo Dhaay Tubaako."},{"question":"من مبتكر شخصية طرزان؟","answer":"إدغار رايس بوروس هو مبتكر شخصية طرزان. إدغار رايس بوروس (بالإنجليزية: Edgar Rice Burroughs)‏ ولد 1 أيلول/سبتمبر 1875 وتوفي في 19 آذار/مارس 1950. تخرج من الأكاديمية العسكرية في ميشيغان  في الولايات المتحدة عام 1895 .ثم أصبح عضواً في فوج الخيالة السابع لكن حياته العسكرية انتهت عندما اكتشف الأطباء خللا في أحد صمامات قلبه فتم تسريحه من الخدمة العسكرية.انتقل من مهنة لأخرى حتى عمل بائعاً للقرطاسية، في أحد الأيام وعندما كان بانتظار صاحب متجر ليبيعه بعض من منتوجات الشركة التي كان يمثلها وقع نظره على مجلة قصص مصورة وبدأ يطلع عليها. ويقول في مذكراته أنه بدأ يفكر بصوت عال قائلاً «إذا كان الكتاب يقبضون ثمناً لكتابة مثل هذه الخزعبلات فإن بإمكاني كتابة خزعبلات احسن من هذه».كانت أول قصصه بعنوان أميرة المريخ وذلك في العام 1912، وفي ذات العام في شهر تشرين الأول/أكتوبر كتب أولى قصص طرزان وحملت عنوان «طرزان الرجل القرد»."},{"question":"Sheeg shinida imisa Indhood ayey leedahay?","answer":"Shinida waxay leedahay shan (5) Indhood."},{"question":"A ina dajin falgore yake?","answer":"A kudancin jahar Kano Nijeriya."},{"question":"હિન્દુ ધર્મ માં વર્ણવેલ ૧૨ જ્યોતિર્લિંગ વિષે જણાવો.","answer":"જ્યારે તમે \\"જ્યોતિર્લિંગ\\" શબ્દ ની સંધિ છૂટી પાડો છો, ત્યારે બને ​​છે,  'જ્યોતિ' અને 'લિંગ'.  'જ્યોતિ' નો અર્થ થાય છે 'તેજ' અને 'લિંગ', નો અર્થ થાય છે ફલસ. આ જ્યોતિર્લિંગોને શિવના જુદા જુદા સ્વરૂપ માનવામાં આવે છે. ભારતમાં 12 જ્યોતિર્લિંગો વ્યૂહાત્મક સ્થળોએ ફેલાયેલા છે, અને સમગ્ર દેશમાંથી હિંદુ ભક્તો તેમની આધ્યાત્મિક યાત્રામાં દરેકની મુલાકાત લે છે. તેથી જો તમે પણ આધ્યાત્મિક યાત્રા પર જવાની યોજના બનાવી રહ્યા છો, તો આ જ્યોતિર્લિંગો સાથે તમારી આધ્યાત્મિક યાત્રા શરૂ કરો જે સર્વશક્તિમાન ભગવાનની હાજરીની જેમ દિવ્ય છે.૧. ગુજરાતમાં સોમનાથ જ્યોતિર્લિંગ૨. મધ્ય પ્રદેશમાં મહાકાલેશ્વર જ્યોતિર્લિંગ૩. મધ્ય પ્રદેશમાં ઓમકારેશ્વર જ્યોતિર્લિંગ૪. આંધ્ર પ્રદેશમાં મલ્લિકાર્જુન જ્યોતિર્લિંગ૫. મહારાષ્ટ્રમાં વૈજનાથ જ્યોતિર્લિંગ૬. ઉત્તરાખંડમાં કેદારનાથ જ્યોતિર્લિંગ૭. ગુજરાતમાં નાગેશ્વર જ્યોતિર્લિંગ૮. મહારાષ્ટ્રમાં ત્ર્યંબકેશ્વર જ્યોતિર્લિંગ૯. મહારાષ્ટ્રમાં ભીમાશંકર જ્યોતિર્લિંગ૧૦. તમિલનાડુમાં રામેશ્વરમ જ્યોતિર્લિંગ૧૧. મહારાષ્ટ્રમાં ગ્રીષ્નેશ્વર જ્યોતિર્લિંગ૧૨. ઉત્તર પ્રદેશમાં કાશી વિશ્વનાથ જ્યોતિર્લિંગ"},{"question":"SLBC හි දේශීය FM ජාලය මගින් පිරිනමනු ලබන ගුවන්විදුලි සේවා මොනවාද?","answer":"SLBC (ශ්‍රී ලංකා ගුවන්විදුලි සංස්ථාව) සතු FM ජාලය දැනට ශ්‍රී ලංකාව පුරා ගුවන්විදුලි මධ්‍යස්ථාන හයක් විකාශනය කරයි. එම ස්ථාන පහත පරිදිය.1. සිංහල ස්වදේශීය සේවය (සිංහල ජාතික සේවය)2. දෙමළ ජාතික සේවය3. ඉංග්‍රීසි සේවය4. සිටි එෆ්එම් (සිංහල)5. වෙළද සේවය (සිංහල වානිජ සේවය),6. තේන්ද්‍රල් (දෙමළ වාණිජ සේවය) සහ හින්දි සේවාවක් ඇතුළත් වේ."},{"question":"Slutför den här frasen: Division I Grupp B i världsmästerskapet i ishockey för herrar 2017 spelades 23-29 april 2017 i Belfast i Storbritannien. Storbritannien vann","answer":"turneringen och flyttades upp till Division I A inför Världsmästerskapet i ishockey för herrar 2018."},{"question":"தமிழ்நாட்டின் முக்கியமான சுற்றுலா தளங்கள் யாவை?","answer":"தமிழ்நாட்டில் மதுரை மீனாட்சி அம்மன் கோயில், தஞ்சை பெரிய கோயில், மாமல்லபுரம் கடற்கரை கோயில்கள், உதகமண்டலம், கன்னியாகுமரி என பல்வேறு சுற்றுலா தளங்கள் உள்ளன."},{"question":"fan la Napoleyoo Bonapat nekkon buur ?","answer":"Nguuru Farãs."},{"question":"Deport kararı kaç günde çıkar?","answer":"Mahkemeye başvuran kişi, sınır dışı etme kararını veren makama da başvurusunu bildirir. Mahkemeye yapılan başvurular on beş gün içinde sonuçlandırılır. Mahkemenin bu konuda vermiş olduğu karar kesindir."},{"question":"வினா:இதை தமிழில் மொழிபெயர்க்கவும்-boot","answer":"விடை:துவக்க்கு "},{"question":"Berikan jawapan untuk teka-teki berikut: Dalam mahkamah berbicara apa?","answer":"Jawapannya ialah kes. "},{"question":"Responda: Na mitologia Romana quem é Telure?","answer":"Deusa da terra ou das colheitas."},{"question":"பெரியாரின் எழுத்துகளிலிருந்து  மேற்கோள் ஒன்றை தரவும்.","answer":"நான் ஜாதி ஒழிப்புக் கிளர்ச்சிக்காரன். இந்திய அரசியல் சட்டத்தில் ஜாதிக்குப் பாதுகாப்பு அளிக்கப்பட்டு இருக்கிறது. ஆதலால் என் எதிர்ப்பைக் காட்ட இச்சட்டத்தைக் கொளுத்துகிறேன்."},{"question":"Consulte el pasaje siguiente y luego responda a la pregunta posteriormente en el mismo idioma que el pasaje:  Joe Elliott propuso el nombre \\"Deaf Leopard\\" que originalmente era un nombre de banda que se le ocurrió mientras escribía reseñas para bandas de rock imaginarias en su clase de inglés. A sugerencia de Tony Kenning, la ortografía fue ligeramente modificada para que el nombre pareciera menos el de una banda punk. En enero de 1978, Steve Clark se unió a la banda. Según Elliott, él audicionó con éxito para la banda tocando \\"Free Bird\\" de Lynyrd Skynyrd en su totalidad. En noviembre, justo antes de las sesiones de grabación para lo que sería un lanzamiento de tres canciones conocido como The Def Leppard E.P., Kenning dejó abruptamente la banda; más tarde formaría la banda Cairo. Fue reemplazado por Frank Noon. Al final del mes, Rick Allen, entonces de solo 15 años, se había unido a la banda como su baterista de tiempo completo. Las ventas del EP se dispararon después de que la canción \\"Getcha Rocks Off\\" recibió un amplio tiempo de emisión por el renombrado DJ de BBC Radio 1 John Peel, considerado en ese momento como un campeón del punk rock y la música new wave. A lo largo de 1979, la banda desarrolló un seguimiento leal entre los fanáticos del hard rock y el heavy metal británicos y se consideraron entre los líderes de la nueva ola del movimiento heavy metal británico. Su creciente popularidad llevó a un acuerdo discográfico con el sello discográfico Phonogram / Vertigo (Mercury Records) en los EE.UU. La dirección original de Def Leppard, MSB, un dúo local formado por Pete Martin y Frank Stuart-Brown, fueron despedidos después de que Martin y Joe Elliott se pelearon por un incidente en la carretera. La banda se acercó a Peter Mensch de la administración de Leber-Krebs, quien los había reservado en una gira por el Reino Unido apoyando a AC/DC. Mensch, quien admitió que había puesto su ojo en la banda, se convirtió en su mánager.  Pregunta: ¿Quién fue miembro de Def Leppard?","answer":"Durante su historia, Def Leppard ha tenido varios miembros. Sus miembros iniciales fueron Joe Elliot, Tony Kenning y Steve Clark. Kenning dejó la banda y fue reemplazado por Frank Noon. Rick Allen se unió a la banda como baterista de tiempo completo."},{"question":"Sino ang unang nanalo sa Pilipinas Got Talent?","answer":"Si Jovit Baldivino ang unang nanalo sa Pilipinas Got Talent noong 2010. Lumahok siya sa kompetisyon bilang mang-aawit at upang tulungan ang kanyang pamilya. Nanalo siya pagkatapos niyang kumunta ng cover ng \\"Too Much Love Will Kill You\\" ng Queen. Pagkatapos niyang manalo sa Pilipinas Got Talent, naglabas siya ng sarili niyang album ng mga song cover, katulad ng \\"Ika'y Mahal Pa Rin\\" ng Rockstar 2 at \\"Faithfully\\" ng Journey."},{"question":"次の文章に書かれている内容に基づいて、少なくとも200語の段落を書いてください。： 新幹線を使って新鮮なかつおをたくさん運ぶ","answer":"JR九州は、新幹線で物を運ぶ実験を行っています。21日の午前、1つの車両を全部使って、鹿児島県から福岡県までかつおなど新鮮な魚を運びました。4tのトラック1台で運ぶことができる量です。新幹線は1時間半ぐらいで福岡市に着きました。昼ごろには、スーパーで刺身などにして売りました。かつおを買った女性は「かつおが新幹線に乗ってきたんですね。今晩かつおの料理を食べます」と話していました。法律が変わって、来年4月からトラックの運転手が働く時間の規則が厳しくなります。荷物を運ぶ会社などでは、働く人が足りなくなって、運ぶ荷物が少なくなることを心配しています。JR九州は「この実験でどんな問題があるかを調べて、これから新幹線で物を運ぶことができるようにしていきたいです」と話していました。"},{"question":"नेपाली संस्कृतिमा परम्परागत पञ्चाङ्गको भूमिका व्याख्या गर्नुहोस्।","answer":"पञ्चाङ्गहरूले ज्योतिषीय जानकारी, शुभ मितिहरू र नेपालका कार्यक्रमहरू एवम् चाडपर्वहरूको लागि सांस्कृतिक मार्गदर्शन प्रदान गर्दछ।"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bapa angkat\\"? Berikan satu contoh ayat untuknya.","answer":"Ia bermaksud orang yang mengaku sebagai bapa dan memelihara kita, walaupun tiada pertalian darah. Contoh ayat: \\"Bapa angkat saya memelihara saya seperti anaknya sendiri,\\" kata Salmah kepada Karim."},{"question":"Qimaynta Cabiraada Jirka?","answer":"Cabbirka jirka waa hab lagu cabiro xajmiga jirka waxaana loo isticmaalaa in lagu fahmo heerka nafaqo ee qofka. Cabiraadahan soo socda ayaa badanaaba la isticmaalaa. Culays: Isbeddelka kuyimaada culayska ilmaha wuxuu tilmaan muhiim ah u yahay caafimaadka guud iyo ladnaanta bulshada. Si kastaba ha ahaatee xilliyada duruufaha gaarka ah waxaa muhiim noqon kara in la cabiro da’aha kale. Jiif ama Joog: Dhererka ilmuhu wuxuu isla beddelaa wakhtiga isagoo ku xiran nafaqeeyayaalka la qaatay iyo sida jirku uga faa’iidaystay.Dhexroorka bartamaha cududda sare (MUAC): kani waa cabbir deg-deg ah waxtarna u leh in lasaadaaliyo carruurta dhimashada khatarta ugu jirata da’dooduna u dhexayso 12 –  59 bilood.MUAC waa aalad baaritaan oo muhiima u ah go’aaminta ilmaha khatarta ku jira xilligamasiibooyinku jiraan. Tusaha cufnaanta jirka (BMI): waa aalad muhiim ah marka la cabirayo heerka nafaqada dadka waaweyn. Cabbirka culayska iyo dhererka ayaa la qaadaa ka dibna waxaa lagu xisaabiyaa tusaha. Isticmaalka BMI ee dadka waaweyn waa mid aan lagu kalsoonaan karin waayo saxnaanta dhererka ayaa waxaa carqaladeeya arrimo da’da la xiriira sida soo godashada lafta dhabarka (spinal curvature).Sidaas awgeed MUAC-gu waa cabbiraadda ugu haboon maadaama ilaa xad aanu ku xirnayn da’da. Barar(oedama): Ururitaanka dheecaanada aan caadiga ahayn unugyada dhexdooda wuxuu tilmaamaa nafaqo-darro halis ah."},{"question":"O que é a Revolução Industrial?","answer":"A Revolução Industrial foi um período de transformação econômica e social que ocorreu no final do século XVIII e início do século XIX, principalmente na Inglaterra. Ela marcou a transição da manufatura manual e da agricultura para a produção em massa, impulsionada por máquinas a vapor, inovações tecnológicas e urbanização. A Revolução Industrial teve um impacto profundo na indústria, economia e sociedade, alterando fundamentalmente a forma como as pessoas viviam e trabalhavam."},{"question":"Чоң Билгич жеңилип калып Китеге барып кандай кеңеш берет?а) Буруттардыжеңе албай койдук Индия канынын Чоң Керги кызы Бурулду алсаңыз Чоңтемир аттуу уулдуу болосуз ошол гана кыргызды жеңе алат дейтб) Кыргыздарды жеңүү үчүн көп кол топтоп аларды амалкөйлүк менен гана жеңүүбүз керек. Өзүңүз баш болуп кайра кол салабыз дейтв) Чоң Билгичтин жаралуу болуп келгенин көрүп, кыргыздарга биздин күчүбүз тең келбейт экен деп Кителер кайтып кетишетг) Сейтекке бир гана өзүңүздүн күчүңүз жетет, бирок кол салуудан мурда чоң атаңыз Коңур-байдын арбагына өтүп өзүңүздүн минген атыңызды курмандыкка чалышыңыз керек дейт","answer":"Туура жообу:в) Чоң Билгичтин жаралуу болуп келгенин көрүп, кыргыздарга биздин күчүбүз тең келбейт экен деп Кителер кайтып кетишет"},{"question":"Sheeg magaca Naadigii u u ciyaari jiray ciyaaryahan Cumar Calasow iyo lambarkii           uu xiran jiray? ","answer":" Ciyaryahan Cumar Calasow waxa uu u ciyaari jiray Naadigii Madbacadda (MBC) waxa uuna qaadan jiray lambarka 10aad."},{"question":"Tanzania ni nchi ya amani","answer":"Tanzania ni nchi yenye uongozi bora na amani"},{"question":"Amfanin Adabin Gargajiya?","answer":"Koyar da tarbiyya: Adabin baka hanya ce da kaka da kakanni ke amfani da ita wajen koyawa yara tarbiya cikin hikima ta hanyar magana kodai kai tsaye ko kuma cikin labari.Taskace al’adu: Ta hanyar adabin baka Bahaushe ya ke taskace al’adun gargajiya.Fito da yanayin zamantakewa: Ta hanyar adabin gargajiya Bahaushe ya ke sanar da jama’a yadda yanayin zamantakewarsa ya ke.Koyar da Fasaha da kuma Taskace ta: Ta hanyar adabin gargajiya na gaba suke koyar da ‘yan baya irin fasahar da Allah ya hore musu, kamar idan muka duba yanayin zamantakewar Bahaushe za mu ga a cike take da darrusa a ko da wane lokaci kuma a ko’ina za ka ga yara suna ɗamfare da manya suna koyon abubuwa.Taskace tarihi da kuma yaɗa shi: Ta hanyar adabin gargajiya ne tarihin al’ummar Hausa ya ke wanzuwa, musamman ta hanyar nan da aka fi sani da kunne ya girmi kaka.Nishaɗantarwa: Ta hanyar adabin gargajiya Bahaushe ya ke nishantar da kansa. Waƙoƙi, tatsuniya, kaɗa-kaɗe, barkwanci, wasanni, da bukubuwa da sauransu, dukkan waɗannan suna daga cikin hanyoyin da Bahaushe ya ke bi yana nishaɗantar da kansa ko dai a lokutan bukukuwa ko kuma a lokacin zama haka kawai."},{"question":"नेपालमा बोलिने प्रमुख जातीय समूह र भाषाहरूबारे छलफल गर्नुहोस्।","answer":"नेपाल गुरुङ, नेवार र तामाङ लगायत विभिन्न जातजातिहरुको विविधता भएको देश हो र यहाँ नेपाली, नेवारी र मैथिली जस्ता भाषाहरु बोलिन्छन्।"},{"question":"Ity fanambarana manaraka ity dia amin'ny teny anglisy, adikao amin'ny teny malagasy\\"Have a nice day\\"","answer":"Mirary tontolo andro mafinaritra"},{"question":"புதிர்:  வெளிச்சத்திலே பிடிப்பதை இருட்டிலே பார்க்கிறோம் அது என்ன? ","answer":"விடை: திரைப்படம் "},{"question":"የኢንፍራሬድ ጨረር  ግኝት ባለቤት ማን ነው?","answer":"ዊሊያም ኸርሽል"},{"question":"قم بكتابة مقال يجيب على هذا السؤال من كان مستشار الأمن في حكومة جارج دبليو بوش ؟.","answer":"وفقا لمكغريفي في كتابه \\"الاعتراف\\"، كانت \\" ذا ريكورد\\" أول جريدة تنشر أخبار العلاقة بين مكغريفي وسيبل. ذكر مكغريفي اسم سيبل بعد ستة أسابيع من بداية إدارته في 14 فبراير 2002، في مقابلة مع هيئة تحرير \\"ذا ريكورد\\" في مكاتبها قائلاً: \\"نحن لن نتهاون في الأمن. جلبنا في الواقع مستشارًا أمنيًا من قوات الدفاع الإسرائيلية، ربما يكون الأفضل في العالم.\\""},{"question":"O ṣẹlẹ! Akeredolu sọrẹnda","answer":"Lẹyin bii ọdun mẹta o le to ti gori aleefa, Gomina ipinlẹ Ondo, Rotimi Akeredolu, ti yi ohun pada pẹlu bo ṣe gba lati bẹbẹ, ko si ko gbogbo awọn tinu n bi ninu ẹgbẹ APC mọra. Akeredolu sọrọ yii lasiko to n ki alaga igbimọ apẹtusaawọ ẹgbẹ ọhun to tun jẹ gomina ipinlẹ Niger, Abubakar Bello, kaabọ si ọfiisi rẹ to wa ni Alagbaka, niluu Akurẹ, lọsan-an ọjọ Ẹti, Furaidee, ọsẹ yii. Gomina ọhun rọ gbogbo awọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ tinu n bi ki fọwọ wọnu, ki wọn si jọ ṣiṣẹ pọ ko baa le rọrun fun ẹgbẹ APC lati rọwọ mu ninu eto ibo to n bọ lọjọ kẹwaa, osu kẹwaa, ọdun yii. O ni idi ree ti oun fi pinnu ati tọrọ idariji lọwọ gbogbo awọn ti oun ti ṣẹ lati ọdun 2017 toun ti de ori aleefa. Alaga igbimọ olupari ija ọhun ni olori iṣẹ ti awọn asaaju ẹgbẹ gbe le awọn lọwọ ni lati yanju gbogbo ede-aiyede to ba wa laarin awọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ patapata ki ọjọ idibo too pe. O ni igbesẹ yii pọn dandan ti ẹgbẹ APC ba fẹẹ jawe olubori lasiko eto idibo naa. Gẹgẹ ba a ṣe gbọ, bii igba meji ọtọọtọ ni Aṣiwaju Bọla Tinubu ti gbe igbesẹ lati pari ija to n waye laarin Akeredolu atawọn agbaagba ẹgbẹ ọhun kan latari magomago ti wọn lo suyọ ninu eto idibo abẹle ti wọn ṣe lọjọ kẹta, oṣu kẹsan-an, ọdun 2016."},{"question":"नेपाली साहित्यका पिता को हुन ?","answer":"भानुभक्त आचार्य (१८१४–१८६८ ईस्वी) (१८७१–१९२५) एक नेपाली लेखक, कवि र अनुवादक थिए। उहाँलाई नेपाली भाषाको पहिलो कविको रूपमा व्यापक रूपमा मानिन्छ, जसको लागि उहाँलाई \\"आदिकबी\\" को उपाधिबाट सम्मानित गरिएको थियो: शाब्दिक रूपमा, \\"पहिलो कवि\\"।"},{"question":"මල් හට නොගන්නා  යන්නට තනි වචනයක් දෙන්න.","answer":"අපුෂ්පක "},{"question":"Qual o nome da filha de Jair Rodrigues, que seguiu a carreira do pai?Luciana MelloWanessa CamargoPreta GilNegra Li","answer":"A resposta correta é Luciana Mello"},{"question":"basic-இதை தமிழில் மொழிபெயர்க்கவும் ","answer":"அடிப்படை"},{"question":"Việt Nam có dân số đứng thứ mấy Đông Nam Á?Chọn câu trả lời đúng cho câu hỏi trên trong những câu sau:A. 2B. 3C. 4","answer":"Đáp án B. 3Giải thích Việt Nam đông dân thứ ba Đông Nam Á.Người dân tập trung tại phố đi bộ Nguyễn Huệ, TP HCM, để xem bóng đá, năm 2018. Ảnh: Quỳnh TrầnTính tới tháng 5/2023, Việt Nam có 99,86 triệu dân, đứng thứ ba Đông Nam Á, theo Worldommeters. Trong khi đó, dân số Philippines là 113,75 triệu, còn Indonesia 281,84 triệu, là hai quốc gia dẫn đầu về dân số ở Đông Nam Á. Xét trên phạm vi thế giới, dân số Việt Nam đứng thứ 15, chiếm 1,25% dân số toàn cầu."},{"question":"ബുദ്ധമതത്തിൽ ആശ്രമങ്ങൾ എങ്ങനെ പ്രാധാന്യമർഹിക്കുന്നു?","answer":"ബുദ്ധമതത്തിലെ മൊണാസ്റ്ററികൾ ആത്മീയ പരിശീലനത്തിനും പഠനത്തിനും സമൂഹത്തിനുമുള്ള നിർണായക കേന്ദ്രങ്ങളാണ്. സന്യാസിമാർക്കും കന്യാസ്ത്രീകൾക്കും ധ്യാനിക്കാനും ബുദ്ധമത പഠിപ്പിക്കലുകൾ പഠിക്കാനും പ്രബുദ്ധതയിലേക്കുള്ള പാതയിൽ മുന്നേറാനും അവർ ഇടം നൽകുന്നു. ബുദ്ധമത വിശ്വാസികളുടെ ആരാധനാലയമായും മൊണാസ്ട്രികൾ പ്രവർത്തിക്കുന്നു, ബുദ്ധമത പാരമ്പര്യങ്ങളും സംസ്കാരവും സംരക്ഷിക്കുന്നതിലും കൈമാറുന്നതിലും ഒരു പങ്കു വഹിക്കുന്നു."},{"question":"Menene tarihin Bayajidda?","answer":"Haƙiƙa almara na Bayajidda shine mafi mahimmancin asalin tarihin ƙasar Hausa. Yana nufin kafuwar Daura, wanda a al'adance tsohon birnin kasar Hausa ne, da kuma karawa da kafa wasu kasashen Hausa da bakin haure suka yi."},{"question":"Inhengo ipi yomuviri inochinjanisa magasi nemhoteredzo? ZVOKUSARUDZA: A). endocrine. B). kutenderera. C). kufema. D) integumentary.","answer":"C). kufema kunoita nemapapu ivo anogona kunzi ma lungs. Panoitwa kuchinjaniswa kwema gasi kana kuti mweya. "},{"question":"Ki lo de tawọn eeyan yii n sọ ominira di inira fun wa","answer":"A fẹran lati maa fi ara wa ṣe yẹyẹ ju. Mo wa ọrẹ mi kan lọ sile nijẹta n ko ri i, nitori alagbara ninu ijọba yii ni. Mo pe e pe nibo lo wa, o ni awọn n ṣe wahala ọdun ominira ọgọta ọdun lọwọ. Nigba ti mo pada ri i, to si sọ iye ti awọn fẹẹ na, ẹnu ya mi. Ṣugbọn mo kuku mọ pe wọn o le na owo to to bẹẹ, wọn maa ko o jẹ ni. Ṣugbọn mo beere lọwọ ẹ pe ṣe ninu ominira la wa ni tabi ninu inira. Mo ni owo ti wọn n na danu yii, bi wọn ba ni laakaye ati inu ti wọn n ro ni, iṣọkan Naijiria lo yẹ ki wọn fi wa, nitori emi ri i pe Naijiria yii o ni i pẹe fọ, ti yoo si pin yẹlẹyẹlẹ.Ko si ki Naijiria yii ma pin si wẹwẹ. Mo woye titi, n ko ri ọna ti a oo gbe e gba. N ko ri i bi wọn ti fẹẹ ṣe e ki Yoruba ma ṣe tirẹ lọtọ laarin awọn eeyan ti a ko tira yii, ti a jọ n pe ara wa ni Naijiria yii, nitori awọn eeyan naa ko fẹ wa fun daadaa rara. Yatọ si pe wọn o fẹ wa fun rere, gbogbo ọna pata ni wọn n gba lati sọ wa di ẹru. Gbogbo ọna pata ni wọn n gba lati mu ki awa ẹya to ku ka maa ṣiṣẹ fun Fulani jẹ. Bi a ba pa owo ni ilẹ Yoruba, wọn aa wa gbogbo ọna lati ko o lọ silẹ Hausa, wọn aa si bẹreẹ si i pin in laarin ara wọn. Ohun to maa waa tete mu ki orilẹ-ede yii fọ ni iru ijọba ti Buhari n ṣe yii, ijọba ti ko sẹni to ri iru ẹ ri ni Naijiria yii ni. Afi bii ẹni pe aditi lọkunrin yii, tabi bii ẹni to ti ku sara ti ko mọ ohun to n lọ ni ayika ẹ ati laarin orilẹ-ede to ti n ṣe olori wọn.Lojoojumọ la n pariwo: awọn ẹgbọn ti wọn ju iru awa yii lọ, awọn ti ko to wa, awọn ti wọn ti ṣejọba ri, awọn ti wọn ti ṣe ṣọja ri, awọn ọmọwe to ti ni iriri iwe ati ti ọjọ ori, lojoojumọ la n pariwo pe bi ọkunrin yii ti n ṣejọba ko dara. Ṣugbọn bi wọn ba ti bu u nidiii eyi to n ṣe yii, ko ni i ṣiwọ nibẹ naa o, eyi to si tun maa ṣe ni iwa ibajẹ mi-in to maa buru ju ti tẹlẹ lọ. N o mọ ohun ti awọn ti wọn n gbeja Buhari yii fẹẹ sọ, n o mọ ohun ti wọn fẹẹ wi si iru ohun tọkunrin naa tun ṣe yii. Boya ẹyin naa o si ti i gbọ. Lọsẹ to kọja yii, ijọba Buhari fọwọ si i pe ki awọn ṣe ọna reluwee to maa gbera lati Kano, ti yoo gba Daura, niluu Buhari funra ẹ kọja, ti yoo si yọ si orilẹ-ede Nijee (Niger Republic). Orilẹ-ede Nijee yii ni ilu ti Naijiria ba paala, nibi ti awọn Fulani pọ si, agbegbe tawọn Boko Haram ati Fulani onijaadi n ba wọ ilẹ wa.Ọrọ naa ki i ṣe ọrọ ti ẹnikẹni gbọdọ rẹrin-in si, ọrọ ti ẹni to ba ni omi loju le tori ẹ sunkun ni, nitori ijọba Buhari yii fẹẹ fi ogun ja wa, ohun ti wọn si n ṣe ye wọn daadaa. Ohun ti wọn n ṣe ni lati ṣi ọna fun awọn Fulani wọnyi, ko ma si si ohun ti yoo da wọn duro lati wọ Naijiria wa, ati lati ri i pe ko sohun to da awọn Fulani ọdọ tiwa bii awọn Buhari yii naa duro lati lọọ ba awọn eeyan wọn to wa ni orilẹ-ede mi-in. Ta ni yoo da awọn Fulani wọnyi duro lati ma wa si Naijiria lati Nijee, boya wọn ko maaluu wa, boya wọn kan n bọ waa ṣiṣẹ, koda ko jẹ iṣẹ aburu ni wọn fẹẹ waa ṣe. Ta ni yoo da wọn duro. Bi ibo ba de ti wọn ba fẹ ki awọn eeyan yii waa dibo, wọn maa ya wọ Naijiria bii eṣu ni, ko si sẹni to le da wọn duro, nitori awa ti a wa ni isalẹ nibi ko ni i ri wọn, a ko tilẹ ni i mọ igba ti wọn de tabi ti wọn wọle.Ọna meji to buru ni nnkan yii ko fi dara. Ọna akọkọ ni ti eto ọrọ aje to mu lọwọ, ifowoṣofo lasan ati fifi owo ti Naijiria ran wọn lọwọ lorilẹ-ede awọn Fulani, ti wọn yoo si maa purọ fun wa pe awọn eeyan naa lo n ran wa lọwọ. Ọna keji ni nidii eto aabo, bi ogun ba ṣẹlẹ ni Naijiria yii, reluwee lawọn Fulani yii aa fi maa wọle, ti wọn aa maa jade. Pẹlu iwa ifẹmiṣọfo to kari aye bayii, ki i ṣe asiko ti Naijiria yẹ ko kọ reluwee lati maa ko ero wa lati Nijee si Naijiria niyi! Nitori kin ni? Anfaani wo lo wa nibẹ fun wa! Ko si aanfaani nibẹ afi ofo nikan! Wọn fẹẹ ko wa lẹru, wọn ko si fi bo fun wa pe awọn fẹẹ ṣe bẹẹ, nitori bi ko ṣe bẹẹ ni, eyi ti wọn ṣe yii, bii baba onile to fi ọwọ ara rẹ ṣilẹkun fun awọn ole ki wọn wọle ni. Ohun meji lo si le fa eleyii, bi baba onile funra ẹ ko ba jẹ ole, aa jẹ agbẹyinbẹbọjẹ to fẹẹ ṣe awọn ara adugbo rẹ to ku leṣe.Nigba ti tawọn eeyan yii kọkọ bẹrẹ, mo pariwo ọrọ naa sita o. Koda, mo sọ fun gbogbo Yoruba to ba leti. Ṣugbọn awọn kan ki mi mọlẹ, wọn bu mi titi, ẹni kan si sọ fun mi pe lori ọrọ ti mo kọ nigba naa yii, niṣe lo yẹ ki awọn DSS waa gbe mi, nitori iwa to le da ilu ru ni mo n hu, ohun to le fọ Naijiria si wẹwẹ ni mo ṣe. Lọdun to kọja lọhun-un ni, nigba ti awọn ti wọn n ba wọn wa epo kede pe awọn n lọo kọ ileeṣe ifọpo kan si itosi orilẹ-de Nijee yii. Wọn ni awọn fẹẹ maa ra epo lati orilẹ-ede Nijee wa si Naijiria, awọn aa si maa fọ epo naa nibẹ ki awọn too pin in si aarin awọn eeyan Naijiria. Mo sọ fun yin nigba naa pe irọ ni wọn n pa, ọtọ lohun ti wọn fẹe ṣe. Ohu ti mo ṣe sọ bẹẹ ni pe arun oju ni, ohun ti ko mọgbọn dani ni ijọba Buhari kede nigba naa, bi ko ba si jẹ wọn ko lọgbọn, a jẹ etekete ni wọn fẹẹ ṣe.Orilẹ-ede Nijee ti wọn ni awọn ti fẹẹ maa ra epo bẹntiroolu yii, epo ti awọn yẹn n ṣe ni gbogbo ọdun kan ko to eyi ti Naijiria yoo fi oṣu kan pere ṣe, mo si sọ bẹẹ nigba naa fawọn eeyan. Bawo ni ibi ti wọn ti n ṣe epo ti ko to ẹyọ kan ninu ọgọrun-un, eyi ti Naijiria n ṣe ṣe waa di ibi ti Naijiria yoo ti maa lọọ ra epo wa. Ẹni to ba ti gbọ eyi aa ti mọ pe jibiti ni, ijọba Buhari fẹẹ lu wa ni jibiti fawọn Fulani ni. Ohun ti wọn fẹẹ ṣe ni lati maa fi ọgbọn gbe epo ti wọn ba ṣe lọdọ wa yii naa lọ sibẹ ni, wọn aa si maa fi ọgbọn ko owo Naijiria jade si Nijee, wọn aa ni awọn ni wọn n ta epo bẹntiroolu fun wa. Loootọ ni ko dun mọ awọn eeyan yii ninu pe ilu Eko, nilẹ Yoruba, ni epo n ba wọ Naijiria, ati pe gbogbo ọna ni wọn fi n wa bi epo bẹntiroolu yii yoo ṣe lalẹ yọ lati apa ọdọ wọn. Ṣugbọn epo naa ko wa, wọn ko ri epo nibẹ, iyẹn lo fa ọgbon buruku ti wọn fẹe da yii.Bo tilẹ jẹ pe ọpọ eeyan lo tun sọ iru ọrọ ti mo sọ yi nigba naa pe ohun tijọba lawọn fẹẹ ṣe yii ko daa, sibẹ, wọn o gbọ! Kinni naa ni wọn n ba lọ yii, oun ni wọn si ṣe ya biiliọnu meji owo dọla sọtọ, ti wọn ni awọn yoo fi kọ ọna reluwee. Ọtọ ni wọn ya owo sọtọ pe awọn fẹẹ fi kọ ileeṣẹ ifọpo yii o, bẹẹ ni ileeṣẹ ifọpo kan wa ni Kaduna ti wọn ko tun un ṣe, ọkan wa ni Pota ti ko ṣiṣẹ daadaa, wọn pa gbogbo eyi ti, wọn ni awọn fẹẹ kọ ile-ifọpo tuntun sitosi Nijee. Ẹ wọ iye owo ti wọn yoo na lati gbe epo de inu aṣalẹ buruku yii, epo ti wọn n ṣe ni Naija-Delta, ti wọn aa kọkọ ru u lọ si Nijee lati lọọ fọ, ti wọn yoo ṣẹṣẹ tun da a pada waa fun wa ni owo gọbọi pe ka ra a, ka si maa ta a fawọn eeyan wa. Ibeere to yẹ ki awọn ọmọ Naijiria beere lọwọ awọn Buhari yii ni pe ki lo de ti wọn ko tun ile-ifọpo to wa ni Kaduna ṣe, ki lo de ti awọn to ku ko ṣiṣẹ, ṣebi ti wọn ba tun awọn yii ṣe, ko ni i si wahala lati maa wa ileefọpo mi-in kiri.Iranlọwọ wo ni ileeṣẹ ifọpo to ba wa nitosi Nijee fẹẹ ṣe fun wa? Ko si! Ohun ti wọn fẹe ṣe naa ni wọn n ṣe yii, lati fi owo Naijiria kọ ilu ati le ati ileeṣẹ fun Fulani nitosi Nijee, ki awọn si fi ọgbọn sọ awọn ọmọ orilẹ-ede naa di ọmọ Naijiria, ọna lati sọ ilẹ Naijiria di ti Fulani ni. Ṣugbọn eyi ko ni i ṣee se. Ko le ṣee ṣe rara. Naijiria yoo yaa pada fọ naa ni. Idi ni pe iran Yoruba ko ni i ṣe eru iran mi-in, ohun to ba gba ni gbogbo wa yoo jọ fun un. Tabi kin ni a ṣe fun wọn, kin ni idi ti awọn eeyan naa fi fẹe gba ilẹ wa ati ohun-ini wa fun iran tiwọn. Kin ni idi ti Buhari di fẹẹ ṣe eleyii fun Naijira! Awọn ti wọn ba sọ fun un pe eleyii yo ṣee ṣe n tan an ni o, nitori ohun ti ko ni i ṣee ṣe ni. Ija naa ni yoo gbẹyin, ogun ni yoo gbẹyin, bo ba ya, onikaluku yoo gba ile baba rẹ lọ. Inira yii ṣẹ n pọ ju, nitori eyi ti a wa ninu ẹ yii ki i ṣe ominira, ninu ide awọn Fulani la fẹẹ bọ si."},{"question":"ما الاسم الذي يطلق على الميتة بسبب السقوط من مكان مرتفع؟","answer":"الإجابة: المتردية."},{"question":"Ọọdunrun simẹnti lawọn to n wa Maruwa yii ji tọwọ fi ba wọn nipinlẹ Ogun","answer":"Awọn ọkunrin mẹta yii, Lawal Bidemi, Ọlalekan Azeez ati Ọpẹloyẹru Kayọde ti wọn n wa kẹkẹ Marwa ti bọ sọwọ ọlọpaa nipinlẹ Ogun bayii. Niṣe lawọn agbofinro ka wọn mọ’bi ti wọn ti n ko simẹnti sinu kẹkẹ ninu igbo kan ni Awa Ijẹbu, iyẹn lẹyin ti wọn ti ji ọọdunrun (300) simẹnti nile ikẹru-si ileeṣẹ simẹnti kan.Ọkan lara awọn oṣiṣẹ ileeṣẹ onisimẹnti naa lo lọọ fẹjọ sun awọn ọlọpaa ni teṣan Awa Ijẹbu, pe oun ri awọn kan ti wọn n ko simẹnti lapolapo sinu kẹkẹ Maruwa. Bẹẹ, ibi ti wọn ti n ko simẹnti yii ko jinna sileeṣẹ onisimẹnti toun ti n ṣiṣẹ.Kia ni DPO teṣan naa, CSP Adewalẹyinmi Joshua, ti ko awọn eeyan rẹ lọ sibi ti wọn ni iṣẹ buruku naa ti n lọ lọwọ, wọn si ba awọn gende ti wọn n ko simẹnti si kẹkẹ loootọ.Ṣugbọn bawọn onimaruwa naa ṣe ri awọn ọlọpaa ni wọn bẹrẹ si i sa lọ, awọn mẹta yii lọwọ ọlọpaa ba.Nigba ti wọn mu wọn, awọn mẹtẹẹta jẹwọ pe ileeṣẹ simẹnti to wa nitosi lawọn ti ji awọn simẹnti ọhun, awọn  tọju ẹ sinu igbo ni. Wọn ni lati inu igbo naa lawọn ti n ko o lọ nipele ipele, tawọn si n ta a fawọn onibaara awọn ko too di pe awọn ọlọpaa de.Apo simẹnti mọkanlelaaadọta (51) lawọn agbofinro ri gba lọwọ awọn eeyan naa, wọn si ri ogun (20) apo mi-in gba lọwọ ẹni kan ninu awọn ti wọn ta a fun. Awọn ọlọpaa ti gba kẹkẹ Maruwa ti wọn fi n ko ẹru ole naa wọgboro lọwọ wọn.Ọjọ keji, oṣu kẹfa yii, lawọn ọlọpaa mu wọn gẹgẹ bi DSP Abimbọla Oyeyẹmi to fiṣẹlẹ naa sita ṣe sọ. O ni ijọba faaye beeli silẹ fun wọn nigba naa, wọn si ni ti kootu ba ti bẹrẹ iṣẹ, awọn yoo ko wọn lọ si kootu.Ṣugbọn niṣe lawọn ọdaran yii ko fẹẹ yọju si kootu mọ, wọn si bẹrẹ si i sọ ọ kiri pe DPO fẹẹ gbowo ẹyin lọwọ awọn ni, ati pe nigba tawọn ko fun un lowo naa lo ṣe gbẹsẹ le kẹkẹ tawọn fi n ṣiṣẹ.Eyi lo jẹ kawọn ọlọpaa wa wọn de ibi ti wọn n fara pamọ si n’Ijẹbu-Ode, ibẹ ni wọn si ti tun wọn mu ni Satide, ọjọ kẹrindinlọgbọn, oṣu kẹfa.Gbogbo awọn to sa lọ atawọn onibaara to ra ẹru ole naa lọwọ wọn ni ọga ọlọpaa nipinlẹ Ogun, CP Edward Ajogun, ti ni kawọn ọmọọṣẹ oun ri i daju pe wọn mu, o ni gbogbo wọn lo ni ijiya to tọ si wọn labẹ ofin."},{"question":"ጥያቄ፡- ከምርት መጠን አንጻር በዓለም ላይ በጣም ተወዳጅ የሆነው ፍራፍሬ ምንድን ነው? ","answer":"መልስ፡- ቲማቲም - አዎ ቲማቲም ፍራፍሬ ነው።"},{"question":"Inona ary izany: vakiana ny vatapaty, esorina ny lamba mena vao tsakoy fa mitera-menaka?","answer":"voanjo"},{"question":"Según una persona que tiene mucha experiencia, la mejor universidad del mundo es la universidad de la vida. ¿Cómo se podría resumir esta frase?","answer":"\\"La mejor universidad es la de la vida\\"."},{"question":"Inty misy fehezanteny:Ry Soa sy Avoko no miasa sy mikarama, ry dada kosa no miakatra isam-bolana handray ny karamany ary tsy mainsy ho toy izany koa no hataony amin'ny karamako. Inona amin'ireto sarin-teny ireto no hita ao amin'io fehezanteny io: fanoharana, fehezan-kevitra mitovy rafitra, tamberim-pototeny, filazan-javatra manao an-tanan-tohatra ?","answer":"Ny tamberim-pototeny avy amin'ny karama no sarin-teny hita ao amin'io fehezanteny io."},{"question":"inona no antsoina hoe \\"lahatsoratry ny literatiora\\" ?","answer":"Ny lahatsoratry ny literatiora dia karazana lahatsoratra izay ny tena tanjona dia ny hanasongadinana ny asan'ny poetika na ara-estetika amin'ny lahateniny."},{"question":" Sheeg Sanadkii La-aasaasey Hay-Adda Caalamiga Ah Ee Horumarinta Mashaariicda (Undp)?","answer":"Waxaa La-aasaasey Sanadkii 1965Xaruunteedana Waxay Ku Taalaa GenevaSwizerland."},{"question":"Isi tempat kosong dalam ayat berikut dengan kata sendi yang paling sesuai: Sambutan Hari Kemerdekaan di Stadium Indera Mulia berlarutan _________ke tengah malam","answer":"Jawapan untuk tempat kosong di atas ialah perkataan 'hingga'. Hingga ialah kata sendi nama yang digunakan untuk menyatakan had masa, waktu, atau tempat tertentu."},{"question":"inona no vola famangiana ny marary?","answer":"soslon-tsiramamy no vola famangiana omena ny marary"},{"question":"नेपालमा उच्च शिक्षाको विकासमा अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय सहकार्यको भूमिकाबारे चर्चा गर्नुहोस्।","answer":"अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय सहकार्यहरूमा शैक्षिक साझेदारी, आदानप्रदान कार्यक्रम, र संयुक्त अनुसन्धान पहलहरू समावेश छन्, जसले नेपाली विद्यार्थीहरूको लागि शैक्षिक अनुभवलाई समृद्ध बनाउँछ।"},{"question":"శివాజీ కోపానికి కారణమేమిటి ? కోపంలో శివాజీ ఎలా ఉన్నాడు?","answer":"ఓడిపోయిన వీరుని సో దేవుడు బంధించి తెచ్చాడు. అతనితో బాటు అతని రాణివాసాన్ని కూడా బంధించి తెచ్చాడు. రాణివాసాన్ని బంధించి తేవడమే శివాజీ కోపానికి కారణమైంది.కోపంలో శివాజీకి కళ్లు ఎఱ్ఱబడ్డాయి. పెదవులు అదిరాయి. బొమముడి కదుల్తోంది. హుంకరిస్తున్నాడు. గర్జిస్తున్నాడు. శివాజీని చూడడానికి కూడా రాజసభ జంకింది. అంటే ప్రళయకాల రుద్రుడిలా ఉన్నాడు శివాజీ."},{"question":"\\"انه جميل وراقي 😙😙😙😍😍❤❤\\" الجملة السابقة تم كتابتها في تقييم فندق. اعط قيمة بين 1 و 5 تتوافق مع التقييم السابق.","answer":"الجملة كانت غالباً إيجابية وتدل على تقييم كامل أي 5 من 5."},{"question":"అనిల్ ఒక పనిని 15 రోజులలో చేయగలడు, సునీల్ 25 రోజులలో చేయగలడు. ఇద్దరూ కలిసి పనిచేస్తే ఎంత సమయం పడుతుంది? ఎంపికలు: (ఎ) 9 3/7 రోజులు (బి) 9 7/8 రోజులు (సి) 9 3/8 రోజులు (D) 4 3/8 రోజులు (E) 9 6/8 రోజులు కొన్ని స్పృహ ప్రవాహం:","answer":"ఇచ్చిన సమాచారం:అనిల్ ఒక పనిని 15 రోజులలో చేయగలడు, సునీల్ 25 రోజులలో చేయగలడు.కావాల్సింది:ఇద్దరూ కలిసి పనిచేస్తే ఎంత సమయం పడుతుంది?వివరణ:ఒక్క రోజులో సునీల్ చేసే పని = 1/25ఒక్క రోజులో అనిల్ చేసే పని = 1/15 ఇద్దరు కలిపి ఒక్క రోజులో చేసే పని = 1/15 + 1/25 = 8/75 ఒక్క రోజులో ఇద్దరు కలిపి 8/75 పని చేస్తారు.'ఏ' రోజులో ఇద్దరు కలిపి పని పూర్తి చేస్తారు అని అనుకుంటే.ఇప్పటి వరకు కనుగొన్నది ఇలా రాయోచ్చు:రోజులు -> ఎంత పని పూర్తి చేసారు 1 -> 8/75  ఏ -> 1  ఏ = 75/8 = 9 3/8 ఇలా అనిల్ మరియు సునీల్ ఇద్దరు కలిపి 9 3/8 రోజులలో పని పూర్తి చేస్తారు.జవాబు: (సి)."},{"question":"Đặt tiêu đề cho đoạn văn sau: Với chuyến thăm sắp tới của Thủ tướng Úc Anthony Albanese đến Philippines, không chỉ có mối quan hệ giữa hai nước được thúc đẩy mạnh mẽ, mà Canberra còn có thêm mắt xích mới trong mạng lưới những liên kết an ninh và hợp tác quân sự ở khu vực Ấn Độ Dương - Thái Bình Dương (Indo-Pacific). Chuyến thăm dự kiến diễn ra vào đầu tháng 9 tới và ông Albanese sẽ là Thủ tướng Úc đầu tiên thăm Philippines trong 20 năm qua.Cho tới nay, Úc đã gây dựng được vị thế ngày càng thêm nổi bật về quân sự và an ninh ở Indo-Pacific. Úc cùng với Ấn Độ, Nhật Bản và Mỹ tạo thành \\"bộ tứ\\" ở khu vực, đồng thời kết hợp với Mỹ và Anh đạt thỏa thuận 3 bên có tên là AUKUS. Canberra cũng thúc đẩy mạnh mẽ hợp tác về quân sự, quốc phòng và an ninh song phương với Washington, Tokyo và New Delhi. Úc còn cùng với Mỹ và New Zealand tập hợp các đảo quốc ở vùng nam Thái Bình Dương vào các mô hình và cấu trúc an ninh chung mới.ASEAN nói chung và các thành viên của khối cũng được Úc hướng đến, nhưng việc gây dựng liên kết an ninh với các đối tác này không đơn giản và dễ dàng. Vì thế, Philippines là đối tác lý tưởng nhất đối với Úc trong chiến lược này.","answer":"Thủ tướng Úc Anthony Albanese và Mối Quan Hệ Đặc Biệt với Philippines trong Khối Vùng Indo-Pacific"},{"question":"ما هي عاصمة بنما؟","answer":"عاصمة بنما هي مدينة بنما.مدينة بنما هي المركز السياسي والإداري والثقافي للبلاد ورمز الحداثة وفن طهي الطعام والتجارة. المدينة القديمة مصنفة كموقع للتراث العالمي. اختيرت لتكون عاصمة الثقافة الأمريكية لعام 2003."},{"question":"Qual é a capital do Vanuatu?","answer":"Porto Vila."},{"question":"‘Ọmọ ti wọn fi ṣe mi laaanu nigba tọmọ mi ku ni Baba Ijẹṣa fipa ba lo pọ’","answer":"Pẹlu bi iwadii tawọn ọlọpaa n ṣe lori ẹsun biba ọmọde ṣeṣekuṣe ati ifipabanilopọ ti wọn fi kan gbajugbaja oṣere onitiata ilẹ wa nni, Ọlanrewaju James Omiyinka tawọn eeyan mọ si Baba Ijẹṣa, ṣe n lọ lọwọ, ọpọ aṣiri lo n tu sita nipa bi iṣẹlẹ naa ṣe waye, ati bi ọkunrin naa ṣe ja awọn ololufẹ rẹ kulẹ.Oṣere-binrin alawada kan, Damilọla Adekọya, ti inagijẹ rẹ n jẹ Princess, lo ṣalaye ninu fọran fidio kan to n ja ranyin lori atẹ ayelujara pẹlu omi loju pe ọdọ oun ni iṣẹlẹ naa ti waye, o ni ọmọbinrin toun gba ṣọmọ lati ọjọ pipẹ sẹyin ni Baba Ijẹṣa ki mọlẹ, to ṣe baṣubaṣu.Ninu fidio tobinrin naa fi sori atẹ ayelujara insitagiraamu rẹ, o ṣalaye hulẹhulẹ ọrọ naa bayii pe:“Mo ti gbọ, mo si ti ka gbogbo ohun tawọn eeyan n sọ nipa iṣẹlẹ yii, mi o tiẹ gbadura pe kiru ohun to ṣẹlẹ si mi yii ṣẹlẹ sẹnikan.“Lọdun diẹ sẹyin, mo lawọn idojukọ kan ninu igbeyawo mi, ọmọ mi ku, ọfọ nla lo si jẹ fun mi, lawọn obi kan laduugbo mi ba ṣeto pe kawọn ọmọ wọn maa waa gbe ọdọ mi, ki wọn le rẹ mi lẹkun, ki wọn maa ba mi ṣere. Bi mo ṣe mu wọn bii ọmọ niyẹn, mẹfa ni wọn, ọkunrin mẹta obinrin mẹta.“Aarin kan ni Baba Ijẹṣa waa ba mi pe oun lawọn iṣoro kan, pe ki n jọwọ, ran oun lọwọ, mo si gba lati hẹẹpu ẹ, emi ni mo sanwo to fi forukọ silẹ fun lẹsinni (lesson) kan ti mo wa fun un, o ṣe idanwo oniwee-mẹwaa nibẹ (GCE), mo si bẹrẹ si i ba a ṣọna bo ṣe wọle si Fasiti Eko, UNILAG.Nibi tọrọ iwakiwa ẹ ti bẹrẹ ni pe, lọjọ kan, Baba Ijẹṣa tun waa ba mi pe ki n tun ran oun lọwọ si i. Awọn ọmọkunrin mẹta to wa lọdọ mi lawọn fẹẹ lọọ ṣere laduugbo, mo si gba fun wọn, ọmọbinrin kan tẹle wọn lọ. Emi, aunti mi, Baba Ijẹṣa atawọn ọmọbinrin meji to ku la ṣẹ ku sile. Nigba ti aunti mi fẹẹ maa lọ, mo sin wọn jade, mo tilẹkun geeti ile wa, mi o si mọ nnkan to ṣẹlẹ laarin iṣẹju mẹta si mẹrin ki n too pada de.Lọsẹ to tẹle e, awọn ọga ileewe tọmọbinrin naa n lọ pe mi lori aago, wọn ni ki n waa wo nnkan ti ọmọ mi n ṣe. Wọn lọmọ naa jokoo sori itan akẹkọọ ẹgbẹ ẹ, lo ba n ṣe bakan bakan. Wọn tun pe awọn obi ọmọkunrin naa gan-an, kristẹni ni wọn. Wọn ni boya iṣoro ọmọbinrin naa ki i ṣe oju lasan, ni wọn ba bẹrẹ si i gbadura.Emi o mọ pe Baba Ijẹṣa ti kilọ fọmọ yẹn pe ko gbọdọ sọ fẹnikan ni, mo ṣaa ri i pe o tun wa sile mi lọjọ keji, lati waa wo o boya ọmọ ti sọrọ tabi ko sọ. Nigba to de, o loun ra awọn eeso kan wa fawọn ọmọ, o ni kọmọbinrin yii tẹle oun lọ sidii mọto toun gbe wa, aṣe niṣe ni Baba Ijẹṣa lọọ ki kọkọrọ mọto bọ ọmọọlọmọ nidii ninu ọkọ rẹ.Lẹyin iyẹn, ko wa sile mi mọ, igbakigba to ba nilo iranlọwọ mi, o maa n pe mi lori aago ni, iyẹn lo fi ba mi lọkan jẹ nigba tawọn kan n sọ pe lati ọdun meje sẹyin ni Baba Ijẹṣa ti n fipa ba ọmọ ọhun lo pọ, iyẹn ki i ṣe ootọ rara.O daa, o ti ṣeṣekuṣe to fẹẹ ṣe, ko si wa sile wa mọ, igba kan to pe mi pe ki n tun ran oun lọwọ, pe oun n ya fiimu kan lọwọ, mo ni ko yẹ ko jẹ emi ti mo fẹẹ ran an lọwọ ni mo maa wa a lọ, ṣugbọn mọ lọ si lokeṣan to loun wa, mo kan kiyesi i pe nigba ti mo de’bẹ, niṣe lo n sa fun mi, o n dọgbọn yẹ mi silẹ, ara ba bẹrẹ si i fu mi, mo n ro o pe ‘ki lo le fa a’.Ohun mi-in ni pe iṣẹlẹ naa ti nipa lori ọmọbinrin naa. O bẹrẹ si i feeli nileewe, mo ni lati fi i si lẹsinni kan. Mo sọ akiyesi mi fawọn eeyan mi atawọn obi ọmọ ọhun, gbogbo wọn si gba pe kọmọ naa ṣi wa lọdọ mi, wọn ni ka maa gbadura fun un.Ni bayii, awọn ọmọ naa ti dagba, inu ọgba ileewe (Boarding House), ni wọn n gbe. Mo waa wo o pe ile maa da bi awọn ọmọ yii ba ti tun pada lọ sileewe, emi nikan lo maa ku. Iyẹni ni mo ṣe pinnu lati lọọ gba ọmọ tọ nile awọn ọmọ alainiyaa, ti emi pẹlu rẹ yoo jọ maa wa ninu ile ti Korona ba kasẹ nilẹ. Eyi ni mo n ro lọwọ, ọmọbinrin naa si wa lọdọ mi, lọjọ kan temi ati ọrẹ mi atoun naa, ta a n wo fiimu kan lọwọ, emi ati Baba Ijẹṣa wa ninu fiimu yẹn, bọmọ yii ṣe ri Baba Ijẹṣa lo poṣe, o si dide laarin wa. Ẹnu ya emi atọrẹ mi, la ba lọọ ba a, igba to pẹ ti a ti n beere ohun to ṣẹlẹ, lọmọ ba jẹwọ gbogbo ohun ti Baba Ijẹṣa ti ṣe.Emi atọrẹ mi pinnu lati wadii ootọ ọrọ lẹnu Baba Ijẹṣa, mo pe e lori aago ẹ, ṣugbọn ko wọle, ni mo ba fọrọ ranṣẹ si i lori instagiraamu ẹ, mo sọ fun un pe mo fẹẹ ya fiimu tuntun kan, mo si fẹ ko kopa ninu ẹ. Bẹẹ niṣe lemi ati mama mi fẹẹ bi i leere ọrọ o.Awọn eeyan gba mi nimọran pe ki n jẹ kọrọ mi lẹrii, ka ma mu un nigunpaa, ka mu un lọrun ọwọ, eyi lo mu ki n pe ileeṣẹ to n ta kamẹra aṣofofo CCTV, kan, wọn si waa ba mi ṣeto ẹ, ọjọ to loun maa wa naa la fi CCTV sibẹ, koda Baba Ijẹṣa ba awọn oṣiṣẹ ti wọn waa fi kamẹra aṣofofo naa sibẹ, o si beere lọwọ mi nipa wọn, mo purọ fun un pe awọn ti wọn waa tun ẹrọ DSTV mi ṣe ni.Nigba tawọn yẹn n lọ, mo tẹle wọn, mo sọ fun Baba Ijẹṣa pe mo n bọ, a ti sọ fọmọbinrin yẹn tẹlẹ pe oun ati Baba Ijẹṣa maa wa nile o, a o ni i pẹẹ pada, koda mi o mu foonu mi jade. Ọmọ loun o le da nikan wa nile pẹlu Baba Ijẹṣa, ṣugbọn a sọ fun un pe ko ma wọri, ko le si nnkan kan.Ba a ṣe jade la ti n wo gbogbo ohun to n ṣẹlẹ nile latori foonu mi-in. Gbogbo inu ile mi ni Baba Ijẹṣa yẹ wo patapata. A ri i bo ṣe n yẹ awọn ile wo boya eeyan ṣi wa nile abi ko sẹnikan. O tun wo ibi ti kamẹra naa wa pẹlu, a o mọ boya o kiyesi i tabi bẹẹ kọ.Mi o le maa sọ awọn nnkan to ṣe tori a n mọnitọ ẹ ni, ṣugbọn nigba ta a ri i pe o dide lati lọ si yara idana (kiṣinni), ta a si mọ pe ko si kamẹra aṣofofo nibẹ, a tete dari sile, a si pe ọlọpaa ba a ṣe n bọ. Awọn ọlọpaa mu un, wọn si bi i leere pe ki lo fa ohun to ṣe, niṣe lo bẹrẹ si i kilolo, to n ṣe ‘ẹm, ẹm, ẹm.’“O dun mi pe awọn eeyan kan n beere pe afi tawọn ba ri fọran fidio naa, mo si n ṣe kayeefi pe kin nidii, ki ni wọn fẹẹ fiyẹn ṣe. Awọn ọlọpaa ti bẹrẹ iwadii wọn, Baba Ijẹṣa si ti jẹwọ, ẹẹmẹrin ọtọọtọ lo sọ pe loootọ ni. Kin ni mo fẹẹ purọ mọ ọn fun? Ẹni ti mo ti n ran lọwọ bọ fun ọpọ ọdun, kin ni mo fẹẹ fi iṣubu ẹ ṣe?”Bayii ni Princess ṣe ṣalaye hulẹhulẹ ọrọ naa ninu fidio oniṣẹju-mẹrindinlogun to fi sori atẹ ayelujara ẹ. Gbogbo eeyan lo si n reti ibi tọrọ yii maa ja si gbẹyin."},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"berbuih mulut\\"?","answer":"Ia bermaksud berleter tidak berhenti-henti atau memberikan nasihat."},{"question":"Келер чак деген эмне ?","answer":"Этиштин келер чагы кыймыл-аракеттин алдыда боло тургандыгын билдирет. Ага эмне кылат? эмне болот? деген суроолор берилет.М и с а л ы: ойнойт, утат, көрөт ж. б."},{"question":"ఇచ్చిన పదానికి నానార్ధాలు ఇవ్వండి: దాహం","answer":"దప్పిక, "},{"question":"Malt bira ne demek ?","answer":"Malt bira, standart biralar gibi üretilen ancak fermentasyon süresi kısa tutulan tatlı, düşük oranda alkol içeren bir bira türüdür. Malta ya da malzbier olarak da bilinirler."},{"question":"अमीर खुसरो याने भारतीय संगीताबद्दल कोणते पुस्तक लिहिले आहे ?","answer":"नूहसिपहर"},{"question":"Olamide","answer":"Ọlámídé Adédèjì tí a bí ní ọjọ́ Kéẹ̀dógún oṣù Kẹta,ọdún 1989 (15-3-1989), ní agbègbè Bàrígà ní Ìpínlẹ̀ Èkó tí ìnagijẹ rẹ̀ ń jẹ́ Ọlámidé Badoo tàbí BaddoSneh, jẹ́ gbajú gbajà olórin hip-hop, ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà. Ó jẹ́ olórin hip-hop tí ó ń akọrin pẹ̀lú àmúlù-ma la èdè Yorùbá àti èdè Gẹ̀ẹ́sì. Ní ọdún 2011, ó ṣe àgbéjáde àwo orin kan Rapsodi lẹ́yìn tí ó tọwọ́bọ̀wé Coded Tunes. YBNL, tó jẹ́ orin ẹlẹ́ẹ̀kejìrẹ̀ jáde lábẹ́ ẹgbẹ́ orin rẹ̀ \\"Yahoo Boy No Laptop\\" tí a tún mọ̀ sí YBNL Nation. Ní ọjọ́ keje oṣù kọkànlá, ọdún 2013, ó ṣe àgbéjáde àwo orin ẹlẹ́ẹ̀kẹta rẹ̀ Baddest Guy Ever Liveth. Orin àdákọ rẹ̀ \\"Durosoke\\" àti \\"Yemi My Lover\\" jáde nínú àwo orin náà. Ní ọjọ́ kẹtàdínlógún, oṣù keje, ọdún 2013, Olamide jẹ́ olórinàkọ́kọ́ tó máa tẹwọ́ bọ̀wé pẹ̀lú Cîroc.A bí Olamide Gbenga Adedeji sí Bariga, Ipinle Èkó, ní ọjọ́ karùndínlógún, oṣù kẹta, ọdún1989. Òun ni ọmọ kejì láàárín àwọn ọmọ mẹ́tẹ̀ẹ̀ta tí Pa Adedeji àti ìyàwó kejì rẹ̀, Ronke Osisanya Adedeji bí. Olamide ní àbúrò méjì, orúkọ ìkan ń jẹ́ TemmyGold ẹ̀kejì sì ń jẹ́ Eniola Olamilekan (tí a tún mọ̀ sí DJ Enimoney).Ọlámidé gbé orin tí akọ́lé rẹ̀ ń jẹ́ ' Ẹni Dúró' jáde lábẹ́ Ilé-iṣẹ́ agbórin jáde Coded Tunes lábẹ́ àkóso ID Cabasa ní ọdún 2010. Ó kẹ́kọ̀ọ́ mass communication ní Tai Solarin University àmọ́ kò kà á gboyè torí owó ìṣúná.Adedeji fẹ́ abábìnrin kan tí orúkọ rẹ̀ ń jẹ́ Adebukunmi Aisha Suleiman. Wọ́n sì jọ bímọ méjì, tí orúkọ wọn ń jẹ́ Maximilian Boluwatife àti Tunrepin Myles. Orin \\"Eni duro\\" ló gbe Ọlámidé sí ipò gíga láàrín àwọn olórin Hip-hop lóríẹ̀ èdè Nàìjíríà."},{"question":"මෙලොව යන වචනයට අදහසක් ගෙන දෙන වචනය ලියා  දක්වන්න.","answer":"මෙලොව යන්නට විරුද්ධ අර්ථයක් ඇති පදය එලොව වේ. "},{"question":"Jelaskan konsep Parlimen di Malaysia dalam ayat-ayat yang tidak melebihi 230 patah perkataan. ","answer":"Konsep parlimen secara umum ialah jarak masa sesuatu kerajaan terbentuk mulai tarikh pilihanraya hingga ke suatu pilihanraya seterusnya manakala konsep parlimen secara khusus pula ialah parlimen merupakan badan perundangan tertinggi yang diberi kuasa menggubal dan meluluskan undang – undang pada peringkat persekutuan. Parlimen akan bersidang apabila dipanggil oleh Yang di-Pertuan Agong. Persidangan Parlimen tidak boleh ditangguhkan enam bulan berselang diantara mesyuarat akhir bagi satu penggal dengan mesyuarat pertama bagi penggal yang akan datang. Parlimen akan kekal untuk selama lima tahun dari tarikh mesyuaratnya yang pertama. Apabila genap lima tahun, Parlimen akan bubar dengan sendirinya melainkan sebelum cukup tempoh ia dibubarkan oleh Yang di-Pertuan Agong. Setelah Parlimen dibubarkan, pilihanraya umum akan diadakan dalam tempoh 60 hari dari tarikh pembubaran bagi semenanjung dan 90 hari bagi Sabah dan Sarawak. Parlimen hendaklah dipanggil bersidang tidak lewat dari 120 hari selepas tarikh pembubarannya. Semua mesyuarat Parlimen disusun dalam satu kalendar yang dinamakan Takwin Parlimen. Kalendar ini dibahagi kepada lima bahagian dan setiap penggal mengambil masa selama satu tahun. Parlimen tidak bersidang di sepanjang penggal tetapi mengadakan mesyuarat sebanyak tiga atau empat kali dalam satu penggal. Setiap satu mesyuarat mengambil masa selama dua minggu bagi Dewan Rakyat, manakala Dewan Negara pula memakan masa selama satu minggu, kecuali mesyuarat belanjawan yang mengambil masa selama lima atau enam minggu. Parlimen Malaysia mengandungi tiga komponen utama iaitu Yang di-Pertuan Agong(YDPA), Dewan Negara dan Dewan Rakyat."},{"question":"ਨਵੀਂ ਦਿੱਲੀ, 26 ਫਰਵਰੀਦਿੱਲੀ ਦੀ ਅਦਾਲਤ ਨੇ ਅਗਸਤਾ ਵੈਸਟਲੈਂਡ ਮਾਮਲੇ ਵਿੱਚ ਅੱਜ ਵਕੀਲ ਗੌਤਮ ਖੇਤਾਨ ਖ਼ਿਲਾਫ਼ ਪੇਸ਼ੀ ਵਾਰੰਟ ਜਾਰੀ ਕਰ ਦਿੱਤੇ। ਖੇਤਾਨ ’ਤੇ 3600 ਕਰੋੜ ਰੁਪਏ ਦੇ ਵੀਵੀਆਈਪੀ ਅਗਸਤਾ ਵੈਸਟਲੈਂਡ ਹੈਲੀਕਾਪਟਰ ਸੌਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਜੁੜੇ ਮਾਮਲੇ ਵਿੱਚ ਮਨੀ ਲਾਂਡਰਿੰਗ ਦਾ ਦੋਸ਼ ਹੈ। ਵਿਸ਼ੇਸ਼ ਜੱਜ ਅਰਵਿੰਦ ਕੁਮਾਰ ਨੇ ਪੇਸ਼ ਵਾਰੰਟ ਜਾਰੀ ਕਰਦਿਆਂ ਕੇਸ ਦੀ ਅਗਲੀ ਸੁਣਵਾਈ 9 ਮਈ ਨਿਰਧਾਰਿਤ ਕਰ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਹੈ। ਐਨਫੋਰਸਮੈਂਟ ਡਾਇਰੈਕਟੋਰੇਟ ਨੇ ਅਦਾਲਤ ਨੂੰ ਦੱਸਿਆ ਕਿ ਇਸ ਮਾਮਲੇ ਵਿੱਚ ਕਥਿਤ ਵਿਚੋਲੇ ਗੁਇਦੋ ਹਸਕੇ ਤੇ ਕਾਰਲੋ ਗੇਰੋਸਾ ਜਿਹੇ ਹੋਰਨਾਂ ਅਪਰਾਧੀਆਂ ਬਾਰੇ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਲਈ ਕੇਂਦਰੀ ਗ੍ਰਹਿ ਮੰਤਰਾਲੇ ਦੀ ਰਿਪੋਰਟ ਦੀ ਉਡੀਕ ਹੈ।ਦਿੱਲੀ ਦੀ ਅਦਾਲਤ ਨੇ ਗੌਤਮ ਖੇਤਾਨ ਦੇ ਖਿਲਾਫ ਪੇਸ਼ੀ ਵਾਰੰਟ ਕਦੋਂ ਲਈ ਜਾਰੀ ਕੀਤਾ?","answer":"ਪੇਸ਼ੀ ਵਾਰੰਟ 9 ਮਈ  ਲਈ ਜਾਰੀ ਕੀਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ।"},{"question":"Skriv en fortsättning till detta stycke - Efter Stora nordiska krigets utbrott 1700 skeppades regementet 1701 över till Baltikum, och deltog i kampanjerna i Polen 1702–1706 och i ryska fälttåget 1707–1709. Bland viktigare fältslag där regementet deltog kan nämnas","answer":"Kliszów (1702) och Poltava (1709). Av den överlevande delen av Södra skånska kavalleriregementet ingick merparten i kapitulationen vid Perevolotjna, men en avdelning medföljde Karl XII till Bender. Regementet nyuppsattes 1709–1710 och deltog senare i fälttåget mot Norge 1718."},{"question":"इन्सुलिन चा उपयोग कोणत्या आजाराच्या उपचारासाठी केला जातो?उत्तर :","answer":"मधुमेह"},{"question":"Akẹkọọ Fasiti Bowen jẹ ẹbun ọkọ ayọkẹlẹ ninu idije arokọ tijọba ipinlẹ Ọṣun ṣe","answer":"Mọto Toyota Corolla ni akẹkọọ kan to wa ni ẹka imọ iṣegun ni Fasiti Bowen, niluu Iwo, Adeyẹmọ Victor Ayọdeji, fi ṣefa jẹ lẹyin to perege ninu arokọ ayajọ ọjọ Ominira orileede Naijiria ti ijọba ipinlẹ Ọṣun ṣagbekalẹ rẹ.Ọdun to kọja ni eto naa bẹrẹ lati fi ṣe koriya fun awọn akẹkọọ nileewe girama ati ile-ẹkọ giga kaakiri ipinlẹ Ọṣun, ṣugbọn ẹbun ọkọ ayọkẹlẹ ti wọn fi ti i nidii lọdun yii tun jẹ ko jẹ ara ọtọ.Nnkan bii oṣu kan sẹyin nijọba, nipasẹ ileeṣẹ to n ri si ọrọ akanṣe iṣẹ ati ibaṣepọ ẹlẹkunjẹkun, ti fi ikede sita lori koko (topic) ti awọn akẹkọọ ti wọn ba nifẹẹ si eto naa yoo kọ arokọ le lori.Lẹyin ti awọn akẹkọọ naa fi iwe kalẹ ni wọn ko awọn igbimọ ọlọpọlọ pipe jọ, ninu eyi ti a ti ri Dokita Lasisi Ọlagunju, Ọgbẹni Fẹmi Ọlanipẹkun, Dokita Temitọpẹ Akintunde, Dokita Fọlọrunsọ Ladapọ ati Dokita Yesooro Ọlọṣọ wa.Awọn ni wọn ṣayẹwo akọsilẹ awọn akẹkọọ yii, bẹẹ ni wọn tun ko wọn jọ lati sọrọ lori awọn koko naa, lẹyin eyi ni wọn si kede orukọ awọn to yege.Adegboyega Abisola Faith lati ileewe Fakunle Comprehensive High School, Osogbo, lo ṣe ipo kin-in-ni ni ẹka ileewe girama, Ọlaniyi Inioluwa Ọpẹyẹmi lati Ambassadors College, Ile-Ife, lo ṣe ipo keji, nigba ti Onwugbofor Happiness lati Our Lady and St. Francis College, niluu Oṣogbo, wa ni ipo kẹta.Adeyẹmọ Victor Ayọdeji ti Fasiti Bowen, niluu Iwo, lo wa ni ipo kin-in-ni ni ẹka awọn ile-ẹkọ giga, Ayọọla Victor Oluwagbemiga lati Yunifasiti Ibadan lo ṣe ipo keji, nigba ti Ademuyi Stella Jesuloluwa lati Adeleke University, Ẹdẹ wa ni ipo kẹta.Ninu ọrọ rẹ, Gomina Oyetọla, ẹni ti Igbakeji rẹ, Benedict Alabi, ṣoju fun nibi eto naa sọ pe iṣejọba oun nigbagbọ pe ti amojuto to peye ba ti wa fun awọn akẹkọọ, alaafia ati isinmi pipe yoo wa fun ipinlẹ Ọṣun lọjọ iwaju.O ni eto naa wa lati jẹ ki ironu awọn ọdọ naa wulo fun igbega orileede Naijiria, yatọ si awọn ọna ti ko bojumu ti ọpọlọpọ wọn n lo ọgbọn-ori wọn si lasiko yii.Oyetọla ṣeleri pe iṣejọba oun yoo maa tẹsiwaju ninu oniruuru awọn eto bẹẹ fun awọn ọdọ nitori awọn ni ogo orileede Naijiria.Bakan naa ni Kọmiṣanna fun ọrọ iṣẹ akanṣe ati ibaṣepọ ẹlẹkunjẹkun, Ọnarebu Lekan Badmus, dupẹ pupọ lọwọ gomina fun bi ko ṣe kaaarẹ ninu igbelarugẹ awọn ọdọ kaakiri ipinlẹ Ọṣun.Badmus ṣalaye pe iwuri lo jẹ lati ri i pe awọn akẹkọọ bii ẹẹdẹgbẹrin ni wọn kopa ninu arokọ naa kaakiri awọn ileewe aladaani ati tijọba bii mẹrinlelọgbọn lorileede yii.O ni erongba eto naa ni lati jẹ ki awọn akẹkọọ yii tubọ nifẹẹ si iwe kika ati kikọ lọna ti wọn yoo fi maa ronu jinlẹ ninu ohun gbogbo to n lọ lorileede Naijiria, ti yoo si maa mura lọdọọdun lati fakọyọ.Racheal Adebimpe Ṣowade Foundation lo gbe ọkọ ayọkẹlẹ naa pẹlu oniruuru awọn mi-in kalẹ fun ẹni to fakọyọ, nigba tijọba ipinlẹ Ọṣun atawọn eeyan mi-in naa gbe ẹbun owo nla kalẹ fun awọn oloriire ọmọ naa."},{"question":"¿Donde está ubicado Rionegro Antioquía?","answer":"Está localizado en el valle de San Nicolás o también llamado Altiplano del Oriente, en la subregión Oriente, siendo la ciudad con mayor población y la que concentra el movimiento económico de la subregión. Está ubicada a tan solo 35 minutos de Medellín, capital del departamento, gracias al túnel de interconexión Aburrá-Oriente. Su nombre oficial es Ciudad Santiago de Arma de Rionegro"},{"question":"Miposaka any andrefana ve ny masoandro?","answer":"Tsia"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਆਸਾ ਮਹਲਾ ੪ ॥ਜਨਮੁ ਪਦਾਰਥੁ ਪਾਇ ਨਾਮੁ ਧਿਆਇਆ ॥ਗੁਰ ਪਰਸਾਦੀ ਬੁਝਿ ਸਚਿ ਸਮਾਇਆ ॥੧॥ਜਿਨੑ ਧੁਰਿ ਲਿਖਿਆ ਲੇਖੁ ਤਿਨੑੀ ਨਾਮੁ ਕਮਾਇਆ ॥ਦਰਿ ਸਚੈ ਸਚਿਆਰ ਮਹਲਿ ਬੁਲਾਇਆ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਅੰਤਰਿ ਨਾਮੁ ਨਿਧਾਨੁ ਗੁਰਮੁਖਿ ਪਾਈਐ ॥ਅਨਦਿਨੁ ਨਾਮੁ ਧਿਆਇ ਹਰਿ ਗੁਣ ਗਾਈਐ ॥੨॥ਅੰਤਰਿ ਵਸਤੁ ਅਨੇਕ ਮਨਮੁਖਿ ਨਹੀ ਪਾਈਐ ॥ਹਉਮੈ ਗਰਬੈ ਗਰਬੁ ਆਪਿ ਖੁਆਈਐ ॥੩॥ਨਾਨਕ ਆਪੇ ਆਪਿ ਆਪਿ ਖੁਆਈਐ ॥ਗੁਰਮਤਿ ਮਨਿ ਪਰਗਾਸੁ ਸਚਾ ਪਾਈਐ ॥੪॥੧੩॥੬੫॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 369 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਰਾਮਦਾਸ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਸਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਮਨੁੱਖਾਂ ਨੇ ਕੀਮਤੀ ਮਨੁੱਖਾ ਜਨਮ ਹਾਸਲ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਿਆ, ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਨਾਲ (ਉਹ ਮਨੁੱਖਾ ਜਨਮ ਦੀ ਕਦਰ) ਸਮਝ ਕੇ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਵਿਚ ਲੀਨ ਹੋ ਗਏ ।੧।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਉਹਨਾਂ ਮਨੁੱਖਾਂ ਨੇ ਹੀ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦਾ ਕਮਾਈ ਕੀਤੀ ਹੈ ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੇ ਮੱਥੇ ਉੱਤੇ ਧੁਰ ਦਰਗਾਹ ਤੋਂ ਇਹ ਕਮਾਈ ਕਰਨ ਦਾ ਲੇਖ ਲਿਖਿਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ ਉਹ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੁੂ ਦੇ ਦਰ ਤੇ ਸੁਰਖ਼ਰੂ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਹਨ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਹਜ਼ੂਰੀ ਵਿਚ ਸੱਦਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ (ਆਦਰ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈ) ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ ।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਨਾਮ-ਖ਼ਜ਼ਾਨਾ ਹਰੇਕ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਮੌਜੂਦ ਹੈ, ਪਰ ਇਹ ਲੱਭਦਾ ਹੈ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਪਿਆਂ (ਇਸ ਵਾਸਤੇ) ਹਰ ਰੋਜ਼ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰ ਕੇ (ਆਉ, ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਗੁਣ ਗਾਂਦੇ ਰਹੀਏ ।੨।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਨਾਮ-ਪਦਾਰਥ ਹਰੇਕ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਹੈ (ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਵਾਲੇ) ਅਨੇਕਾਂ (ਗੁਣ) ਹਰੇਕ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਹਨ, ਪਰ ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਦੇ ਪਿੱਛੇ ਤੁਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਕੁਝ ਭੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਲੱਭਦਾ ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਦੇ ਪਿੱਛੇ ਤੁਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਆਪਣੀ ਹਉਮੈ ਦੇ ਕਾਰਨ (ਆਪਣੀ ਸੂਝ-ਬੂਝ ਦਾ ਹੀ) ਅਹੰਕਾਰ ਕਰਦਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, (ਤੇ ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ) ਆਪ ਹੀ (ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਤੋਂ) ਵਿਛੁੜਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।੩।ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! ਮਨਮੁਖ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਸਦਾ ਆਪ ਹੀ (ਆਪਣੀ ਹੀ ਮਨਮੁਖਤਾ ਦੇ ਕਾਰਨ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਤੋਂ ਵਿੱਛੁੜਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ । ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਮਤਿ ਤੇ ਤੁਰਿਆਂ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਚਾਨਣ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤੇ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਮਿਲ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੪।੧੩।੬੪।\\""},{"question":"வினா: இந்தியாவின் மிகப்பெரிய நன்னீர் ஏரி எது?","answer":"விடை:  இந்தியாவின் மிகப்பெரிய நன்னீர் ஏரி 'வுலர் ஏரி' ஆகும்."},{"question":"කියබු, කියම්බු, කියඹු, සහ කියුඹු: අක්ෂර වින්‍යාස හතරක් සහ අර්ථ පහක්","answer":"0. සාරාංශය“කියබු”, සහ “කියම්බු” යන ස්වරූපවලින් අටවන සියවසේ සිට සීගිරි ගීවල හමු වී, පසුව කියඹු ලෙස සිංහල බසේ යෙදෙන සුළු වශයෙන් වුනත් කව්මිණි කොඬොල ටී. ඇස්. ධර්මබන්ධු සංස්කරණය සහ ඒ. පී. සොයිසාගේ ධර්මසමය ශබ්දකෝෂය වැනි මූලාශ්‍ර කිහිපයක පමණක් “කියුඹු” ලෙසත් යෙදෙන වචනය, සිංහලේ නිෂ්පන්න වචනයක් ලෙස සැලකිය හැක්කේ එම ස්වරූපයේ වචනයක් සංස්කෘත, පාලි, දෙමළ ආදී සිංහලට වචන ආ අනික් භාෂාවලින් සොයා ගත නො හැකි නිසා. මීට සමාන සංස්කෘත පදය වන්නේ අලක अलक යන්න.මෙම වචනයේ අර්ථ පහක් නිඝණ්ටු, ශබ්දකෝෂ, සහ භාවිතය ඇසුරෙන් හඳුනා ගන්න පුළුවන්. ඉන් පළමු අර්ථය වන්නේ කාන්තාවන්ගේ නළලතට හෝ කොපුල් තලයට වැටෙන සේ, කෙටි කර කපා හෝ නො කපා, රැළි සහිතව වකුටු කොට හෝ එසේ නොකොට, සැදූ ඉස කෙස් රොද කියන එක. මෙයට භාවිතයේ දී පෙම් රැල්ල නොහොත් Kiss curl ලෙසත් යෙදෙනවා. මෙම අර්ථය තහවුරු කරන ව්‍යාඛ්‍යාන කරුවකු වන්නේ මකුළුදූවේ පියරතන හිමි. දෙවන අර්ථය වන්නේ අලංකාරය සඳහා නළල දෙ පසින් හෝ කණ දෙ පසින් හෝ දෙකොපුල් මතින්, කන් ගොටු ‍දෙක අඩක් මුවා වන සේ උර හිස තෙක් හෝ බෙල්ල තෙක් හෝ පියොවුරු තෙක් සිරුරෙහි ඉදිරිපස දෙ පසෙහි හෙළනා, මුතු සහ කොඳ කැකුළු, කුන්ද, සින්ධුවාර, නිකමල්, මීපුප් ආදී මල් යොදා සරසා, වකුටු ව ගොතා සැකසූ කෙස් වැල කියන එක. මෙසේ ගොතන ලද කියඹු ලිහෙන බවක් ද කුලරත්න ආරියවංශ ගී පද රචනයක ඇති “කියඹු වැල් ලිහී ඔබේ” යන්න අනුව පෙනෙනවා. වැලිවිටියේ සෝරත, මුනිදාස කුමාරතුංග, රැ. තෙන්නකෝන්, කේ. ජී. ප්‍රේමරත්න වැනි බහුතර ව්‍යාඛ්‍යාන කරුවන් මෙම අර්ථය තහවුරු කරන්නේ සංස්කෘත ශ්ලොකවල අලක යන්න මෙසේ විස්තර කර ඇති නිසා කියඹු යන්න අලක යන්නට සමානව සිංහලේ යොදා ඇති බවට ඔවුන් සලකන නිසාත් බව පේනවා. තුන් වන අර්ථයක් ලෙස හිස පිටුපසට කර ගොතන ලද කෙස් (Hair platted and tucked up behind the head) යන්න ක්ලව් ශබ්දකෝෂය ආදී මූලාශ්‍ර දෙකක් දෙතත් මෙම අර්ථය කෙතෙක් දුරට නිවැරදි ද යන්න සැක සහිතයි. හතර වන අර්ථයක් ලෙස කොණ්ඩයට ම හෙවත් කේශ කලාපය, වරල, ඉස කෙස්, යන්නට ම යෙදෙන වචනයක් ලෙසත් කියඹු යෙදෙනවා. මෙම අර්ථය සියලු ම නිඝණ්ටුවලින් තහවුරු වෙනවා. පස් වන සහ පොදුවේ පිළිනොගැනෙන අර්ථය වන්නේ 1838 මාතර සරණපාල හිමියන්ගේ හෙලදිව් අබිදානවත නිඝණ්ටුවෙහි පමණක් එන “කියඹු = නළල” යන්නයි. කියඹුව, කියඹු ලතාව, කියඹු ලිය, කියඹු වැල්, යන වචන එකම දෙයටත් කියඹු වැළවරලූ යන්න කියඹු වැල සහ කෙහෙකළඹ යන්නටත් යෙදෙනවා.0.1. කියුඹු යන පදයෙහි විවිධ අක්ෂර වින්‍යාස හතරක්1. කියබු = සීගිරි ගීවල 8 වන සියවසේ සිට යෙදුණු මුල් ස්වරූප දෙකෙන් එකක් (ධර්මසමය; සුමංගල - හිස කෙස්; සිරිමල් රණවැල්ල - සෙල්ලිපි අකාරාදිය සීගිරි ගී පරණවිතාන 258, 377)2. කියම්බු, කියම්බු වැළ = සීගිරි ගීවල 8 වන සියවසේ සිට යෙදුණු මුල් ස්වරූප දෙකෙන් එකක් (සී. 364, 380 හිස කෙස් - සී. 364 හිස කෙස් රොද - සීගිරි ගී පරණවිතාන - සිරිමල් රණවැල්ල - සෙල්ලිපි අකාරාදිය)3. කියඹු = සුලබ ව යෙදෙන සහ අති බහුතර ශබ්දකෝෂ පිළිගත් අක්ෂර වින්‍යාසය.4. කියුඹු = අඩු වශයෙන් යෙදෙන -උදා: මකුළුදූවේ පියරතන කව්මිණි කොඬොල සංස්කරණය, ටී. ඇස්. ධර්මබන්ධු සරස්වතී සහ ඒ. පී. සොයිසා ධර්මසමය ශබ්දකෝෂයට පමණක් ඇතුළත් කළ- අක්ෂර වින්‍යාසය.සංස්කෘත = අලක.අමරකෝෂයේ 628 ශ්ලෝකය “අලකාශ්මීර්‍ණකුන්තලාඃ”(තවෘන්දෙ) කෛශිකං කෛශ්‍ය - හිස කෙස් රැස Head of hairමලකාශ වුර්ණ කුන්තලාඃ - කියඹු වැල Curls(තෙලලාටෙ) භ්‍රමරකාඃ - කියඹු වැල නළලෙහි වූයේ Curls on the foreheadකාක පක්ෂඃ ශිඛණ්ඩකඃ - කුඩුම්බිය Locks left at the tonsureත්වාන්දේ කෛශිකං කෛශ්‍යම’ලකාශ් චුර්ණි කුන්තලාඃතෙ ලලාට භ්‍රමරකාඃ කාක පක්ෂඃ ශිඛණ්ඩකඃ.0.2. කියඹු යන පදයෙහි අර්ථ පහක්1. ස්ත්‍රීන්ගේ නළලතට හෝ කොපුල් තලයට වැටෙන සේ සැදූ කෙස් රොද, අලකාවලිය - curl or lock or plait of hair on the forehead or temples; කපා නළලට වැටෙන්න සැලැස්වූ ඉස කෙස් රොද; ස්ත්‍රීන්ගේ නළල දෙපැත්තේ පිහිටි අග කපා හෝ නො කපා වකුටු කොට නළලට හෙළන ලද කෙස් රොද, පෙර යෙදුම්: කුස දා කව “නොයෙක් රුවින් දිසි එළඳගෙ සිරි වත උදක් කියඹු වැල යුතු පටු නළලත''; කුරු ඉස කෙස් වැටිය, කුරු වූ ඉසකේ වැටිය, වකුටු කෙස් රොද - plait of curly hair; නළලට වැටෙන ලෙස කොට කර කැපූ ඉස කෙස් වැටිය - hair cut short to fall to the forehead; පෙම් රැල්ල Kiss curl = a small curl of hair trained to lie flat on the forehead, at the nape of the neck, or in front of the ear. North American term spit curl; beaucatcher, A small flat curl worn on the temple by women; කියුඹු - නළලට වැටෙන සේ කොට කර කැපූ රැළි සහිත කෙස් රොදට නමි. මකුළුදූවේ පියරතන - දහම් සොඬ කව; නළලත්හි සුන් කෙස වේ. (රජයේ සිංහල මහා ශබ්දකෝෂය / රජයේ සංක්ෂිප්ත / ගුණසේන මහා සිංහල / Charles Carter; හරිස්චන්ද්‍ර විජයතුංග; සරසවි සිංහල-සිංහල ශබ්දකෝෂය; ක්ලව්; ධර්මසමය; ශබ්දාර්ථ රත්නාකාරය - බෝරුග්ගමුවේ රේවත; මධුර; සුමංගල ශබ්දකෝෂය දෙන පෙර යෙදුම් - කව්සිළුමිණ 1946 සෝරත පිට 38, ජාතක අටුවා ගැටපදය ජයතිලක පිට 116 පෙළ 20, රුවන් මල් නිඝණ්ටුව විජේසේකර 491 පද්‍ය;)2. නළල දෙ පසින් බෙල්ල තෙක් වැටෙනා මුතු සහ මල් යොදා සරසන කෙස් රොද; ස්ත්‍රීන්ගේ කර්ණාන්තයෙහි ගොතන කෙස් රොද; “කියඹු නිකම්ම හෝ මල් සමග රැළි සැකසෙන සේ ගොතනු ලැබේ.” “කියඹු වැල් යනු කාන්තාවන්ගේ කණ දෙ පසින් ළැම පෙදෙස දෙසට,පහළට වැටෙනා සේ ගොතා සැකසූ කෙස් වැලකි.”; කියඹු - නළල දෙ පසෙහි ගෙතුණු කෙස් රොද මේ නමින් ගැනේ. සංස්කෘතයෙහි මෙයට නම් අලක යනු යි. මෙය කුන්ද - සින්ධුවාරාදි කුසුමයෙන් සරසනු සිරිති - මුනිදාස කුමාරතුංග - මුවදෙව් දා විවරණය, පිට 136 - සාක්ෂි පිණිස “චුම්බනාදලක” නම් කාලිදාස ශ්ලෝකය ඉදිරිපත් කරයි; මුතු කුසුම් ආදියෙන් ගොතා ඉදිරි දෙ පසෙහි හෙළන කෙස් රොද ‘කියඹු’ නමි - මුනිදාස කුමාරතුංග - සසදා විවරණය; කොපුලින්, තන මඬලෙහි වැටෙන්නා වූ, වකුටු වූ කියඹුව, සිසි බිඹුයෙන්, මෙරුයයෙහි, එල්බෙන්නා වූ, නයකු මෙන්, දිසේ. මෙයින් කියඹු වැළෙහි දිග මැන ගත හැකි වේ. කොහි සිටැ කොයි දෙසින් කොයිට යේ දැයි ද මැනවින් මැ හැඟවෙයි. කාලිදාසයෝ කියඹු මුතු ලා කොඳ කැකුළු ලා ගොතනු ලබන බව කියත්. ‘මුක්තාජාලග්රලථිතමලකං’ [ මුතු දැලින් ගොතන ලද අලකා ඇති.] ‘අ‍ලකෙ බාලකුන්දානුවිද්ධං’ [ කියඹුයෙහි තරුණ කුන්දයෙන් අනුවිදුනා ලද.] මුනිදාස කුමාරතුංග - සසදා විවරණය; කියඹු - නළලට වැටෙන සේ ගොතා හෙළූ කෙස් රොද මෙ නම් වේ. සංස්කෘතයෙහි ‘අලකා’ යනු නමි. මුනිදාස කුමාරතුංග - මයුර සන්දේශය; “අලකාශ්මීර්‍ණකුන්තලාඃ’” යනු අමරකෝෂය යි. ස්ත්‍රීන් අලංකරණය පිණිස ‘නිකමල්’ ‘මී මල්’ යොදා කියුඹු සදන බව කාව්‍යයෙහි ප්‍රසිද්ධ යි. - වැලිවිටියේ සෝරත - කව්සිළුමිණ; ‘මිහිසිඳුවර’ යනු මී මල් හා නිකමල්ය. අඟනෝ එයින් කියඹු සරසති. ඒ බව ගුරුළුගෝමී හුද “මීසිඳුවරින් කියඹුලිය සදා” (ධර්මප්‍රදීපිකාව 54) යනුවෙන් කීහ. වැලිවිටියේ සෝරත - කව්සිළුමිණ; ‘කියඹු’ යනු ගැහැණුන්ගේ නළල දෙ පසෙහි කොට කර කැපූ නොහොත් මුතුහර, කොඳ කැකුළු, මීපුප්, නිකමල් ආදිය දමා ගෙතූ කෙස්රොද යි. “අලකාශ්මීර්‍ණකුන්තලාඃ’” යනු අමරකෝෂ යි. ස්ත්‍රීන් අලංකරණය පිණිස ‘නිකමල්’ ‘මී මල්’ යොදා කියුඹු සදන බව කාව්‍යයෙහි ප්‍රසිද්ධ යි. - වැලිවිටියේ සෝරත - කව්සිළුමිණ; කියඹු වැළ හෙවත් අලකාවලිය, කන් ගොටු ‍දෙක අඩක් මුවා වන සේ උර හිස තෙක් වැටෙන්නට ගොතා හෙළූ කෙස් රොදයි. එහි මල් හෝ මුතු හෝ ගැවසීම් කැරේ. කියඹු වැළි = කීයඹු වැළ ඇති. රැ. තෙන්නකෝන් -කෝකිල සන්දේශය; කියඹූ වැළ නම් දෙ කොපොල වසා පියොවුරු තෙක් වැටෙන මුතු මල් ආදියෙන් සරසන ලද කෙස් රොදයි. රැ. තෙන්නකෝන් - කෝකිල සන්දේශය; ඔවුන් ගේ අලකා වැළ මුහුණට වැටෙයි (පලග හුණු මුහුණු?). අලකාව නම් ඉදිරි පිට දෙපැත්තේ හෙළන, මලින් මුතුයෙන් සෑදූ කෙස් රොද දෙකයි. ‘කියඹු’ වැළ යනු ද මීට මැ නමෙකි. “කියඹු වතළ දළ කැළලොතළ සේකර” යැයි මියුරු අසුන් කරුවන් කීයේ එ හෙයිනි. මෙය දෙ කොපොල පහසිමින් පියොවුරු මතට වැටෙන සේ හෙළුව බව “ස්තනාහෝගේ පතන් භාති කපොලාත් කුටිලෝලඃ ශශාංකබිම්බතෝ මේරෞ ලම්බමාන ඉවෝරගඃ - කොපොලින් තන මඬලෙහි වැටෙන්නා වූ වක් හෙවත් වැකැටි ගැසුණු අලකාව සිසි බිඹුයෙන් මේරුයෙහි එල්ලෙන නයකු සේ පෙනේ” යන්නෙන් පළ වෙයි. මුහුණ සඳ මෙනි, නළල් තලයට අලකා රොද වැටුණා ම මුහුණේ පසක් වැසෙනුයෙන්, අඩක් රාහුට අසු වූ සඳ මෙන් එය පෙනේ. රැ. තෙන්නකෝන් - කෝකිල සන්දේශය; “මිසිඳුවරින් කියඹුලිය සදා” ධර්මප්‍රදීපිකාව; කියඹු වැල් ලිහී ඔබේ - කුලරත්න ආරියවංශ; අලක - අලංකාරය සඳහා කන අගින් නවා පහතට හෙළන කෙස් රොද. මෙයට කියඹු වැල යයි ද කියනු ලැබේ. කන අක් අලක රොද මුතු පටකින් ගොතා බැඳ ගෙන. කේ. ජී. ප්‍රේමරත්න - ගිරා සන්දේශය (රජයේ සංක්ෂිප්ත; සරස්වතී අකාරාදිය - ටී ඇස් ධර්මබන්ධු; ධර්මසමය ඒ. පී. සොයිසා; පියුම් මල් නිඝණ්ටුව; ගුණසේන සිංහල මහා අකාරාදිය ටී. ඇස්. ධර්මබන්ධු)3. හිස පිටුපසට කර ගොතන ලද කෙස් Hair platted and tucked up behind the head; තූප්පය (ක්ලව්; ධර්මසමය - ඒ. පී. සොයිසා; බෝරුග්ගමුවේ රේවත - ශබ්දාර්ථ රත්නාකාරය; පුරාණ නාමාවලිය; නව නාමාවලිය)4. කේශ කලාපය, වරල, වරලස, ඉස කෙස්, Hair of the head (රජයේ සිංහල මහා ශබ්දකෝෂය / රජයේ සංක්ෂිප්ත / ගුණසේන මහා සිංහල - හරිස්චන්ද්‍ර විජයතුංග; සරසවි සිංහල-සිංහල ශබ්දකෝෂය; සුමංගල; ක්ලව්; පියුම් මල් නිඝණ්ටුව 85-2; රුවන් මල් නිඝණ්ටුව 293, 491; පුරාණ නාමාවලිය 260; හෙලදිව් අබිදානවත 474; සුමුගු දා කාව්‍ය සංග්‍රහය ටිප්පණි 1954 බී. ඒ. ගුණසේකර - වරල, ධම්මිල්ලය, මුහුළු, වරල්, කියඹු යනාදිය හිසකෙයට නමි.)5. නළල (1838 මාතර සරණපාල හිමියන්ගේ හෙලදිව් අබිදානවත නිඝණ්ටුවෙහි පමණි)පළමු සහ දෙවන අර්ථයන්ට සමාන “අලක” වචනයේ අර්ථ:6. අලකය, අලකා, අලකාව - A. කියඹු වැල; ස්ත්‍රීන්ගේ නළල මත හෝ දෙකොපුල මත වැටෙන වකුටු වූ කෙස් රොද; B. වැල්වල හට ගන්නා දඟර වැටුණු සිහින් කෙන්ද; ප්‍රතානය (රජයේ සංක්ෂිප්ත)7. අලකාවලිය = කේශ කලාපය (සරසවි සිංහල-සිංහල ශබ්දකෝෂය)0.3. කියඹු යන පදයෙහි පළමු, දෙවන, සහ තුන් වන අර්ථවලට සමාන පදපළමු අර්ථයට1. අලකා, අලක (සංස්කෘත තත්සම अलक a curly hair, lock of hair)දෙවන අර්ථයට1. අලකා, අලක (සංස්කෘත තත්සම अलक)තුන් වන අර්ථයට1. තූප්පය (බෝරුග්ගමුවේ රේවත - ශබ්දාර්ථ රත්නාකාරය)තූප්පය - ස්ත්‍රීන් කෙස් වැටියට යොදන මෝස්තරයක් (ගොඩගේ ප්‍රායෝගික - හරිස්චන්ද්‍ර විජයතුංග)තූප්පය - දෙපස උස්ව සිටින සේ පීරා සකස් කරන කොණ්ඩා මෝස්තරය (රජයේ සංක්ෂිප්ත)0.4. එකම අර්ථයෙන් යෙදෙන කියඹු වචනයේ විවිධ ස්වරූප1. කියඹුව2. කියඹු ලතාව (පෙර යෙදුම් - කාව්‍යා. III 89 - රජයේ සිංහල මහා)3. කියඹු ලිය; (පෙර යෙදුම් - කව් මුතුහර (1) 646; ධර්මප්‍රදීපිකාව 208-33 - ''කියඹුලිය සදා ලතු අලුත් පතුල් තඹුරෙහි නූපුර රාවයෙන්'' - රජයේ සිංහල මහා; ධර්ම ප්‍රදීපිකාව 1927 ශ්‍රී ධර්මාරාම 215-80- සුමංගල ශබ්දකෝෂය)4. කියඹු වැල්, කියඹු වැළ (කව්සිළුමිණ 1946 සෝරත 414; මුවදෙව්දාවත බටුවන්තුඩාවේ 80- වැලක් වැනි කියඹුව - සුමංගල ශබ්දකෝෂය; එඩ්මන් මහා සිංහල සාහිත්‍ය ශබ්දකෝෂය; රජයේ සිංහල මහා පෙර යෙදුම් - සසදා. 211; කව්සිළුමිණ 414; අමරකෝෂය 628; කව්මිණි කො. 197; කව් මුතුහර. (1) 614; අනුරාධ යු. 141-23 - “මඳ නෙලෙන් නැටවුණු කියඹුවැළින් හෙබි'')5. කියඹු වැළුවරලු / කියඹු වැළවරලූ (කියඹුවැළ හා කේශ කලාපය - ධර්ම ප්‍රදීපිකාව 1927 ශ්‍රී ධර්මාරාම 283-19, 300-13 “ලලන සුනිල් කියඹු වැළවරලූ මැ බිඟු පෙළ ඇති \\" - සුමංගල ශබ්දකෝෂය; කියඹු වැල සහ කෙහෙ කළඹ - අලකාලතාවෙන් යුත් කෙස් කලඹ - සරසවි සිංහල-සිංහල ශබ්දකෝෂය; රජයේ සිංහල මහා ශබ්දකෝෂය).6. කියඹ රාජිය, කියඹරාජිය (කුරු වූ ඉසකේ වැටිය - row of curls - ධර්මසමය; කියඹුවැළ - රජයේ සිංහල මහා ශබ්දකෝෂය දෙන පෙර යෙදුම චාල්ස් කාටර්)පළමු සහ දෙවන අර්ථයන්ට සමාන පදය:7. අලකය8. අලකාවලිය (අලක+ආවලි)A. නිඝණ්ටුA.1. 1270 - 1293 පියුම් මල් නිඝණ්ටුව - කතෘ අඥාතකියඹු - 1. කේස කලාප, 2. නළාටාන්තයෙහි ගෙතූ කේස; යන දෙක්හි.A.2. 1421-04-30 පුරාණ නාමාවලිය - නල්ළූරුතුන් මිනි සන්හස් මැතිඳුමුහුළු, වරල්, කියඹු, (නම් වේ ඉස කෙසට) [The names for the hair on the head are]A.3. 1422 – 1466 රුවන් මල් නිඝණ්ටුව - 6 වන සිරි සඟ බෝ පරාක්‍රමබාහු රජ486. කියඹු 1. වරල්හිදු 2. නළලත්හි සුන් කෙස වේ.A.4. 1778 නව නාමාවලිය - තල්ගහගොඩ රත්න හිමිවරල, කේ, කියඹු, කෙස්, නලකේ, මුහුළු,කෙහෙ, නර (මෙඅට ඉසකේසට නම් වේ ළු)A.5. 1838-10-02 - හෙලදිව් අබිදානවත - මාතර සරණපාල හිමිකියඹු, නලල්, බහළය, (මේ නම් නොලෙසනළලට කියන නමි දැනගන් සැකය පිස)B. පෙර යෙදුම්B.1. කියඹු - පද්‍ය පෙර යෙදුම්B.1.1. 1100-1200 මුවදෙව් දාව - මුනිදාස කුමාරතුංග විවරණය80. ලළන කියඹු වැළින්ගලතැ'ස්හි සිඳුවර රොන් [සිදු මරණෙන්]එතර නුදුටුහු පියෝ [නුහුටුහු පියන්]පැහැසර වටොර සෙපියන්අන්වය: ලළන කියඹු වැළින් සිඳුවර රොන් ඇස්හි ගලත. එතෙර පියෝ සෙපියන් පැහැ සර වටොර නුදුටු හු.අර්ථය: චඤචල වන්නා වූ අලකාවලියෙන් සින්ධුවාර කුසුම් රේණුත් (නික මල් රොන්) ඇස්හි ගිලිහෙත් මැ, ඒ කාලයෙහි ප්‍රියයෝ (වල්ලභයෝ) ස්වකීය ප්‍රියාවන්ගේ වට වූ ඌරු නො දුටු හ.ප්‍රියාවන්ගේ ව ඌරු දර්ශනයෙහි බද්ධාභිලාෂ ඇති වල්ලභයන් එ දෙසැ නෙත් හැළන කලැ, ලජ්ජායෙන් මිරිකුණා වූ ප්‍රියාවෝ ඌරු දර්ශනයට අවකාශ නොදෙන පිණිසැ සැමියන් ගෙල වැලැඳ මුඛ චුම්බනය කෙරෙත්. එ කලැ ඔවුන්ගේ කියඹු වැළින් නික මල් රොන් වල්ලභයන්ගේ ඇස්හි හෙයි, එයින් පීඩිත වූ ඇස් ඇති වල්ලභයෝ ප්‍රියාවන්ගේ ඌරුව නො දකිත් මැ යි.චුම්බනයෙන් අලක චූණිය ඇස්හි ගලන සේ කාලිදාසයෝ ද කී හු:චුම්බනාදලකචූණිදූෂිතංශඞක‍රොපිනයනං ලලාටජම්උච්ඡවසත කමලගන්ධපයෙ දදෞපාර්වසතිවදනගන්ධෙවාහිනෙ’ ෴ යි.ශංකාරඃ අපි - ඊශ්වර තෙමේ ද, චුම්බනාත් - චුම්බනය හේතු කොටැ ගෙනැ, අලකචූණි - කියඹුයෙහි යෙදූ චුණියෙන්, දුෂිතම් - පීඩිත වූ , ලලාවජනයනම් - නළල්හි වූ ඇස, උච්ඡවසත් - හමන්නා වූ, කමල ගන්ධයෙ - නෙළුම් සුවඳ ඇති. පාර්වති වදන ගන්ධූවාහිනෙ - පාර්වතියගේ මුඛමාරුතයට, දදෙ‍ - දිනි උමාව ඊශ්වරයාගේ ඇසට පිඹ අලක චූණිය දුරැ ලූ හ යි කියූ සේ යි.ටිප්පණි : කියඹු - නළල දෙ පසෙහි ගෙතුණු කෙස් රොද මේ නමින් ගැනේ. සංස්කෘතයෙහි මෙයට නම් ‘අලක’ යනු යි. මෙය කුන්දම, සින්ධුටවරාදි කුසුමයෙන් සරසනු සිරිති.B.1.2. 1197-1200 සසදා වත - මුනිදාස කුමාරතුංග විවරණය211. එ රජ රුපු කලුන් – කියඹු වැළ හුණු වුවනත්පලග අඩ ගහණ ඔත – මැලෑ සඳ සිරි ඉසිලීඅන්වය: එ රජ රුපු කලුන් කියඹු වැල හුණු වුවනත්, පලග අඩ ගහණ ඔත මැලැ සඳ සිරි ඉසිලී.පදාර්ථ: ඒ රාජයා ගේ සතුරු කාන්තාවන්ගේ අලකාවලී වැටුණා වූ වක්ත්‍රය (තෙමේ,) රාහු විසින් අර්ධ ග්‍රහණය කරන ලද්දා වූ මිලාන වූ චන්ද්‍රයාගේ ආකාරය දැරී යැ.විස්තර: බ්‍රහ්මදත්ත රාජයා ගේ සතුරන් ගේ කාන්තාවෝ සිය සැමියනට පත් විපත නිසා ශෝකයෙන් තැවෙති. පෙරැ මෙන් ඔවුන් ගේ අලකා ගොතා සරසන ලද්දේ නො වේ, නිකම් මැ මුහුණට වැටී මුහුණින් අඩක් වසාගෙනැ සිටී. එ හෙයින් ඒ මුහුණ, රාහුහු විසින් අඩක් ගන්නා ලද සඳ වැන්නැ.ටිප්පණී: කියඹු - මුතු කුසුම් ආදියෙන් ගොතා ඉදිරි දෙ පසෙහි හෙළන කෙස් රොද ‘කියඹු’ නමි. සංස්කෘතයෙහි ‘අලක’ යනු වෙයි.“සත්නාහොගෙ පතන් භාති කපොලාත් කුටීලො ‘ලකඃ ශශාඞ්කඛීම්බතො මෙරෞ ලම්බමාන ඉචොරගඃකොපුලින්, තන මඬලෙහි වැටෙන්නා වූ, වකුටු වූ කියඹුව, සිසි බිඹුයෙන්, මෙරුයයෙහි, එල්බෙන්නා වූ, නයකු මෙන්, දිසේ). මෙයින් කියඹු වැළෙහි දිග මැන ගත හැකි වේ. කොහි සිටැ කොයි දෙසින් කොයට යේ දැයි ද මැනවින් මැ හැඟැ වෙයි. කාලිදාසයෝ කියඹු මුතු ලා කොඳ කැකුළු ලා ගොතනු ලබන බව කියත්.‘මුක්තාජාලග්රලථිතමලකං’ [ මුතු දැලින්ගොතන ලද අලකා ඇති.] ‘අ‍ලකෙ බාලකුන්දානුවිද්ධං’ [ කියඹුයෙහි තරුණ කුන්දයෙන් අනුවිදුනා ලද.] -B.1.3. 1266-1269 කව්සිළුමිණ - වැලිවිටියේ සෝරත 1960 සංස්කරණය38 වන කවියඔහු කග මේ හිවි රුපුනඹුවන් බැම මියුරුනළල්තල රන් අතළේ කියඹු සිකිපිල් අතළේඅර්ථය: ඔහුගේ (හිවි) එසෙවූ ඛඬ්ගය නමැති මේඝය තෙමේ රුපුන්ගේ අඹුවන්ගේ බැම නමැති මොනරාගේ (කියඹු) අලකා නමැති (සිකිපිල්) සඳැස්පිල් නලල්තලය නමැති රන්ගල් තලාවෙහි ඇතිරී ය.විස්තර: මේ රජු කඩුව එසෙවූ (යුද්ධාරම්භ කළ) විට සතුරු රජුන්ගේ දේවීහු සියහිමියන්ට නියතින් ම අන්තරාය වෙති යි ශොකයෙන් කියඹුවැල් තැබුම් ආදී ප්‍රසාධන කාර්යයන්හි නො යෙදෙති. එවිට කියඹුවැල් නළලෙහි වැටේ. බැම මොනරෙකු සේ සැලකූ විට උගේ පිල් ලෙස තැකිය හැක්කේ කියඹුවැල් ය.‘කියඹු’ යනු ගැහැණුන්ගේ නළල දෙපසෙහි කොට කර කැපූ නොහොත් මුතුහර, කොඳකැකුළු, මීපුප්, නිකමල් ආදිය දමා ගෙතූ කෙස්රොද යි. “අලකාශ්මීර්‍ණකුන්තලාඃ’” යනු අමරකෝෂ යි. ස්ත්‍රීන් අලංකරණය පිණිස ‘නිකමල්’ ‘මී මල්’ යොදා කියුඹු සදන බව කාව්‍යයෙහි ප්‍රසිද්ධ යි. - වැලිවිටියේ සෝරත කව්සිළුමිණ 1960.305 වන කවියකතක බොන මිහිවිත [මීවිත්ත]හෙත කියඹු මිහි සිඳුවරදුර ලන්නාසින් පිඹියේමුව මිහිගත [මුවමී ගතෙ] නරවරාඅන්වය: කතක බොන මිහිවිතැ - හෙත කියඹුමිහිසිඳුවර, දුරැ ලන්න්සින් පිඹි සේ - මුවමිහි ගතෙ මිහිසුරා කියඹු සිඳුවර.අර්ථය: කාන්තාවක බොන මීවිතෙහි කියඹුවෙහි මී සිඳුවර මල් වැටෙත් ම ඒ මහීශ්වර තෙමේ එය දුර ලන අදහසින් පිඹි පරිද්දෙන් (ඒ කතගේ) මුඛමධුව ගත්තේ ය. / තම කියඹු වැළෙහි වූ මල ගිලිහී තමාගේ මී තැටියෙහිම වැටෙන කල, එය දුරලන්ට පිඹිත්ම රජ ඇගේ මුහුණ සිම්බේ ය. (මාටින් වික්‍රමසිංහ)විස්තර: රජතෙමේ මිහිසුරුය. මීවිතෙහි වැටුනු මීසිඳුවර බැහැර කරන්නට මිහිසුරු තෙමේ පිඹින්නාක් මෙන් දක්වා මුවමී ගති. ‘මිහිසිඳුවර’ යනු මී මල් හා නිකමල්ය. අඟනෝ එයින් කියඹු සරසති. ඒ බව ගුරුළුගෝමීහු ද “මීසිඳුවරින් කියඹුලිය සදා” (ධර්මප්‍රදීපිකාව 54) යනුවෙන් කීහ. වැලිවිටියේ සෝරත - කව්සිළුමිණ414 වන කවියසිකිනඹළ පිල් ලෙල කියඹු වැල පොද සිඳුවරදස අඹුවන් පලන් හර විලසින් දිසි බලා වැලඅන්වය: සිකිනඹල පිල් ලෙල - කියඹුවැල පොද සිඳුවර, දස අඹුවන් පලන්හර - විලසින් දිසි බලා වැල.අර්ථය: ශිඛීන් විසින් (අඹළ) විහිදවූ (සඳැස්) පිල් (දස අඹුවන්) දිශා නමැති කාන්තාවගේ (ලෙල කියඹු වැල විලසින් දිසි) ලීලොපෙත වූ කියඹුවැල ලෙසින් දෘශ්‍යමාන වීය. (පොද) වැහිදියබිඳු දසඅඹුවන්ගේ (සිඳුවර) නිකමල් විලසින් දිසි. බලාවැල (කොක්පෙළ) දසඅඹුවන් පලන් (පැලඳි) (මුතු) හර විලසින් දිසි.B.1.4. 1385-1391 මයුර සන්දේශය - මුනිදාස කුමාරතුංග 1935 සංස්කරණය35. කියඹු වතළ දළ කැළැ ලොතළ සේකරපැළැඳි ඔරැදි මලිගිය මලිනි සේකරලියෙව් ලියන් කැලුමළු ළපලු සේකරතො දැකැ නොපටු සිතිවිලි සිතැ තොසේකරඅන්වය: කියඹු වතළ දළ කැළැල ඹතළ සේකර, ඔරැඳි මලිගිය මලිනි සේකර පැළැඳි, කර ළ පලු සේ කැලුම් අළු, ලිය එව් ලියන් දැකැ, තෝ සිතැ නොපටු සිතිවිලි තොසේ කර.අර්ථය: අලකා වැතුරුණා වු නළල සස ලපය වැටුණා වු තරුණ චන්ද්‍රයා සේ විරාජමාන වු (බැබැළුණා වු) මාලති කුසුමයෙන් ‍ශේඛර (මුදුන මල් කඩ) පැළැන්දා වු, හස්තය තරුණ පල්ලවය මෙන් කාන්තිය දුන්නා වු, ලතාවන් වැනි වු ස්ත්‍රීන් දැකැ, තෝ සිතෙහි අල්ප නුවු සිතිවිලි සන්තෝෂයෙන් කරව.විස්තර: කැලණියෙහි ස්ත්‍රීන් දැකැ උන්ගේ රූප සෞන්දර්යවයෙන් බෙහෙවින් පහදුව යි මේ කි සැටි යැ. ඒ ස්ත්‍රීන් ගේ අලකා විසිරි ගිය නළල සස ලපය ඇති බාල සඳ (අඩ සඳ) වැන්නැ. ඒ ස්ත්‍රී හු සත්පෙති දැ සමන් මලින් කළ මුඳුන් මල් කඩ පැළැඳියෝ යැ. උන් ගේ අත් ළා දළු මෙන් රතු යැ. එ හෙයින් ඔහු ලතාවන් වැනි වෙත්.ටිප්පණි : කියඹු - නළලට වැටෙන සේ ගොතා හෙළූ කෙස් රොද මෙ නම් වේ. සංස්කෘතයෙහි ‘අලකා’ යනු නමි. මයුර සන්දේශය - මුනිදාස කුමාරතුංගB.1.5. 1440-1446 කෝකිල සන්දේශය - රැ. තෙන්නකෝන් 1961 සංස්කරණය42 වන කවියවිකසිත තමලු ලිය මල් බර කියඹු වැළීඅකණු නිතඹ පුල් වනඟන කරන තිළීඑක සර සරන පැහසර රෑන සැදි කිළීදැක තට සිතෙයි සැක නොවැ ලෙළෙන මිණී වැළීඅන්වය: විකසින තමලු ලිය මල් බර කියඹු වැළි, (නිතඹ) අකණු නිතඹ, පුල් වන අගන නිළිකරන, එක සර සරන පැහැයර රෑන සැදි කිළි දැකැ සැක නොවැ තට සිතෙයි ලෙළෙන මිණි වැළි.අර්ථය: පිපුණා වු කොල්ලම් වැල් නැමැති මලින් බර අලකා රොද ඇති, (අවට පියෙස නැමැති) පටු නුවු උකුළ ඇති, මල් පිපුණ වනය නැමැති තුටු කරවන්නා වු, එක් හඬින් සරන්නා වු, රංචු ගැසුණු ගිරවුන් දැක තට සැක නැතිවැමැ සිතෙයි ලෙළ දෙන්නා වු මැණික් මාල යැයි.විස්තරය: වැල්ලේ මඬමෙන් ඔබ්බෙහි වන රොදක් වු බව මින් පෙනේ. මියුරු අසුන් කරුවෝ ද එයට දෙස් දෙති. ඒ වන රොඳ හෙවත් කැලැ කැටිය අගනක කොටැ මෙහි දැක්වේ. මල් පිපුණු වනය අඟනයි, එහි ඇති මල් පිපුණු කොල්ලම් වැල් ගොල්ල එ අඟන ගේ ගවසත ලද මලින් බර අලකා රොදයි. අවට පැතිරි බිම් තලය (නිතඹ) පටුනු වු හෙවත් පුඵල් වු උකුළ (නිතඹ) යි. එහි ගිරවු සරති. ඔවුන් සරන්නේ එක් හඩින් සරන්නේ රංචු (රෑන්) ගැසීයි. ඒ ගිරා රංචු (රෑන්) දුටුවා මැ සැක නැති වැ මැ කොවුලාට සිතෙනවා ඇති ලෙළ දෙන මැණික් වැළ යැ කියා. ඒ රෑන ගිරවුන් කරන්නේ මල් පුල් වන රොද නැමති අනගනට නොස දිමයි.ටිප්පණි: කියඹු වැළ හෙවත් අලකැවලිය, කන් ගොටු ‍දෙක අඩක් මුවා වන සේ උර හිස තෙක් වැටෙන්නට ගොතා හෙළූ කෙස් රොදයි. එහි මල් හෝ මුතු හෝ ගැවැසිම් කැරේ. (කියඹු) වැළි = (කීයඹු) වැළ ඇති. රැ. තෙන්නකෝන් -කෝකිල සන්දේශය.278 වන කවියලෙළ දළ කියඹු වැළ සැදීවෙළ වරඟන ලිය වැලැඳීදළ මුතු හර මලෙහි බැඳීදොළ කරැ සත සිටිනි ළඳීඅන්වය: දළැ ලෙළ කියඹූ වැළ සැදි, වෙළ වැ රඟන ලිය වැලැඳී දළ මුත් හර මලෙහි බැඳි සත දොළ කැරැ ළඳි සි‍ටිති.අර්ථය: නළලේ ලෙළ දෙන කෙස් රොද රැඳුණා වූ, ලහි වැ නටන්නා වූ ගෑනුන්ගේ ඇඟේ එතුණු පට මහ මුතු වැළ නැමැති මල පුඬුයේ බැඳි දනෝ ආසා කොටැ සිත දී සිටිත් .ටිප්පණි: කියඹූ වැළ නම් දෙ කොපොල වසා පියොවුරු තෙක් වැටෙන මුතු මල් ආදියෙන් සරසන ලද කෙස් රොදයි. රැ. තෙන්නකෝන් - කෝකිල සන්දේශය143 වන කවියපලග වන් වියත් දද තුටු වන්ට බලීපලඟ අවි රැගත් වරැ මෙ විරු රුපු කලී[පලග] හුණු මුහුණු සහදුන් කඳුළු හැලීපලඟ අඬ ගහණ මිලි තරිඳු සිරිසිලිවියන් දද තුටු වන්ව බලි පලග වන් මෙ විරු පලග අවි රැගත් වරැ රැපු කලී සහඳුන් කඳුළු හැලි පලග හුණු මුහුණු පලග අඬ ගහණ මිලි තරිඳු වැනි. / වියත්ද ද, ද්වීජගණයා; තුටුවන්ට, සන්තෝෂ ජනනය කිරීමට; බළ, ගෝචර වූ; පලගවත්, අග්‍ර ඵලයක් වැනි; මෙමරු, මේ විර බලපරාක්‍රම පරා ක්‍රමබාහු මහරජානන්; පලඟ අවිරැගත්වර, පටලායුධ සන්නද්ධව රණ ප්‍රාප්ත වූ කල්හි; රුපු කලී, වෛරීනෘප කලත්‍රැන්ගේ; සහඳුන්, අංජනා ලෙ පදිගු පුළුල්නයනින්; කඳු එ හැලි, නෙත්‍ර ජල වහන කළා වූ; පලඟහුනු, පලා වන් වූ; මුහුනු, මුඛයෝ තුමු; පලඟ, රාහු ග්‍රහයා විසින්; අඩ ගහණ, අර්ධ ග්‍රහණය කළා වූ; මිලිතරිඳු, මලීන චන්ද්‍රයාගේ; සිරි සිලී, සෝභාව දරුසේයි; - පී. එස්. පෙරේරා 1906 සංස්කරණය.වියතුන් හෙවත් උගතුන් නැමැති කුරුල්ලනට තුටු වීම පිණිසැ මහත් වූ පල තුරක් වැනි මේ වීරයා පලිය සහිත ආයුධ අතට ගත් විටැ සතුරු අඹුවන් ගේ අඳුන් වැ ඇති කඳුළු දහාරා වැගිරෙන අලකාවලිය වැටී ඇති මුහුණ රාහු අඬක් ගත් දුමුරස වූ සඳ වැනියි.වියත් දනෝ - වෙසෙසින් කිවියෝ - කුරුල්ලෝයි. මේ රජ තෙමේ මහත් වූ පල තුරෙකි හෙවත් පල දරන ගසෙකි. පල ඇති රුකට කුරුල්ලන් පියාඹා අවුත් වසා පලබුදිමින් තුටු වන්නා සේ මෙ රජ කරා වියත්තු පැමිණැ සැපත් ලබති. පල රසින් මත් කුරුල්ලන් නද දෙන්නා සේ සැපත් ලැබීමෙන් තුස්නා වියත්තු මෙ රජු පසසිත්.එ අයුරු වූ මෙ රජු සටනට පලිස් කඩු දුනු ඈ අවි ගත් විටැ සතුරනට මර නියතයි. එ බව දන්නා සතුරු අඹුවෝ සිය හිමියන් ගෙන් වන වියෝව සලකා සොවින් සැලෙත්, ඔවුන් ගේ අලකා වැළ මුහුණට වැටෙයි. ඇසින් කඳුළු දහර ගලයි. එ කඳුළින් ඇසැ අඳුන් සේදී යයි. මුහුණ දුමුරස හෙවත් දිඹිරි ගැසේ.ඔවුන් ගේ අලකා වැළ මුහුණට වැටෙයි (පලග හුණු මුහුණු?). අලකාව නම් ඉදිරි පිට දෙ පැතතේ හෙළන, මලින් මුතුයෙන් සෑදූ කෙස් රොද දෙකයි. ‘කියඹු’ වැළ යනු ද මීට මැ නමෙකි. “කියඹු වතළ දළ කැළලොත ළසේකර” යැයි මියුරු අසුන් කරුවන් කීයේ එ හෙයිනි. මෙය දෙ කොපොල පහසිමින් පියොවුරු මතට වැටෙන සේ හෙළුව බව “ස්තනාහෝගේ පතන් භාති කපොලාත් කුටිලෝලඃ ශශාංකබිම්බතෝ මේරෞ ලම්බමාන ඉවෝරගඃ -- කොපොලින් තන මඩලෙහි වැටෙන්නා වූ වක් හෙවත් වැකැටි ගැසුණු අලකාව සිසි බිඹුයෙන් මේරුයෙහි එල්ලෙන වයකු සේ පෙනේ” යන්නෙන් පළ වෙයි. මුහුණ සඳ මෙනි, නළල් තලයට අලකා රොද වැටුණාම එහි (මුහුණේ) පසක් වැසෙනුයෙන් අඬක් අසු වූ සඳ මෙන් එය පෙනේ. රැ. තෙන්නකෝන් - කෝකිල සන්දේශය.B.1.6. 1581-1592 දහම් සොඬ කව - මකුළුදූවේ පියරතන දහම් සොඬ කව51. ඔහු කග මේ නඟතරුපඹු බැම සිකි නළලතරන් ගිරි අතල මතකියඹු සඳපිල් කැල විදා ගතඅර්ථය: (ඔහු) ඒ රාජයා විසින්, කග නමැති මේඝයා, නගන කල්හි, රුපඹු බැම නමැති මයුරයෝ, නළලත නමැති රන්ගිරි අතල මත, කියඹු සඳ පිල් කැල විදහා ගත්තේය.විස්තරය: වැසි වසින විට පිල් විදහා ගැනීම මොනරුන්ගේ සිරිතය. මේ රජුගේ කඩුව මේඝය වැන්න. එය ඔසොවන කල සතුරු ස්ත්‍රීන්ගේ බැම නැමති මොනරු නළල නැමති ගල්තලය මතුයෙහි කියඹු නැමති සඳ පිල් විදා ගත්හ. මොනරුන් වැසි වසින විට පිල් විදහාගෙන නටන්නේ සතුට හේතුකොට ගෙනය. සතුරු අඹුවන්ගේ බැම නැමති මොනරුන් නැටුයේ සතුට නිසා නොවේ. සිය හිමියනට විපත්වෙති බියෙනි. කියඹු වැල් නළලෙහි කරනුයේ අලඬකාරය පිණිසය. රජු‍ ගේ කග මේ නැගීමෙන් බිය පත් වූ සතුරු ස්ත්‍රීන්ගේ ශෝකයෙන් කියඹු වැල් නළල මත අතුර, ගත් බව මෙහි අදහස යි.ටිප්පණි: කියුඹු -නළලට වැටෙන සේ කොට කර කැපූ රැළි සහිත කෙස් රොදට නමි. මකුළුදූවේ පියරතන - දහම් සොඬ කවB.1.7. 1610 කුස දා කව - වේරගොඩ අමරමොලි 1949 කුස ජාතක කාව්‍ය198. නොයෙක් රුවින් දිසි එළඳගෙ සිරි වතඋදක් කියඹු වැල යුතු පටු නළලතපසක් වැසුනු ගණ කුලකින් කැළලොතසසක් මඬල ලෙස බබළයි පැහැපත”අර්ථය: නොයෙක් රුවින් දිසි ඒ ලඳගේ මුහුණෙහි කියඹුවැලෙන් යුක්ත වූ පටු නළල පමණක්, මේඝ කූටයකින් අඩක් වැසීමෙන් කැලලින් යුක්ත වූ පැහැපත් වූ සඳ මඬල මෙන් බැබලේ.නොයෙක් රුවින්, අපමණ ශ්‍රීයෙන්; දිසි, දෘශ්‍යමානවූ; එලඳගෙ, ඒ ස්ත්රිලයගේ; සිරි වත, මුහුණෙහි වූ, කියඹුවැල යුතු, අලකාවලියෙන් යුක්තවූ; උදක් පටු නළලත, පටු නළල පමණක්, ගණ කුලකින්, මේඝකූටයකින්; පසක් වැසුනු, අඩක් වැසීමෙන්; කැලලොත, කැලලින් යුක්තවූ; පැහැපත, ප්‍රභා ප්‍රාප්තවූ; සසක් මඬලලෙස, චන්ද්‍ර මණ්ඩලය මෙන්; බබලයි, බැබලේ.B.1.8. 1678 රාජසිංහ විරුදාවලි 1 හෙවත් රජසිහ සිරිත 1 හෙවත් රාජසිංහ වර්ණනා 4113. සිරිගත් වරල මනා - ගන කුළුකියඹු නළල සිරිනා - නව බැමසක් සරසන - ගහණ කුසුමනීල නයන සුනිල මිණි නිලුපුල සිරිනාB.1.9. 1773 කව්මිණි මල්දම - ඩී. පී. ආර්. සමරනායක 1961 සංස්කරණය394. එකල නළඹුන් පෙළසඳු'නැඟ සදා රෑ දුලඅවුනා කියඹු වැලතෙලින් ගලතා මුදු සරණ තලඅර්ථය: එකල රෑ දුල, නළඹුන් පෙළ, ඇඟ සඳුන් සදා, කියඹුවැල අවුනා, මුදු සරණතල තෙලින් ගලතා රෑ කාලයෙහි රූපයෙන් දිලිසෙන්නා වූ, නාටිකා ස්ත්‍රීන් සමුහය, ඇඟ සඳුන් ගා; අලකාවලිය අමුනමින්, මෘදුව පා යුග තෙලින් ගල්වා.B.1.10. 1773 කව්මිණි කොඬොල - ටී. ඇස්. ධර්මබන්ධු 1955197 වන කවියඑ රජ රුපු කල නන්කියුඹු වැල හුනු උවනන්පළඟ අඩ ගහ නන්සඳ ඉසිලි නොව නත් ලෙවන්ඒ රාජයාගේ අනන්ත වූ සතුරු කාන්තාවන්ගේ කියඹු වැල පතිත වූ මුහුණ රාහු අසුරිඳු විසින් අඩක් ගිල ගැනීමෙන් කාන්ති රහිත වූ චන්ද්‍රයාගේ ශ්‍රී ය නො වෙනස්ව ඉසිලී.280 වන කවියතොබිදු සිඳු වර දුලසිකි කැල කියඹු වැල දුලදස වමිය ගෙන දුලහරෙව් පළවී බලා වැල දුලදිය බිඳු නමැති මුක්තාකලාපයෙන් බබළන්නාවූ, මයුර සමූහ නමැති අලකාවලියෙන් දිලිසෙන්නාවූ, දිශා නමැති කාන්තාවගේ ග්‍රීවයෙහි බැබළුණු බලාකාවලිය මුතු වැලක් මෙන් ප්‍රකාශ විය.B.1.11. 1895 කව් සඟරාව2077. දෙමින් තිලක නළලත මුව මැදගෙනනොමින් අනගි මිණි මුතු බැඳ සසොබනරුවන් තෝඩු තබමින් සෙද දෙසවනවැලින් කියඹු දළ අස බැඳ ගොතමිනB.2. කියඹු - ගද්‍ය පෙර යෙදුම්B.2.1. 1187-1225 ධර්මප්‍රදීපිකාව - අබිසම්බෝධි කතා - ගුරුළු ගෝමී“මිසිඳුවරින් කියඹුලිය සදා”“ එක්බිති රජ කුමර ඇය සිනිඳු පහන් පැහැ මැ සම වැ මමන සිලිල් ඇති, තුන් කැලැති මැ තරඟ වැද ඇති, නැබ මඬුලු මැ සළා වැටුම් ඇති, සොමි වුවන් මැ නම පුබුදු පියුම් ඇති, නෙත් මැ මහනේල ඇති, මෙළෙක් අත් මැ පොකුරු දැළි ඇති, [ක‍ියඹු වැලු වරළු මැ බිඟු පෙළ ඇති], ඉහිල් වසන් රසන් වැළ මැ හුන් මිදෙල් කුසුම රිණි ඇති, නැහැ අලුත් අඟරා මැ පියුම් රජ තවර ඇති, තනන තන මඬුලු මැ වජඹනා මත් හස් රජුන් ඇති, විළි බර සිනා මැ පුප්නා කුමුදු ඇති, වජන් මැ මි බඳු ඇති,”B.2.2. 1303-1333 බෝධි වංශයකියඹු සහිත වූ නළල්තලයෙහි ගොරද බින්දුයෙන් තිලක නො දෙන්නීයැ.බෝධිගැ. 72-7 (රජයේ සිංහල මහා ශබ්දකෝෂය)B.2.3. 1909-1987 සිංහල මේඝ දූතය“බැහැර ගිය හිමියන් ගේ අඹුහු අහස් අරා යෙන ඔබ තුටු සිතින් දැක පෙම්බරයන් නියතින් එතැ’යි හදවතින් දැන අලකාව අතින් නඟා ඔබ දෙස නෙත් නඟති.”“එහි යුවතීන් අතින් ලෙලු’පුලක් ගෙන, අලකයේ නවමු කොඳ මලක් පැළැඳ,”“නො ලස් ගමනේ දී අලකයෙන් හොත් මඳාරා කුසුම්නෙන්, වැටී ගිය කොපුල් අ‍ලෙව්නෙන්, සවන් පෙත්තෙන් හොත් කනාමය උපුල් පියැල්ලෙන්,”“අලකයෙන් වැසී ගත් නෙත’ග බැලුම්නෙන් යුත්, අඳන් ගා ලකළ නො කළ,”“ලෙලු’පුලක් ගෙන’තින්, කොඳ මල් දමක් අලකයේ ගවසා,”“රැය’ඳුරේ නො ලසා ගමනොත් නිසා අලකයෙන් හුණු නේ මඳරා කුසුම් දෙ කොපුලෙන් ගිලි හි ගිය පත් අලෙව් දෙ සවනින් බිම හොත් පෙති රන් උපුල්”B.2.4. රජයේ සිංහල මහා ශබ්දකෝෂයැ දෙන වෙනත් පෙර යෙදුම් උදාහරණජාතක අටුවා ගැටපදය (හෙ.ර. 85-21 - (රජයේ සිංහල මහා ශබ්දකෝෂය)ජානකීහරණ XIII-38 “කොපොල් හී...... පෙරළෙන්නා වූ ......කියඹු ඇත්තා වූ '' (රජයේ සිංහල මහා ශබ්දකෝෂය)B.3. කියඹු - ගීත සාහිත්‍ය පෙර යෙදුම්B.3.1. ප්‍රේම සැදෑවෝ - අජන්තා රණසිංහ / ප්‍රේමසිරි කේමදාස / අමරදේවනීල නයන කිඳුරුලතා - නළල පැලඳ කියුඹු ලතාමානවිකාවෝ මවනා ප්‍රේම සැදෑවෝB.3.2. සඳ හොරෙන්,හොරෙන් හොරෙන් බලා - කුලරත්න ආරියවංශ / ප්‍රේමසිරි කේමදාස / අමරදේවකියඹු වැල් ලිහී ඔබේ - මාරුතේ සැලීකොපුල් තල ගැටී මගේ - සිතුම් සසලවයිB.3.3. කියඹු ලතා නළලෙ ගැටී රඟන ලතාව - ෂෙල්ටන් වීරරත්න / චන්ද්‍රලාල් ෆොන්සේකා / ඇනස්ලි මාලේවනකියඹු ලතා නළලෙ ගැටී රඟන ලතාවනෙතට නෙතක් දොඩමළු වී කියන කතාවB.3.4. කියඹු ලතා නළලෙ නටන සීතල පවනැල්ලේ - ? / ? / මිල්ටන් මල්ලවාරච්චිකියඹු ලතා නළලෙ නටන සීතල පවනැල්ලේහංස ලතා දියට ඇදෙයි මේ රන් අරුණැල්ලේB.3.5. නීල නුවන් මානෙල් මල් - මඩවල එස් රත්නායක / දේවානන්ද වෛද්‍යසේකර / දේවානන්ද වෛද්‍යසේකරකියඹු ලතා නළලේ වැටී - නව රසයක් මුහුණේ සැදීකොමල පාද තියා තියා - ටිකිරිලියා ටිකිරිලියාකළෙත් අරන් ලිඳ ගියා -කළෙත් අරන් ලිඳට ගියාB.3.6. කුන්ද සමන් මල් මල් - ක්ලැරන්ස් විජේවර්ධන / ක්ලැරන්ස් විජේවර්ධන / ටී. එම්. ජයරත්නමට නොදැනී - මට අමතාපටු නළලේ - කියඹු ලතාමුදු මුදු සේ - සැලෙන ලතාB.3.7. කහ මල් අත්තක් සැලුනා - සුනිල් යෝගේන්ද්‍ර / ලක්ශ්මන් හිල්මි / 01. රොහාන් තිසේරා 02. ලක්ශ්මන් හිල්මිකියඹු ලතා ඇගෙ සොලවාවිහිලු කලා මද පවනාB.3.8. දිලි දිලි දිලි දිල්ලියේ දිල්ලි නුවර නංගියේ - සුනිල් සරත් පෙරේරා / ආනන්ද පෙරේරා / ආනන්ද පෙරේරාසුළඟ සමග වෙලි වෙලීකියඹු වැලද නැලවුණීපෙමට පෙමින් බැඳි බැඳීඅසල නිබඳ ඔබ හිඳීB.3.9. බඹර රැඟුම් රැයේ නුහුරැ හැඟුම් පැයේ මෝහනීය යොවුන් වියේ මොණර කුරැල්ලා - අජන්තා රණසිංහ / වික්ටර් රත්නායක / වික්ටර් රත්නායකඅනංග දෙව් කුසුම් සැරේ ආසිර්වාදෙන්නළල් පුරා කියුඹු ලතා අවුල්ව යා දෙන්B.3.10. අන්දර වැටෙන් එබෙන සුන්දරී - සුනිල් ආරියරත්න / රෝහණ වීරසිංහ / සුනිල් එදිරිසිංහනළලත කියඹු ලතාවෙන්දෙව් ලිය සදිසි කතාවෙන්B.3.11. මිහිරියේ පිය බඳේ - මඩවල එස් රත්නායක / අමරදේව / අමරදේවඔබ මුහුණ දකින සඳනොපිපි වන මල් පිපේකියඹු වැල් මා බලාඔබේ නළලත හැපේB.3.12. නළලත කියඹු ලතා පළඳින සිරිලියේ - ශිල්පිණි සුජාතා අත්තනායක - 1979 ගී පද- නැසිගිය කරුණාරත්න අබේසේකර ? තනුව හා සංගීතය - ප්‍රවිණ සංගීතවෙSදී නැසිගිය ස්‌ටැන්ලි පීරිස්‌ ?නළලත කියඹු ලතා පළඳින සිරිලියේB.3.13. සිහින් කියඹු වැල් එකනෙක වෙන් කර - කරුණාරත්න අබේසේකර / සරත් දසනායක / ජෝතිපාලසිහින් කියඹු වැල් එකනෙක වෙන් කරබැලුවමි එහි දක්නට නැත්තේB.3.14. බෝධිය හෙවණක ළා දලු පිස එන - ප්‍රියානන්ද විජේසුන්දර / සේන ජයන්ත වීරසේකර / නන්දා මාලිනීපවනි'නබල කළ කියඹු වැලකි ඔබවිරහිනියක පටු නළලේශරත් නිශාවක සඳ රැහැනකි ඔබමුදුවකි විල්ලුද සුමුගේB.3.15. මල් මුවරද පවනේ නදී තෙර - අජන්තා රණසිංහ / ඩී. ආර්. පීරිස් / නන්දා මාලිනීසීත සමීරේ සඳ සිලිලාරේනළල අකීකරු කියඹු ලතාවෝරැඟුම් රඟට රඟනාB.3.16. මධුර වසන්තේ මල් ලියකම් බබලා - අජන්තා රණසිංහ / අතුල අධිකාරී / අතුල අධිකාරි සමඟ සමිතා මුදුන්කොටුවකියඹු ලතා මැදචන්දන තිලකය ඔබගේදිලි දිලි දිලිහේB.3.17. මී පැණි රහසක් ගැලුවා සුකිරි කන්දෙන් - සුනිල් විමලවීර / සිරිල් පෙරේරා / කිත්සිරි ජයසේකරසුසුම් කිමැයි මෙතරම් උණුසුම්කසුන් කියඹු සසෙලෙයි මිහිරෙන්B.3.18. සුනිල්වන් දියේ පිපිලා මල් හිනැහෙනවා - මූන් ස්ටෝන්ස්කුසුමලතා කුසුමලතාඇගේ නළල මත කියඹු ලතාB.3.19. දරා දුක සතුට හිරිහැර - මාධවි හේරත් / ඩැනිස්ටර් පෙරේරා / අමරසිරි පීරිස්සුළඟ හා තරඟ වැදීකියඹු වැල් මැදින්සිඹින්නට සිතයි ඇගේසුමුදු මුදු දෙතොල්B.3.20. දිමංක වෙල්ලාලගේ - කියඹු ලතාවේB.4. කියඹු - වෙනත් පෙර යෙදුම්B.4.1. ඔරුවල බන්ධු 1969 පස් අවුරුදුපාවෙන සුලන් රැල්ලෙන් ඇගේ කියුඹු රොද සලිතවනුයේ, හද සලිත බව කියා පෑමට ද!B.4.2. ඔරුවල බන්ධු 1987 කේ. ජී. බීකියුඹු රොදක් ඇගේ වම් ඇස කොනින් පහලට ඇද වැටෙනුයේ, අමුතුම ලතාවකටය.B.4.3. ඔරුවල බන්ධු 1979 සෝවියට් සිර මැදිරියේ සිට“කියුඹු රොද ඇයට පවන් සලනු වැන්න.”B.4.4. කැදැල්ල 1989 සුසිරි සිරිවර්ධන“කියුඹු වැල් සේ පෙනෙයි. නෙළුම් කැටපතේ දිස්වන තම ප්‍රතිරූපයට විරිත්තුවාය.”B.4.5. සිංහල ගී කාව්‍ය සංග්‍රහය 1967 අනුරාධ සෙනෙවිරත්න“කියුඹු වැල කෙරෙහි ම මගේ සිත ඇදී ගියේය.”B.4.6. සම්ප්‍රාප්තිය 1980 පී කරුණාරත්න“මොණර පිල් වන් කියුඹුපුන් පයෝදරඑළඳ සන්තක නෑ”B.4.7. දයා ගුණතිලක - නුදුටි මොක්පුර“තෙමී ගිය කියඹු රැළි කිහිපය හිරු රැසින් ඔපවත් කළ නළල් තල යෙන් ගලා බසී.”B.4.8. ගොඩකුඹුර“නළල වටේ කියඹු වැලකි”B.4.9. චිත්‍රානන්ද අබේසේකර“කියඹු ලතාවෙන් අලකාවලිය නටනවාපෙති ගෝමර විසිරි විසිරි ළැම දිලිසෙනවානළලත පිරි රන් තිලකය එළිය වැටෙනවාකළු එතනා මාව දැකල ඔමරි කරනවා”B.4.10. මධුරසිංහ ගුණතිලක 1988 ප්‍රකෘතියේ රහස සහ වෙනත් කෙටි කතාහැටි ද දැක ගන්නට මට පින පෑදුවේ සෞම්‍යා ය. ඇගේ නළලේ දඟකාර කියඹු රැලි පිස ගෙන එන මඳ පවන් රැල්ලෙන් මම නොමඳ ආස්වාදයක් ලදිමි.B.4.11. සිංහල විරහ කව් කළඹ 1965 ශ්‍රී චාල්ස් ද සිල්වාරුවන් තෝඩු තබමින් සෙද දෙ සවනමලින් කියඹු දළ ඇස බැඳ ගොතමිනB.5. කියබු, කියම්බු - පෙර යෙදීම් - සීගිරි ගීB.5.1. 258 වන ගීය(ගත)බගිරි මෙයුලමි මයි ගී බලත ‍මෙය ත ම හයි ත කී විසි ඇය (අ)ත මල් මෙ ලි (නිතබු) කියබු සුනිල් වෙ සිරිත මෙ ව(ද) වි(යො)වනඅන්වය: ම හයි ත මෙය බලත සුනිල් කියබු මෙ ලි. නිතබු, ඇය අත මල් විසි ත කී, වියොවන මෙ සිරිත වෙ?අර්ථය: ගතබහිරි (නම් ස්ථානයෙන් පැමිණි) මෙයුල (නමැත්තා) වෙමි. (මේ) මගේ ගීයයි. මා හා (එක්ව) තොප මෙය බලන කල සුනිල් කියඹු ඇති මේ කාන්තාව පහතට නැමී, ඇය අත තුබූ මල් විසි කළ බව තොප (විසින්) කියන ලදි. (ප්‍රියයන්ගෙන්) වියෝවූ (කතුන්ගේ) සිරිතක් වේද මෙය? කියව.ටිප්පණි: කියබු. (සං. ශ්යාවමක. අලක. ආදී වචන හා සැසඳිය හැක. පා. අඩ්ඪ - පාදට්ඨපත. කියඹු, කියඹු - වැළැ, කියඹු වැළැනෙන්, ඈ විසින්ද යෙදී ඇත.විස්තර: කාලය - 8 වෙනි ශතවර්ෂය හෝ 9 වෙනි ශතවර්ෂයේ මුල් භාගය විය හැක.B.5.2. 355 වන ගීයකියුබු සුරල නළල අතර ලියුණ වරල එක පසෙක මෙබිත දෙසින් මලදමක ඇජැ දෙ යෙම්නි ලබුයට පිය(ල්)(බති) මෙ ගිය ලියාඅන්වය:නළල අතර කියුබු සුරල ලියුණ වරල එක, මෙ බිත දෙසින් පසෙක ලබුයට මලදමක ඇජැ දෙ.අර්ථය:නළල අතර කියුඹ සහිත ව එතී ගිය ලිහිල් වරල ඇති එක් (කතක්) මේ භිත්තිය දෙසින් පසෙකට වී පහතට යමින් මල් දමක් ඇද දෙයි. මේ ගීය ලියා පියල් බති (නමැත්තා) ආයේය.1. කියබු - කියඹු. (සං. අලක)විස්තර: කාලය 8 වෙනි ශතවර්ෂයේ අවසාන භාගය.B.5.3. 377 වන ගීයස්වස්ති. නිල් කඩ (සිරි) ගී ලි(ය) තනරනමලී රතඅතින ගත විලුවන් මලදම්සිරි නිනබු කියබු මා සෙ දුටුයුන අදවයි.අන්වය: ලිය තන රතමලී, රත අතින ගත විලවුන්, මලදම් සිරි, නිතබු කියබු , මා සෙ දුටුයුන අදවයි.අර්ථෙය: යහපතක් වේවා! නිල්කඩ (නම් ස්ථානයෙන් පැමිණි) සිරි (නමැත්තාගේ) ගීයයි. කාන්තාවගේ පයෝදරයෙහි (පැලඳි) රන්දාමය ද, රතු අතින් ගත් විලෙවුන් ද, මල්දමෙහි ශෙභාව ද, පහතට නැමී ගිය අලකාවලිය ද (යන මෙකී එකිනෙක්ම) මා සෙයින් දුටුවන් අදවයි.ටිප්පණි: කියුබු - (සං. අලක; ශ්යදමක.) ‘කියඹු’ යනු විසින් ද යෙදෙයි.විස්තර: කාලය 9 වෙනි ශතවර්ෂයේ මුල් භාගය.B.5.4. 685 වන ගීයසකපතරින් සුනිල් හිස දිගැ(ස) නළල කි(ය)බු පැහැ වි දිවි සි(ටි) ම(ත) අබුයුහු (ම) ආ සන්දි (නො) බණිත් කිත් අග්බොයිමි ලීමි.අන්වය: හිස සුනිල් සකපතරින්, දිගැස, නළල කියබු පැහැ දිවි වි, මත සිටි අබුයුහු ම ආ සන්දම නො බණිත්.අර්ථය: හිසෙහි අතිශය නිලවර්ණ වූ ශිඛා ප්‍රදේශයෙන් (ද), දිගු ඇසින් (ද), නළලෙහි (රැඳුණු) අලකාවලියෙන් ද පැහැය දිවෙන්නේ වූ, මස්තකයෙහි සිටි කාන්තාවෝ මා (මෙහි) පැමිණි කල කථා නො කරත්. කිත් අග්බොයි (නමැත්තා) වෙමි. (මෙය) ලීමි.ටිප්පණි: කියබු - සං. ශ්යාමක, අලකවිස්තර: කාලය 9 වෙනි ශතවර්ෂයේ මුල් භාගයB.5.5. 364 වන ගීයස්වස්ති බොයලමි මයි ගී. නිලබැමැසැව් හැජැ සුනිල්කි(ය)ම්බු වැළනෙන් වන ලක් වි(දි) ම සිත් (සෙයි) දිග්ඇස් දිග්ඇස්හියෙන්.අන්වය: සුනිල් කියම්බු වැළනෙන් නිල බැමැ සැව් හැජැ දිග් ඇස් දිග්ඇස්හියෙන් ම සිත් ලක්වන සෙයි විදි.අර්ථය: යහපතක් වේවා! බොයල (නමැත්තා) වෙමි. (මේ) මගේ ගීයයි. අතිශය නිල් වන් කියඹු වැළ (නමැති දුනුදියෙන්) නිල්බම (නැමැති) දුන්න ඇද, දිගැසිතොමෝ දිගු ඇස් (නැමැති) හීයෙන් මා හදවත ඉලක්කය සේ (ගෙන) විද්දාය.විස්තරය: කාලය 8 වෙනි ශතවර්ෂය.B.5.6. 380 වන ගීයඇය විසි මල් බලය් නොමෙ බැණැ හි රසැත්තක්නිනබු සුනිල් කියම්බු හෙළිල්ලම්බු ලම්බු සිත් මය්ඉතා නිල් අලකා සහිත නිනාහී රූමතිය කෙරේ මගේ සිත එල්බිණ. රසවත් දෙයක් කියාගත නුහුණු ඇය මල් බලමින් සිටියාය. වැසි වලාවකට සමාන කළ හැකි ඇගේ සුනිල් කියඹු වැල කෙරෙහිම මගේ සිත ඇදී ගියේය.B.6. අලක පෙර යෙදුම්B.6.1. ගිරා සන්දේශය 1987 කේ. ජී. ප්‍රේමරත්න සංස්කරණය26. රොද’ක් කන අලක මුතු පට ගොතා බැඳසඳක් බඳු වුවන මඳ හස යොදා නඳමඳක් මතු මහල සිටි එළි පෙනී සොඳඋදක් සුර’ඟනන් වැනි පුර’ඟනෝ ළඳඅර්ථය: කන කෙළවර කියඹු වැල මුතු පට හා ගොතා බැඳ සඳ වැනි මුහුණෙහි සිත් සතුටු කරවන මඳ සිනහවක් පා, උඩුමහලින් ටිකක් එළියට පෙනෙන පරිදි සිටි යහපත් තරුණ පුර ස්ත්‍රී හු විශේෂයෙන් දිව්‍යාංගනාවන් වැන්නාහ.ටිප්පණි: අක් කන - කනෙහි කෙළවර - කණ අග - ‘ග’ යන්න හල් වූ විට නොයෙක් තැන්වල ‘ක්’ හැටියට සිටී.අලක - අලංකාරය සඳහා කන අගින් නවා පහතට හෙළන කෙස් රොද. මෙයට කියඹු වැල යයිද කියනු ලැබේ. කේ. ජී. ප්‍රේමරත්න - ගිරා සන්දේශයවිස්තර: කන අක් අලක රොද මුතුපටකින් ගොතා බැඳ ගෙන. අලක රොද තමයි කියඹුවැල. [වැටෙන්නෙ කණ අගින් කම්මුල් දිගේ පහළට. එහි මුතු එල්ලා ඇත]. අලකරොද - කියඹු වැල, මුතුපට ගොතා - මුතුපටින් ග්‍රන්ථනය කර සැරැසූ.108. දිවසර කය රුසිරින් පෑ දන සකයසැදි අලකය ඇඳි නළලතෙහි තිලකයසිටි නිසැකය ළද කොමළඟනන් දැකයපරතර කය වැද යව මග නොවැළකයඅන්වය: පරතරකය වැද, රුසිරින් දිව අසර කය දන සකය පෑ තිලකය ඇඳි නළලතෙහි අලකය සැදි නිසැකය සිටි ළද කොමළ අඟනක් දැක මග නොවැළක යව.අර්ථය: පරතරකයට පැමිණ රූප ශ්‍රීයෙන් දිව්‍ය අප්සරාවන්ගේ ශරීරය ජනයාගේ ඇස්වලට පෙන්වූ තිලකය ඇඳි නළලෙහි කියඹුවැල ගැවසුණු සැකක් නැතිව සිටි තරුණ කාන්තාවන් දැක මග නොනැවතී යන්න.B.6.2. ඔබේ නමින් සෑය බඳිමි විමානයෙන් බසිනු මැනවි ස්වර්ණමාලියේ - මහගම සේකර / අමරදේව / අමරදේවබාලචන්ද්‍ර පටු නළලතඅලක අඳුන් අඳින ලියේඅඩ සඳ හැඩය ගත් පටු නළලේ අලකාවලි හෙවත් කියඹු ලතා වලින් කළු පැහැති අංජන තවරන බව.B.6.3. කාලිදාස - අලකාචුම්බනාදලක චූර්ණ දූෂිතංශංකරොපි නයනං ලලාටජම්උච්ඡ වසත කමල ගන්ධයෙ දදෞපාර්වතීව දන ගන්ධ වාහිනෙශංකරඃ අපි - ඊශ්වර තෙමේ ද, චුම්බනාත් - චුම්බනය හේතු කොටැ ගෙනැ, අලකචූර්ණි - කියඹුයෙහි යෙදු චූර්ණයෙන්, දුෂිතම් - පීඩිත වූ, ලලාටජ නය නම් - නළල්හි වූ ඇස, උච්ඡ වසත් - හමන්නා වූ, කමල ගන්ධයෙ - නෙළුම් සුවඳ ඇති, පාර්වතී වදන ගන්ධ වාහිනෙ - පාර්වතිය ගේ මුඛමාරුතයට, දදෞ - දිනි. උමාව ඊශවර්යා ගේ ඇසට පිඹැ අලක චූර්ණය දුරැ ලූ හයි කි යූ සේයි.B.6.4. 1773 කව්මිණි මල්දම - ඩී.පී.ර් සමරනායක 1961 සංස්කරණය663. දලව වළ ද ලද ලද නවදල රස සහදරද ස නවදල දස නව දද නද නවදල ‘ලකවණ’ ද ‘සදද නවඅන්වය: දළව අවල, දල, දල, දනව දලරස, සහදරද, සතව. දළද, නව. දද හඳනව, දල අලක වණ අද අසද දනව.අර්ථය: මහත්ව ආකූලවූ, (පියුම්) පෙතිද, ජලයද, ජනිතව ජලයෙහි රසින්, පෘථිවි රාජිතොමෝ. ජනප්‍රාප්ත වූවාය. දැඩි බවින් තෙත්ව ශාඛාවෝද (ජල බරින්) නැමී ගත්හ. පක්ෂිහුද සතුටුවූහ. පීරා හැරියාවූ කියඹු රාජී ඇති විරහීනීන්ගේ හෘදයෙහි රති ආශාවද ජනිත වූයේය. ප්‍රතිලෝම පක්ෂයෙහි වනයෙහි ලා කොළ දැඩි වශයෙන් ආකුලද වූයේය. විරහ ස්ත්‍රීහු කමාශ්‍රවයෙන්, නිරන්තරයෙන් ගැවසුනාහ. හංසයෝද විල් දුරු කළහ. ජලයද මේඝ නාදයද පැමිණියේය. වනබිම කුසතණින් ගැවසී ගතී. වැසි කලුවෙන් දශ දිශාවෙන්ද වැසුනේය."},{"question":"Dựa theo câu mở đầu các truyền thuyết và cổ tích đã học, hãy viết câu mở đầu giới thiệu nhân vật của một truyền thuyết hoặc cổ tích khác.","answer":"Mở đầu cổ tích Thạch Sanh bằng lời kể khác:Truyện kể về một chàng trai có tên là Thạch Sanh vốn là thái tử trên trời cao. Được Ngọc Hoàng phái xuống làm con trai của một cặp vợ chồng già tốt bụng. Vì vốn là thần tiên trên trời, nên khi chàng xuống trần gian, người mẹ phải mang thai suốt nhiều năm mới sinh nở. Mãi sau khi cha Thạch Sanh qua đời từ thì chàng được sinh ra. Sau khi mẹ mất, Thạch Sanh sống một mình lủi thủi trong túp lều cũ dưới gốc cây đa. Đến khi chàng trưởng thành, Ngọc Hoàng phái thiên thần xuống dạy cho đủ các môn võ nghệ và nhiều phép thần thông."},{"question":"අධිආරක්ෂිත බෙල්මාෂ්' බන්ධනාගාරය පිහිටා  තිබෙන්නේ ?","answer":"ලන්ඩන්"},{"question":"काठमाडौंको पशुपतिनाथ मन्दिरको वास्तुकलाका विशेषताहरू वर्णन गर्नुहोस्।","answer":"पशुपतिनाथ मन्दिर यसको प्यागोडा शैलीको वास्तुकला, जटिल काठको नक्काशी र नजिकै बग्ने पवित्र बागमती नदीको लागि परिचित छ।"},{"question":"Awọn sọja mu mẹrin balẹ ninu awọn ajinigbe to da awọn arinrin-ajo lọna l’Ondo","answer":"Ọrọ bẹyin yọ fawọn ikọ ajinigbe kan lọjọ Ẹti, Furaidee, ọsẹ yii, pẹlu bawọn sọja ṣe yinbọn pa mẹrin ninu wọn lasiko ti wọn n gbiyanju ati ji awọn arinrin-ajo kan gbe loju ọna marosẹ Ọwọ si Ifọn.Awọn agbebọn ọhun la gbọ pe wọn ti kọkọ ji awọn eeyan kan gbe pamọ lara awọn arinrin-ajo to ko si wọn lọwọ lọjọ naa.Ibi ti wọn ti n da ọkọ mi-in duro ki wọn le ri awọn ero inu rẹ ji gbe lawọn ọmọ ologun to n rin kaakiri agbegbe naa ti de ba wọn, ti wọn si fija pẹẹta fun bii wakati kan gbako.Aarin asiko yii ni wọn mu mẹrin ninu awọn janduku ọhun balẹ, tí wọn si fipa gba awọn ẹni ẹlẹni ti wọn ti ji gbe silẹ lọwọ wọn.Nigba to n fidi iṣẹlẹ yii mulẹ, Alukoro ileesẹ ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Ondo, Tee-Leo Ikoro, ni lati bii ọjọ diẹ sẹyin lawọn sọja ti n wa gbogbo inu aginju to wa lagbegbe naa nitori awọn ajinigbe to n fi ibẹ ṣe ibuba wọn."},{"question":"පහත තුන් තෙරවිල්ල තෝරන්න.වගේ වෙල ","answer":"වගේ නම් වැනි , වෙල නම් වෙල් = වැනිවෙල් , වෙනිවැල්"},{"question":"Quantas vezes o Brasil foi campeão da Copa do Mundo?","answer":"Até 2023, o Brasil é o único pentacampeão da competição, tendo vencido cinco vezes, nos anos de 1958, 1962, 1970, 1994 e 2002."},{"question":"विश्वको सबैभन्दा बढि चाँदी उत्पादन गर्ने देश कुन हो?","answer":"विश्वको सबैभन्दा बढि चाँदी उत्पादन गर्ने देश मेक्सिको हो "},{"question":"Ẹ̀sùn lásán ni wọ́n ṣì fi kan Aiyedatiwa, a kò tíì yọọ́ nípò — Ilé Aṣòfin Ondo","answer":"Ile aṣofin ipinlẹ Ondo lo ti fi lede pe awọn ko ni fi igba kan bọ ọkan ninu lori iwadi ẹsun iwa ibajẹ ti wọn fi kan igbakeji gomina ipinlẹ ọun, Lucky Aiyedatiwa.Atẹjade kan latọwọ ẹni to jẹ alaga igbimọ to n moju to eto iroyin nile aṣofin naa, Olatunji Oshati, ni awọn aṣofin naa ti wi pe ifẹsunkanni lasan ṣi ni ọrọ naa titi di igba ti iwadi yoo pari.Oshati to rọ awọn araalu lati ma ṣe sọ ọrọ ana di bamii kojumọ o too mọ ṣalaye pe “ni tootọ, bi a ṣe kọwe si igbakeji gomina lori ẹsun ti wọn fi kan-an ni ibẹrẹ iyọni nipo, amọ awọn igbesẹ to rọ mọọ pọ gan kii sii ṣe ohun tẹnikan lee ṣe loru mọju.“A mọ pe awọn araalu n reti ki a ṣe ohun to tọna, a ko si nii jawọn kulẹ.“A fẹẹ ki wọn mọ pe ilana to kẹnu wa ninu ofin orilẹ ede yi nipa iru iṣẹlẹ yi taa gbọdọ tẹlẹ, a si ni ẹtọ labẹ ofin lati rii pe a moju to gbogbo ohun to ba n lọ nipa eto iṣejọba ko ma baa si magomago ninu eto inawo.“A waa rọ gbogbo araalu lati yago fun ahesọ to le domi alaafia ilu ru tori pe ko si ẹnikẹni ninu gomina ati igbakeji rẹ to kọja ofin.“A ti kọwe ranṣẹ si igbakeji gomina nipa ẹsun ti wọn fi kan-an, o si ni ẹtọ labẹ ofin lati sọrọ gbera rẹ lẹyin leyi ti yoo mu ẹkọ o fi oju mimu han.“A si fi da gbogbo aye loju pe ilana ti ofin la kalẹ ni a maa tẹle lai si makaruru kankan.”Ẹwẹ, awọn agbofinro lo ti sọ ọna abawọle sile aṣofin naa di ibi to nira lati wọ pẹlu bi wọ ṣe pọ niye ju ti tẹlẹ lọ.Awọn agbofinro ọun ni wọn n ṣe ayẹwo finnifinni fun ẹnikẹni to ba fẹẹ wọ ile aṣofin naa ti wọn si n da ẹni ti ko ba ni idi pataki lati wọle pada.Ọkan lara awọn agbofinro naa to ni ohun ko lẹtọ lati ba akọroyin sọrọ wi pe niṣe ni awọn wa nibẹ lati pese aabo to peye ati lati dena ohunkohun to le fa laasigbo nile igbimọ naa.Titi akoko ti a n ko iroyin yi jọ, igbakeji gomina, Lucky Aiyedatiwa ni ko tii wi ohunkohun lori gbogbo ọrọ naa bo ti lẹ pe o ti di aruwo laarin ilu ati lori ẹrọ ayelujara.Ilé aṣòfin ìpínlẹ̀ Ondo kọ̀wé sí igbákejì gómìnà kó wá wí tẹnu rẹ̀ lórí ẹ̀sùn ìwà ìbàjẹ́.Ile igbimọ aṣofin ipinlẹ Ondo ni Ọjọru, ogunjọ oṣu kẹsan ọdun yi lo ti pa akọwe ile aṣofin naa laṣẹ lati fi iwe ranṣẹ si igbakeji gomina ipinlẹ ọun, Lucky Aiyedatiwa, lati sọ ohun to mọ nipa ẹsun iwa ibajẹ ti awọn kan nile aṣofin naa fi kan-an.Adari ọmọ ile to pọ ju lọ, Oluwole Ogunmolasuyi, lo gbe aba naa kalẹ niwaju awọn akẹgbẹ rẹ, ti Tope Agbulu, to n ṣoju ẹkun iwọ-oorun-guusu Akoko keji, si kin aba naa lẹyin.Eyi lo mu ki abẹnugan ile aṣofin ọun, Olamide Oladiji, ni ki awọn to ba faramọ aba naa o paruwo soke ti ko si si aṣofin kan to tako aba naa.Lẹyin eyi ni Oladiji paa laṣẹ fun akọwe ile aṣofin naa, Benjamin Jaiyeola, lati kọ iwe ranṣẹ si ọgbẹni Aiyedatiwa ko le mọ ẹsun ti wọn fi kan-an.Oladiji wi pe aṣofin mẹsan lo buwọ lu iwe ẹsun naa ki Ogunmolasuyi o too gbe ka iwaju ile.Bo tilẹ jẹ pe wọn ko sọ iwa ibajẹ ọun ni pato ninu gbogbo ọrọ ti wọn sọ nibi ijoko awọn aṣofin naa, iwadi ileeṣẹ BBC News Yoruba fihan pe ẹsun ti wọn fi kan igbakeji gomina naa ni pe o buwọ lu rira ọkọ ayẹta ti owo rẹ to ọọdunrun miliọnu naira fun ara rẹ lai fi to igbimọ iṣejọba leti.Aiyedatiwa ni wọn ni o buwọ lu rira ọkọ naa lakoko to jẹ adele gomina laarin oṣu mẹta ti gomina Oluwarotimi Akeredolu fi n gba itọju lorilẹ ede Germany.Ọkan lara awọn amugbalẹgbẹ gomina Akeredolu to ni aaye ko gba oun lati sọrọ sita wi pe Aiyedatiwa lo da gbe igbesẹ naa lai fi ọrọ lọ ẹnikẹni.O fi kun pe ninu owo iranwọ ‘subsidy’ ni Aiyedatiwa ti ni ki wọn yọ ọọdunrun miliọnu naira owo ọkọ ọun.Ẹwẹ, Lucky Aiyedatiwa ni ikọ iroyin BBC News Yoruba ko lee ba sọrọ titi di akoko yi ni bi igbakeji gomina naa ko ṣe gbe ipe, ti ko si fesi si atẹjiṣẹ taa fi ṣọwọ sii.Ṣaaju ni Gomina Akeredolu ti fi ọwọ osi juwe ile fun gbogbo awọn oluranlọwọ feto iroyin to n ṣiṣẹ lọfiisi Aiyedatiwa lọjọ kejila oṣu yi leyi ti ko fi si ẹnikẹni to le sọrọ lorukọ igbakeji gomina ọun."},{"question":"Apakah jawapan untuk teka-teki berikut: Saya biasanya di atas, duduk di sebelah kiri, kanan atau tengah, bercorak dan boleh menutup, siapa saya?","answer":"Jawapannya ialah topi. Topi adalah sejenis pakaian yang dikenakan di kepala. Topi biasanya memiliki bahagian melengkung yang tinggi dengan bahagian sisi. Topi boleh dikenakan di kepala atau, bagi beberapa jenis topi perempuan, dilengkapi dengan penyemat topi."},{"question":"O que é a teoria da evolução cultural?","answer":"A teoria da evolução cultural é uma abordagem que se baseia na ideia de que a cultura humana, como linguagem, tecnologia e normas sociais, evolui de maneira semelhante à evolução biológica. Ela sugere que as ideias e práticas culturais podem ser transmitidas, modificadas e adaptadas ao longo do tempo, moldando a sociedade de maneira análoga à seleção natural."},{"question":"Ndiani akanyora rondedzero inoti \\"murume ari muIron Mask\\"?","answer":"Munyori  anonzi Alexandre Dumas, akagadzira rondedzero inonakidza inonzi \\"The Man in the Iron Mask.\\" Kuburikidza nehunyanzvi hwake hwekunyora, Dumas akataura ngano yezvakavanzika uye zvinokwezva vaverengi."},{"question":"\\"தென்னாட்டைத் தன்னந்தனியே ஆண்ட பெண்ணரசி\\" என்னும் புகழைப் பெற்றவர் யார்?(1) இராணி மங்கம்மாள்(2) தில்லையாடி வள்ளியம்மை(3) ஜான்சி ராணி(4) வேலுநாச்சியார்","answer":"(1) இராணி மங்கம்மாள்.  இராணி மங்கம்மாள் (இறப்பு: அண். 1705) பெண்கள் முடி சூட்டி ஆட்சி செய்யாத நாயக்கர் மரபில் காப்பாட்சியாளராக இருந்து மதுரையை 1689 முதல் 1704 வரை ஆண்ட பெண்மணி ஆவார்.மதுரையை ஆண்ட சொக்கநாத நாயக்கரின் மனைவி ஆவார். கணவர் இறந்ததும் தன் மகன் அரங்க கிருஷ்ண முத்துவீரப்ப நாயக்கர் இளம் வயதினனாக இருந்த காரணத்தால் தான் உடன்கட்டை ஏறாமல் மகனுக்குத் துணையாகக் காப்பாட்சியாளராக இருந்து மதுரையை ஆண்டவர். திறமையான ஆட்சியாளர். சமயப் பொறை மிக்கவர். எதிர்ப்புகளைத் தன் ஆற்றலாலும் அறிவு நுட்பத்தாலும் முறியடித்தவர். 18 ஆண்டு காலம் தென்னாட்டை தனியே ஆண்ட பெண்ணரசி. இவருடைய ஆட்சி காலத்தில் மதுரை நாயக்கர்களின் தலைநகரமாக திருச்சிராப்பள்ளி விளங்கியது.இராணி மங்கம்மாளின் அறப்பணிகள்:இராணி மங்கம்மாள் மக்கள் நலம் பேணும் பல அறச் செயல்களைச் செய்தார். மதுரையில் பெரியதொரு அன்னச்சத்திரம் அமைத்தார். அது 'மங்கம்மாள் சத்திரம்' என இன்றும் அழைக்கப்படுகிறது. புதிய சாலைகள் பலவற்றை அமைத்தார். கன்னியாகுமரிக்கும் மதுரைக்கும் இடையே அமைந்த நெடுஞ்சாலை மங்கம்மாள் சாலை என அழைக்கப்படுகிறது.     குதிரைகள், பசுக்கள், காளைகள் முதலியவை நீர் அருந்துவதற்காக சாலையோரங்களில் தண்ணீர்த் தொட்டிகள் அமைக்க ஆணையிட்டார். பொது மக்களுக்காக குடிநீர் ஊருணிகள், கிணறுகள் ஆகியவற்றைத் தோண்டச்செய்தார். தொழில் வளர்ச்சி, வாணிகம், மக்கள் தொடர்பு ஆகியவற்றிற்கு வழிவகுத்தார். கொள்ளிடத்தில் வெள்ளம் ஏற்பட்டு மக்கள் துன்புற்ற போது அவர்களுக்கு உணவு, உடை, வீடு மற்றும் பாதுகாப்பு வசதிகளை வழங்குவதற்கு ஆணையிட்டார். வெள்ளத்தால் அழிந்த கரையோரத்துச் சிற்றூர்களையும் சீரமைத்தார்.    தற்போது மகாத்மா காந்தி அருங்காட்சியகமாக விளங்கும் தமுக்கம் அரண்மனையே இராணி மங்கம்மாளின் கோடைக்கால அரண்மனையாகும். இதிலுள்ள தமுக்கம் மைதானத்தில் தான் அக்காலத்தில் யானைச் சண்டை முதலான பொழுதுபோக்கு விளையாட்டுகளும் அரச விழாக்களும் நடைபெற்றன."},{"question":"السؤال: في أي عصر ظهرت الخوارج؟","answer":"الإجابة: في نهاية عصر الخلفاء الراشدين"},{"question":"ಕೆನಡಾದ ಅಧಿಕೃತ ಭಾಷೆಗಳು ಯಾವುವು","answer":"ಕೆನಡಾ ದೇಶವು ಕಾಮನ್‌ವೆಲ್ತ್ ಕ್ಷೇತ್ರವಾಗಿದೆ ಮತ್ತು ಫೆಡರಲ್ ನ್ಯಾಯವ್ಯಾಪ್ತಿಯಲ್ಲಿ ಅಧಿಕೃತವಾಗಿ ದ್ವಿಭಾಷಾ (ಇಂಗ್ಲಿಷ್ ಮತ್ತು ಫ್ರೆಂಚ್) ಆಗಿದೆ"},{"question":" Wacce sura ce ta ke daidai daya bisa ukun Qur'ani ?","answer":"(a) Taghabun (b) Ikhlasi (c) Bakara"},{"question":"مشخصات ماهی سالم برای طبخ چیست؟","answer":"ماهی سالم این ویژگی‌ها را دارد:_ فلس براق با جلای فلزی_ آبشش صورتی مایل به قرمز روشن    _ چشمان پر و براق  _ بوی تازگی"},{"question":"Tôi bị bệnh Lupus 10 năm hiện đang uống medrol 4mg và 1 viên HCQ 200mg/ngày, đã tiêm 3 mũi vaccine AstraZeneca nhưng vẫn bị nhiễm Covid-19. Khi nhiễm tôi có uống thuốc molnupiravir 400mg để điều trị. Tôi có thể tiêm kháng thể đơn dòng được không?","answer":"Bạn đã tiêm 3 mũi vaccine ngừa Covid-19 mà vẫn mắc thì chứng tỏ vaccine đã không tạo được hoặc không tạo đủ kháng thể ngừa Covid-19. Sau khi mắc Covid-19 cơ thể sẽ tạo kháng thể. Tuy nhiên kháng thể đó có đủ để tránh tái nhiễm hay không và tồn tại bao lâu, lại là 1 vấn đề. Nếu đã tiêm mũi 3 vaccine mà vẫn bị tái nhiễm thì có thể lượng kháng thể vẫn chưa đủ. Kháng thể tạo ra cũng giảm và gần như hết hiệu lực sau 6 tháng. Như vậy, bạn có thể tiêm kháng thể đơn dòng phòng Covid-19 được. Khi tiêm kháng thể đơn dòng không phải thay đổi liều thuốc ức chế miễn dịch."},{"question":"ما هي نسبه المياه من الكره الارضيه ؟","answer":"71 %."},{"question":"Hãy tiếp tục đoạn văn sau: Trao đổi qua điện thoại với PV Dân Việt sáng 31/7, ông Hoàng Văn Minh (lái xe liên quan đến vụ TNGT khiến nữ sinh lớp 12 ở TP Phan Rang-Tháp Chàm (Ninh Thuận) tử vong cho biết, hiện ông đang ở đơn vị và không tiếp xúc với ai. Ông Minh cho biết, mọi chuyện sẽ có pháp luật xử lý nên xin không phát biểu gì trong thời điểm này. \\"Tôi không muốn phát ngôn lúc này vì mọi thứ đều có pháp luật xử lý. Đôi khi có những người lợi dụng truyền thông để thế này thế kia...\\", ông Minh nói. Khi PV đặt câu hỏi về việc có ","answer":"muốn nói gì với gia đình nạn nhân hay không, ông Minh cho biết \\"đó là phương diện cá nhân của ông và sẽ nói với gia đình nạn nhân sau\\". Liên quan đến vụ việc nói trên, ông Hồ Hoàng Hùng, cha của nữ sinh Hồ Hoàng Anh đã tử vong cho biết, gia đình đã làm đơn gửi bệnh viện đa khoa tỉnh Ninh Thuận từ (gửi ngày 13/7/2022) để yêu cầu sao lục hồ sơ bệnh án của con gái ông. Tuy nhiên đến nay vẫn chưa nhận được hồi âm từ bệnh viện. \\"Trong thời gian tới, gia đình sẽ tiếp tục làm việc với các ngành chức năng để giải quyết vụ việc\\", ông Hùng nói. "},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਮਾਝ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ਸੁਣਿ ਸੁਣਿ ਜੀਵਾ ਸੋਇ ਤੁਮਾਰੀ ॥ਤੂੰ ਪ੍ਰੀਤਮੁ ਠਾਕੁਰੁ ਅਤਿ ਭਾਰੀ ॥ਤੁਮਰੇ ਕਰਤਬ ਤੁਮ ਹੀ ਜਾਣਹੁ ਤੁਮਰੀ ਓਟ ਗੋੁਪਾਲਾ ਜੀਉ ॥੧॥ਗੁਣ ਗਾਵਤ ਮਨੁ ਹਰਿਆ ਹੋਵੈ ॥ਕਥਾ ਸੁਣਤ ਮਲੁ ਸਗਲੀ ਖੋਵੈ ॥ਭੇਟਤ ਸੰਗਿ ਸਾਧ ਸੰਤਨ ਕੈ ਸਦਾ ਜਪਉ ਦਇਆਲਾ ਜੀਉ ॥੨॥ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਅਪੁਨਾ ਸਾਸਿ ਸਾਸਿ ਸਮਾਰਉ ॥ਇਹ ਮਤਿ ਗੁਰ ਪ੍ਰਸਾਦਿ ਮਨਿ ਧਾਰਉ ॥ਤੁਮਰੀ ਕ੍ਰਿਪਾ ਤੇ ਹੋਇ ਪ੍ਰਗਾਸਾ ਸਰਬ ਮਇਆ ਪ੍ਰਤਿਪਾਲਾ ਜੀਉ ॥੩॥ਸਤਿ ਸਤਿ ਸਤਿ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਸੋਈ ॥ਸਦਾ ਸਦਾ ਸਦ ਆਪੇ ਹੋਈ ॥ਚਲਿਤ ਤੁਮਾਰੇ ਪ੍ਰਗਟ ਪਿਆਰੇ ਦੇਖਿ ਨਾਨਕ ਭਏ ਨਿਹਾਲਾ ਜੀਉ ॥੪॥੨੬॥੩੩॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 104 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਤੇਰੀਆਂ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਦੀਆਂ ਗੱਲਾਂ ਸੁਣ ਸੁਣ ਕੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਪੈਦਾ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ । ਤੂੰ ਮੇਰਾ ਪਿਆਰਾ ਹੈਂ, ਤੂੰ ਮੇਰਾ ਪਾਲਣਹਾਰ ਹੈਂ, ਤੂੰ ਬਹੁਤ ਵੱਡਾ (ਮਾਲਕ) ਹੈਂ । ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਆਪਣੇ ਫ਼ਰਜ਼ ਤੂੰ ਆਪ ਹੀ ਜਾਣਦਾ ਹੈਂ । ਹੇ ਸ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਟੀ ਦੇ ਪਾਲਣ ਵਾਲੇ ! ਮੈਨੂੰ ਤੇਰਾ ਹੀ ਆਸਰਾ ਹੈ ।੧।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ !) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਕਰ ਕੇ (ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਵਲੋਂ ਮੇਰਾ ਸੁੱਕਾ ਹੋਇਆ) ਮਨ ਹਰਾ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਜਾ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ,ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀਆਂ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਦੀਆਂ ਗੱਲਾਂ ਸੁਣ ਕੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਨ ਦੀ ਸਾਰੀ (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਦੀ) ਮੇੈਲ ਦੂਰ ਹੋ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ । ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਵਿਚ ਸੰਤ ਜਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਵਿਚ ਮਿਲ ਕੇ ਮੈਂ ਸਦਾ ਉਸ ਦਇਆਲ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਜਪਦਾ ਹਾਂ ।੨।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ !) ਮੈਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਹਰੇਕ ਸਾਹ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਚੇਤੇ ਕਰਦਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹਾਂਇਹ ਸੁਚੱਜ ਮੈਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਨਾਲ ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਟਿਕਾਇਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਹੈ ।ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਤੇਰੀ ਕਿਰਪਾ ਨਾਲ ਹੀ (ਜੀਵਾਂ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਤੇਰੇ ਨਾਮ ਦਾ) ਚਾਨਣ ਹੋ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤੂੰ ਸਭ ਉਤੇ ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈਂ ਤੇ ਸਭ ਦੀ ਰੱਖਿਆ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈਂ ।੩।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ !) ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਸਦਾ ਕਾਇਮ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈ, ਸਦਾ ਕਾਇਮ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈ, ਸਦਾ ਕਾਇਮ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈ । ਸਦਾ ਹੀ,  ਸਦਾ ਹੀ, ਸਦਾ ਹੀ ਉਹ ਆਪ ਹੀ ਆਪ ਹੈ ।ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! (ਆਖ—) ਹੇ ਪਿਆਰੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! ਤੇਰੇ ਚੋਜ-ਤਮਾਸ਼ੇ ਤੇਰੇ ਰਚੇ ਹੋਏ ਸੰਸਾਰ ਵਿਚ ਪਰਤੱਖ ਦਿੱਸ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ । (ਤੇਰਾ ਇਹ ਦਾਸ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ) ਵੇਖ ਕੇ ਪ੍ਰਸੰਨ ਹੋ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ ।੪।੨੬।੩੩।\\""},{"question":"এশিয়া মহাদেশের ভৌগোলিক অবস্থান বর্ণনা করো।","answer":"এশিয়া ১০° দক্ষিণ অক্ষরেখা থেকে ৮০° উত্তর অক্ষরেখা এবং ২৫° পূর্ব দ্রাঘিমারেখা থেকে ১৭০° পশ্চিম দ্রাঘিমারেখা পর্যন্ত বিস্তৃত। এ মহাদেশের পূর্বে প্রশান্ত মহাসাগর, পশ্চিমে ইউরোপ মহাদেশ ও ভূমধ্যসাগর; দক্ষিণ-পশ্চিমে আফ্রিকা ও লোহিত সাগর; উত্তরে উত্তর মহাসাগর এবং দক্ষিণে ভারত মহাসাগর অবস্থিত। ইউরোপ মহাদেশের সাথে স্থলভাগ দ্বারা যুক্ত হওয়ায় এশিয়া ও ইউরোপকে একসাথে ইউরেশিয়া বলা হয়। এশিয়া থেকে ইউরোপকে পৃথক করেছে ইউরাল পর্বত, ইউরাল নদী ও কাস্পিয়ান সাগর। "},{"question":"السؤال: كم عدد البحار الواقعة في تركيا؟","answer":"الإجابة: 4 بحار "},{"question":"\\"Забынына калуу\\" - деген сөз айкашы эмне билдирет?","answer":"\\"Забынына калуу\\" -  деген сөз айкашы: убалына калуу, бөөдө кыянатчылык кылуу, жок жерден жапа чектирүү дегенди билдирет. Мисалы: Айыбым болсо башымды кес, болбосо забыныма калба (Абдукаимов)."},{"question":"दिइएको वाक्यलाई कोष्ठकमा बताएअनुसार परिवर्तन गर्नुहोस् :तिमी सधै डुल्थ्यौ । (अपूर्ण वर्तमान)","answer":"तिमी सधै डुल्दै छौँ ।"},{"question":"في أي عام بنيت هجري بنيت قبة الصخرة ؟","answer":"عام 72 هجري"},{"question":"Жооп бергиле: Илимий жарманкеге катышуу үчүн эксперимент жүргүзүп жатканда, алынган маалыматтар гипотезаны колдобосо, эмне кылуу керек?А. Каталарды текшерип, экспериментти кайрадан жүргүзүңүз.В. Гипотезаны жыйынтыкка ылайык өзгөртүү. В. маалымат гипотезага дал келиши үчүн өзгөрмөлүүсүн өзгөртүү. Д. Маалыматтарды четке кагып, илимий жарманкеге даярдануу.","answer":"А. үчүн"},{"question":"他於1930年2月20日在瓦尼達去世. 他被埋葬在紐約奧爾巴尼的格倫伍德墓地. 他於1930年2月20日在紐約奧爾巴尼去世, 問:第一句和第二句是否表達相同的意思? 這是什麼意思?","answer":"第一句和第二句的意思不相同，第一句的意思是他在瓦尼達去世，並在紐約被埋葬；第二句的意思是他在紐約去世，並沒有提到他在哪裡被埋葬"},{"question":"أجب على السؤال التالي :كل الإمارات العربية المتحدة على الخليج العربى إلا واحدة فما هي؟","answer":"الإجابة الصحيحة هي أم القيوين."},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai besi dengan penempa\\"?","answer":"Orang lemah dikuasai orang kuat"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਭਗਤ ਜਨਾ ਕੀ ਬਰਤਨਿ ਨਾਮੁ ॥ਸੰਤ ਜਨਾ ਕੈ ਮਨਿ ਬਿਸ੍ਰਾਮੁ ॥ਹਰਿ ਕਾ ਨਾਮੁ ਦਾਸ ਕੀ ਓਟ ॥ਹਰਿ ਕੈ ਨਾਮਿ ਉਧਰੇ ਜਨ ਕੋਟਿ ॥ਹਰਿ ਜਸੁ ਕਰਤ ਸੰਤ ਦਿਨੁ ਰਾਤਿ ॥ਹਰਿ ਹਰਿ ਅਉਖਧੁ ਸਾਧ ਕਮਾਤਿ ॥ਹਰਿ ਜਨ ਕੈ ਹਰਿ ਨਾਮੁ ਨਿਧਾਨੁ ॥ਪਾਰਬ੍ਰਹਮਿ ਜਨ ਕੀਨੋ ਦਾਨ ॥ਮਨ ਤਨ ਰੰਗਿ ਰਤੇ ਰੰਗ ਏਕੈ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਜਨ ਕੈ ਬਿਰਤਿ ਬਿਬੇਕੈ ॥੫॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 264 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਨਾਮ ਭਗਤਾਂ ਦਾ ਹੱਥ-ਠੋਕਾ ਹੈ, ਭਗਤਾਂ ਦੇ ਹੀ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਇਹ ਟਿਕਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਭਗਤਾਂ ਦਾ ਆਸਰਾ ਹੈ, ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਨਾਮ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਕਰੋੜਾਂ ਬੰਦੇ (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਤੋਂ) ਬਚ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।ਭਗਤ ਜਨ ਦਿਨ ਰਾਤ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਵਡਿਆਈ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ, ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਨਾਮ ਰੂਪੀ ਦਵਾਈ ਇਕੱਠੀ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ (ਜਿਸ ਨਾਲ ਹਉਮੈ ਰੋਗ ਦੂਰ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ) ।ਭਗਤਾਂ ਦੇ ਪਾਸ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਹੀ ਖ਼ਜ਼ਾਨਾ ਹੈ, ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੇ ਨਾਮ ਦੀ ਬਖ਼ਸ਼ਸ਼ ਆਪਣੇ ਸੇਵਕਾਂ ਤੇ ਆਪ ਕੀਤੀ ਹੈ ।ਭਗਤ ਜਨ ਮਨੋਂ ਤਨੋਂ ਇਕ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਪਿਆਰ ਵਿਚ ਰੰਗੇ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ; ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! ਭਗਤਾਂ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਚੰਗੇ ਮੰਦੇ ਦੀ ਪਰਖ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਸੁਭਾਉ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੫।\\""},{"question":"یک سؤال و جواب از متن زیر استخراج کن:متن: دریاچهٔ ارومیه یک دریاچه شور در شمال غربی ایران و بزرگ‌ترین دریاچه داخلی این کشور است. این دریاچه میان دو استان آذربایجان غربی و آذربایجان شرقی قرار گرفته‌است. سطح آب دریاچه در دهه‌های اخیر به‌طور چشمگیری کاهش پیدا کرده و تا سال ۱۴۰۱، ۹۵ درصد دریاچه خشک شده‌است. مساحت این دریاچه در سال ۱۳۷۷ در حدود شش هزار کیلومتر مربع بود که در ردیف بیست و پنجمین دریاچه بزرگ دنیا از نظر مساحت قرار می‌گرفت. دریاچهٔ ارومیه به عنوان بزرگ‌ترین دریاچهٔ داخلی ایران، بزرگ‌ترین دریاچهٔ آب شور در خاورمیانه، و ششمین دریاچهٔ بزرگ آب شور دنیا شناخته می‌شد.","answer":"سؤال: بزرگ‌ترین دریاچه ایران چه نام دارد و در کجا واقع شده است؟جواب: دریاچه ارومیه بزرگترین دریاچه داخلی ایران است که در شمال غربی کشور واقع شده است."},{"question":"Tunjukkan resipi untuk tomyam campur Thai dengan langkah-langkah yang terperinci. ","answer":"Tom yam campur Thai ialah sejenis hidangan sup yang berasal dari Thailand. Sup ini mempunyai rasa pedas, masam dan pedas yang tersendiri, dan biasanya dibuat daripada bahan-bahan seperti udang, ayam, atau cendawan.Bahan: 150 gm isi ayam, 8 ekor udang segar, 5 ekor sotong segar, 2 sudu besar pes tomyam / 1 ketul kiub tomyam, 3 ulas bawang putih, 1 biji bawang besar, 2 biji buah tomato segar, 100 gm bunga kubis, 3 batang serai, 1 inci lengkuas, 1 pokok daun ketumbar, 4 helai daun limau purut, 8 biji cili padi (kalau nak lagi pedas, letak lebih), 2 biji limau nipis, Serbuk perasa◦ Garam dan gula secukup rasa. 5 cawan airCara penyediaan:1. Potong kecil ayam dan potong bulat sotong.2. Bersihkan udang - belah belakang udang, tarik keluar urat hitam perlahan-lahan supaya tidak putus, bilas dan kemudian tuskan.3. Ketuk serai, lengkuas dan bawang putih.4.Belah empat buah tomato dan limau nipis.5. Potong kecil bunga kobis dan cili padi, potong bulat bawang besar.Cara memasak:1. Didihkan air dalam periuk.2. Kemudian masukkan ayam dan masak sehingga empuk (berubah ke warna putih).3. Masukkan udang, sotong, kiub/pes tomyam, bawang putih, bunga kobis, cili padi, serai, bawang besar dandaun limau purut. Kacau rata dan masak dengan api sederhana.4. Perasakan dengan gula dan garam.5. Bila mendidih, masukkan tomato dan daun ketumbar. Kacau sekejap, kemudian angkat.6. Perah asam limau nipis sebelum dihidang."},{"question":"కింది ప్రశ్నకు సమాధానం ఇవ్వండిఅధిశోషణం అనువర్తనాలను గురించి వివరంగా తెలపండి.","answer":"(i) అధిక శూన్యస్థితిని ఏర్పరచడం :ఒక పాత్రలో అధిక శూన్య స్థితిని పొందడానికి ఆ పాత్రలోని గాలిని నిర్వాత పంపు ‘ద్వారా తొలగిస్తారు. ఈ ప్రక్రియలో. పాత్రలో ఇంకా మిగిలి ఉన్న కొద్దిపాటి గాలిని, బొగ్గును ఉపయోగించి అధిశోషణ ప్రక్రియ ద్వారా తొలగిస్తారు.(ii) వాయు ముసుగు:బొగ్గు గనులలో పనిచేసే కార్మికులు గాలిని పీల్చుకొనేటప్పుడు గాలిలోని విషవాయువులను అధిశోషించుకోవడానికి వాడే సాధనాన్ని వాయు ముసుగు అంటారు. ఇది ఉత్తేజపరిచిన బొగ్గు లేదా ఇతర అధిశోషకాల మిశ్రమంతో నిండి ఉంటుంది.(iii) తేమను నియంత్రణ చేయడం :నివాస గదులలో ఉండే తేమను తొలగించి, గాలిలోని తేమను నియంత్రణ చేయడానికి సిలికాజెల్ అల్యూమినాజెల్లను అధిశోషకాలుగా ఉపయోగిస్తారు.(iv) మలిన రంగు ద్రావణాల నుంచి రంగు మలినాలను తొలగించడం :మలిన రంగు ద్రావణాల రంగుకు కారణమైన రంగు మలినాలను, ద్రావణాల నుంచి జాంతవ బొగ్గు ద్వారా తొలగిస్తారు.(v) విజాతి ఉత్ప్రేరణం :ఘనస్థితిలో ఉండే ఉత్ప్రేరకాల ఉపరితలాలపై చర్యలోని క్రియాజనకాలు అధిశోషణం చెందడం ద్వారా చర్యావేగం పెరుగుతుంది. ఘనస్థితి ఉత్ప్రేరకాల వాడకాన్ని పారిశ్రామిక ప్రాముఖ్యం ఉన్న చాలా వాయుస్థితి చర్యలలో మనం గమనిస్తాం. హేబర్ పద్ధతిలో అమోనియా సంశ్లేషణలలో ఐరన్ ను, స్పర్శ (కాంటాక్ట్) పద్ధతిలో H2SO4 తయారీలో V2O6 ను, తైలాలను హైడ్రోజనీకరణం చేసే (వనస్పతి) చర్యలలో సూక్ష్మవిభాజిత Niను ఉత్ప్రేరకాలుగా ఉపయోగించే చర్యలు విజాతి ఉత్ప్రేరణ చర్యలకు ఉదాహరణలు.(vi) జడ వాయువులను వాటి మిశ్రమం నుంచి వేరుపరచడం :బొగ్గుపై వాయువుల అధిశోషణం సామర్థ్యం లేదా అవధి భిన్న వాయువులకు భిన్నంగా ఉంటుంది. కొబ్బరి బొగ్గుపై భిన్న జడవాయువుల అధిశోషణం అవధి భిన్న ఉష్ణోగ్రతల వద్ద భిన్నంగా ఉండటం ఆధారంగా, వ్యక్తిగత జడవాయువులను వాటి మిశ్రమం నుంచి భిన్న ఉష్ణోగ్రతల వద్ద జరిపే అధిశోషణ ప్రక్రియ ద్వారా వేరుపరుస్తారు.(vii) వ్యాధులను నయం చేయడం :క్రిముల ద్వారా కలిగే వ్యాధులను నయం చేయడానికి వాడే చాలా ఔషధాలు ఈ . క్రిములపై అధిశోషణం చెంది వాటి చంపుతాయి.(viii) నురుగు ప్లవన ప్రక్రియ :అల్ప నాణ్యత గల సల్ఫైడ్ ఖనిజాల నుంచి సిలికా లేదా ఇతర మట్టి మలినాలను పైన్ నూనెను నురుగు కారకాలను వాడి తొలగించి, ఖనిజాన్ని గాఢతపరిచే విధానంలో అధిశోషణం ప్రక్రియ చోటుచేసుకొంటుంది.(ix) అధిశోషణ సూచికలు :సిల్వలర్ హాలైడ్ల వంటి కొన్ని అవక్షేపాలు, వాటి ఉపరితలాలపై ఇయోసిన్, ఫ్లోరసీన్ లాంటి కొన్ని రంజనాలను అధిశోషణ చెందించుకొని, అభిలాక్షణిక రంగు మార్పును కలిగించుకుంటాయి. దీని ఆధారంగా అర్జెంటోమెట్రిక్ టైట్రేషన్లలో అంతిమ బిందువును రంజన పదార్థాల ద్వారా నిర్ణయిస్తారు.(x) క్రొమొటోగ్రాఫిక్ విశ్లేషణం :విశ్లేషణ పద్ధతులలోను, పారిశ్రామిక పద్ధతులలోను, అధిశోషణ దృగ్విషయం ఆధారంగా రూపొందించబడిన క్రొమొటోగ్రాఫిక్ పద్ధతులను విస్తారంగా ఉపయోగిస్తారు."},{"question":"شحال كاين من باب فالجنه ؟","answer":"7 أبواب"},{"question":"Kíni a ń pe Ọba Ọ̀yọ́?","answer":"Aláàfin tí ìlú Ọ̀yọ́ ni."},{"question":"Seorang budak lelaki sedang ____________ di atas papan gelungsor sambil__________ oleh rakannya","answer":"meluncur ... diikuti"},{"question":"Hãy hoàn thiện đoạn văn sau: Tối 31/7, tại khu đô thị Vịnh Xuân Đài, Ủy ban nhân dân thị xã Sông Cầu (tỉnh Phú Yên) tổ chức bế mạc Lễ hội tôm hùm Sông Cầu lần thứ nhất - năm 2022. Buổi lễ cũng đón nhận kỷ lục","answer":"Guiness Việt Nam 100 món ăn từ tôm hùm và vinh danh người nuôi tôm hùm tiêu biểu. Trước đó, vào chiều cùng ngày, Hội thi trình diễn Ẩm thực \\"Tôm hùm - Tinh hoa của biển\\" và xác lập kỷ lục Việt Nam \\"100 món ăn từ tôm hùm\\" đã diễn ra tại nhà Văn hóa Thể thao thị xã Sông Cầu, tỉnh Phú Yên."},{"question":"নিম্নোক্ত পাঠ্যের সারাংশ বলো:জাতিকে শক্তিশালী, শ্রেষ্ঠ, ধন-সম্পদশালী, উন্নত ও সুখী করতে হলে শিক্ষা ও জ্ঞান বর্ষার বারিধারার মতো সর্বসাধারণের মধ্যে সমভাবে বিতরণ করতে হবে। দেশে সরল ও সহজ ভাষার নানা প্রকারের পুস্তক প্রচারের দ্বারা এ কার্য সিদ্ধ হয়। শক্তিশালী দৃষ্টিসম্পন্ন মহাপুরুষদের লেখনীর প্রভাবে একটি জাতির মানসিক ও পার্থিব অবস্থার পরিবর্তন অপেক্ষাকৃত অল্পসময়ে সংশোধিত হয়ে থাকে। দেশের প্রত্যেক মানুষ তার ভুল ও কুসংস্কার, অন্ধতা ও জড়তা, হীনতা ও সংকীর্ণতা পরিহার করে একটি বিনয় মহিমোজ্জ্বল উচ্চ জীবনের ধারণা করতে শেখে। মনুষ্যত্ব ও ন্যায়ের প্রতিষ্ঠা করাই সে ধর্ম মনে করে আত্মমর্যাদাসম্পন্ন হয় এবং গভীর দৃষ্টি লাভ করে। তারপর বিরাট জাতির বিরাট বিরাট দেহে শক্তি জেগে ওঠে।","answer":"কোনো জাতিকে সমৃদ্ধি অর্জন করতে হলে সর্বসাধারণকে শিক্ষা ও জ্ঞানের সমান সুযোগ দিতে হবে। সরল ভাষায় লিখিত বই প্রচারের মাধ্যমে এ কাজ সহজেই করা সম্ভব। এসকল বইয়ে থাকে মহাপুরুষদের শক্তিশালী দৃষ্টির স্পর্শ যা একটি জাতিকে তার সকল ক্ষুদ্রতা, সংকীর্ণতা পরিহার করে মানসিকভাবে সমুন্নত হতে সাহায্য করে। "},{"question":"வினா: கலவைப் பொருள் என்பது எது ?1.பால்2.வினிகர்3.அசிட்டோன்4.பார்மலின்","answer":"விடை:1.பால்"},{"question":"ਵੀਅਤਨਾਮ ਦੀ ਰਾਜਧਾਨੀ ਹੈਨੋਈ ਵਿੱਚ ਅਮਰੀਕਾ ਦੇ ਰਾਸ਼ਟਰਪਤੀ ਡੋਨਲਡ ਟਰੰਪ ਤੇ ਉੱਤਰੀ ਕੋਰੀਆ ਦੇ ਕਿਮ ਜੋਂਗ ਉਨ ਮੀਟਿੰਗ ਦੌਰਾਨ ਇਕ-ਦੂਜੇ ਨੂੰ ਮਿਲੇ । ਮੀਟਿੰਗ ਕਿੱਥੇ ਹੋਈ?","answer":"ਮੀਟਿੰਗ ਹਨੋਈ ਵਿਖੇ ਹੋਈ।"},{"question":"Mene ne Hukunci idan Juma’a ta haɗu da ranar idi?","answer":"Amsa: Maluma sun samu tsaɓani game da wanda yayi Sallar idi shin Wajabcin Juma’a zata faɗi a kansa a bisa zantuka biyu shahararru:Na farko: Wajabcin Juma’a bata faɗi a kansa ba, Wannan Shine Mazahaba ta Jamhur. Hanafiyya, Shafi’iyya da Malikiyya. Mafi yawancin Malumar Fiqhu suna tafiya kan wannan, kuma shine zaɓi na Ibnul Munzir, da Ibnu Hazm, da Ibnu Abdul Bar.Magana ta biyu itace: duk wanda yaje Sallar Idi ranar da Juma’a ta haɗu da idi to wajabcin Juma’a ta faɗi akan sa, duk da cewa Wajibi ne ga limamin gari yayi sallar, domin wa’inda suke so suyi sallar suyi tare dashi. Wannan itace Mazahaba ta Hanabila(Kasshaful Kanna: 2/40,. Almugni: 2/265)"},{"question":"*ما عاصمة إيطاليا ؟","answer":"روما"},{"question":"‘కంగారు’ అనే జంతువు …………. ఖండంలో మాత్రమే కనబడుతుంది.ఎ) ఆసియాబి) ఆస్ట్రేలియాసి) ఆఫ్రికాడి) అమెరికా","answer":"బి) ఆస్ట్రేలియా"},{"question":"问题：朝鲜的传统美食有哪些？","answer":"答案：朝鲜的传统美食有泡菜、辣白菜、炸鸡和石锅拌饭等。"},{"question":"Irúfẹ́ àròkọ wo ni ó dálé lórí ìyàn jíjà? ","answer":"Àròkọ Alárìyànjiyàn. "},{"question":"Иш таштоо дегенди кандай түшүнөсүз ","answer":"Өздөрүнүн саясий жана экономикалык талаптарын орундатуу максатында жумушчулардын уюмдашкан түрдө иш таштоосу, уюшкан түрдө кызматка чыкпай коюу. Былтыркы забастовкага катышкандыгым үчүн өч алгысы келип жаткандыр, – деди Рудаушек (Баялинов)"},{"question":"મુકેશ માલવણકરની \\"દીકરી મારી લાડકવાયી\\" કવિતા લખો.","answer":"દીકરી મારી લાડકવાયી લક્ષ્મીનો અવતારએ સૂએ તો રાત પડે ને જાગે તો સવારદીકરી મારી...દીકરી તારા વ્હાલનો દરિયો જીવનભર છલકાયપામતા જીવન માત-પિતાનું ધન્ય થઈ જાયએક જ સ્મિતમાં તારા ચમકે મોતીડાં હાજરદીકરી મારી...ઢીંગલા સાથે રમતી ઢીંગલી જેવું મારું બાળરમતા થાકીને ભૂખ લાગે તો ખીર રાખું તૈયારરૂપમાં તારા લાગે મને પરીનો અણસારદીકરી મારી...કાળી ઘેલી વાણીથી ઘર ઘૂઘરો થઈ ને ગુંજેપા-પા પગલી ચલાવતા બાપનું હૈયું ઝૂમેદીકરી તું તો માત-પિતાનો સાચો છે આધારદીકરી મારી...હૈયાના ઝૂલે હેતની દોરી બાંધી તને ઝૂલવુંહાલરડાની રેશ્મી રજાઈ તને હું ઓઢાડુંપાવન પગલે તારા મારો ઉજળો છે સંસારદીકરી મારી..."},{"question":"Riga mooy gëblag man réew ?","answer":"Riga mooy gëblag réewum Lettonie."},{"question":"Hãy chọn đáp án đúng nhất cho câu hỏi sau:Tôn Ngộ Không bị đè dưới núi Ngũ Hành bao nhiêu năm?a. 50 nămb. 500 nămc. 5.000 năm","answer":"b. 500 nămTôn Ngộ Không bị giam dưới núi suốt 500 nămĐại náo Thiên Cung là giai đoạn nổi tiếng nhất trong bộ truyện Tây du ký, nói về nhân vật Tôn Ngộ Không khi còn xưng hùng xưng bá. Tôn Ngộ Không được Ngọc Hoàng mời lên thiên đình với mục đích giao cho một chức vụ nhỏ.Tuy nhiên, Ngộ Không tính nào tật nấy, sau khi không được mời dự tiệc đã ăn quả đào Trường Thọ và uống những viên thuốc trường sinh bất tử của Thái Thượng Lão Quân. Thiên đình đành phải tìm cách khống chế Ngộ Không. Tề Thiên phải liên tục kháng cự mười vạn thiên binh, tứ đại thiên vương, Nhị Lang Thần - cháu Ngọc Hoàng Đại Đế  và Na Tra. Cuối cùng, Ngộ Không bị bắt. Tuy nhiên, tất cả hành hình của thiên đình đều thất bại nên họ phải nhốt Ngộ Không vào lò bát quái của Thái Thượng Lão Quân. Sau khi bị nung đốt suốt 49 ngày, Ngộ Không làm nổ tung lò và thoát ra, càng mạnh hơn trước.Đến đường cùng, thiên đình đành phải xin Phật Thích Ca Mâu Ni giúp đỡ. Phật đánh cược rằng Ngộ Không sẽ không thể thoát khỏi lòng bàn tay của Phật, nếu thua thì xin dâng cả Thiên giới cho Ngộ Không. Ngộ Không tự tin vì có thể nhào lộn một cái trên một vạn tám ngàn dặm nên đã đồng ý. Ngộ Không nhảy xa và đi đến một nơi xa lạ như là tận cùng của trời đất, xung quanh chỉ có năm cây cột và tưởng rằng mình đã đi đến tận chân trời.Ngộ Không viết tám chữ \\"Tề Thiên Đại Thánh đáo thử nhất du\\" trên cột ở giữa rồi tiểu tiện xuống gốc cột thứ nhất. Song, Ngộ Không không biết rằng thật ra chưa ra khỏi lòng bàn tay, cái cột kia chỉ là ngón tay của Phật.Ngộ Không thua cuộc, tìm cách trốn chạy nhưng Phật đã úp lòng bàn tay và nhốt Mỹ hầu vương dưới dãy núi Ngũ Hành.Ngộ Không bị đè dưới núi 500 năm, trước khi được giải thoát để đi lấy kinh."},{"question":"வினா : இந்தியாவையும் இலங்கையும் பிரிக்கும் நீர்ச்சந்தி?","answer":" விடை :  பாக் நீர்ச்சந்தி."},{"question":"Apakah jawapan untuk teka-teki yang bertemakan permainan berikut: Sejenis sukan yang berkaitan dengan pasir, jaring dan bikini.","answer":"Jawapannya ialah bola tampar."},{"question":"أين تتكون الرابطة الأيونية ؟ أجب على السؤال السابق بإستخدام هذا النص: تحدث الرابطة التساهمية غالبا بين الذرات التي لها سالبية كهربية متماثلة (عالية)، حيث أنه تلزم طاقة كبيرة لتحريك إلكترون من الذرة. الرابطة التساهمية غالبا ما تحدث بين اللا فلزات، بينما تكون الرابطة الأيونية أكثر شيوعا بين الذرات الفلزية والذرات اللافلزية.","answer":"بالتأكيد الإجابة هي بين الذرات الفلزية والذرات اللافلزية."},{"question":"ලෙමන්ග්‍රාස් බෝග ස්ථාපිත කිරීම ගැන විස්තරයක් කරන්න. ","answer":"රෝපණ ද්‍රව්‍ය: බීජ හා මොරෙයියන් යන දෙකම රෝපණ ද්‍රව්‍ය ලෙස භාවිතා කරයි.ලෙමන්ග්‍රාස් මල් යනු බීජ විශාල ප්‍රමාණයක් නිපදවන ශුකියකි. පරිණත වීමෙන් පසු, මල් අස්වැන්න ලබා ගත හැකි අතර වියළී දින 2-3 කට පසු බීජ වෙන් කළ හැකිය. කෙලින්ම ක්ෂේත්‍රයට බීජ වැපිරිය හැකි අතර සෘජු බීජ පැළ කිරීම සඳහා හෙක්ටයාරයකට කි.ග්‍රෑ. 25 ක් පමණ බීජ අවශ්‍ය වේ. එසේ නොමැතිනම්, පැළෑටි ලබා ගැනීම සඳහා තවාන් පාත්ති තුළ බීජ වපුරා ගත හැකි අතර පසුව එම පැළ ක්ෂේත්‍රයේ සිටුවිය හැකිය. තවාන් වල වපුරන්නේ නම් සඳහා බීජ කිලෝග්‍රෑම් 3-4 ක් පමණ ප්‍රමාණවත් වේ.අස්වැන්න නෙලීමෙන් පසු බීජ වල ජීව්‍යතාවය විශාල ලෙස පහත වැටෙන බැවින් බීජ හැකි ඉක්මනින් වැපිරිය යුතුය.ප්‍රචාරණය සඳහා භාවිතා කරන පොදු ක්‍රමය වන්නේ මොරෙයියන් භාවිතා කිරීමයි. මොරෙයියන් මව් පඳුරු වලින් වෙන් කොට ක්ෂේත්‍රයේ සිටුවනු ලැබේ. සෙන්ටිමීටර් 60×60 හෝ සෙන්ටිමීටර් 60×45 පරතරයකින් එක් හෙක්ටයාරයක් සිටුවීමට මොරෙයියන් 24000-30000 ක් පමණ අවශ්‍ය වේ."},{"question":"दिइएको कवितांश पढी सोधिएका प्रश्नको उत्तर दिनुहोस्‌ ।जुटेका ज्ञानले जो छन्‌ पार्दै धर्ती मनोहरउठेका कर्मले जो छन्‌ गर्दै निर्माण सुन्दर ।समर्पित भएका छन्‌ जो सदा न्यायखातिरसंसारमा उठेका छन्‌ तिनैका विजयी शिर ।प्रश्न :  कर्म गर्नेको जिन्दगी कस्तो बन्छ ?","answer":"उत्तर : कर्म गर्नेको जिन्दगी सुन्दर बन्छ र उनीहरुले कर्म गरेर समाज र देशलाई पनि सुन्दर बनाउँछन्‌ ।"},{"question":"Rumuskan jawaban untuk pertanyaan rumit ini: Keahlian Chien-Shiung Wu dalam fisika eksperimental memunculkan perbandingan dengan seorang ilmuwan yang meninggal pada tahun berapa?","answer":"Tahun 1934"},{"question":"Hãy tiếp tục đoạn văn sau: Chiều 31/7, Công an tỉnh TT-Huế đã có thông tin chính thức ban đầu về vụ dùng súng AK cướp tiệm vàng gây chấn động dư luận tại Huế xảy ra vào trưa cùng ngày. Theo đó, vào khoảng 12h30 trưa 31/7, một đối tượng sử dụng súng AK bất ngờ xông vào hai tiệm vàng Hoàng Đức và Thái Lợi (trước chợ Đông Ba, phường Đông Ba) nổ súng chỉ thiên uy hiếp chủ tiệm vàng rồi cướp vàng. Tuy nhiên, sau đó đối tượng đem số vàng này vứt ra phía vỉa hè, rồi di chuyển đến khu vực cầu Gia Hội. Ngay khi nhận được tin báo, Giám đốc Công an tỉnh TT-Huế Nguyễn Thanh Tuấn đã trực tiếp chỉ đạo các lực lượng chức năng thuộc Công an tỉnh, Công an TP Huế nhanh chóng có mặt tại hiện trường, triển khai đồng bộ các biện pháp nghiệp vụ, khoanh vùng và ngăn chặn người dân đi chuyển vào khu vực hiện trường. Do đây là khu vực trung tâm TP Huế, đông dân cư, để đảm bảo an toàn cho người dân, lực lượng công an đã tìm cách hướng đối tượng di chuyển đến khu nhà lục giác thuộc công viên Trịnh Công Sơn (phường Đông Ba, Huế). Theo cơ quan công an, thời điểm này, nghi phạm cướp tiệm vàng có biểu hiện kích động, muốn tự vẫn. Đại tá Phạm Văn Toàn - Trưởng","answer":"phòng Cảnh sát Hình sự Công an tỉnh TT-Huế và một số cán bộ công an đã trực tiếp tiếp cận, trò chuyện và thuyết phục đối tượng; tuy nhiên, nghi phạm yêu cầu được nói chuyện với đại tá Đặng Ngọc Sơn - Phó Giám đốc Công an tỉnh TT-Huế. Khi nghe đại tá Đặng Ngọc Sơn động viên, thuyết phục, đối tượng đã giao nộp vũ khí và xin đầu thú. Lực lượng công an ngay sau đó đã khống chế, dẫn giải nghi phạm cướp tiệm vàng về trụ sở cơ quan chức năng để lấy lời khai, điều tra vụ việc. Bước đầu xác định nghi phạm khai tên là Ngô Văn Quốc (SN 1984, trú tại thị xã Hương Thủy, tỉnh TT-Huế)."},{"question":"VR म्हणजे काय? VR हेडसेट कसे कार्य करतात?","answer":"व्हर्च्युअल रिअॅलिटी (VR) म्हणजे संगणकाद्वारे व्युत्पन्न केलेले सिम्युलेशन किंवा त्रि-आयामी वातावरणातील मनोरंजन ज्याचा एखाद्या व्यक्तीशी संवाद साधता येतो किंवा त्याचा शोध घेता येतो. हे सिम्युलेशन वापरकर्त्याला अशा प्रकारे विसर्जित करण्यासाठी डिझाइन केले आहे की त्यांना असे वाटते की ते त्या वातावरणात प्रत्यक्षरित्या उपस्थित आहेत, जरी ते प्रत्यक्षात डिजिटल माध्यमांद्वारे ते अनुभवत आहेत.VR हेडसेट ही प्राथमिक हार्डवेअर उपकरणे आहेत जी आभासी वास्तवाचा अनुभव घेण्यासाठी वापरली जातात. त्यामध्ये हेड-माउंटेड डिस्प्ले (HMD) असतो जो वापरकर्त्याच्या डोक्यावर गॉगल किंवा हेल्मेटच्या जोडीप्रमाणे परिधान केला जातो. इमर्सिव्ह VR अनुभव तयार करण्यासाठी VR हेडसेट विशेष स्क्रीन, सेन्सर आणि काहीवेळा अतिरिक्त घटकांसह सुसज्ज आहे.VR हेडसेट कसे कार्य करतात ते येथे आहे:1. हेड-माउंटेड डिस्प्ले (HMD): VR हेडसेटचा मुख्य घटक हेड-माउंट केलेला डिस्प्ले आहे. येथेच आभासी वातावरण वापरकर्त्याच्या डोळ्यांसमोर सादर केले जाते. HMD मध्ये दोन स्वतंत्र डिस्प्ले असतात, प्रत्येक डोळ्यासाठी एक, जे स्टिरीओस्कोपिक प्रभाव तयार करते जे दृश्यांना खोली देते.2. सेन्सर्स: VR हेडसेट विविध सेन्सर्सने सुसज्ज आहेत जसे की एक्सेलेरोमीटर, जायरोस्कोप आणि काहीवेळा बाह्य कॅमेरे. हे सेन्सर्स रिअल टाइममध्ये वापरकर्त्याच्या डोक्याच्या हालचाली आणि अभिमुखतेचा मागोवा घेतात. वापरकर्ता डोके हलवताना आभासी वातावरणाचे योग्य दृश्य प्रस्तुत करण्यासाठी हा डेटा महत्त्वपूर्ण आहे.3. ऑप्टिक्स: VR हेडसेटचे ऑप्टिक्स डिस्प्लेमधून वापरकर्त्याच्या डोळ्यांकडे योग्यरित्या निर्देशित करण्यासाठी आणि प्रतिमा फोकस करण्यासाठी डिझाइन केलेले आहेत. लेन्सचा वापर बर्‍याचदा दृश्याचे विस्तृत क्षेत्र तयार करण्यासाठी आणि आरामदायी आणि स्पष्ट दृश्य अनुभव सुनिश्चित करण्यासाठी वापरकर्त्याच्या डोळ्यांमधील अंतर (इंटरप्युपिलरी अंतर) समायोजित करण्यासाठी केला जातो.4. पोझिशनल ट्रॅकिंग: हेड रोटेशन ट्रॅक करण्याव्यतिरिक्त, अनेक VR हेडसेट पोझिशनल ट्रॅकिंग देखील देतात. याचा अर्थ ते एखाद्या भौतिक जागेत वापरकर्त्याच्या हालचालींचा मागोवा घेऊ शकतात, त्यांना फिरू शकतात आणि आभासी वातावरणाशी संवाद साधू शकतात. हे सामान्यत: खोलीत ठेवलेल्या बाह्य सेन्सरद्वारे किंवा इनसाइड-आउट ट्रॅकिंग तंत्रज्ञानाचा वापर करून साध्य केले जाते जे हेडसेटच्या स्वतःच्या कॅमेर्‍यांचा वापर करून पर्यावरणाची जाणीव करून देते.5. कंट्रोलर्स आणि इनपुट डिव्हाइसेस: आभासी वातावरणाशी संवाद साधण्यासाठी, VR हेडसेट अनेकदा हँडहेल्ड कंट्रोलर किंवा इतर इनपुट डिव्हाइसेससह येतात. हे नियंत्रक आभासी जागेत ट्रॅक केले जाऊ शकतात आणि वापरकर्त्यांना वस्तूंशी संवाद साधू शकतात, मेनू नेव्हिगेट करू शकतात आणि आभासी जगात क्रिया करू शकतात.6. संगणक प्रणाली: रिअल टाइममध्ये इमर्सिव्ह व्हिज्युअल तयार करण्यासाठी VR अनुभवांना महत्त्वपूर्ण संगणकीय शक्ती आवश्यक असते. बहुतेक VR हेडसेटला सुसंगत संगणक किंवा गेमिंग कन्सोलशी कनेक्ट करणे आवश्यक आहे जे VR सामग्रीच्या प्रस्तुतीकरणाच्या मागण्या हाताळू शकतात.7. सामग्री: व्हर्च्युअल रिअॅलिटी अनुभव, गेम, सिम्युलेशन आणि अॅप्लिकेशन्स विशेषतः VR च्या इमर्सिव्ह क्षमतांचा वापर करण्यासाठी डिझाइन केलेले आहेत. हे अॅप्लिकेशन वापरकर्ते एक्सप्लोर करू शकतील आणि संवाद साधू शकतील असे आभासी वातावरण आणि परिस्थिती निर्माण करतात.जेव्हा वापरकर्ता VR हेडसेट वापरतो तेव्हा या घटकांचे संयोजन त्यांच्या सभोवतालच्या आभासी जगाचा भ्रम निर्माण करण्यासाठी एकत्रितपणे कार्य करते. नियंत्रक वापरून ते त्यांचे डोके हलवतात किंवा पर्यावरणाशी संवाद साधतात तेव्हा, हेडसेट व्हिज्युअल अद्यतनित करतो आणि त्यांच्या क्रियांशी जुळण्यासाठी दृष्टीकोन समायोजित करतो, ज्यामुळे एक अत्यंत इमर्सिव्ह अनुभव येतो."},{"question":"வினா: பறவைத்தீவு என அழைக்கப்படுவது எது?","answer":"விடை: நியூசிலாந்து"},{"question":" talantaalli","answer":"Wax si kala googo'an oo waqti u dhexeeya u dhaca."},{"question":"अर्थशास्त्रात नोबेल पारितोषिक मिळवणारे पहिले भारतीय कोण होते?(A) रवींद्रनाथ ठाकूर(B) व्यंकटरामन रामकृष्णन(C) अमर्त्य सेन(D) यांपैकी नाही=> ","answer":"(C) अमर्त्य सेन"},{"question":"Dựa trên tiêu đề sau, hãy viết một đoạn văn tối đa 500 chữ: Trọng tài gây tranh cãi trên sân Cần Thơ","answer":"Trận đấu giữa Cần Thơ và Phú Thọ là 1 trong 2 trận cuối của vòng 9 hạng  Nhất diễn ra vào chiều 31/7. Sau hiệp 1 hòa với tỷ số 0-0, Phú Thọ bất ngờ dẫn bàn ở đầu hiệp 2 nhờ công của Văn Tùng. Cần Thơ sau nhiều nỗ lực thì đến phút 70, Thiện Chí thực hiện cú đệm bóng làm tung lưới đội khách. Trong tình huống này, trọng tài biên đã căng cờ báo việt vị nhưng trọng tài chính vẫn công nhận bàn thắng, dẫn đến phản ứng của đội Phú Thọ. Bàn gỡ được công nhận trong tình huống tranh cãi giúp cho Cần Thơ hưng phấn hơn. Phút 83, đội trưởng Thanh Long thể hiện sức càn lướt rất tốt khi vượt qua sự truy cản quyết liệt của hậu vệ đội khách rồi ghi bàn nâng tỷ số 2-1 cho Cần Thơ. Trong nỗ lực còn nước còn tát, Phú Thọ vùng lên và được hưởng quả đá phạt trực tiếp ở phút 90+6. Từ đường chuyền của đồng đội, Mạnh Duy đánh đầu cân bằng tỷ số 2-2 cho Phú Thọ.  Ở trận còn lại, Khánh Hòa nhập cuộc rất quyết tâm, nắm thế chủ động và tạo được hàng loạt cơ hội ăn bàn khá rõ nét về phía khung thành của Bà Rịa Vũng Tàu. Nhưng trong một trận đấu xuất sắc, thủ môn Thanh Tuấn đã hóa giải gần như tất cả các tình huống nguy hiểm nhất của Khánh Hòa tạo về phía cầu môn của BRVT. Về phần mình, đội khách chỉ tạo được một tình huống ăn bàn rõ nét trong suốt 90 phút từ quả đánh đầu của Duy Khánh nhưng không thể chuyển hóa thành bàn thắng. Khi tưởng chừng như chủ nhà phải tiếc nuối bởi một trận hòa thì ở phút bù giờ thứ hai, trong một tình huống được hưởng quả đá phạt trực tiếp, Kim Hùng câu bóng như đặt để trung vệ Thành Lộc bật cao đánh đầu ghi bàn thắng duy nhất, mang về 3 điểm cho chủ nhà. Thắng lợi này giúp cho Khánh Hòa gia nhập Top 3. "},{"question":"Ity misy ampahan-dahatsoratra: \\"Be loatra ny fitaka nataon'ny filoha teo aloha Andry Rajoelina\\"Iza ilay filoha teo aloha nanao fitaka be loatra?","answer":"Ilay filoha teo aloha nanao fitaka be loatra dia i Andry Rajoelina"},{"question":"Apakah jawapan untuk teka-teki ini? Apa yang berkaki lapan tetapi tidak mempunyai tangan, bermata dua dan perut dipenuhi sarang.","answer":"Jawapannya ialah labah-labah. Labah-labah merupakan haiwan invertebrata artropoda pemangsa yang berkaki lapan, mulut yang tidak boleh mengunyah, mempunyai dua tagma dan organ menghasilkan sutera."},{"question":"සිංහල ළමා  කතන්දරයක් ලියන්න.","answer":"ඔන්න එකමත් එක කාලෙක එක රටක් තිබුනා. මේ රටේ මිනිස්සු බොහොම සතුටින් ජීවත් වුනා. ඒකට ලොකු හේතුවක් තිබුනා. මොකක්ද දන්නවද මේ රට පාලනය කරපු රජතුමා බොහොම යහපත් රජෙක් හින්දා තමයි එහෙම වුනේ. ඉතිං ඔන්න දවසක් මේ රජතුමාට හිතුනා මුළු රට පුරාම සංචාරය කරන්න.හැබැයි විශේෂත්වයක් තිබුනා මොකක්ද දන්නවද රජතුමාට තනියෙන්ම තමයි සංචාරය කරන්න ඕනෙ වුනේ.මේ සංචාරයේ එක අරමුණක් තමයි රටේ ජනතාවගේ දුක සැප සොයා බැලීම. ඔන්න දුවේ පුතේ මේ රජතුමා දවසක් තනියෙන්ම ගමන යන්න පටන්ගත්තා.රජතුමා ගමන ගියේ පයින්මයි. යන අතරමඟ හමුවෙන මිනිස්සුත් එක්ක කතාබහ කරන්න මේ රජතුමා අමතක කරේ නෑ. මේ මිනිස්සුන්ටත් ගොඩක් සතුටු හිතුනා.තමන්ගේ රටේ රජ්ජුරුවෝ මේ විදියට එයාලගේ දුක සැප බලන්න ආපු එක  ගැන. තමන්ගේ රටේ මිනිස්සු ගොඩක් සතුටින් ජීවත් වෙනවා දැකපු රජතුමා ගොඩක් සතුටින් එයාගේ සංචාරය ඉවර කරලා ආපහු රජ වාසලට පැමිණියා. රජවාසලට ආපු රජතුමාගේ කකුල් ඉදිමිලා යටිපතුල් හොඳටම රිදෙන්න පටන් ගත්තා.ඒ මොකද දන්නවද රටේ පාරවල් ගොඩක් හදලා තිබ්බෙ කළු ගල් තලලා දාලයි.සමහර පාරවල් එහමවත් තිබුනේ නැහැ ගොඩක් අමාරුයි ඒවාගේ පයින් ඇවිදින්න.ඉතිං මේ රජතුමාට ලොකු දුකක් ඇතිවුනා.මහජනයාටත් මේ කටුක මාර්ග හින්දා ගොඩක් වේදනා විදින්න වෙනවා නේද කියලා.වහාම අමාත්‍ය මණ්ඩලය රැස් කරපු මේ රජතුමා රටේ සියලුම පාරවල් සම් වලින් ආවරණය කරන්න කියලා අණ කරා.මුළු රාජ සභාවෙම කසු කුසුවක් පැතිරෙන්න වුනා. අමාත්‍ය මණ්ඩලයේ මතය වුනේ රටේ සියළුම මාර්ග සම් වලින් ආවරණය කරන්න නම් විශාල සම් ප්‍රමාණයක් අවශ්‍ය වෙනවා. ඉතිං ඒ නිසා මේ වැඩේට විශාල මුදල් ප්‍රමාණයක් වැය වෙනවා කියලා අමාත්‍ය මණ්ඩලය රජතුමාට කිව්වා. මේ අතර එක බුද්ධිමත් ඇමති කෙනෙක්, රජතුමනි රටේ සියළුම මාර්ග සම් වලින් ආවරණය කරනවා වෙනුවට අපි මහජනයාට පවසමු එයාලගේ කකුල් සම් වලින් හදපු ආවරණයකින් ආවරණය කරගෙන මේ මාර්ග වල ගමන් කරන්න කියලා.ඒ ඇමති තුමාගේ යෝජනාව රාජ සභාවේ හැමෝගෙම ප්‍රශංසාවට ලක් වුනා.රජතුමාටත් ගොඩක් සතුටුයි. මොකද ඒ යෝජනාව ඇත්තටම හොඳ යෝජනාවක් නිසා.ඉතිං රජතුමා රටවැසියන් හැමෝටම මේ යෝජනාව දැනුවත් කරන්න පණිවිඩකාරයෝ යැව්වා.දැක්කා නේද පුංචි පුතේ මේ කතාවෙන් අපිට ආදර්ශ ගොඩක් ගන්න පුළුවන් නේද ප්‍රශ්නයක් බුද්ධිමත්ව විසඳන්නේ කොහොමද වගේම අපි තේරුම්ගන්න ඕනෙ අපිට මුළු ලෝකයක්ම හදන්න අමාරුයි ඒත් අපි තනි තනියෙන් බුද්ධිමත්ව වැඩ කරොත් මුළු ලෝකෙටම බලපාන ප්‍රශ්න බොහොම ලේසියෙන්ම විසඳගන්න පුලුවන් කියලා."},{"question":"Inona ny fomba fivavahana voalohany teto Madagasikara ?1- Fivavahana nentin-drazana2- Fivavahana kristianina3- Fivavahana silamo","answer":"1 : Fivavahana nentin-drazana. Io no fivavahana nisy voalohany teto Madagasikara izay mino ny fitahian'ny Zanahary, Andriamanitra ary ny Razana. Misy ihany koa mivavaka amin'ny zavatra na ilay lazaina hoe sampy (sary, vato, hazo, voninkazo ...)."},{"question":"Көл деген сөздү кандай түшүнөсүз?","answer":"Көл — бул чанактары, чөйчөктөрү табигый түрдө суу менен толтурулган көлмө. Өлчөмдөрү жана тереңдиги ар кандай. Суусу тунук жана туздуу болот. \\"Атың барда жер тааны, атаң барда эл тааны\\" дейт кыргызда. Өлкөбүздөгү айыл-кыштактардын, жер-суулардын аталыш тарыхын билген жакшы."},{"question":"नेपालमा कति प्रजाति छन् ?","answer":"नेपालले यसको परिदृश्यमा धेरै वन्यजन्तुहरू पाइन्छ, यसको जंगलहरूले ३०१६७ जीवित प्रजातिहरूलाई आश्रय दिन्छ; १३०६७ बिरुवा र १७०९७ जनावरहरू सहित।"},{"question":"வினா:Activity-தமிழில் மொழிபெயர்க்கவும்","answer":"விடை:செயல்பாடு"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"cantik bagai bidadari\\"? Berikan satu contoh ayat. ","answer":"Maksudnya adalah wajah yang manis atau sangat menarik. Contohnya, wajahnya yang cantik bagai bidadari membolehkannya memenangi Miss Malaysia apabila dia masih muda. "},{"question":"What are the challenges in handling sarcasm and irony in sentiment analysis?","answer":"Sarcasm and irony pose challenges in sentiment analysis because the literal meaning of words may differ from the intended sentiment. Contextual understanding and tone analysis are crucial for accurate interpretation."},{"question":"Lithetha ukuthini igama u\\"Notyayambo\\" nesilungu?","answer":"A flower,The word can be used as a pronoun for a girl child, meaning mother of all flowers."},{"question":"मेळघाट व्याघ्र प्रकल्पातील फुलपाखरू प्रजातींची एकूण संख्या कितीवर पोहचली आहे?(A)  १४१(B)  १४८(C)  १४१(D)  १५०","answer":"(C) १४१"},{"question":"Bu yazı hangi önemli olay hakkındadır?: 2014 yılında gençlerde dünya şampiyonu olan Bolkvadze, 2015'teki dünya şampiyonasında 7. sırada yer aldı. Erkekler grekoromen 66 kg kategorisinde Rio de Janeiro'daki 2016 Yaz Olimpiyatları'na katıldı ve bronz madalya elde etti. Avrupa Şampiyonaları'nda 2016'da bronz, 2018'de ise gümüş madalya kazandı. Ayrıca Minsk'te düzenlenen 2019 Avrupa Oyunları'nda 67 kg'da ikinci olarak gümüş madalyanın sahibi oldu.","answer":"Bolkvadze'nin 2014 ile 2019 yılları arasındaki şampiyonlukları ve başarıları."},{"question":"在加拿大，交叉路口，並有讓牌標誌面對時，你怎麼做？","answer":"慢行，如有需要時停車及讓有優先權車輛先行。"},{"question":" भौतिकशास्त्रात नोबेल पारितोषिक मिळवणारे पहिले भारतीय कोण होते?(A) कैलाश सत्यार्थी(B) जे जे थॉमसन(C) सी. व्ही. रमण(D) मदर टेरेसा=>","answer":" (C) सी. व्ही. रमण"},{"question":"アメリカ合衆国で、大統領、副大統領ともいなくなった場合に職務を代行するのはどんな役職でしょう？","answer":"下院議長です。"},{"question":"Quels sont les principaux défis et enjeux liés à la cybersécurité dans le monde moderne ?","answer":"Les défis de la cybersécurité incluent les attaques informatiques, la protection des données personnelles, la cybercriminalité, et la défense contre les menaces numériques. Les enjeux comprennent la protection de la vie privée, la sécurité nationale, et la stabilité des infrastructures critiques."},{"question":"Isi tempat kosong dengan jawapan yang paling sesuai. Usaha yang dilakukannya selama ini tidak __ apabila dia berjaya memperoleh segulung ijazag dalam bidang perakaunan. A) payah-payahB) ragu-raguC) sudah-sudahD) sia-sia","answer":"Jawapan yang betul ialah D) sia-sia"},{"question":"Maak de volgende zin af: Elementen van het bataljon werden uit Koerland geëvacueerd. Via Kassel en Putlos bereikte zij het","answer":"Westfront en werden en hadden hun laatste gevecht daar. Deze groep werd door de westelijke geallieerde gevangengenomen. Een kampfgruppe met de laatste 15 Tigers, gecommandeerd door Leutnant Wisse bleef achter in Koerland. Dit gedeelte van het bataljon werd gevangengenomen door het Rode Leger."},{"question":"இந்தியாவில் புலிகள் பாதுகாப்புத் திட்டம் எப்போது தொடங்கப்பட்டது?","answer":"புராஜெக்ட் டைகர் என்பது 1973 ஆம் ஆண்டு ஏப்ரல் மாதம் தொடங்கப்பட்ட ஒரு பிரபலமான வனவிலங்கு பாதுகாப்புத் திட்டமாகும். இது வங்காளப் புலிகளின் எண்ணிக்கையை அவற்றின் இயற்கையான வாழ்விடங்களில் பாதுகாப்பதை நோக்கமாகக் கொண்டுள்ளது. உலகில் உள்ள காட்டுப் புலிகளில் கிட்டத்தட்ட 75% இப்போது இந்தியாவில் காணப்படுகின்றன. சேகரிக்கப்பட்ட தரவுகளின் அடிப்படையில் முன்கூட்டிய மதிப்பீட்டின்படி, 20 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டின் தொடக்கத்தில் இந்தியாவில் மட்டும் 50,000 புலிகள் வாழ்ந்திருக்கலாம்.புலிகளை காப்பாற்றவும் பாதுகாக்கவும் முடிந்த அனைத்தையும் செய்வதன் மூலம் புலிகளை காப்பாற்றுவதை நோக்கமாகக் கொண்டது புலிகள் திட்டம். 1960 களில், இந்தியாவின் வனவிலங்குகள் தொடர்ந்து வேட்டையாடுதல், வேட்டையாடுதல் மற்றும் வாழ்விட இழப்பு ஆகியவற்றின் காரணமாக முன்னெப்போதும் இல்லாத நிலையை அடைந்தன. வனவிலங்குகள் சரியாக நடத்தப்படவில்லை, எனவே இந்தப் பிரச்சினையைத் தீர்க்கவும் புலிகளின் எண்ணிக்கையை மீட்டெடுக்கவும் அரசாங்கத்திடம் இருந்து புலி பாதுகாப்புப் படை தேவைப்பட்டது."},{"question":"ලෙමන්ග්‍රාස් භෝගය ගැන විස්තරයක් කරන්න. ","answer":"Cymbopogon citratus / Cymbopogon flexuosusකුලය : ග්‍රැමිනේලෙමන්ග්‍රාස් තෙල් පිළිබඳ පැරණිතම සටහන 17 වන සියවසේදී පිලිපීනයෙන් සොයාගෙන ඇත. එය 1799 දී ජැමෙයිකාවට සහ 1917 දී හයිටියට සහ ඇමරිකා එක්සත් ජනපදයට හඳුන්වා දී ඇත. 1947 දී ඇමරිකා එක්සත් ජනපදයේ ෆ්ලොරිඩා සහ හයිටිවල පළමු වරට වාණිජමය වගා කිරීම් වාර්තා විය. ශ්‍රී ලංකාවට ලෙමන්ග්‍රාස් හඳුන්වා දුන්නේ කවදාද හෝ කවුරුන්ද යන්න නොදනී. 1905 දී ජාතික ශාකාගාරයේ ඇති වාර්තාවලට අනුව, ශ්‍රී ලංකා පර්යේෂකයෙකු වන ජේ. එෆ්. ජොවිට් මහතා දකුණු ඉන්දියාවෙන් “කොචින් සේර” (Cymbopogon citrates) පැල කිහිපයක් ලබා ගෙන පර්යේෂණ කටයුතු සඳහා බණ්ඩරාවල ගොවිපලෙහි වගාකර තිබේ. දශක කිහිපයකට පෙර ශ්‍රී ලංකාවේ විශාල ප්‍රමාණයේ ලෙමන්ග්‍රාස් වගාවන් පැවතුනද දැනට පවතින්නේ කුඩා වගාවන් කිහිපයක් පමණි."},{"question":"පහත  නාම පදයට අදාළ ස්ත්‍රී ලිංග නාම පාදක කුමක්ද?වලහා ","answer":"වැලහින්න "},{"question":"حمید سوریان در بازی‌های قهرمانی جهان سال ۲۰۰۵ در بوداپست چگونه عمل کرد؟","answer":"سوریان جوان که در آن زمان کشتی‌گیری ناشناخته بود، در بوداپست دو کشتی‌گیر به نام‌های ووگار راگیموف اوکراینی و بایرام اوزدمیر از ترکیه را در دوره‌های نخست مسابقه‌ها به ترتیب با امتیاز ۶–۲ و ۷–۲ شکست داد و در کشتی با ازارو ریواس کوبایی که قهرمان سال ۱۹۹۹ جهان و نایب قهرمان المپیک سیدنی و قهرمان قاره آمریکا شد بود، در این پیکار سرنوشت‌ساز، موفق شد در زمانِ نخست ۲ بر ۱، در زمانِ دوم ۷ بر ۱ (و نتیجه نهایی ۹–۲)؛ این حریف کوبایی را شکست دهد. ارمک کوکتیف از قزاقستان حریف بعدی سوریان بود که در این دیدار او حریف خود را با ۶ امتیاز شکست داد و راهی مسابقه نهایی شد و با شکست پارگ ائون چول از کره جنوبی مدال طلا گرفت. سوریان در پنج کشتی که برگزار کرد، مجموعاً ۳۵ امتیاز از حریفان گرفت."},{"question":"Xikmadii: 37aad","answer":"Xikmadii 37aadNoloshu duruus bilaash ah cidna ma barto, marka aan ku leeyahay 'waayaha ayaa wax i baray', ogow in aan qiimaheeda bixiyey.\\"Ku xidhnoow boggeena, oo hel xikmadaha xulkoodii si maalinle ah...."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਤੇਹਾ ਕੋਇ ਨ ਸੁਝਈ ਜਿ ਤਿਸੁ ਗੁਣੁ ਕੋਇ ਕਰੇ ॥੭॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 2 ਤੋਂ ਲਈ ਗਈ ਇੱਕ ਤੁਕ ਦਾ ਵਾਕ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਨਾਨਕ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਸ ਬਾਣੀ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸਦਾ ਮਤਲਬ ਇਹ ਹੈ,\\"ਇਹੋ ਜਿਹਾ ਕੋਈ ਹੋਰ ਨਹੀਂ ਦਿੱਸਦਾ, ਜੋ ਨਿਰਗੁਣ ਜੀਵ ਨੂੰ ਕੋਈ ਗੁਣ ਦੇ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੋਵੇ। ੭।\\""},{"question":"Com que idade pode começar a dirigir no Brasil?","answer":"Até 2023, só é permitido dirigir no Brasil após os 18 anos, ou seja, após atingir a maioridade penal."},{"question":"ماأسم وحده قياس شده الصوت ؟","answer":"الديسيبل"},{"question":"السؤال: من النبي الذي طلب منه قومه أن ينزل لهم مائدة من السماء ؟","answer":"الإجابة: عيسى عليه السلام."},{"question":"Sheeg Magaca wasaaradii uu hoostagi jiray Naadigii Kubbadda Cagta ee Waxool","answer":" Waxaa uu hoos tegi jiray Wasaaradda Xannaanada Xoolaha Dhirta iyo Daaqa"},{"question":"هل الدائر هي عاصمة السعودية؟","answer":"لا، عاصمة المملكة العربية السعودية هي الرياض."},{"question":"ചോദ്യം: ഹോളിവുഡ് എപ്പോഴാണ് സിനിമാ വ്യവസായത്തിന്റെ കേന്ദ്രമായി മാറിയത്? ഉത്തരം:","answer":"1912-ൽ ഹോളിവുഡ് സിനിമാ വ്യവസായത്തിന്റെ കേന്ദ്രമായി മാറി. "},{"question":"အောက်ပါ မေးခွန်းကိုဖြေပါ။ New Jersey က Atlantic City မှာ ကာစီနိုတွေ ဘယ်နှစ်ခုရှိလဲ။","answer":"New Jersey က Atlantic City မှာ ကာစီနို ၉ ခု ရှိပါတယ်။"},{"question":"क्षेत्रफळात भारताचा जगात किताब नंबर लागतो?(A) नववा(B) चौथा(C) आठवा(D) सातवा=>","answer":"(D) सातवा"},{"question":"ما هو مصدر كلمة \\"إضافة\\"؟","answer":"المصدر هو \\"أضاف\\""},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਉੜੀ ॥ਨਿੰਦਉ ਨਿੰਦਉ ਮੋ ਕਉ ਲੋਗੁ ਨਿੰਦਉ ॥ਨਿੰਦਾ ਜਨ ਕਉ ਖਰੀ ਪਿਆਰੀ ॥ਨਿੰਦਾ ਬਾਪੁ ਨਿੰਦਾ ਮਹਤਾਰੀ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਨਿੰਦਾ ਹੋਇ ਤ ਬੈਕੁੰਠਿ ਜਾਈਐ ॥ਨਾਮੁ ਪਦਾਰਥੁ ਮਨਹਿ ਬਸਾਈਐ ॥ਰਿਦੈ ਸੁਧ ਜਉ ਨਿੰਦਾ ਹੋਇ ॥ਹਮਰੇ ਕਪਰੇ ਨਿੰਦਕੁ ਧੋਇ ॥੧॥ਨਿੰਦਾ ਕਰੈ ਸੁ ਹਮਰਾ ਮੀਤੁ ॥ਨਿੰਦਕ ਮਾਹਿ ਹਮਾਰਾ ਚੀਤੁ ॥ਨਿੰਦਕੁ ਸੋ ਜੋ ਨਿੰਦਾ ਹੋਰੈ ॥ਹਮਰਾ ਜੀਵਨੁ ਨਿੰਦਕੁ ਲੋਰੈ ॥੨॥ਨਿੰਦਾ ਹਮਰੀ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਪਿਆਰੁ ॥ਨਿੰਦਾ ਹਮਰਾ ਕਰੈ ਉਧਾਰੁ ॥ਜਨ ਕਬੀਰ ਕਉ ਨਿੰਦਾ ਸਾਰੁ ॥ਨਿੰਦਕੁ ਡੂਬਾ ਹਮ ਉਤਰੇ ਪਾਰਿ ॥੩॥੨੦॥੭੧॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 339 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਭਗਤ ਕਬੀਰ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਵਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਸਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਜਗਤ ਬੇਸ਼ੱਕ ਮੇਰੀ ਨਿੰਦਾ ਕਰੇ, ਬੇਸ਼ੱਕ ਮੇਰੇ ਔਗੁਣ ਭੰਡੇਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਸੇਵਕ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੀ ਨਿੰਦਿਆ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਚੰਗੀ ਲੱਗਦੀ ਹੈਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਨਿੰਦਿਆ ਸੇਵਕ ਦਾ ਮਾਂ ਪਿਉ ਹੈ (ਭਾਵ, ਜਿਵੇਂ ਮਾਪੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਬਾਲ ਵਿਚ ਸ਼ੁਭ ਗੁਣ ਵਧਦੇ ਵੇਖਣਾ ਲੋੜਦੇ ਹਨ, ਤਿਵੇਂ ਨਿੰਦਿਆ ਭੀ ਔਗੁਣ ਨਸ਼ਰ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਭਲੇ ਗੁਣਾਂ ਲਈ ਸਹਾਇਤਾ ਕਰਦੀ ਹੈ) ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।ਜੇ ਲੋਕ ਔਗੁਣ ਨਸ਼ਰ ਕਰਨ ਤਾਂ ਹੀ ਬੈਕੁੰਠ ਵਿਚ ਜਾ ਸਕੀਦਾ ਹੈ (ਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਔਗੁਣ ਛੱਡ ਕੇ) ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ-ਰੂਪ ਧਨ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਵਸਾ ਸਕੀਦਾ ਹੈ ਜੇ ਹਿਰਦਾ ਸੁੱਧ ਹੁੰਦਿਆਂ ਸਾਡੀ ਨਿੰਦਿਆ ਹੋਵੇ (ਭਾਵ, ਜੇ ਸੁੱਧ ਭਾਵਨਾ ਨਾਲ ਅਸੀ ਆਪਣੇ ਔਗੁਣ ਨਸ਼ਰ ਹੁੰਦੇ ਸੁਣੀਏ) ਤਾਂ  ਤਾਂ ਨਿੰਦਕ ਸਾਡੇ ਮਨ ਨੂੰ ਪਵਿੱਤਰ ਕਰਨ ਵਿਚ ਸਹਾਇਤਾ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ (ਤਾਂ ਤੇ) ਜੋ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਸਾਨੂੰ ਭੰਡਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਸਾਡਾ ਮਿੱਤਰ ਹੈਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਸਾਡੀ ਸੁਰਤ ਆਪਣੇ ਨਿੰਦਕ ਵਿਚ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ (ਭਾਵ, ਅਸੀ ਆਪਣੇ ਨਿੰਦਕ ਦੀ ਗੱਲ ਬੜੇ ਧਿਆਨ ਨਾਲ ਸੁਣਦੇ ਹਾਂ) ।(ਅਸਲ ਵਿਚ) ਸਾਡਾ ਮੰਦਾ ਚਿਤਵਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਉਹ ਹੈ, ਜੋ ਸਾਡੇ ਐਬ ਨਸ਼ਰ ਹੋਣੋਂ ਰੋਕਦਾ ਹੈ । ਨਿੰਦਕ ਤਾਂ ਸਗੋਂ ਇਹ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਸਾਡਾ ਜੀਵਨ ਚੰਗਾ ਬਣੇ ।੨।ਜਿਉਂ ਜਿਉਂ ਸਾਡੀ ਨਿੰਦਿਆ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਹੈ, ਤਿਉਂ ਤਿਉਂ ਸਾਡੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ-ਪਿਆਰ ਪੈਦਾ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਕਿਉਂਕਿ ਸਾਡੀ ਨਿੰਦਿਆ ਸਾਨੂੰ ਔਗੁਣਾਂ ਵਲੋਂ ਬਚਾਉਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।ਸੋ, ਦਾਸ ਕਬੀਰ ਲਈ ਤਾਂ ਉਸ ਦੇ ਔਗੁਣਾਂ ਦਾ ਨਸ਼ਰ ਹੋਣਾ ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਵਧੀਆ ਗੱਲ ਹੈ ।ਪਰ (ਵਿਚਾਰਾ) ਨਿੰਦਕ (ਸਦਾ ਦੂਜਿਆਂ ਦੇ ਔਗੁਣਾਂ ਦੀਆਂ ਗੱਲਾਂ ਕਰ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਆਪ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਔਗੁਣਾਂ ਵਿਚ) ਡੁੱਬ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਤੇ ਅਸੀ (ਆਪਣੇ ਔਗੁਣਾਂ ਦੀ ਚੇਤਾਵਨੀ ਨਾਲ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਤੋਂ) ਬਚ ਨਿਕਲਦੇ ਹਾਂ ।੩।੨੦।੭੧।\\""},{"question":"およそ454gずつのバター・卵・砂糖を小麦粉に混ぜて作ったことにその名が因む洋菓子は何でしょう？","answer":"パウンドケーキです。"},{"question":"How does classification differ from clustering in data mining?","answer":"Classification involves assigning predefined labels to data based on learned patterns, while clustering groups data points based on similarities without predefined labels."},{"question":"Kumuu ahaa madaxweyniihii 9aad ee somara dalka soomaliya ?","answer":"Wuxuu ahaa Madaxweynihii 9aad Mohamad Abdullahi Farmaajo."},{"question":"தமிழோவியம் கவிதையில் நும்மை மிகவும் ஈர்த்த அடிகள் குறித்து எழுதுக.","answer":"“மானிட மேன்மையைச் சாதித்திடக் குறள்மட்டுமே போதுமே ஓதி நட”மானிடத்தின் மேன்மையைச் சாதனை செய்ய குறள் மட்டுமே போதும் அதைப் படித்து நடக்க வேண்டும்."},{"question":"ప్రశ్న: అశోకుని శిలాశాసనాలు నిరక్షరాస్యులు కూడా అర్థం చేసుకోగలుగుతున్నారు. ఇది ఎలా సాధ్యమని నీవు అనుకుంటున్నావు?","answer":"అశోకుని శిలాశాసనాలు నిరక్షరాస్యులు కూడా ఎలా అర్థం చేసుకోగలిగినారంటే :1. ‘అశోకుడు’ ధర్మమహామాత్రులు’ అనే అధికారులను నియమించాడు. వారు రాజ్యంలోని వివిధ ప్రాంతాలకు వెళ్ళి ప్రజలకు ధర్మప్రచారం చేసేవారు.2. అశోకుడు తన సందేశాలను శాసనాల రూపంలో రాళ్లపైన, స్తంభాలపైన చెక్కించాడు.3. చదువు రానివారికి వాటి పైనున్న సందేశాలను చదివి వినిపించాలని అధికారులను ఆదేశించాడు.4. అశోకుడు తన ధర్మాన్ని సుదూర ప్రదేశాలైన సిరియా, ఈజిప్టు, గ్రీస్, శ్రీలంకలకు వ్యాప్తి చేయటానికి రాయబారులను పంపించాడు."},{"question":"સમાસના પ્રકારો કેટલા છે? ","answer":"ગુજરાતી વ્યાકરણમા સમાસ ના મુખ્ય સાત (7) પ્રકાર છે. જે નીચે મુજબ છે.1) દ્વન્દ સમાસ2) તપુરુષ સમાસ 3) મધ્યમપદલોપી સમાસ 4) ઉપપદ સમાસ 5) કર્મધારય સમાસ 6) બહુવ્રીહિ સમાસ 7) અવ્યવીભાવ સમાસ"},{"question":"السؤال: كم مرة ورد لفظ الحيوانات على سبيل العموم؟","answer":"إجابة: وردت 14 مرة في كلمة: ” دابة” و 4 في كلمة: ” دواب”"},{"question":"විංශතිය යන පදය පැහැදිලි කර දෙන්න","answer":"විංශතිය යනු අවුරුදු විස්සක කාලයයි."},{"question":"Indil péeteg waat yi ci kàddu gii: Xeex bi kenn xaaru ci CPI, kenn yaakaaru ko ci.","answer":"Waat yi nekk ci kàddu gii di \\"Xeex bi kenn xaaru ci CPI, kenn yaakaaru ko ci.\\" ak séen i péete ñoo di:Xeex: NOUNbi: DETkenn: PRONxaaru: VERBci: ADPCPI: PROPN,: PUNCTkenn: PRONyaakaaru: VERBko: PRONci: ADP.: PUNCT"},{"question":"పారగమ్యత సామర్థ్యం కణాలకి లేకపోతే ఏమవుతుంది?","answer":"కణములకు పారగమ్యత సామర్థ్యం లేకపోయినట్లయితే, అవి ముఖ్యమైన జీవక్రియలను నిర్వహించలేవు.ఆక్సిజన్, గ్లూకోజ్, విటమినులు, క్రొవ్వులు కణమునకు అందకపోయినట్లయితే కణములు జీవక్రియలను జరపలేవు.పరిపక్వం చెందిన కణములకు పారగమ్యత సామర్థ్యం లేకపోయినట్లయితే విషపదార్ధములు పేరుకొనిపోతాయి. తద్వారా కణం నశించిపోతుంది."},{"question":"Manana teny mikorotana ianao : KIRAITRAAlamino ny teny ary omeno ny teny tena marina:","answer":"Ny teny marina voalamina dia \\"RAIKITRA\\""},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਗਉੜੀ ਗੁਆਰੇਰੀ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ॥ਬਿਆਪਤ ਹਰਖ ਸੋਗ ਬਿਸਥਾਰ ॥ਬਿਆਪਤ ਸੁਰਗ ਨਰਕ ਅਵਤਾਰ ॥ਬਿਆਪਤ ਧਨ ਨਿਰਧਨ ਪੇਖਿ ਸੋਭਾ ॥ਮੂਲੁ ਬਿਆਧੀ ਬਿਆਪਸਿ ਲੋਭਾ ॥੧॥ਮਾਇਆ ਬਿਆਪਤ ਬਹੁ ਪਰਕਾਰੀ ॥ਸੰਤ ਜੀਵਹਿ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਓਟ ਤੁਮਾਰੀ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਬਿਆਪਤ ਅਹੰਬੁਧਿ ਕਾ ਮਾਤਾ ॥ਬਿਆਪਤ ਪੁਤ੍ਰ ਕਲਤ੍ਰ ਸੰਗਿ ਰਾਤਾ ॥ਬਿਆਪਤ ਹਸਤਿ ਘੋੜੇ ਅਰੁ ਬਸਤਾ ॥ਬਿਆਪਤ ਰੂਪ ਜੋਬਨ ਮਦ ਮਸਤਾ ॥੨॥ਬਿਆਪਤ ਭੂਮਿ ਰੰਕ ਅਰੁ ਰੰਗਾ ॥ਬਿਆਪਤ ਗੀਤ ਨਾਦ ਸੁਣਿ ਸੰਗਾ ॥ਬਿਆਪਤ ਸੇਜ ਮਹਲ ਸੀਗਾਰ ॥ਪੰਚ ਦੂਤ ਬਿਆਪਤ ਅੰਧਿਆਰ ॥੩॥ਬਿਆਪਤ ਕਰਮ ਕਰੈ ਹਉ ਫਾਸਾ ॥ਬਿਆਪਤਿ ਗਿਰਸਤ ਬਿਆਪਤ ਉਦਾਸਾ ॥ਆਚਾਰ ਬਿਉਹਾਰ ਬਿਆਪਤ ਇਹ ਜਾਤਿ ॥ਸਭ ਕਿਛੁ ਬਿਆਪਤ ਬਿਨੁ ਹਰਿ ਰੰਗ ਰਾਤ ॥੪॥ਸੰਤਨ ਕੇ ਬੰਧਨ ਕਾਟੇ ਹਰਿ ਰਾਇ ॥ਤਾ ਕਉ ਕਹਾ ਬਿਆਪੈ ਮਾਇ ॥ਕਹੁ ਨਾਨਕ ਜਿਨਿ ਧੂਰਿ ਸੰਤ ਪਾਈ ॥ ਤਾ ਕੈ ਨਿਕਟਿ ਨ ਆਵੈ ਮਾਈ ॥੫॥੧੯॥੮੮॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 181 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਕਿਤੇ ਖ਼ੁਸ਼ੀ ਗ਼ਮੀ ਦਾ ਖਿਲਾਰਾ ਹੈ, ਕਿਤੇ ਜੀਵ ਨਰਕਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਪੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਕਿਤੇ ਸੁਰਗਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਪਹੁੰਚਦੇ ਹਨ, ਕਿਤੇ ਕੋਈ ਧਨ ਵਾਲੇ ਹਨ, ਕਿਤੇ ਕੰਗਾਲ ਹਨ, ਕਿਤੇ ਕੋਈ ਆਪਣੀ ਸੋਭਾ ਹੁੰਦੀ ਵੇਖ ਕੇ (ਖ਼ੁਸ਼ ਹਨ)—ਇਹਨਾਂ ਅਨੇਕਾਂ ਤਰੀਕਿਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਮਾਇਆ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਉਤੇ ਪ੍ਰਭਾਵ ਪਾ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ । ਕਿਤੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਰੋਗਾਂ ਦਾ ਮੂਲ ਲੋਭ ਬਣ ਕੇ ਮਾਇਆ ਆਪਣਾ ਜ਼ੋਰ ਪਾ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ ।੧। ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ! (ਤੇਰੀ ਰਚੀ) ਮਾਇਆ ਅਨੇਕਾਂ ਤਰੀਕਿਆਂ ਨਾਲ (ਜੀਵਾਂ ਉਤੇ) ਪ੍ਰਭਾਵ ਪਾਈ ਰੱਖਦੀ ਹੈ (ਤੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਮੌਤੇ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਮਾਰ ਦੇਂਦੀ ਹੈ), ਤੇਰੇ ਸੰਤ ਤੇਰੇ ਆਸਰੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਮਾਣਦੇ ਹਨ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ। ਕਿਤੇ ਕੋਈ ‘ਹਉ ਹਉ, ਮੈਂ ਮੈਂ ਦੀ ਅਕਲ ਵਿਚ ਮਸਤ ਹੈ, ਕਿਤੇ ਕੋਈ ਪੁੱਤਰ ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਦੇ ਮੋਹ ਵਿਚ ਰੱਤਾ ਪਿਆ ਹੈ, ਕਿਤੇ ਹਾਥੀ ਘੋੜਿਆਂ (ਸੁੰਦਰ) ਕੱਪੜਿਆਂ (ਦੀ ਲਗਨ ਹੈ), ਕਿਤੇ ਕੋਈ ਰੂਪ ਤੇ ਜਵਾਨੀ ਦੇ ਨਸ਼ੇ ਵਿਚ ਮਸਤ ਹੈ—ਇਹਨਾਂ ਅਨੇਕਾਂ ਤਰੀਕਿਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਮਾਇਆ ਆਪਣਾ ਜ਼ੋਰ ਪਾ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ ।੨। ਕਿਤੇ ਭੁਇਂ ਦੀ ਮਾਲਕੀ ਹੈ, ਕਿਤੇ ਕੰਗਾਲ ਹਨ, ਕਿਤੇ ਅਮੀਰ ਹਨ, ਕਿਤੇ ਮੰਡਲੀਆਂ ਵਿਚ ਗੀਤ ਨਾਦ ਸੁਣ ਕੇ (ਖ਼ੁਸ਼ ਹੋ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ), ਕਿਤੇ (ਸੋਹਣੀ) ਸੇਜ, ਹਾਰ-ਸਿੰਗਾਰ ਤੇ ਮਹਲ-ਮਾੜੀਆਂ (ਦੀ ਲਾਲਸਾ ਹੈ), ਇਹਨਾਂ ਅਨੇਕਾਂ ਤਰੀਕਿਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਮਾਇਆ ਪ੍ਰਭਾਵ ਪਾ ਰਹੀ ਹੈ । ਕਿਤੇ ਮੋਹ ਦੇ ਹਨੇਰੇ ਵਿਚ ਕਾਮਾਦਿਕ ਪੰਜੇ ਦੂਤ ਬਣ ਕੇ ਮਾਇਆ ਜ਼ੋਰ ਪਾ ਰਹੀ ।੩।ਕਿਤੇ ਕੋਈ ਹਉਮੈ ਵਿਚ ਫਸਿਆ ਹੋਇਆ (ਆਪਣੇ ਵਲੋਂ ਧਾਰਮਿਕ) ਕੰਮ ਕਰ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ, ਕੋਈ ਗ੍ਰਿਹਸਤ ਵਿਚ ਪ੍ਰਵਿਰਤ ਹੈ, ਕੋਈ ਉਦਾਸੀ ਰੂਪ ਵਿਚ ਹੈ, ਕਿਤੇ ਕੋਈ ਧਾਰਮਿਕ ਰਸਮਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਪ੍ਰਵਿਰਤ ਹੈ, ਕੋਈ (ਉੱਚੀ) ਜਾਤਿ ਦੇ ਮਾਣ ਵਿਚ ਹੈਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਵਿਚ ਮਗਨ ਹੋਣ ਤੋਂ ਵਾਂਜੇ ਰਹਿ ਕੇ ਇਹ ਸਭ ਕੁਝ ਮਾਇਆ ਦਾ ਪ੍ਰਭਾਵ ਹੀ ਹੈ ।੪। ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਆਪ ਹੀ ਸੰਤ ਜਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਬੰਧਨ ਕੱਟ ਦੇਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਉਹਨਾਂ ਉਤੇ ਮਾਇਆ ਆਪਣਾ ਜ਼ੋਰ ਨਹੀਂ ਪਾ ਸਕਦੀ । ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! ਆਖ—ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੇ ਸੰਤ ਜਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਧੂੜ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਕਰ ਲਈ ਹੈ, ਮਾਇਆ ਉਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦੇ ਨੇੜੇ ਨਹੀਂ ਢੁੱਕ ਸਕਦੀ ।੪।੧੯।੮੮।\\""},{"question":"Көрөр көзү Агеркеч Алмамбет менен соо эмес деген ушакты ким Көкчөгө жеткирди?а) чоросу Дөөкүр б) досу Салимбайв) тууганы Жаанбай г) күндөшү Бидайкүл","answer":"Көрөр көзү Агеркеч Алмамбет менен соо эмес деген ушакты күндөшү Бидайкүл Көкчөгө жеткирди. Туура жообу г) варианты болот."},{"question":"‘செம்பரிதி மலைமேட்டில் தலையைச் சாய்ப்பான் செந்நிறத்துப் பூக்காடாம் வான மெல்லாம்’ தொடர் வெளிப்படுத்தும் காட்சி நயத்தை விளக்குக.","answer":"* கதிரவன் தன் கதிர்களைச் சுருக்கிக் கொண்டு மேற்கு நோக்கி மறைவது இயற்கை.* ஆனால் கவிஞர் செம்மைமிகு சூரியன் மாலையில் மலைமுகட்டில் தன் தலை சாய்க்கிறான் என்கிறார்.* கதிரவனின் கதிரொளி பட்டு வானமெனும் காடெல்லாம் பூக்காடாய் மாறின என்று சிற்பி நயம்பட விளக்குகிறார்."},{"question":"出家する前は佐藤義清（のりきよ）という名前だった、「山家集（さんかしゅう）」で知られる歌人は誰でしょう？","answer":"西行です。"},{"question":"Đặt tiêu đề cho đoạn văn sau: Trong khoảng thời gian 4 năm ấy, môi trường chính trị đối ngoại và an ninh đã có nhiều chuyển biến rất cơ bản và sâu sắc đối với cả Nga lẫn Triều Tiên. Nga xung đột với Ukraine và đối địch quyết liệt phương Tây. Nước Mỹ cũng đã thay đổi lãnh đạo và Tổng thống đương nhiệm Joe Biden không có cùng cách tiếp cận như người tiền nhiệm Donald Trump đối với Nga và Triều Tiên.Thúc đẩy mạnh mẽ mối quan hệ hợp tác song phương đương nhiên là mục tiêu chính trong chuyến thăm Nga của ông Kim Jong-un lần này. Nhưng bối cảnh tình hình đặc biệt làm cho sự kiện đương nhiên ấy có thêm mục đích và ý nghĩa đặc biệt. Bối cảnh đặc biệt ấy vừa tạo tiền đề thuận lợi vừa thôi thúc Moscow và Bình Nhưỡng không chỉ tăng cường quan hệ đối tác mà còn trở thành đồng minh của nhau về chính trị và quân sự. Điều đó khiến các bên như Mỹ và đồng minh không hài lòng.Ở chuyến thăm Nga lần này của ông Kim Jong-un, phương Tây dĩ nhiên lo ngại Bình Nhưỡng hỗ trợ quân sự cho Moscow. Mỹ dọa sẽ trừng phạt tất cả những bên hậu thuẫn quân sự cho Nga, nhưng Bình Nhưỡng có lẽ không vì sự răn đe này mà ngần ngại trợ giúp quân sự và ủng hộ Moscow.Đổi lại, Nga có thể giúp Triều Tiên về kinh tế và kỹ thuật, công nghệ quân sự, thậm chí cả công nghệ tên lửa và hạt nhân. Một khi Nga, Trung Quốc và Triều Tiên tăng cường hợp tác thì tình hình sẽ rất khác với phương Tây. ","answer":"Tiêu đề cho đoạn văn có thể là: \\"Chuyến thăm của Kim Jong-un tới Nga: Sự kết hợp giữa tình hình đặc biệt và quan hệ đối tác chính trị và quân sự\\""},{"question":"Waxaad sheegtaa magacyada xayawaankada ee suuradaha Qur’aanka ku jiraan?","answer":"Magacyada xayawaanka ee suuradaha quraanka ku jiro waxaa ka mid ah:Al-Baqara (Saca)An-Naxal (Shinnida)An-Namal (Quraanjada)Al-Cankabuut (Caarada)Al-Fiil (MAroodiga).Waxan weliba ku deri karnaa Al-Ancaam (Xoolaha).    "},{"question":"එක්සත් ජාතීන්ගේ වත්මන් මහ ලේකම් කවුද?","answer":"එක්සත් ජාතීන්ගේ වත්මන් මහ ලේකම් අන්තෝනියෝ ගුටරෙස් මහතාය."},{"question":"ቢል ክሊንተን የት ተወለደ?","answer":"በሆፕ አርካንሳው"},{"question":"දෘශ්‍ය නිර්මාණයේ පොදු අංග සමහරක් මොනවාද?","answer":"රේඛාව, හැඩය, ප්‍රමාණය, වයනය, වර්ණය සහ දිශාව සාමාන්‍ය දෘශ්‍ය නිර්මාණ අංග කිහිපයකි. නිර්මාණ මූලද්‍රව්‍ය යනු ඕනෑම දෘශ්‍ය නිර්මාණයක මූලික ඒකක වන අතර එය එහි ව්‍යුහය සාදන අතර දෘශ්‍ය පණිවිඩ ලබා දෙයි. දෘෂ්‍ය නිර්මාණයේ සෞන්දර්යාත්මක අනුපිළිවෙලෙහි මූලික මූලධර්ම ගැබ් කිරීමට උත්සාහ කළ චිත්‍ර ශිල්පියා සහ නිර්මාණ න්‍යායාචාර්ය මේට්ලන්ඩ් ඊ. ග්‍රේව්ස් (1902-1978), ඔහුගේ The Art of Color and Design (1941) නම් කෘතියේ දී නිර්මාණයේ මූලද්‍රව්‍ය රේඛාවක් ලෙස අර්ථ දැක්වීය. දිශාව, හැඩය, ප්රමාණය, වයනය, අගය සහ වර්ණය, \\"මෙම මූලද්රව්ය සියලු මෝස්තර ගොඩනඟා ඇති ද්රව්ය\\" බව නිගමනය කරයි."},{"question":"ما هي عاصمة الإمارات","answer":"أبوظبي"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਪਉੜੀ ॥ਪੂਰਨਮਾ ਪੂਰਨ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਏਕੁ ਕਰਣ ਕਾਰਣ ਸਮਰਥੁ ॥ਜੀਅ ਜੰਤ ਦਇਆਲ ਪੁਰਖੁ ਸਭ ਊਪਰਿ ਜਾ ਕਾ ਹਥੁ ॥ਗੁਣ ਨਿਧਾਨ ਗੋਬਿੰਦ ਗੁਰ ਕੀਆ ਜਾ ਕਾ ਹੋਇ ॥ਅੰਤਰਜਾਮੀ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਸੁਜਾਨੁ ਅਲਖ ਨਿਰੰਜਨ ਸੋਇ ॥ਪਾਰਬ੍ਰਹਮੁ ਪਰਮੇਸਰੋ ਸਭ ਬਿਧਿ ਜਾਨਣਹਾਰ ॥ਸੰਤ ਸਹਾਈ ਸਰਨਿ ਜੋਗੁ ਆਠ ਪਹਰ ਨਮਸਕਾਰ ॥ਅਕਥ ਕਥਾ ਨਹ ਬੂਝੀਐ ਸਿਮਰਹੁ ਹਰਿ ਕੇ ਚਰਨ ॥ਪਤਿਤ ਉਧਾਰਨ ਅਨਾਥ ਨਾਥ ਨਾਨਕ ਪ੍ਰਭ ਕੀ ਸਰਨ ॥੧੬॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 300 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਸਿਰਫ਼ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਹੀ ਸਾਰੇ ਗੁਣਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਭਰਪੂਰ ਹੈ, ਸਾਰੇ ਜਗਤ ਦਾ ਮੂਲ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਸਾਰੀਆਂ ਤਾਕਤਾਂ ਦਾ ਮਾਲਕ ਹੈ । ਉਹ ਸਰਬ ਵਿਆਪਕ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਸਭ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਉਤੇ ਦਇਆਵਾਨ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਸਭ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਉਤੇ ਉਸ (ਦੀ ਸਹਾਇਤਾ) ਦਾ ਹੱਥ ਹੈ ।ਉਹ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਸਾਰੇ ਗੁਣਾਂ ਦਾ ਖ਼ਜ਼ਾਨਾ ਹੈ, ਸਾਰੀ ਸ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਟੀ ਦਾ ਪਾਲਕ ਹੈ, ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਵੱਡਾ ਹੈ, ਸਭ ਕੁਝ ਉਸੇ ਦਾ ਹੀ ਕੀਤਾ ਵਾਪਰਦਾ ਹੈ । ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਸਭ ਦੇ ਦਿਲ ਦੀ ਜਾਣਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈ, ਸਿਆਣਾ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਦਾ ਮੁਕੰਮਲ ਸਰੂਪ ਬਿਆਨ ਨਹੀਂ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ, ਉਹ ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਪ੍ਰਭਾਵ ਤੋਂ ਪਰੇ ਹੈ ।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਉਹ ਪਾਰਬ੍ਰਹਮ ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਵੱਡਾ ਮਾਲਕ ਹੈ (ਜੀਵਾਂ ਦੇ ਭਲੇ ਦਾ) ਹਰੇਕ ਢੰਗ ਜਾਣਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈ, ਸੰਤਾਂ ਦਾ ਰਾਖਾ ਹੈ, ਸਰਨ ਆਏ ਦੀ ਸਹਾਇਤਾ ਕਰਨ ਜੋਗਾ ਹੈ—ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨੂੰ ਅੱਠੇ ਪਹਰ ਨਮਸਕਾਰ ਕਰ ।ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਗੁਣ ਬਿਆਨ ਨਹੀਂ ਕੀਤੇ ਜਾ ਸਕਦੇ, ਉਸ ਦਾ ਸਹੀ ਸਰੂਪ ਸਮਝਿਆ ਨਹੀਂ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ । ਉਸ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਦਾ ਧਿਆਨ ਧਰ । ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! ਉਹ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਵਿਚ) ਡਿੱਗੇ ਬੰਦਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਤੋਂ) ਬਚਾਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਨਿਖਸਮਿਆਂ ਦਾ ਖਸਮ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਦਾ ਆਸਰਾ ਲੈ ।੧੬।\\""},{"question":"અમેરિકન સરકારની અંતરિક્ષ સંસ્થા  નાસા વિષે જણાવો.","answer":"અમેરિકન સરકારની અંતરિક્ષ સંસ્થા છે, જે દેશનાં જાહેર અંતરિક્ષ કાર્યક્રમોનું સંચાલન કરે છે. આ સંસ્થાની સ્થાપના જુલાઇ ૨૯,૧૯૫૮ નાં રોજ, રાષ્ટ્રીય એરોનોટિક્સ અને અંતરિક્ષ અધિનિયમ હેઠળ થયેલ.અવકાશ કાર્યક્રમની સાથે, નાસા લાંબાગાળાનાં નાગરીક અને લશ્કરી સંશોધનો માટે પણ જવાબદાર છે.નાસાનો મુદ્રાલેખ \\"સર્વજન હિતાય\\"  છે."},{"question":"Qual artista pintou 'Auto-retrato com dois círculos' no século VII?","answer":"Rembrandt van Rijn"},{"question":"‘அஞ்சலை அரக்க ! பார் விட்டந்தர மடைந்தா’ எனும் பாடல் இடம்பெறும் நூல் ?","answer":"‘அஞ்சலை அரக்க ! பார் விட்டந்தர மடைந்தா’ எனும் பாடல் இடம்பெறும் கம்பராமாயணம் ஆகும்.கம்பராமாயணம் எனும் நூல் கம்பரால் இயற்றப்பட்ட தமிழ் நூலாகும். இந்நூல் இந்து சமய இதிகாசங்கள் இரண்டினுள் ஒன்றான இராமாயணத்தினை மூலமாகக் கொண்டு இயற்றப்பட்டதாகும். இராமாவதாரம் என்ற பெயரில் கம்பரால் இயற்றப்பட்ட கம்பராமாயணம் ஒரு வழி நூலாகும் (வெவ்வேறு நூல்களிலும் பல வேறுபாடுகள் உண்டு). இது வடமொழியில் வால்மீகி என்பவர் இயற்றிய இராமாயணத்தினைத் தழுவி எழுதப்பட்ட நூல் ஆகும். இது ஒரு வழி நூலாகவே இருந்தாலும் கம்பர் தனக்கே உரித்தான பாணியில் தன் புலமையை வெளிக்காட்ட தமிழ் மொழியில் இயற்றியுள்ளார். வடமொழி கலவாத தூய தமிழ் சொற்களைத் தனது நூலில் கையாண்டதால் கம்பர், தொல்காப்பிய நெறி நின்றவர் என்று புகழப்படுகிறார்.கம்பராமாயணம் பாலகாண்டம், அயோத்தியா காண்டம், ஆரண்ய காண்டம், கிட்கிந்தா காண்டம், சுந்தர காண்டம், யுத்த காண்டம் எனும் ஆறு காண்டங்களையும், 118 படலங்களையும் உடையது. இதில் 10589 பாடல்கள் உள்ளன. காண்டம் என்பது பெரும்பிரிவினையும் படலம் என்பது அதன் உட்பிரிவினையும் குறிக்கும். ஏழாம் காண்டமாகிய \\"உத்திர காண்டம்\\" என்னும் பகுதியை கம்பரின் சம காலத்தவராகிய \\"ஒட்டக்கூத்தர்\\" இயற்றினார் என்பர். தமிழிலக்கியத்தில் காப்பிய வளர்ச்சி கம்பரின் காலத்தில் (பொ.ஊ. பன்னிரண்டாம் நூற்றாண்டு) உச்சநிலையினை அடைந்தது என்பர். இந்நூலின் சிறப்பு கருதியும் திருக்குறளின் பெருமை கருதியும் இவ்விரு நூல்களையும் \\"தமிழுக்குக் கதி\\" (கம்பராமாயணம் திருக்குறள்) என்பர்.பாலகாண்டம்இராவணனை அழிக்க திருமால் மனித அவதாரம் எடுக்கிறார். தசரதன் - கோசலை தம்பதியினருக்கு இராமனாக திருமால் பிறக்கிறார். தசரதனுக்கும் கைகேயி மற்றும் சுமித்திரை ஆகியோருக்கும் இலக்குவன், பரதன், சத்ருகன் ஆகியோர் பிறக்கின்றனர். நால்வரும் தசரதனுடைய அரண்மனையில் வளர்ந்து வருகின்றனர்.இராமனையும், இலக்குவனையும் விசுவாமித்திரர், தன்னுடைய யாகத்திற்குக் காவலாக அழைத்துச் செல்கின்றார். விசுவாமித்திரரின் யாகத்தினை அழிக்க வந்த தாடகை எனும் அரக்கியை இராமன் கொல்கிறார். தாடகையைப் போல யாகத்தினை அழிக்க வந்த அரக்கர்களையும் இராமனும், இலக்குவனும் அழிக்கின்றனர்.மிதிலைக்கு இராமனையும், இலக்குவனையும் விசுவாமித்திரர் அழைத்துச் செல்கிறார். வழியில், கல்லாக இருந்த அகலிகை இராமனின் கால்தூசு பட்டு உயிர்பெறுகிறாள். அவளை கௌதம முனிவருடன் சேர்த்துவிட்டு மிதிலைக்குச் செல்கின்றனர். அங்கு சீதைக்கு சுயம்வரம் நடக்கிறது. அதில் இராமன் கலந்து கொண்டு சிவதனுசை உடைத்து, சீதையை மணக்கிறார்.அயோத்தியா காண்டம்இராமன் சீதையைத் திருமணம் செய்து கொண்டு அயோத்தியாவிற்குச் செல்கிறார். உடன் இலக்குவனும், விசுவாமித்திரரும் செல்கின்றனர். அயோத்தியின் மன்னரான தசரதன் இராமனுக்கு பட்டாபிசேகம் செய்ய ஏற்பாடுகளைச் செய்கிறார். அதனை அறிந்த மக்களும், மந்திரிகளும் மகிழ்கின்றனர். மந்தரை எனும் கூனி பரதனின் தாயான கைகேயிடம் சென்று அவளுடைய மனதினை மாற்றுகிறாள். கைகேயி தசரதன் முன்பு தந்த இரண்டு வரங்களை இப்போதைய சூழ்நிலைக்குத் தக்கவாறு, இராமன் காடாளவும், பரதன் நாடாளவும் கேட்டுப் பெறுகிறாள்.இராமனும், சீதையும் காட்டிற்கு செல்லுகையில், இலக்குவனும் உடன் செல்கிறான். மூவரும் காட்டிற்கு சென்று முனிவர்களையும், குகனையும் சந்திக்கின்றார்கள். குகனை தன்னுடைய மற்றொரு சகோதரன் என்று இராமன் பெருமையாக கூறுகிறார். தசரதன் இறந்து போனதால், இறுதிக் காரியங்களைச் செய்துவிட்டு பரதன் இராமனைக் காட்டில் வந்து சந்திக்கிறார். அயோத்திய அரசை ஏற்க இராமனிடம் வற்புறுத்துகிறார். ஆனால் இராமன் அதனை ஏற்க மறுக்கின்றார். பரதன் இராமன் மீண்டும் வந்து பொறுப்பு ஏற்கும் வரை இராமனின் பாதுகைகளை வைத்து அரசு செய்கிறான்.ஆரண்ய காண்டம்இராமன் காட்டில் விராதன், சரபங்கன், அகத்தியர், சடாயு ஆகியோர்களைச் சந்திக்கிறார். அவர்களின் மூலமாக அரக்கர்களைப் பற்றியும், ஆயுதங்களைப் பற்றியும் அறிந்து கொள்கிறார்.இராவணனுடைய தங்கை சூர்ப்பணகை இராமனைக் கண்டு காதல் கொள்கிறாள். ஆனால் இராமன் ஏகப்பத்தினி விரதன் என்று பிற பெண்களை ஏற்காமல் இருக்கிறான். இலக்குவன் சூர்ப்பணகையின் மூக்கினை அரிந்து அனுப்புகிறான். அதனால் இராவணனிடம் சென்று இராமனின் மனைவி சீதையைப் பற்றியும் அவளுடைய அழகினையும் கூறி, சீதையின் மீது மோகம் கொள்ள வைக்கிறாள்.[3]இராவணன் மாயமானை அனுப்பி இராமனையும், இலக்குவனையும் சீதையிடமிருந்து பிரித்து, சீதையைக் கவர்ந்து செல்கிறார். வழியில் சடாயு சீதையை மீட்கப் போராடி வீழ்கிறார். சீதையை இல்லத்தில் காணாது தேடி வரும் சகோதரர்களுக்கு இராவணனைப் பற்றிக் கூறிவிட்டு உயிர்விடுகிறார் சடாயு.[3]கிட்கிந்தா காண்டம்சீதையைத் தேடிச் செல்கின்ற இராமனும், இலக்குவனும் கிட்கிந்தைக்கு வருகிறார்கள். அங்கு அனுமனைச் சந்திக்கிறார் இராமர். அனுமன் சுக்கிரீவன் என்பவரை இராமருக்கு அறிமுகம் செய்கிறார். சுக்கிரீவனின் மனைவியை சுக்கிரீவனுடைய அண்ணன் வாலியே கவர்ந்து சென்று விடுகிறார். அதனால் இராமன் வாலியைக் கொன்று சுக்கிரீவனின் மனைவியை மீட்கிறார்.[3]இராமனும் தன்னைப் போல மனைவியை இழந்து தவிக்கிறான் என்பதை அறிந்த சுக்கிரீவனும், அவனுடைய குடிமக்களான வானரங்களும் இராமனுக்கு உதவ முன்வருகிறார்கள்.[3]அங்கதன் என்பவர் தலைமையில் அனைவரும் செல்கின்றனர். வழியில் சம்பாதி எனும் சடாயுவின் அண்ணனைச் சந்திக்கின்றனர். சம்பாதி இலங்கையில் சீதை சிறைப்பட்டு இருப்பதைத் தெரிவிக்கின்றார். இலங்கைக்குச் செல்ல ஏற்றவர் அனுமன் என்று தீர்மானித்து அனுமனிடம் தெரிவிக்கின்றனர். அனுமனுக்கு அவருடைய பெருமையை உணர்த்தி அவர் இலங்கை செல்ல விஸ்வரூபம் எடுக்கிறார்.[3]சுந்தர காண்டம்அனுமன் இலங்கைக்குச் செல்ல வான்வெளியில் பறந்து செல்கிறார். வழியில் எதிர்படும் தடைகளை இராம நாமம் கொண்டு வெற்றிபெற்று இலங்கையை அடைகிறார். அங்கே அசோகவனத்தில் உள்ள சீதையைக் கண்டு, தான் இராமனின் தூதுவன் என்று கூறி, இராமனின் அடையாளமான மோதிரத்தினைத் தந்து தெரிவிக்கிறார். சீதையும் அந்த மோதிரத்தினைப் பெற்றுக் கொண்டு சூளாமணி எனும் அணியைத் தருகிறாள்.[3]இராவணனைச் சந்தித்து அனுமன் இராமனின் பெருமைகளைக் கூறி, சீதையை இராமனிடம் சேர்த்துவிடும்படி கூறுகிறார். ஆனால் இராவணன் அனுமன் வாலில் தீயிடுகிறான். அனுமன் இலங்கையையே எரித்துவிட்டு இராமனிடம் சென்று சீதையைக் கண்டதைக் கூறுகிறார்.[3]யுத்த காண்டம்இராமன் இலங்கைக்குப் பாலம் அமைத்து வானரப் படையுடன் சென்று, இராவணனுடன் போர் செய்கிறான். அப்போது இராவணனின் சகோதரன் வீடணன் இராமனுடன் இணைந்து கொள்கிறான். இராமன் இராவணனுடைய தம்பியான கும்பகருணன், மகன் இந்திரசித்து என அனைவரையும் போரிட்டுக் கொல்கிறார். இறுதியாக இராவணனைக் கொன்று வீடணனுக்கு இலங்கையைத் தந்துவிட்டு, சீதையை மீட்டு அயோத்திக்குச் செல்கிறார். அயோத்தியில் இராமருக்குப் பட்டாபிசேகம் நடைபெற்றது.[3]கம்பராமாயணத்திற்கு பிறகு தோன்றியவைகம்பர் இந்த நூலை இயற்றிய பிறகு எண்ணற்ற இராமாயண நூல்கள் படைக்கப்பட்டன. இவ்வாறு இராமாயண நூல்கள் தோன்றுவதற்கு கம்பராமாயணம் தூண்டுதலாக இருந்தது என்று அறிஞர்கள் குறிப்பிடுகின்றனர். அவையாவன, தக்க ராமாயணம், குயில் ராமாயணம், இராமாயண அகவல், கோகில இராமாயணம், அமர்த இராமாயணம், இராமாயணக் கீர்த்தைகள் மற்றும் பால இராமாயணம்."},{"question":"Hvilken skole er ikke for drenge i Auckland? Skriv et svar i sammenhæng med det foregående spørgsmål. Det kan være 1 - 20 sætninger.","answer":"Private skoler er ofte anglikanske, såsom King's College og Diocese School for Girls i Auckland, St Paul's Collegiate School i Hamilton, St Peter's School i Cambridge, Samuel Marsden Collegiate School i Wellington, og Christ's College og St Margaret's College i Christchurch; eller presbyterianske, såsom Saint Kentigern College og St Cuthbert's College i Auckland, Scots College og Queen Margaret College i Wellington, og St Andrew's College og Rangi Ruru Girls' School i Christchurch. Academic Colleges Group er en ny gruppe af private skoler, der drives som en virksomhed, med skoler i hele Auckland, herunder ACG Senior College i Aucklands CBD, ACG Parnell College i Parnell og den internationale skole ACG New Zealand International College. Der er tre private skoler (inklusive gymnasiet, St. Dominic's College), der drives af den katolske skismatiske gruppe, Society of St. Pius X i Wanganui."},{"question":"A quantos quilómetros corresponde uma milha?","answer":"Uma milha equivale a aproximadamente 1.61 quilómetros."},{"question":"《天龙八部》中，谁得到了屠龙刀和倚天剑？","answer":"乔峰得到了屠龙刀，而倚天剑则由赵敏得到。"},{"question":"A que categoría corresponde la siguiente pregunta : ¿Quién es el último primer ministro de Gran Bretaña que no fue a la universidad?.","answer":"La categoría corresponde a historia. "},{"question":"Tohizo izao ohabolana izao : \\"  Tsa misy raha te ho anao fa _\\" ","answer":"\\"  Tsa misy raha te ho anao fa agnao ro te hanagn'azy.\\" "},{"question":"“东西南北客”这句话是什么意思呢？","answer":"这句谚语指居处无定之人。"},{"question":"Wanene manajan farko na chelsea?","answer":"John Robertson ne na farko."},{"question":"Iza no nanoratra ny tantara an-tsehatra \\"Romeo sy Juliet\\"?","answer":" \\"Romeo sy Juliet\\" dia nosoratan'i William Shakespeare."},{"question":"Cần Thơ có bao nhiêu con sông chảy qua?","answer":"Trên địa bàn thành phố Cần Thơ có tổng cộng 13 sông. Trong đó, các sông chính là sông Hậu (sông liên quốc gia), sông Đờn Dang, sông Rạch Sỏi, sông Ô Môn, sông Cần Thơ, sông Bình Thuận."},{"question":"Inona no tokony hohadiana alohan’ny hambolena azy?","answer":"Tsy maintsy misy lavaka ao anaty tany vao mamboly zavatra ao anatiny."},{"question":"طلب ابني مني تدريسه الجملة الاسمية المثبتة والمنفية في اللغة العربية، ولكنني نسيت بعض المعلومات المتعلقة بهذا الدرس، وأرغب بمعرفة هل الجملة الاسمية المثبتة هي التي تخلو من أدوات النفي؟ وما هي الجملة الاسمية المثبتة؟ وما هي أدوات النفي؟","answer":"نعم صحيح، إنّ الجملة الاسمية المثبتة هي التي تخلو من أدوات النفي، وأدوات النفي، هي: لا، ليس، لن، لام الجحود، ما، لات، غير، لم، لمّا، وتُفيد الجملة الاسمية المثبتة الدوام والثبوت، نحو: الطالبُ مجتهدٌ، أما الجملة الاسمية المنفية هي التي يدخل عليها إحدى أدوات النفي سابقة الذكر، نحو: لا نجاح دون اجتهاد.جدير بالذكر أنّ الجملة الاسمية هي التي تبدأ باسم، وتتكون من ركنين، هما: المبتدأ والخبر، وإليك أمثلة أُخرى عن الجملة الاسمية المثبتة والمنفية فيما يأتي:لا خير دون جزاء. (جملة اسمية منفية)الطفل ذكي. (جملة اسمية مثبتة)العلم نور. (جملة اسمية مثبتة)لا فوز دون إرادة. (جملة اسمية منفية)"},{"question":"Gobalka ugu weyn Gobalad soomali","answer":"Waa Gobalka Bari"},{"question":"ప్రశ్న: కళింగ రాజ్యాన్ని ప్రస్తుత భారతదేశంలో ఏ పేరుతో పిలుస్తారు?","answer":"ఒడిషాగా పిలుస్తున్నారు. ఒడిశా ( పాత పేరు ఒరిస్సా) తూర్పు భారతదేశంలో ఉన్న ఒక రాష్ట్రం . దీనికి ఉత్తరాన ఝార్ఖండ్ రాష్ట్రం, ఈశాన్యాన పశ్చిమ బెంగాల్, దక్షిణాన ఆంధ్ర ప్రదేశ్, పశ్చిమాన ఛత్తీస్‌గఢ్ రాష్ట్రాలు, తూర్పున బంగాళాఖాతం సముద్రమున్నాయి. ఇది విస్తీర్ణంలో 8 వ అతిపెద్ద రాష్ట్రం, జనాభా ప్రకారం 11 వ అతిపెద్ద రాష్ట్రం. షెడ్యూల్డ్ తెగల జనాభా పరంగా భారతదేశంలో మూడవ స్థానంలో ఉంది. ఉత్తరాన పశ్చిమ బెంగాల్, జార్ఖండ్, పశ్చిమాన ఛత్తీస్‌గఢ్, దక్షిణాన ఆంధ్రప్రదేశ్ రాష్ట్రాలు హద్దులుగా ఉన్నాయి. బంగాళాఖాతం వెంబడి 485 కిలోమీటర్స్ (301 మైల్స్) తీరం ఉంది. ఈ ప్రాంతాన్ని ఉత్కల అని కూడా పిలుస్తారు. ఈ పదం భారతదేశ జాతీయ గీతం \\" జన గణ మన \\"లో ప్రస్తావించబడింది. ఒడిశా భాష ఒడియా, ఇది భారతదేశ ప్రాచీన భాషలలో ఒకటి .సా.శ.పూ 261 లో మౌర్య చక్రవర్తి అశోకుడు కళింగ యుద్ధంలో ఖారవేలుడు రాజును ఓడించినా ఖారవేలుడు మరల రాజ్యాన్ని పొందాడు. ఈ యుద్ధం ప్రతీకారవాంఛగల చక్రవర్తి అశోకుడిని బౌద్ధమతం స్వీకరణతో ప్రశాంతుడిగా మార్చడానికి కారణమైంది., అప్పటి ప్రాంతం, ఆధునిక ఒడిశా సరిహద్దులతో సరిపోలుతుంది. బ్రిటిష్ భారత ప్రభుత్వం ఒడిస్సా ప్రావిన్స్ ను 1936 ఏప్రిల్ 1 న స్థాపించబడినప్పుడు ఒడిశా యొక్క ఆధునిక సరిహద్దులను గుర్తించింది. ఇందులో బీహార్, ఒరిస్సా ప్రావిన్స్ లో ఒడియా మాట్లాడే జిల్లాలు ఉన్నాయి. ఏప్రిల్ 1ని ఉత్కల దిబసగా జరుపుకుంటారు. సా.శ. 1135 లో అనంతవర్మన్ చోడగాంగ రాజు కటక్ రాజధానిగా పరిపాలించాడు. తరువాత బ్రిటిష్ శకం వరకు ఈ నగరాన్ని చాలా మంది పాలకులు రాజధానిగా ఉపయోగించారు. ఆ తరువాత భువనేశ్వర్ ఒడిశా రాజధాని అయ్యింది.ఒడిశా ఆర్థిక స్థూల రాష్ట్రీయ ఉత్పత్తి ₹ 5.33 లక్షల కోట్లు, తలసరి స్థూల రాష్ట్రీయ ఉత్పత్తి ₹ 116.614 గా భారతదేశం లో16 వ అతిపెద్ద ఆర్థిక వ్యవస్థ గల రాష్ట్రంగా ఉంది. మానవ అభివృద్ధి సూచికలో ఒడిశా భారత రాష్ట్రాలలో 32 వ స్థానంలో ఉంది.కోణార్క, పూరి, భువనేశ్వర్లు ప్రసిద్ధి చెందిన మందిరాలు గల పట్టణాలు."},{"question":"Magacaa?","answer":"Magacaygu waa Axmad."},{"question":"ਬਿਜਲੀ ਜਨਰੇਟਰ ਦਾ ਸਿਧਾਂਤ ਲਿਖੋ ।","answer":"ਬਿਜਲੀ ਜਨਰੇਟਰ ਦਾ ਸਿਧਾਂਤ – “ਜਦੋਂ ਕਿਸੇ ਬੰਦ ਕੁੰਡਲੀ ਨੂੰ ਕਿਸੇ ਸ਼ਕਤੀਸ਼ਾਲੀ ਚੁੰਬਕੀ ਖੇਤਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਤੇਜ਼ ਗਤੀ ਨਾਲ ਘੁੰਮਾਇਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਤਾਂ ਉਸ ਵਿਚੋਂ ਗੁਜਰਨ ਵਾਲੇ ਚੁੰਬਕੀ-ਫਲੱਕਸ ਵਿੱਚ ਲਗਾਤਾਰ ਪਰਿਵਰਤਨ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਜਿਸ ਕਰਕੇ ਕੁੰਡਲੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਬਿਜਲਈ ਧਾਰਾ ਪ੍ਰੇਰਿਤ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ । ਕੁੰਡਲੀ ਨੂੰ ਘੁੰਮਾਉਣ ਲਈ ਕੀਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਕਾਰਜ ਹੀ ਕੁੰਡਲੀ ਅੰਦਰ ਬਿਜਲੀ ਊਰਜਾ ਦੇ ਰੂਪ ਵਿੱਚ ਵਿਖਾਈ ਦਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।”"},{"question":"時期を外していて役に立たないことを、「六日のあやめ、十日の何」と言うでしょう？","answer":"菊です。"},{"question":"Terjemahkanlah penggalan teks Bahasa Jawa yang disadur dari kumpulan cerita anak dunia berikut ke dalam teks Bahasa Indonesia.Besuke ana lumba-lumba liwat. Lumba-lumba iku liwat ing ndhuwur banyu, ngunjal ambegan jero banjur nyilem. Razia nyoba nglangi kaya lumba-lumba. Dheweke ngangkat sirahe ana ing ndhuwur banyu.Terjemahan:","answer":"Hari berikutnya seekor lumba-lumba lewat. Lumba-lumba muncul ke permukaan air, mengambil napas, dan kembali menyelam. Rasya mencoba berenang seperti lumba-lumba. Ia mengangkat kepalanya ke atas permukaan air."},{"question":"Nderipi pamazwi anotevera ari zvibatanidzi, uye ndezvipi zvivakashure: uye, pakati, asi, nokuda, muna, pa, pa, kana, pasi, zvakadaro.","answer":"\\"Zvinotevera zvibatanidzi: uye, asi, kana, zvakadaroIzvi zvinotevera zvirevo: pakati, kune, mukati, pa, pa, pasi\\""},{"question":"Tamin'ny taona firy no hita ny fasan'i Tutankamen ? ","answer":"Tamin'ny taona 1922 no hitan'i Howard Carter ny fasan'i Tutankamen. "},{"question":"Ilé iṣẹ́ kan ń ṣe ìpolówó ọjà fún àwọn gìtá tí wọ́n ń ṣe lọ́nà àkànṣe. Èwo nínú àwọn gbólóhùn tó wà nísàlẹ̀ yìí ló yẹ kó wà nínú ìpolówó ọjà náà láti fi hàn pé ọ̀nà tí wọ́n gbà ń ṣe iṣẹ́ tí wọ́n ṣe lọ́nà àkànṣe ló dára jù lọ? ÀWỌN ÀṢÀWÒ: (a) Àwọn irinṣẹ́ ọwọ́ la fi ń ṣe àwọn gìtá wa. (b) A máa ń ṣe àwọn gìtá wa ní ìbámu pẹ̀lú àwọn àlàyé rẹ. (d) A máa ń ṣe ẹgbẹẹgbẹ̀rún àwọn gìtá lọ́dọọdún, a sì máa ń tà wọ́n. (é) Àwọn gìtá wa ló dára jù lọ tí owó rẹ lè rà.","answer":"A máa ń ṣe àwọn gìtá wa níbàámu pẹ̀lú àwọn àlàyé rẹ."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਆਸਾ ਮਹਲਾ ੪ ॥ਜਿਨ ਅੰਤਰਿ ਹਰਿ ਹਰਿ ਪ੍ਰੀਤਿ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਜਨ ਸੁਘੜ ਸਿਆਣੇ ਰਾਮ ਰਾਜੇ ॥ਜੇ ਬਾਹਰਹੁ ਭੁਲਿ ਚੁਕਿ ਬੋਲਦੇ ਭੀ ਖਰੇ ਹਰਿ ਭਾਣੇ ॥ਹਰਿ ਸੰਤਾ ਨੋ ਹੋਰੁ ਥਾਉ ਨਾਹੀ ਹਰਿ ਮਾਣੁ ਨਿਮਾਣੇ ॥ਜਨ ਨਾਨਕ ਨਾਮੁ ਦੀਬਾਣੁ ਹੈ ਹਰਿ ਤਾਣੁ ਸਤਾਣੇ ॥੧॥ਜਿਥੈ ਜਾਇ ਬਹੈ ਮੇਰਾ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਸੋ ਥਾਨੁ ਸੁਹਾਵਾ ਰਾਮ ਰਾਜੇ ॥ਗੁਰਸਿਖਂੀ ਸੋ ਥਾਨੁ ਭਾਲਿਆ ਲੈ ਧੂਰਿ ਮੁਖਿ ਲਾਵਾ ॥ਗੁਰਸਿਖਾ ਕੀ ਘਾਲ ਥਾਇ ਪਈ ਜਿਨ ਹਰਿ ਨਾਮੁ ਧਿਆਵਾ ॥ਜਿਨੑ ਨਾਨਕੁ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੁ ਪੂਜਿਆ ਤਿਨ ਹਰਿ ਪੂਜ ਕਰਾਵਾ ॥੨॥ਗੁਰਸਿਖਾ ਮਨਿ ਹਰਿ ਪ੍ਰੀਤਿ ਹੈ ਹਰਿ ਨਾਮ ਹਰਿ ਤੇਰੀ ਰਾਮ ਰਾਜੇ ॥ਕਰਿ ਸੇਵਹਿ ਪੂਰਾ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਭੁਖ ਜਾਇ ਲਹਿ ਮੇਰੀ ॥ਗੁਰਸਿਖਾ ਕੀ ਭੁਖ ਸਭ ਗਈ ਤਿਨ ਪਿਛੈ ਹੋਰ ਖਾਇ ਘਨੇਰੀ ॥ਜਨ ਨਾਨਕ ਹਰਿ ਪੁੰਨੁ ਬੀਜਿਆ ਫਿਰਿ ਤੋਟਿ ਨ ਆਵੈ ਹਰਿ ਪੁੰਨ ਕੇਰੀ ॥੩॥ਗੁਰਸਿਖਾ ਮਨਿ ਵਾਧਾਈਆ ਜਿਨ ਮੇਰਾ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਡਿਠਾ ਰਾਮ ਰਾਜੇ ॥ਕੋਈ ਕਰਿ ਗਲ ਸੁਣਾਵੈ ਹਰਿ ਨਾਮ ਕੀ ਸੋ ਲਗੈ ਗੁਰਸਿਖਾ ਮਨਿ ਮਿਠਾ ॥ਹਰਿ ਦਰਗਹ ਗੁਰਸਿਖ ਪੈਨਾਈਅਹਿ ਜਿਨੑਾ ਮੇਰਾ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੁ ਤੁਠਾ ॥ਜਨ ਨਾਨਕੁ ਹਰਿ ਹਰਿ ਹੋਇਆ ਹਰਿ ਹਰਿ ਮਨਿ ਵੁਠਾ ॥੪॥੧੨॥੧੯॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 450 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਰਾਮਦਾਸ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਸਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਬੰਦਿਆਂ ਦੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਪਿਆਰ ਮੌਜੂਦ ਹੈ (ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀਆਂ ਨਜ਼ਰਾਂ ਵਿਚ) ਉਹ ਬੰਦੇ ਸੁਚੱਜੇ ਹਨ ਸਿਆਣੇ ਹਨ । ਜੇ ਉਹ ਕਦੇ ਉਕਾਈ ਖਾ ਕੇ ਗ਼ਲਤੀ ਨਾਲ ਬਾਹਰ ਲੋਕਾਂ ਵਿਚ (ਉਕਾਈ ਵਾਲੇ ਬੋਲ) ਬੋਲ ਬੈਠਦੇ ਹਨ ਤਾਂ ਭੀ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨੂੰ ਉਹ ਚੰਗੇ ਪਿਆਰੇ ਲੱਗਦੇ ਹਨ । (ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਸੰਤਾਂ ਨੂੰ (ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ) ਹੋਰ ਕੋਈ ਆਸਰਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੁੰਦਾ (ਉਹ ਜਾਣਦੇ ਹਨ ਕਿ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਹੀ ਨਿਮਾਣਿਆਂ ਦਾ ਮਾਣ ਹੈ ।ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! (ਆਖ—) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਸੇਵਕਾਂ ਵਾਸਤੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਹੀ ਸਹਾਰਾ ਹੈ, ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਹੀ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦਾ ਬਾਹੂ-ਬਲ ਹੈ (ਜਿਸ ਦੇ ਆਸਰੇ ਉਹ ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਟਾਕਰੇ ਤੇ) ਤਕੜੇ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ ।੧।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਜਿਸ ਥਾਂ ਤੇ ਪਿਆਰਾ ਗੁਰੂ ਜਾ ਬੈਠਦਾ ਹੈ (ਗੁਰ-ਸਿੱਖਾਂ ਵਾਸਤੇ) ਉਹ ਥਾਂ ਸੋਹਣਾ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ । ਗੁਰਸਿੱਖ ਉਸ ਥਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਲੱਭ ਲੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਤੇ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਧੂੜ ਲੈ ਕੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਮੱਥੇ ਉਤੇ ਲਾ ਲੈਂਦੇ ਹਨ । ਜੇਹੜੇ ਗੁਰਸਿੱਖ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਦੇ ਹਨ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੀ (ਗੁਰ-ਅਸਥਾਨ ਭਾਲਣ ਦੀ) ਮੇਹਨਤ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਦਰ ਤੇ ਕਬੂਲ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।ਨਾਨਕ (ਆਖਦਾ ਹੈ—) ਜੇਹੜੇ ਮਨੁੱਖ (ਆਪਣੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ) ਗੁਰੂ ਦਾ ਆਦਰ-ਸਤਕਾਰ ਬਿਠਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ (ਜਗਤ ਵਿਚ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦਾ) ਆਦਰ ਕਰਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੨।ਹੇ ਹਰੀ! ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਸਿੱਖਾਂ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਤੇਰੀ ਪ੍ਰੀਤਿ ਬਣੀ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ ਤੇਰੇ ਨਾਮ ਦਾ ਪਿਆਰ ਟਿਕਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈਉਹ ਆਪਣੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਨੂੰ ਅਭੁੱਲ ਜਾਣ ਕੇ ਉਸ ਦੀ ਦੱਸੀ ਹੋਈ ਸੇਵਾ ਕਰਦੇ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ(ਜਿਸ ਦੀ ਬਰਕਤਿ ਨਾਲ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚੋਂ) ਮਾਇਆ ਦੀ ਭੁੱਖ ਦੂਰ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੀ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਹੋਰ ਬਥੇਰੀ ਲੁਕਾਈ (ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦੀ ਆਤਮਕ ਖ਼ੁਰਾਕ) ਖਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।ਹੇ ਦਾਸ ਨਾਨਕ! ਜੇਹੜੇ ਮਨੁੱਖ (ਆਪਣੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ-ਖੇਤ ਵਿਚ) ਹਰਿ-ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦਾ ਭਲਾ ਬੀਜ ਬੀਜਦੇ ਹਨ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਇਸ ਭਲੇ ਕਰਮ ਦੀ ਕਦੇ ਕਮੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੁੰਦੀ ।੩।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਗੁਰਸਿੱਖਾਂ ਨੇ ਪਿਆਰੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਦਾ ਦਰਸ਼ਨ ਕਰ ਲਿਆ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਸਦਾ ਚੜ੍ਹਦੀ ਕਲਾ ਬਣੀ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ । ਜੇ ਕੋਈ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਸਿਫ਼ਤਿ-ਸਾਲਾਹ ਦੀ ਗੱਲ ਆ ਸੁਣਾਏ ਤਾਂ ਉਹ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਗੁਰਸਿੱਖਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪਿਆਰਾ ਲੱਗਣ ਲੱਗ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਗੁਰਸਿੱਖਾਂ ਉਤੇ ਪਿਆਰਾ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੂ ਮੇਹਰਬਾਨ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਦਰਗਾਹ ਵਿਚ ਆਦਰ-ਮਾਣ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਨਾਨਕ ਆਖਦਾ ਹੈ ਉਹ ਗੁਰਸਿੱਖ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਰੂਪ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਸਦਾ ਵੱਸਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।੪।੧੨।੧੯।\\""},{"question":"WASAN KWAIKWAYOMene ne jigon Jatau Na Kyallu na S. Maƙarfi?A)Auren karuwaB)Butulcin mataC)Neman haihuwaD)Neman karuwa","answer":"Auren karuwa"},{"question":"Tulis satu karangan yang membincangkan langkah-langkah untuk mengatasi isu pemansan global. ","answer":"Saban tahun, pelbagai bencana alam yang berlaku seperti banjir kilat dan pembakaran hutan sehingga meragut nyawa yang tidak bersalah. Kerakusan manusia mengejar keuntungan dengan menjalankan pembangunan tanpa mengambil kira risiko terhadap persekitaran bakal mengundang padah. Perkembangan teknologi dan perindustrian komersial telah menyebabkan peningkatan gas rumah hijau dalam atmosfera bumi sekaligus meningkatkan suhu bumi. Fenomena ini diberi nama pemanasan sejagat atau pemanasan global yang akan menyebabkan perubahan iklim dan cuaca serta peleburan kutub-kutub ais di hemisfera utara dan selatan. Paras air laut akan meningkat dan kawasan penempatan manusia di pinggir laut berisiko untuk tenggelam dalam jangka masa tertentu. Masyarakat konvensional perlu membuka mata dan mengambil serius terhadap isu ini kerana ia melibatkan kelangsungan hidup generasi akan datang. Maka, penting untuk orang awam mengetahui langkah-langkah dalam mengatasi isu pemanasan global di setiap peringkat.Langkah ulung bagi mengatasi polemik ini adalah dengan menguatkuasakan undang-undang terhadap sebarang tindakan yang menyumbang kepada pemanasan global. Setiap pihak dari setiap peringkat sama ada pengawai penguatkuasa sehingga menteri yang diamanahkan oleh rakyat hendaklah menjalankan tugas dengan tegas dan komited. Tidak bersikap seperti hangat-hangat tahi ayam dalam menegakkan undang-undang serta menghukum mereka yang bersalah. Golongan pemimpin negara seharusnya aktif menyertai konvensyen dan forum antarabangsa bagi menyuarakan serta menyokong usaha mengatasi pemanasan global. Di peringkat domestik pula, penggubal undang-undang perlu menggubal akta-akta yang berkaitan secara berkala agar hukuman yang setimpal akan dikenakan kepada mereka yang bersalah. Sehingga hari ini, kita masih boleh melihat aktiviti pembalakan haram yang menyebabkan pemanasan global dek menebang pokok-pokok di hutan masih berlaku. Tegasnya, isu pemanasan global dapat diatasi sekiranya undang-undang yang digubal dihormati serta dipatuhi oleh setiap ahli masyarakat tanpa pengecualian.Usaha lain yang boleh menyumbang kepada pengurangan kadar pemanasan global adalah dengan menggunakan sumber tenaga yang boleh diperbaharui. Untuk makluman, Malaysia masih lagi menggunakan pembakaran arang sebagai sumber penghasilan tenaga elektrik. Kaedah ini seharusnya diubah kerana kita mempunyai banyak sumber tenaga yang boleh diperbaharui seperti tenaga hidroelektrik dan tenaga solar. Sebagai rakyat marhaen pula, kita oleh beralih kepada pengunaan tenaga solar dirumah bagi menjimatkan penggunaan elektrik konvensional. Selain itu, langkah seperti menutup suis dan menanggalkan plag elektirk apabila tidak digunakan adalah langkah kecil yang mengurangkan penggunaan elektrik sekaligus mengurangkan pemanasan global. Tidak dinafikan negara kita masih banyak bergantung kepada sumber tenaga yang tidak boleh diperbaharui. Tetapi pembina polisi dan dasar negara sudah perlu merencana langkah untuk mengalihkan kebergantungan kepada sumber tenaga yang boleh diperbaharui sebagai usaha mengatasi pemanasan global.Seterusnya, langkah untuk mengatasi isu pemanasan global adalah dengan memastikan pembangunan lestari dilaksanakan di setiap peringkat. Pembangunan lestari bermaksud membina pusat komersial, perindustrian atau perumahan di samping mengekalkan kelestarian kawasan persekitaran. Langkah ini mustahak untuk diimplementasikan kerana antara punca pemanasan global adalah penebangan kawasan hutan yang luas hanya untuk menampung perkembangan dan keperluan manusia sejagat. Pokok merupakan agen penyerap gas karbon semula jadi yang selama ini mengekalkan kestabilan ekosistem di muka bumi. Jika jumlah pokok semakin berkurang dari hari ke hari, jumlah gas karbon yang dilepaskan akan meningkat dan mengakibatkan pemanasan global. Oleh itu, pihak berkuasa perlu memperkenalkan mekanisme kawalan terhadap pembangunan di dalam negara agar isu pemanasan global dapat diatasi dengan baiknya.Bagi memastikan langkah-langkah di atas dapat dilaksanakan, kempen kesedaran tentang pemanasan global perlu diperkasa. Hal ini demikian kerana masih terdapat kurang kesedaran dalam masyarakat tentang pemanasan global. Kita masih boleh lihat segelintir orang awam yang membakar sampah secara terbuka dan membazirkan tenaga elektrik tanpa berasa serba salah. Melalui pesanan khidmat masyarakat dalam iklan di televisyen atau kandungan digital di media elektronik, isu pemanasan global boleh ditularkan. Mutakhir ini, penggunaan media sosial yang sangat kerap oleh masyarakat di dunia secara amnya memudahkan mereka terpengaruh dengan sesuatu perkara. Justeru, pihak berkuasa perlu berganding bahu dengan penggiat kreatif tanah air untuk menghasilkan kempen kesedaran yang malar dalam minda masyarakat sampai bila-bila. Intihannya, langkah untuk mengatasi pemanasan global adalah dengan mendidik ahli masyarakat tentang keburukan dan langkah terbaik untuk mengatasinya.Konklusinya, semua pihak perlu berganding bahu ibarat ke bukit sama didaki, ke lurah sama dituruni untuk mengatasi isu pemanasan global ini. Pemimpin negara seharusnya mengetuai usaha untuk mengatasi pemanasan global di peringkat domestik agar menjadi contoh kepada negara-negara asing yang lain. Jika kita berjaya melakukan segala saranan yang diberikan oleh para saintis dan cendiakawan, nescaya kelangsungan hidup generasi akan datang akan terjamin. Kita perlu mengenang kembali susah-payah nenek dan moyang kita dahulu dalam memastikan kita menikmati kehidupan yang lebih baik pada hari ini. Motivasi dan semangat yang sama perlu dipupuk dalam pemikiran setiap ahli masyarakat pada hari ini. Persis kata peribahasa, berakit-rakit ke hulu, berenang-renang ke tepian, bersakit-sakit dahulu, bersenang-senang kemudian."},{"question":"Waxaad sheegtaa sidde Magic bixinta daawada  (nomenclature) loo sameyaa ?","answer":"Daawo kastaa waxa eey leedahay sadax magic mid kood . 1.Chemical name : Waa magac  utaagan  kiimigada  eey  daawada ka sameeysantahay Tusaale example Amoxicllin cap \\u0002Trade  name. waa  magaca  eey  olo  baxdo  shirgada  daawada soo saartay magaceyda Tusaale    example Emox syrup Generic   name.waa   in   dawada   loo   bixiyaa   maga   la   is layaaqaano  dunida  oo  dhan.  Magaca  nuucaan  ah  waxaa laga soo  dharaan  dhiriyay  kiimikada  daawadu  eey  kasameeysan tahay mid utaagan. Tusaale,        example Chemical ,    Acetyl salicylic acid  Generic,      Aspirin Trade,          Disprin The Dose OF Drugs  1. Minimum Therapeutic  Dose 2. Maximum Therapeutic Dose 3. Normal Therapeutic    Dose 4. The Toxin and death Dose 1.  Minium  therapeutic  dose:  waxaa  loo  Yaqaanaa  qiyaata daawo uguyar ee la isticmaalo  2.  Maximum  threrapeutic  dose:  Waa  qiyaasta  daawo  ee ugubadan 3. Normal  therapeutic  dose:  waa  qiyaata  daawada  oo  dhax dhaxaad ah  4.  The  toxin  and  dheath  dose:  Waa  qiyaasta  daawo  ee  lagu sumowbo ama lagu dhinto."},{"question":"Njẹ́ Ó Yẹ Kí Adájọ́ Tí Ó Bá Hu Ìwà Ìbàjẹ́ Kọjá Òfin?","answer":"Ni ọjọ́ Ẹti, ọjọ́ keje, oṣù kẹwa ọdún Ẹgbàálémẹ̀rindinlógún, ìròyìn pé àwọn Ọ̀tẹlẹ̀múyẹ́ já lu ilé àwọn Adájọ́ ti wọn fi ẹ̀sùn iwà ibàjẹ́ kàn jade lẹhin ti wọn ti dúró titi ki “Ẹgbẹ́ Adájọ́” gbé àwọn iwé ẹ̀sùn iwà ibàjẹ́ yẹ̀wò .  Àwọn Ọ̀tẹlẹ̀múyẹ́ ròyìn pé wọn bá owó rẹpẹtẹ, pàtàki oriṣiriṣi owó òkè òkun, ni ilé awon Adájọ́ wọnyi.   Lati igbà ti iroyin ti jade, àwọn ‘Ẹgbẹ́ Agbẹjọ́rò’ lérí pé àwọn yio da iṣẹ́ silẹ̀ ti Olóri Òṣèlú Muhammadu Buhari kò bá pàṣẹ ki wọn tú àwọn Adájọ́ naa silẹ̀ ni wéréwéré.Ni ọ̀pọ̀lọpọ̀ ọdún sẹhin, Adájọ́ àti Agbẹjọ́rò ki i ṣe iṣẹ́ nitori àgbà ni ó ndá ẹjọ́ bi ijà bá bẹ́ silẹ̀ ni ilẹ̀ Yorùbá.  Fun àpẹrẹ, bi àwọn ọmọdé bá njá, àgbàlagbà ti ó bá wà ni ilé ni yio là wọ́n, bi àwọn iyàwó-ilé bá njà, olóri ẹbi tàbi Àrẹ̀mọ ni yio la ijà.  Bi ó bá jẹ́ ijà nitori ilẹ̀ oko, Baálẹ̀ Abúlé naa ni wọn yio kó ẹjọ́ lọ bá fún idájọ́, ti ó bá jẹ àdúgbò kan si ekeji ló njà, wọn á kó ẹjọ́ lọ bá Ọba ilú àti bẹ́ ẹ̀ bẹ́ ẹ̀ lọ.   Lati wa idi òtitọ́, wọn lè kó àwọn ti ó njà lọ si ojúbọ Òriṣà lati búra.  Lẹhin ti àwọn Ìlú-Ọba pin àwọn ọ̀pọ̀lọpọ̀ ilú àwọn Aláwọ̀dúdú, iṣẹ́ Agbẹjọ́rò di ki kọ́ ni ilé-iwé giga.Kò si ọmọ Nigeria rere ti kò mọ̀ wi pé,  ‘’Ẹ̀ṣẹ̀ nlá ijiyà kékeré tàbi ki ó má si ijiyà rara fún Olówó, ṣùgbọ́n ẹ̀ṣẹ̀ kékeré ijiyà nla ni fún tálákà tàbi aláìní’’, nitori iwà burúkú àwọn Adájọ́ ti ó ti gba àbẹ̀tẹ́lẹ̀ lọ́wọ́ àwọn Agbejoro.  A ri gbọ́ wi pé bi “Ọ̀gá Àgbà Agbẹjọ́rò” bá ni ẹjọ́ ni iwájú Adájọ́ lẹhin ti ẹjọ́  agbejoro ti dé iwájú Adájọ́, wọn yio kọ́kọ́ gbọ́ ẹjọ́ ti “Ọ̀gá Àgbà Agbẹjọ́rò” gbé wá.  Eleyi jẹ́ ikan ninú idi pàtàki ti ọ̀pọ̀lọpọ̀  Agbejoro ti fẹ́ fi ọ̀nàkọnà dé ipò “Ọ̀gá Àgbà Agbẹjọ́rò”.  Ó yẹ ki wọn gbé eyi yẹ̀wò nitori ni ilú ti òfin bá wà, kò yẹ ki ẹnikẹni kọjá òfin.  Ni Òkè-Òkun, Gó́́mìnà, àgbà Òṣèlú àti bẹ́ ẹ̀ bẹ́ ẹ̀ lọ kò kọjá òfin.“Ẹni ma a bèrè ẹ̀tó lábẹ́ òfin yio lọ pẹ̀lú ọwọ́ mímọ́”,  ẹ gb́e ọ̀rọ̀ yi yẹ̀wò bóyá bi wọ́n bá fi ẹ̀sùn iwà ibàjẹ́ kan Adájọ́, kò yẹ ki Ọ̀tẹlẹ̀múyẹ́ wa idi."},{"question":"Ipo Aarẹ 2023: Faṣhọla rọ ẹgbẹ oṣelu APC lati tẹle adehun","answer":"Amofin agba Babatunde Faṣhọla, ti da sọrọ to n ja ran-in-ran-in nilẹ lori apa ibi ti aarẹ yoo ti jade lọdun 2023.Faṣhọla ti ke sawọn ọmọ  ẹgbẹ oṣelu APC ki wọn bọwọ fun ọrọ adehun to ti wa nilẹ lori bi wọn yoo ṣe maa pin ipo Aarẹ laarin agbegbe awọn ẹya to wa ni Naijiria.O ni ṣaaju eto idibo ọdun 2015, lawọn agbaagba oloṣelu ti wọn kora wọn jọ lati da ẹgbẹ oṣelu APC silẹ ti ni ajọsọ ̀ọrọ, bo tilẹ jẹ pe ko si ninu akọsilẹ nipa ibi ti Aarẹ yoo ti jade lọdun 2023 lẹyin ti Buhari ba pari eto iṣakoso ẹ.O ni adehun ṣe pataki pupọ, ti eeyan ba si le tẹle e, yoo mu ilọsiwaju ba orilẹ-ede. Ọkunrin oloṣelu yii wa ninu awọn to jokoo nigba naa lọhun-un lati da ẹgbẹ APC silẹ, ni kete ti Buhari si ti jawe olubori, toun naa ko si nipo gomina mọ, ni wọn ti ba a wa nnkan, nibi to ti jẹ minisita akọkọ to maa ni ipo mẹta ninu ijọba Buhari.Faṣhọla ti waa ke si gbogbo ọmọ ẹgbẹ oṣelu APC lati wa ni iṣọkan, bẹẹ lo tun fidi ẹ mulẹ pe ko si ọna ti ẹgbẹ oṣelu PDP le gba ti wọn le ba APC laelae nidii oṣelu, nitori pupọ ninu awọn ọmọ ẹgbẹ ọhun paapaa ni wọn tun n darapọ mọ APC bayiì, eyi to fi han pe niṣe ni ẹgbẹ oṣelu naa n tẹsiwaju si i.Tẹ o ba gbagbe, laipẹ yii ni gomina ipinlẹ Ebonyi, David Umahi, kuro ninu ẹgbẹ oṣelu PDP, to si waa darapọ mọ ẹgbẹ oṣelu APC.Ohun ti gomina naa sọ pe o mu oun kuro ninu ẹgbẹ PDP  ko ju bi ẹgbẹ naa ko ṣe ronu ri lati lo ọmọ Ibo gẹgẹ bii oludije fun ipo Aarẹ latigba ti eto ijọba awa-ara-wa ti bẹrẹ pada lọdun 1999.Yatọ si eyi, alaga fidi-hẹe ẹgbẹ naa, Mai Mala Buni, ẹni ti ṣe gomina ipinlẹ Yobe, naa tun gbe igbesẹ kan laipẹ yii, nigba to ko awọn kan sodi lọọ ki Aarẹ tẹlẹ, Goodluck Ebere Joanthan, nile lasiko tiyẹn ṣe ọjọọbi ẹ. Ohun tawọn eeyan to mọ tifun-tẹdọ oṣelu n sọ ni pe gbogbo ọgbọn ni APC n wa bayii lati fa oju ọkunrin naa mọra lati waa darapọ mọ wọn.Bẹẹ ni wọn n sọ pe o ṣee ṣe ki wọn fa ọkunrin naa kalẹ fun ipo Aarẹ, paapaa bo ṣe jẹ pe saa kan pere lo tun le ṣe nile ijọba, ati pe lẹyin saa kan ẹ yii lọmọ Hausa yoo gba a pada lọwọ ẹ."},{"question":"Qual criatura marinha popular tem a capacidade de se clonar?","answer":"Água-viva. Quando as águas-vivas são cortadas ao meio, elas têm a capacidade de regenerar suas células e criar outras águas-vivas."},{"question":" ما المادة الرئيسة التي يحتويها معجون الأسنان ؟","answer":"الفلوريد"},{"question":"Adura ati ifọwọsowọpọ wa pẹlu ọga ṣọja ni Naijiria fi le bọ ninu wahala eto aabo – Oluwoo","answer":"Oluwoo tilu Iwo, nipinlẹ Ọṣun, Ọba Abdulrosheed Adewale Akanbi, ti ke si gbogbo awọn ọmọ orileede yii lati gbaruku ti ọga awọn ṣọja ti wọn ṣẹṣẹ yan lorileede yii, Major Gen. Faruk Yahaya, ko le baa ṣaṣeyọri si rere.Ninu atẹjade kan ti akọwe iroyin kabiesi, Alli Ibraheem, fi sita ni Oluwo ti ni wahala to n fojoojumọ yọju lẹka eto aabo ilẹ wa yii ti pe fun ki tolori-tẹlẹmu tọ soju kan naa, ko baa le ho.O ni ọna kan ṣoṣo ti Yahaya fi le ṣaṣeyọri, ti wahala yii yoo si di afisẹyin teegun n fiṣọ ni ki gbogbo ọmọ orileede Naijiria ba a fọwọ sowọ pọ lati wa ojutuu si wahala yii.Ọba Adewale fi kun ọrọ rẹ pe bi ọrọ aabo ṣe mẹhẹ bayii ko dun mọ oun ninu rara, ṣugbọn oun mọ pe akinkanju to ni imọ kikun ninuu bi a ṣe n gbogun ti iwa igbesunmọmi ni ọga awọn ṣọja tuntun naa.O ni ti awọn araalu ba ti le wa niṣọkan pẹlu ileeṣẹ ologun, yoo jẹ koriya fun awọn ṣọja, wọn yoo si ṣiṣẹ naa pẹlu idaniloju pe gbogbo ọmọ Naijiria lo wa lẹyin awọn.Kabiesi sọ siwaju pe awọn ọmọ orileede yii gbọdọ da igbẹkẹle ti wọn ni ninu ileeṣẹ ologun pada, ki wọn si sọ ifẹ wọn fun ileeṣẹ naa di ọtun.O ni oun nigbẹkẹle kikun ninu ipa Yahaya pe yoo ṣe takuntakun lati ri i pe awọn araalu le sun lai foya rara, o si pe fun ki gbogbo eeyan maa fi adura ran an lọwọ lati le jajaṣẹgun lori awọn ikọ agbesunmọmi ti wọn wa kaakiri.Oluwoo ni “Ẹ jẹ ka fọwọ sowọ pọ lati le awọn janduku ti wọn n da orileede wa ru jade. Gbogbo wa la ni orileede yii, a ni ipa lati ko lati tu aṣiri awọn to n yọ wa lẹnu.”"},{"question":"LGS'ye girmeden özel okula gidilir mi?","answer":"Yeni sınav sisteminde sınava isteyen öğrenciler girecektir. 3) Sınava girmeden de herhangi bir okula yerleşebilir miyim? Evet."},{"question":"Naag Maseer Badan?","answer":"Maalin WanaagsanHaweenay ayaa mar kasta waxay aadi jirtay guriga Gabar saaxiibteed ah, iyaduna way u iman jirtay. Ninkeedi ayaa dhibsaday, mar kasta uu shaqada ka yimaado wuxuu arkaa saaxiibadeed oo la joogta ama iyada oo guriga ka maqan. Wuxuu isku dayay in uu kala hadlo laakiin waxay ugu jawaabi jirtay, “Waa Gabadha keliya ee saaxiib ila ah, markaa hadii aan aado ama ay ii timaado maxaa ku jaban”Odaygi waxaa ka dhamaaday dulqaadki, wuu fakiray, wuxuuna gaaray go’aan. Maalin ayuu isagoo ka yimi safar gaaban wuxuu soo galay guriga, wuxuu u yeeray Xaaskiisi. Wuxuu ku yiri, “Bacdan adiga ayaa iska leh. waxaan kuu soo gaday dhar iyo kabo. Bacdan kale waxaa ku jira Dhar qaali ah iyo Dahab waa hadiyad aan u soo iibiyay Gabadhi Saaxiibadaa ahayd”.Xaaski waxay ku dhufatay qeylo “Ma heerkaas ayaa la marayaa. Waa maxay hadiyada qaaliga ah aad u soo iibisay naagta. Ma laha hoos bay kuula soo hadli jirtay, waa hadii ay gurigayga dambe timaado, iwm.” Saaxiibadeed ayaa guriga soo gashay, waxaana haweenaydi xaaska ahayd ka hor gaysay buuq iyo dagaal waxayna ku lahayd hadii aad gurigayga dambe timaado Walaahi wixi kugu dhaca adigaa ka mas’uul ah, aniguna weligay kuu iman maayo. Gabadhi saaxiibadeed iyada oo yaaban ayay guriga orad uga baxday. Haweenaydi socod dambe ma samayn. Odaygina gadaal buu ka qoslayay. "},{"question":"Aïcha Boro","answer":"Chloé Aïcha Boro Letterier (tí wọ́n bí ní 24 Oṣù Kaàrún Ọdún 1978) jẹ́ olùdarí eré àti ònkọ̀tàn ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè Bùrkínà Fasò.Boro dàgbà ní ìlú Ouagadougou nítòsí Balolé quarry. Ó kẹ́kọ̀ọ́ ìmọ̀ nípa àwọn àkọsílẹ̀ ti ìgbàlódé, ó sì lépa ṣíṣe iṣẹ́ agbéròyìn. Ó ti kọ àwọn àyọkà fún àwọn ilé-iṣẹ́ oníròyìn bíi \\"La Voix du Sahel\\" àti \\"Le Marabout\\", ó sì se àtẹ̀jáde àkọ́kọ́ ìwé-ìtàn rẹ̀ tí àkọ́lé rẹ̀ jẹ́ Paroles orpheline ní ọdún 2006. Ìwé náà gba àmì-ẹ̀ye Naji Naaman ní ìlú Lẹ́bánọ́n. Boro padà gbájúmọ́ ṣíṣe iṣẹ́ fíìmù, tó sì ṣe igbákejì adarí àti atọ́kùn ètò tẹlifíṣọ̀nù kan tí wọ́n pè ní Koodo, èyítí ó gba àmì-ẹ̀yẹ ti Galian ní ọdún 2006. Ó tún ṣe atọ́kùn ètò rédíò kan fún ìkànnì Radio Gambidi. Ní ọdún 2010, Boro kó lọ sí orílẹ̀-èdè Fráǹsì.Ní ọdún 2012, ó darí fíìmù fún ìgbà àkọ́kọ́ rẹ̀ pẹ̀lú dídarí fíìmù tí àkọ́lé rẹ̀ jẹ́ Sur les traces de Salimata . Boro tún sẹ àkọ́kọ́ fíìmù gígún oníìrírí-ayé tí àkọ́lé rẹ̀ jẹ́ Farafin Ko ní ọdún 2014. Ní ọdún 2017, ó ṣe adarí eré France-Aurevoir, le nouveau commerce triangulaire . Eré náà gba àmì-ẹ̀yẹ gẹ́gẹ́ bi fíìmù ìrírí-ayé tí ó tayọ jùlọ níbi ayẹyẹ Festival international de cinéma Vues d’Afrique, èyí tí ó wáyé ní ìlú Montreal. Ní ọdún 2018, Boro kọ ìwé-ìtàn kan tí àkọ́lé rẹ̀ jẹ́ Notre Djihad intérieur, èyítí ó n sọ ìtàn nípa ẹnìkan tí ó padà sí abúlé rẹ̀ tí ó wà ní ilẹ́ Áfríkà láti orílẹ̀-èdè Fráǹsì. Boro ṣe adarí eré ìrírí-ayé tí àkọ́lé rẹ̀ jẹ́ Le Loup d'or de Balolé ní ọdún 2019. Eré náà dá lóri ìfipáyí ètò ìṣèjọba tí ó wáyé ní ọdún 2014 àti àwọn ipa tí ó là lára àwọn òṣìṣẹ́ Balolé Quarry. Eré náà gba àmì-ẹ̀yẹ ti eré ìrírí tí ó dára jùlọ níbi ayẹyẹ Panafrican Film and Television Festival of Ouagadougou.Àṣàyàn àwọn eré rè2012: Sur les traces de Salimata2014: Farafin Ko2017: France-Aurevoir, le nouveau commerce triangulaire2019: Le Loup d'or de Balolé"},{"question":"යමෙකුට නිදා ගැනීමට උපකාර වන ක්‍රම මොනවාද?","answer":"නින්දට ආලෝකය බලපානු ඇත, එබැවින් නින්දට පෙර විදුලි පහන් අඳුරු කිරීම සහ තිර භාවිතා කිරීම නැවැත්වීම හොඳ නින්දේ සනීපාරක්ෂාව ලෙස සැලකේ. ඊට අමතරව නිදන කාමරය නිශ්ශබ්ද සහ සිසිල් බව සහතික කර ගැනීම නින්දට බෙහෙවින් උපකාරි වේ."},{"question":"Kuhle ukuzenzela isidlo sasemini esinempilo nsuku zonke. Ukuthenga ukudlakwasemini ezitolo akubizi nje kuphela kodwa kuvame ukungabi nayo impilo.Ama-wraps enziwe ngaphambilini, amasemishi ngisho namasaladi angabanoshukela omningi.Ekugcineni uchwepheshe kwezokudla utshele abantu ukuthi abazilungiseleleukudla okunempilo kwesonto lonke ukuze baphile kahle.1. Guqula leli gama elibhalwe ngokugqamile libe yisikhuliso beseulisebenzisa emshweni ozozakhela wona.Isitolo esinokudla okunomsoco sihle.","answer":"Imisho iyokwehluka:Isitolokazi.Ubaba uthenge isitolokazi edolobheni."},{"question":"问题：瘦金体是什么？","answer":"答案：瘦金体是中国书法的一种字体，起源于唐代，由唐朝著名书法家颜真卿的学生柳公权所创。瘦金体字形秀美，线条细长，如同削金之瘦，因此得名。"},{"question":"Чүй облусу тууралуу маалымат бер.","answer":"Чүй облусу (орус. Чуйская область) — Кыргызстандын түндүк жагында Чүй өрөөнүндө жайгашкан, 1939-жылында 21-ноябрда СССР Жогорку Советинин Президиумунун Указы менен Фрунзе облусу болуп түзүлүп, 1959-жылы жоюлган. 1990-жылы республикалык баш ийүүдөгү райондордон азыркы аталыш менен калыбына келтирилген.Түндүк жана батыштан Казакстан Республикасы менен, түштүк-батыштан Талас, Жалал-Абад, түштүгүнөн Нарын, түштүк-чыгышта Кыргызстандын Ысык-Көл облустары менен чектешет."},{"question":"Terjemahkanlah penggalan teks Bahasa Inggris yang disadur dari kumpulan cerita anak dunia berikut ke teks dalam Bahasa Indonesia.One day a baby elephant was born. She was curious about everything. She had a question for every animal.Terjemahan:","answer":"Suatu hari, seekor bayi gajah lahir. Dia ingin tahu tentang segala hal. Dia punya pertanyaan untuk setiap hewan."},{"question":"Гендик инженерия деген эмне жана ал биотехнологияда кантип колдонулат?","answer":"Гендик инженерия гендерди кошуу же өзгөртүү үчүн организмдин ДНКсын манипуляциялоону камтыйт. Ал биотехнологияда генетикалык жактан өзгөртүлгөн организмдерди түзүү жана медициналык дарылоону өнүктүрүү үчүн колдонулат."},{"question":"Ik krijg deze vraag tijdens een sollicitatiegesprek: \\"Zeg, vertel ons eens. Wie ben jij?\\", wat is het beste hierop te antwoorden?","answer":"Dit klinkt zo makkelijk. Alleen, zonder voorbereiding gaan veel mensen maar wat in het wilde weg vertellen over hun privéleven. Hartstikke leuk, niet de bedoeling! De werkgever stelt deze vraag om te zien wat jij belangrijke eigenschappen van jezelf vindt. Zo weten ze wat ze aan je hebben op de werkvloer.Vind je dit lastig om voor jezelf te bepalen? Tip: vraag aan je (oud)-collega’s, ouders en vrienden wat jouw eigenschappen zijn. Dit geeft een oprecht beeld van wie je bent.Do: Vertel over brede - en voor je potentiële werkgever - interessante eigenschappen, zoals: zorgzaam, flexibel, taakgericht, sociaal of behulpzaam.Don’t: Zomaar wat roepen. Solliciteer je als verpleegkundige? Zeg dan niet dat je van aanpakken weet en graag snel grote stappen zet, maar focus je meer op je zorgzame kant."},{"question":"கேள்வி: புகழ் பெற்ற லைலா மஜ்னு காதல் காவியத்தின் ஆசிரியர் யார்?","answer":"நிஜாமி கஞ்சாவி. லைலா மஜ்னு காதல் காவியம் 7ஆம் நூற்றாண்டில் அரேபிய தீபகற்பத்தின் வடக்கில் வாழ்ந்த காயிஸ் இப்ன் அல் முல்லாவாஹ் எனும் இளைஞனை வாழ்க்கையை அடிப்படையாக வைத்து எழுத்தப்பட்டது. இதை எழுதியவர் 12ஆம் நூற்றாண்டைச் சேர்ந்த முகலாய கவிஞர் நிஜாமி கஞ்சாவி ஆவார்."},{"question":"متى قامت أمريكا بأول رحلة فضائية؟","answer":"قامت أمريكا بأول رحلة فضائية عام 1926 م."},{"question":"Boko Haram ti sọrọ, wọn ni ẹ ma laagun jinna, awọn ọmọleewe yin wa lọdọ wa","answer":"Bo ti ṣe n pe ọjọ karun-un lọ bayii ti wọn ti ji awọn ọmọ ileewe girama kan ko ni Kankara nipinlẹ Katsina, awọn janduku afẹmiṣofo Boko Haram ti  sọ pe awọn gan-an lawọn ṣiṣẹ ibi ọhun.Ninu fidio ti ko ju iṣẹju mẹrin aabọ lọ ni agbẹnusọ wọn, Abubakar Shekau, ti sọ pe awọn lawọn ji awọn ọmọ ọhun gbe, ati pe ọmọleewe bii ọọdunrun (300) lo wa ni akata awọn bayii.Koko ohun ti awọn janduku afẹmiṣofo yii sọ pe o mu awọn ṣiṣẹ ibi ọhun ko ju inu buruku to n bi awọn lọ nitori ti wọn n kọ awọn ọmọ naa lẹkọọ iwe mọ-ọn-kọ, mọ-ọn-ka, eyi ti ko ba ti Ọlọrun mu.Alẹ ana, ọjọ Aje lawọn Boko Haram ti fi fidio ọhun sita, bẹẹ ni Shekau, sọ pe ko si ootọ kan ninu iroyin tawọn kan n gbe kiri wi pe awọn ti sọ ohun tawọn fẹ gan-an.O fi kun un pe bi awọn ṣe kọlu ileewe Government Science Secondary School, ni Kankara, nipinlẹ Katsina, awọn fi ṣapọnle ẹsin Islam ni, ati pe eto ẹkọ mọ-ọn-kọ mọ-ọn-ka ti wọn n kọ wọn nileewe ọhun ko ba ilana Ọlọrun ati ti Anọbi mu rara.Ninu ọrọ ẹ naa lo ti ni ki awọn eeyan ma wulẹ laagun jinna, awọn gan-an lawọn wa nidii ijinigbe ọhun, awọn ọmọ ti wọn n wa wa lọdọ awọn o."},{"question":" Гүлазык деген эмне?","answer":"Гүлазык–эң керектүү азык."},{"question":"UHulumeni ufunelani ukubona kugeleza ingelezane yegazi ezweni?Ufunelani?UHulumeni kuhle azi kahle ukuthi thina asiwuweli uMngeni!Elethu! (Kube nobuhhomuhhomu.)(Asukume.)(Basakazeke. Bayaluze.)Ngipheni indlebe. Ngipheni indlebe bantu bakaSalimani. Ngiyanazinina nithanda ukuthula. UHulumeni akaqonde khona ukuniqhatha.Uyanilamula. Uma le ndawo ingabuyeli kubanikaziyo kuyosukaumbango omubi ngomuso kusale izidumbu phansi senilwa nabayobesebewuwelile uMngeni.(Sivungame.)1. Nikeza isizathu sokuba isimo senhlalo singabi sihle ekuqaleni kwalesisiqeshana.","answer":"Isizathu sidalwa ukungavumelani phakathi kukaSalimani nabantu bakhekanye noZithulele ngenxa yokubanga ukuwelwa koMngeni okungadala ukuthiabantu balwe kuze kuchitheke igazi."},{"question":"Responde la siguiente pregunta: ¿Qué miembro de 30 Seconds to Mars apareció en la película Escuadrón Suicida?","answer":"La respuesta es Jared Leto. "},{"question":"క్రింద ఇచ్చిన అంశం మీద శీర్షిక రాయండి: కనీసం ఐదు పేరాలు వచ్చేలాగా రాయండి ‘కరోనా’ ను భయపెట్టిన ప్రతిబోధ భట్టు ప్రవచనం","answer":"గొప్పలు చెప్పుకోవడం, ఎవరి అనుభవాలనో విని వాటిని తమవిగా వర్తింపచేసుకుని చెప్పుకోవడం, ఎవరో వ్రాసినదాన్ని కాపీ చేసి తమవిగా చెప్పుకోవడం … ఇలాంటి లక్షణాలుండే వ్యక్తులు మనకు తరచూ తగుల్తూనే ఉంటారు. ఒప్పుకోడానికి మనసొప్పదు గానీ మనలోనూ ఆ లక్షణాలు నిండు కుండలా ఉంటాయి. అయితే ఇలాంటి లక్షణాలన్నింటికీ పరాకాష్ఠ, ఎవరెస్ట్ శిఖరం అనదగ్గ కేరెక్టర్ మన ‘ప్రతిబోధ భట్టు’.  మన ‘ప్రతిబోధ భట్టు’ గారు కాలాతీత, భాషాతీత, దేశాతీత వ్యక్తి. ప్రపంచం మొత్తంలో అతను కాలుమోపని ప్రదేశం లేదు.  ‘ప్రతిబోధ భట్టు’ గారి వయసెంతో ఎవరికీ తెలియదు. ‘వారన్ హేస్టింగ్స్’ ఇండియా గవర్నర్ జనరల్‌గా ఉన్నప్పుడు ఏ సమస్య వచ్చినా ‘టేక్ ది కామెంట్స్ ఆఫ్ అవర్ భట్టు’ అనేవారట పాపం.1964 లో జవహర్లాల్ నెహ్రు మరణానంతరం కాంగ్రెస్ పార్టీ దిక్కుతోచని స్థితిలో కొట్టిమిట్టాడుతుండగా భట్టు గారిని ఆశ్రయించగా భట్టు గారు తాత్కాలికంగా గుల్జారీలాల్ నందాను ప్రధాన మంత్రి చేయాల్సిందిగా సలహా ఇచ్చేరు. తరువాత 1966 లో లాల్ బహదూర్ శాస్త్రి గారి మరణానంతరం కాంగ్రెస్ పార్టీ మళ్ళీ భట్టు గారిని సంప్రదించగా అప్పుడుకూడా  గుల్జారీలాల్ నందాను ప్రధాన మంత్రి చేయాల్సిందిగా సలహా ఇచ్చేరు.  లాల్ బహదూర్ శాస్త్రి గారు ప్రజలకు దగ్గరయే మార్గం చెప్పమని భట్టుగారిని అడగ్గా “జైజవాన్ – జై కిసాన్” నినాదంతో ప్రజల దగ్గరకు వెళ్ళమని చెప్పేరు.  అలాగే శాస్త్రి గారి మరణానంతరం ఆయనకీ భారతరత్న ఇవ్వాలని సూచించింది మన భట్టుగారే.  ఎవరినీ ఒక పట్టాన నమ్మని ఇందిరా గాంధీ గారు భట్టుగారిని పూర్తిగా విశ్వసించేవారట. అంతేకాదు భట్టుగారి మాటంటే ఆమెకు వేదవాక్కు.  ఇంకా చెప్పాలంటే ఇందిరా గాంధీ గారిని భట్టుగారు ‘ఇందు’ అనికూడా అనగలరట.  ఆమెకు “గరీబీ హఠావో” నినాదాన్ని ఉపదేశించింది భట్టుగారే.   మన భట్టు గారికి  తెలియని భాష లేదు. బంకించంద్ర చటర్జీ వందేమాతరం గీతాన్ని ముందుగా భట్టు గారికి చూపించి భట్టు గారు సూచించిన మార్పులు, చేర్పులు చేసిన తర్వాతే అది ఆమోదం పొంది ప్రచురణకి యోగ్యమైందిట.  విశ్వనాధ సత్యనారాయణ గారు మంచి కవిగా పురస్కారాలు పొందుతున్న సమయాన, ఒకానొక సన్మానసభలో భట్టు గారిని విశ్వనాధ వారు కలియటం జరిగి మాటామాటా కలిసి ఆ తర్వాత ఇరువురి మధ్య స్నేహం కుదరటం జరిగిందట. అయితే వారిమధ్య కుదిరిన స్నేహం భట్టు గారి అభిప్రాయాన్ని మార్చేసింది.  ఒకసారి భట్టు గారు, విశ్వనాధ వారు ‘కాళిదాసు’ గారి మేఘసందేశం పై చర్చించుకుంటుండగా అనుకోకుండా రామాయణం ప్రస్తావన వచ్చి భట్టు గారు విశ్వనాధవారితో రామాయణం గురించి రాయొచ్చు కదా అని అడిగేరట.  దానికి విశ్వనాథవారు వాల్మీకి రాసేడుగా అన్నారుట.  భట్టుగారు మీరు మీశైలిలో రాయండి అన్నారుట అందుకు విశ్వనాధ వారు కొంచెం వివరంగా చెప్పమన్నారుట.  అప్పుడు భట్టుగారు “రామాయణ కల్పవృక్షం” వ్రాయమని అది ఏ విధంగా ఉండాలో చెప్పేరుట.  వెంటనే విశ్వనాధ వారు భట్టు గారు  విశదీకరించిన  ప్రకారం “రామాయణ కల్పవృక్షం” వ్రాయటం అది జ్ఞానపీఠ అవార్డు పొందిన తొలి తెలుగు రచనగా ఎంపికవడం జరిగి ఆ విధంగా విశ్వనాధ వారు తొలి జ్ఞానపీఠ అవార్డు పొందిన తెలుగు రచయిత అయ్యారట. ఆ సన్మాన పత్రం భట్టు గారే తయారు చేసేరుట.  అందులో భట్టు గారు విశ్వనాధ సత్యనారాయణ గారి గురించి ఆంగ్ల భాషలో అనర్గళంగా ఈ విధంగా వ్రాసేరట  “As a Poet of classic vision and virility, as a novelist and play wright of deep insight and impact, as an essayist and literary critic of force and felicity, and as a stylist of rare “range” Mr. Satyanarayana has carved for himself a place of eminence amongst the immortals of Telugu Literature. His ceaseless creativity and versatility have kept him in the forefront of contemporary Telugu Literary Scene” భట్టు గారు.  తను వ్రాస్తున్న బాలవ్యాకరణం వ్రాసేటప్పుడు పరవస్తు చిన్నయసూరికి సందేహాలు వస్తే చీటిమీద వ్రాసి తన శిష్యుల  ద్వారా భట్టు గారి దగ్గరకు పంపేవారట. నలందా విశ్వ విద్యాలయం అరుగు మీద కూర్చుని మహాత్మా గాంధీకి స్వతంత్ర   పోరాటం గురించి చెబుతుండేవారట. అలాగే గాంధీగారికి రాట్నం వడకటం కూడా భట్టు గారు మప్పినదే.  గాంధీ గారు చేపట్టిన “ఉప్పు సత్యాగ్రహం” భట్టుగారు ప్రతిపాదించినదే. సరోజినీ దేవి తన కవితా సంపుటి ‘గోల్డెన్ త్రెషోల్డ్’‌కు ముందుమాట  వ్రాయమని భట్టు గారిని  కోరిందట. తీరా భట్టు గారు ముందుమాట వ్రాసి ఇచ్చిన తర్వాత ముందుమాట  ‘అసలు కవితల్నే మింగేసేట్లు’ ఉండడంతో ప్రచురించలేదట. ఘంటశాల వెంకటేశ్వర రావు గారిని కలిసినప్పుడు దేశభక్తి  పాటలు పాడమని చెప్పేరుట.  ఆసలహా విని ఘంటశాలగారు “ఆ మొగల్ రణధీరులు, అమ్మా సరోజినీ దేవి మొదలైన పాటలు పాడేరుట.   మన ‘ప్రతిబోధ భట్టు’ నేర్వని శాస్త్రం లేదు. శ్యామశాస్త్రి ని శ్యాము అని  పిలిచేవాడు. శ్యామ శాస్త్రి తాత, ముత్తాతలు సంగీతంలో తమ సందేహాలను భట్టు గారిని  అడిగి నివృత్తి చేసుకునేవారు. భీమ్‌సేన్ జోషి, హరి చౌరాసియాలతో సంగీత చర్చలు జరిపేవాడు మన భట్టు గారు. చౌరాసియాను హరీ అనే పిలిచేవాడు. రాజ్యాంగ రచనలో బాబా సాహెబ్ అంబేద్కర్‌కు పలు సూచనలు ఇచ్చాడు. మన భారతీయ పురాణేతిహాసాలలోని యుద్ధతంత్రాలను నేటి కాలానికి ఆచరణసాధ్యంగా మలచి వ్యూహరచన చేయమని జనరల్ కరియప్పను కోరాడు మన భట్టు గారు. గగనతలంలో ఈథర్ అనే పొర గురించి చేసిన పరిశోధనలో జగదీష్ చంద్రబోస్‌కు భట్టు సహకరించేడు. 1879లో సాలార్ జంగ్ చెంగిజ్ ఖాన్‌కు చెందినదిగా చెప్పబడుతున్న ఒక పురాతన గుర్రపు నాడా అమ్మకానికి రాగా అది అసలేనా, నకిలీయా అని తెలుసుకోవడానికి సలహా కొరకు భట్టు గారినిని సంప్రదించారట. భట్టు గారు చెంగిజ్ ఖాన్ గుర్రపు నాడా సైజు ఇది కాదని తేల్చేశాడు. లండన్ లో భట్టు గారు ప్రసంగిస్తున్నాడని తెలిసి, జనాలు ఎడ్లబండ్లు కట్టుకుని వచ్చి, అన్నాలు వండుకుతింటూ ఎదురుచూశారు. ఆ సభలో భట్టు గారు అందర్నీ కళ్ళు మూసుకోమని, వయొలిన్ మీద సప్తస్వరాలను ఒక్కొక్కదాన్నే పట్టుకుని స్వరప్రస్తారం చేస్తుంటే వాళ్ళకు ఏడురంగులూ కనిపించాయి. ఆ వయొలిన్‌ను లండన్  సెంట్రల్ మ్యూజియంలో అద్దాలపెట్టెలో భద్రపరచారు. అక్షాంశరేఖాంశాలను చూసుకుని భూమిలోపల ‘పన్నెండువేలు కాదుగానీ, పదకొండువేల అడుగులవరకూ’ ఏమున్నాయో పసిగట్టి, చూసినట్లు చెప్పగలడు భట్టు గారు. ఐన్‌స్టయిన్ e=mc2 సూత్రాన్ని భారతీయ వేదవిజ్ఞానంతో సమన్వయపరచింది భట్టు గారేనేట. అందుకని అతనికి దేశ అత్యున్నత పురస్కారం ఇవ్వాలని జమ్‌షెడ్‌జీ టాటా సూచించాడు. అయితే భట్టు ఎప్పుడూ తనకు పేరును కాని, బిరుదులు గానీ కోరుకోడు గనుక ఆయన్ను బిరుదులకు ఒప్పించడం అసాధ్యం అన్నారట కె. ఎం. మున్షీ.భట్టు గారు పరిష్కరించలేని సమస్య లేదు. సబర్మతి ఆశ్రమంలో జిన్నాతో సంప్రదింపులు అనగానే భట్టు గారి పేరు మొదట వినిపించేది. ఎడ్వర్డ్ చక్రవర్తి పట్టాభిషేకం సండర్భంగా సత్కరించ అర్హులైన భారతీయుల పేర్లు చెప్పమని బ్రిటీష్ మహారాణి భట్టు గారిని కోరినప్పుడు భట్టు గారు  పెట్టిన షరతు ‘ఎట్టి పరిస్థితుల్లోనూ తనపేరు అందులో ఉండగూడదని’. బ్రిటన్ నుంచి సరకులు, వంటవారితో వస్తున్న ఓడ రాక ఆలస్యమైంది. 1,20,000 మంది అతిథులకు విందు. పరువు పొయ్యేలా ఉంది. వైస్‌రాయ్‌కి దిక్కుతోచక భట్టు గారిని  హుటాహుటిన రప్పించి సహాయం చెయ్యమని కోరగా. అలెగ్జాండ్రియా ఓడ డెక్‌పై అంతమందికి అప్పడం, వడియం, లడ్డూ, పులిహోరతో సహా విందుభోజనం సిద్ధం చేశాడు మన భట్టు. అలహాబాద్ హైకోర్టులో ఒక క్లిష్టమైన కేసువిషయంలో డిఫెన్స్ లాయరు మోతీలల్ నెహ్రూ. గారు  కేసు ఎలా నడపాలో అంతుచిక్కక భట్టు గారిని  పిలిపించారట  మోతీలాల్ నెహ్రు  గారు. భట్టు గారు అయిదే ఐదు నిమిషాల్లో చిక్కు విడగొట్టి ‘ఉండచుట్టేశాడు’. యూరీ గగారిన్ అంతరిక్ష యాత్రకు ముందు, అతనికి మనో నిబ్బరం కలిగించడానికి భట్టు గారిని  రష్యాకు పిలిపించారట. టెన్సింగ్ నార్కే ఎవరెస్ట్ అధిరోహణ మొదలుపెట్టే సమయానికి అక్కడే ఉన్న భట్టు గారు నార్కేకు పర్వతారోహణలో మెలకువలు, తీసుకోవలసిన జాగ్రత్త్తల గురించి చెప్పాడు. ఫ్రాంక్‌ఫర్ట్ యూనివర్సిటిలో జరిగిన అణుశాస్త్ర సమావేశంలో న్యూట్రాన్లు, ప్రోటాన్లు, ఎలెక్ట్రాన్లు త్రిమూర్తులకు ప్రతీక అని ప్రతిపాదిస్తూ తూర్పు జర్మనీ భాషలో గంటా పన్నెండు నిమిషాలు అనర్గళంగా ప్రసంగించాడు భట్టు గారు. నిజాం తన రాజ్యాన్ని భారతదేశంలో కలిపేట్లు నచ్చచెప్పవలసిందిగా సర్దార్ పటేల్ భట్టు గారిని  అభ్యర్థించాడు. కానీ ఇవన్నీ బయటకు చెప్పుకోవడం భట్టు గారికి  ఇష్టం ఉండదు.సమాజంలో ఉన్న దుర్మార్గాలను ఇతివృత్తంగా సమాజ శ్రేయస్సు కోరుతూ యువతకు సందేశం ఇవ్వాలని వేటూరి సుందర రాంమూర్తి   గారు సంకల్పించి పాట రాద్దామని మొదలుపెడితే “ఈ దుర్యోధన దుశ్శాసన దుర్వినీతలోకంలో అని వ్రాసేక  మరి ముందుకు వెళ్లలేదట వేటూరి గారు నెల రోజులు ఆలోచించినా సరైన పద లయ   దొరకలేదట.  ఇంక ఇది భట్టు గారి వలన మాత్రమే పూర్తవుతుందని వెళ్లి భట్టు గారిని కలిసి విషయం చెప్పేరుట.  అంతా విన్న భట్టు గారు ఒకే ఒక నిమిషం ఆలోచించి వేటూరి గారితో ఉ… సరే… సుందర్రాముడు రాసుకో అని “రక్తాశ్రులు చిందిస్తూ రాస్తున్నా శోకంతో  మరో మహాభారతం… ఆరవ వేదం మానభంగ పర్వంలో మాతృహృదయ నిర్వేదం”…. అని అనర్గళంగా చెప్పి పాట ముగించేసేరు. ఈ పాట సాహిత్యం తాను చెప్పినట్లుగా ఎప్పుడు, ఎక్కడ మాట్లాడొద్దని కూడా వేటూరి గారికి చెప్పేరుట.  వేటూరి గారికి ఆపాటకి రాష్ట్రస్థాయిలో ఉత్తమ గీత రచయితగా నంది బహుమతి వచ్చింది. ఈ మధ్య కాలంలో చైనాలో పుట్టి ప్రపంచ యాత్ర చేస్తున్న ‘కరోనా’ వల్ల వస్తున్న ఇబ్బందుల మూలంగా చనిపోతున్న మానవాళిని కాపాడుకునే ప్రయత్నంలో ప్రపంచ ఆరోగ్య సంస్థ వారు తమ నిజాయితీని ప్రదర్శించుకోవాల్సిన సమయం వచ్చిందని గుర్తించి ఉత్తర కొరియా అధ్యక్షుడైన ‘కిమ్’ ని కలిసి మీ దేశంలో ‘కరోనా’ ప్రవేశించలేకపోయింది ఎందువలనా? అని ప్రశ్నించగా తనకు ముందు చూపు ముందు జాగ్రత్త వగైరా కలగడానికి కారణం భారత దేశంలో ఉన్న ‘ప్రతిబోధ భట్టు’ అని ఆయన బోధనల ద్వారా తాను ఉత్తేజితమయి ఆయన చరిత్రను కధగా మార్చి దాన్ని ప్రతి ఆసుపత్రియందు, మరియు విద్యార్థులకు పాఠ్యఅంశంగాను ప్రవేశపెట్టి ప్రజలందరికి బోధించుట వలన ‘కరోనా’ తమ దేశంలోకి అడుగు పెట్టె సాహసం చేయలేకపోయిందని చెప్పేరట.  అంత ప్రపంచ ఆరోగ్య సంస్థ ప్రపంచ ప్రజలందరికి కూడా ఈ విధానాన్ని ఆచరించమని సూచించింది.  అయితే మన భట్టుగారు మాత్రం తనకి సన్మానం అంటూ హడావిడి చేస్తారన్న ముందు చూపుతో ఎవరికి దొరక్కుండా స్వీయ భూగర్భ గృహ నిర్బంధం లోకి వెళ్లి ఉండొచ్చని ప్రపంచ మేధావులంతా అనుకుంటున్నారు."},{"question":"Kontynuuj zdanie: Isabella Arcila (ur. 11 marca 1994 w Cali) – kolumbijska pływaczka. Arcila przepłynęła 50 m stylem dowolnym","answer":"na Letnich Igrzyskach Olimpijskich 2016."},{"question":"Recep Tayyip Erdoğan hangi takımı tutuyor?","answer":"Recep Tayyip Erdoğan Stadyumu diğer adıyla Kasımpaşa Stadyumu, İstanbul'da bulunan 14,234 koltuk kapasiteli staddır. Bu stad 2010 yılında restore edilmiştir ve UEFA kriterlerine göre hazırlanmıştır. Stad Kasımpaşa SK'nın iç saha maçlarına ev sahipliği yapmaktadır."},{"question":"Có nên rửa mũi hàng ngày cho trẻ để phòng ngừa bệnh, nhất là trong thời tiết giao mùa?","answer":"Đường thở tự nhiên của con người bắt đầu từ mũi rồi vào đến họng và thanh quản, sau đó xuống khí quản - các phế quản lớn nhỏ và tận cùng là các phế nang. Đường thở của trẻ em thường nhỏ và hẹp hơn, do đó dễ bị ngạt thở và khó thở hơn người lớn, nhất là khi thời tiết giao mùa.Nếu nước mũi của trẻ ít, không ảnh hưởng đến thở, trẻ không phải há miệng để thở, không phải cáu khi bú vì tắc mũi không thở được... thì không cần can thiệp. Bệnh thường tự khỏi sau vài ngày.Trường hợp nước mũi đặc, trẻ không thở được bằng mũi mà phải há miệng để thở, ăn bú khó khăn, bạn cần loại bỏ nhầy mũi bằng cách rửa hoặc hút mũi. Lưu ý, hút hay rửa mũi sẽ làm mũi bé thoáng và dễ chịu hơn lúc đó nhưng chỉ sau vài tiếng thì trẻ bị tái lại do đang bị viêm. Do đó, bố mẹ nên tham khảo ý kiến bác sĩ để tự rửa cho con ở nhà, thay vì liên tục đưa trẻ đến bệnh viện.Không nên rửa mũi cho trẻ mỗi ngày, tránh làm tổn thương niêm mạc mũi. Chỉ rửa khi đờm mũi làm ảnh hưởng đến thở và ăn của bé. Nên giảm dần số lần rửa và dừng khi các triệu chứng cải thiện hơn.Lựa chọn phương pháp rửa mũi phù hợp với từng lứa tuổi. Với trẻ sơ sinh và trẻ bú mẹ (nhỏ hơn một tuổi), nên để trẻ nằm nghiêng và dùng lọ nước muối sinh lý loại 10 ml. Với trẻ lớn hơn, mẹ nên dùng bình rửa mũi chuyên dụng.Bạn nên nhờ nhân viên y tế hướng dẫn trực tiếp trước khi tự thực hành ở nhà."},{"question":"අශුද්ධ යන වචනයට අදහසක් ගෙන දෙන වචනය ලියා  දක්වන්න.","answer":"අශුද්ධ යන්නට විරුද්ධ අර්ථයක් ඇති පදය ශුද්ධ වේ. "},{"question":"Inona no anarana nomen'ilay tantsambo portigay ,an'i Madagasikara tamin'ny nandalovany ny morontsiraka Avaratra-andrefana tamin'ny 10 Aogositra 1506?","answer":"Nosy Saint-Laurent no anarana nomen'ilay tantsambo portigay an'i Madagasikara tamin'ny nandalovany ny morontsiraka Avaratra -andrefana tamin'ny 10 Aogositra 1506."},{"question":"次の段落の内容を書き続けてください： 富山県射水市で、若い人たちが作る団体が「アグリスポーツ」という新しい運動を始めました。子どもたちが、農業の仕事と同じように動いて体を強くします。 アグリスポーツをする畑には、子どもや親など30人ぐらいが集まりました。陸上競技の専門家などに教えてもらいながら、高いところや低いところがある畑の中を走りました。そして、スコップなどを使って肥料を運んで、畑の中全部にまきました。","answer":"子どもたちは「肥料が重かったです」とか「走るのが楽しかったです」と話していました。 陸上競技の専門家は「走りやすいように平らにしたグラウンドでは、同じ筋肉だけ使います。農業の仕事では、体の全部の筋肉を使うので、体を強くするのにとても役に立ちます」と話していました。"},{"question":"ఈ క్రింది ప్రశ్నలకు జవాబులు రాయండి.ప్రశ్న : కింది పదార్థాలతో తయారయిన వస్తువులు ఒక్కోదానికి 5 చొప్పున రాయండి.ఎ) గాజు బి) లోహం సి) ప్లాస్టిక్ డి) చెక్క","answer":"ఎ) గాజు : గాజు గ్లాసు, చేపల తొట్టి, గాజు పాత్ర, అద్దము, టేబుల్ గ్లాస్బి) లోహం : కుర్చీ, బకెట్, సైకిల్, కారు, గడ్డపారసి) ప్లాస్టిక్ : . ప్లాస్టిక్ కుర్చీ, డ్బ న్, వాటర్ బాటిల్, ప్లాస్టిక్ స్పూన్, గిన్నెలుడి) చెక్క : కిటికీ, తలుపు, చెక్క బల్ల , డైనింగ్ టేబుల్, మంచం"},{"question":"معنى اشتعط باللهجة التعزية؟","answer":"معناها تمزق بالفصحى."},{"question":"Kuriais metais ir kokiuose šaltinuose pirmą kartą paminėtas, Lietuvos miesto Mažeikiai, pavadinimas? ","answer":"Mažeikių vardas pirmą kartą paminėtas XIII a. Yra žinoma, kad 1290 m. žemaičių žygio į Žiemgalą metu kalavijuočiai sumušė kunigaikščio Mažeikos kariuomenės būrį. Pasak Livonijos kronikos, 1332 m. Livonijos ordino magistro Everhardo vadovaujama kariuomenė „įvykdė karo žygį į netikėlių žemaičių kraštą ir pasiekė Mazeikia (Mažeikių) ir Windeikia (dab. Vindeikių) dvarus“. Remiantis tuo galima manyti, kad XIV a. minima karaliaus Mažeikos žemė yra davusi pavadinimą dabartiniam Mažeikių miestui, šį valdovą reikia laikyti Mažeikių įkūrėju, o 1290 m. yra Mažeikių įkūrimo data."},{"question":"「稜鱗(りょうりん)」とも呼ばれる、魚のアジの仲間に見られる、側線上にあるとげ状の硬いウロコのことを一般に何というでしょう？","answer":"ぜいご（ぜんご）"},{"question":"祖沖之的《綴術》在什麼時候被定為學校的課本？","answer":"《綴術》是中國南北朝時期的一部算經，匯集了祖沖之和祖暅之父子的數學研究成果。"},{"question":"Bu paragrafın devamını yazın:2 Ocak 2016'daki Swansea City maçında attığı skoru belirleyen golle maç 2-1 lehlerine sonuçlanırken bu golle birlikte Cole'u geride bırakarak Premier League'in, Law'u geride bırakarak ise Manchester United tarihinin en golcü ikinci ismi oldu. 9 Ocak'ta, Sheffield United ile oynanan ve 1-0 kazandıkları FA Cup üçüncü turu mücadelesinin duraklama dakikalarında penaltıdan kaydettiği golle takımına 1-0'lık galibiyeti getirdi. 12 Ocak'ta, 3-3 sona eren ligdeki Newscastle United deplasmanında teki penaltıdan olmak üzere iki gol kaydetti. Bir sonraki maç olan 17 Ocak'taki Liverpool deplasmanının tek golünü attı. Bu gol aynı zamanda Premier League'de Manchester United adına 176. golü olurken, Thierry Henry'yi geride bırakarak tek bir takım formasıyla Premier League'de en çok gol atan oyuncu oldu. 29 Ocak'ta, FA Cup'ın dördüncü turunda oynanan ve United'ın 1-3'lük galibiyetiyle sona eren Derby County maçının ilk golü Rooney'den geldi. 2 Şubat'taki Stoke City ile oynanan karşılaşmada skoru 3-0 olarak belirleyen golü attı. 13 Şubat'taki Sunderland maçında dizinden sakatlık yaşasa da oyundan çıkmayı reddetti ve maçı tamamladı; ancak bu sakatlık sebebiyle iki ay kadar sahalardan uzak kaldı. 16 Nisan'daki Aston Villa maçına ilk on birde başlayarak sakatlık sonrası ilk maçına çıktı. 17 Mayıs'ta, Bournemouth karşısında alınan 3-1'lik galibiyette takımının ilk golünü kaydetti. 21 Mayıs'ta, Sunderland ile oynanan 2016 FA Cup Finali","answer":"'nde takım kaptanı olarak sahaya çıktı ve maçın normal süresinin 1-1 berabere sona ermesi sebebiyle oynanan uzatma süresi de dahil olmak üzere 120 dakika sahada kaldı. Manchester United maçı 2-1 kazanırken, Rooney de kariyerindeki ilk FA Cup şampiyonluğunu elde etti. Sezon boyunca 41 resmî maça çıkan ve 15 gol kaydeden Rooney, 17 gollü Anthony Martial'ın ardından United adına sezonun en golcü ikinci oyuncusu oldu."},{"question":"Ολοκλήρωσε το κείμενο: Η Μαρία Έλενα Κυριάκου εκπροσώπησε την Ελλάδα στο διαγωνισμό τραγουδιού Eurovision","answer":"το 2015, με το τραγούδι \\"One Last Breath\\". Το τραγούδι προκρίθηκε στον τελικό, όπου και κατατάχθηκε στη 19η θέση με 23 βαθμούς."},{"question":"Πρόταση 1: Το Bentley Brook ή Bradbourne Brook είναι ένας μικρός παραπόταμος του ποταμού Dove στο Derbyshire της Αγγλίας και έχει μήκος 14,5 χιλιόμετρα (9 μίλια) Πρόταση 2: Η Bentley Brook ή Bradbourne Brook είναι ένας μικρός παραπόταμος του ποταμού Dove στο Derbyshire της Αγγλίας, που έχει μήκος 14,5 χιλιόμετρα. Ερώτηση: Η πρόταση 1 και η πρόταση 2 εκφράζουν το ίδιο νόημα; - Ναι ή όχι;","answer":"Ναι."},{"question":"Crie uma pergunta sobre o jogador de futebol Rogério Ceni.","answer":"Aqui está uma possível pergunta sobre o antigo jogador brasileiro de futebol, Rogério Ceni:\\"Em que clube Rogério Ceni passou a maior parte de sua carreira?\\""},{"question":"问题：铅笔刀的包装方式有哪些？","answer":"答案：铅笔刀的包装方式多样，可以是单独包装或与其他文具一起组合。"},{"question":"Yaya tsawon lokaci aka dauka don gina babbar ganuwa ta kasar Sin?","answer":"fiye da shekaru 2300 ad suka wuce."},{"question":"வினா: இரட்சண்ய யாத்திரிகம் எந்த நூலின் வழி நூலாகும்?","answer":"விடை: பில்கிரிம்ஸ் புரோகிரஸ் (ஆங்கிலம்)"},{"question":"Ahoana no hatao mba ho ampy rano lalandava? Manana vahaolana roa azo atao ianao:Vahaolana 1: Misotroa rano betsaka mandritra ny andro.Vahaolana 2: Mihazakazaka amin'ny lalan-davitra tsy misotro rano.","answer":"Ny vahaolana 1 dia mitombina kokoa. Mampiroborobo ny fahampiana rano araka ny tokony ho izy izany, fa ny mihakazaka amin'ny lalan-davitra tsy mitsotro rano  kosa dia miteraka tsy fahampiana rano amin'ny vatana."},{"question":"A cikin wanne nau'in ra'ayi za ku rarraba tweet mai zuwa? Mai kyau, Marar kyau, ko tsaka tsaki?@user Hmmm toh gamu ga yan iska 🚶🚶","answer":"Zan rarraba tweet ɗin da aka bayar a matsayin: Marar kyau"},{"question":"కింద ఇచ్చిన భావం వచ్చేలాగా పద్యం రాయండి:ఓ ధర్మరాజా! చెట్టుకొమ్మ చివర ఉన్న పక్షితలను స్పష్టంగా చూచావా అని అడుగగా, చక్కగా చూచానని అతడు చెప్పగా, మరల ద్రోణుడు ధర్మరాజుతో ఇట్లా అన్నాడు.","answer":"శే. వృక్షశాఖాగ్రమున నున్న పక్షిశిరముబెల్లముగఁ జూచితే మహీవల్లభుండ!”యనిన నిమ్ముగఁ జూచితి ననిన, వెండియును గురుఁడు ధర్మజున కిట్టు అనియెఁ బ్రీతి."},{"question":"من هو الذي أقام أول حفل بمناسبه عيد الغدير؟","answer":"الرسول (ص)."},{"question":"Inis som faoin pláinéad Mars. ","answer":"Is é Mars an ceathrú pláinéad ón ngrian sa ghrianchóras. Dearg an príomhdhath a aithníonn súil an duine ar Mhars, agus is minic a thugtar \\"an pláinéad dearg\\" air. Bheadh sé chomh maith againn \\"an pláinéad rua\\" a thabhairt air, áfach, nó is é rua na meirge atá i gceist dáiríre: tá dromchla Mharsa saibhir go maith in iarann. Tá uisce ar fáil ar Mhars, siúd is go bhfuil sé sioctha síos inniu. Ceist mhór í i gcónaí, an bhfuil, nó an raibh, aon chineál beatha ar Mhars riamh. An cineál arrachtaigh a d'fheicfeá ar leathanaigh na leabhar le H. G. Wells nó Edgar Rice Burroughs, is léir nach raibh siad ann riamh go bhfios dúinn, ach tá na saineolaithe i bhfad níos dóchasaí as beatha aoncheallach de chineál éigin, ar aon leibhéal le baictéir nó aiméibí, cuir i gcás."},{"question":"Jawab soalan yang rumit ini: Sistem pengendalian apakah yang digunakan dalam permainan video yang ditulis oleh Pedro Camacho?","answer":"Microsoft Windows dan Linux"},{"question":"১৯৫২ সালের ভাষা আন্দোলন বাঙালি জাতীয়তাবাদের বিকাশে যে ভূমিকা পালন করেছে তার প্রভাব ১৯৬৬ সালের ৬ দফা ও ১৯৭০ এর নির্বাচনে সবচেয়ে উল্লেখযোগ্য— এ ব্যাপারে তোমার মতামত দাও।","answer":"১৯৫২ সালের ভাষা আন্দোলন বাঙালি জাতীয়তাবাদের বিকাশে গুরুত্বপূর্ণ ভূমিকা পালন করে। আর ১৯৬৬ সালের ৬ দফা এবং ১৯৭০ এর নির্বাচনে এর প্রভাব ছিল সবচেয়ে বেশি।ভাষা আন্দোলন পাকিস্তান রাষ্ট্র গঠনের পর বাঙালির অধিকার আদায়ের প্রথম আন্দোলন। এ আন্দোলনের মাধ্যমেই পূর্ব পাকিস্তানের বাঙালিরা অসাম্প্রদায়িক জাতীয়তাবাদী চেতনায় উদ্বুদ্ধ হয়। এর প্রতিফলন আমরা ১৯৬৬ সালে বঙ্গবন্ধু শেখ মুজিবুর রহমান উত্থাপিত ছয় দফা দাবিতে দেখতে পাই। ছয় দফায় পূর্ব পাকিস্তানের জনগণের স্বায়ত্তশাসন অর্জনের লক্ষ্যে অর্থনৈতিক ও রাজনৈতিকসহ প্রধান দাবিগুলো তুলে ধরা হয়। এ দাবিগুলোই কালক্রমে বাঙালিকে স্বাধীনতার মন্ত্রে উজ্জীবিত করে। পাকিস্তান সরকার ছয় দফা দাবি উপেক্ষা করায় এ আন্দোলন তীব্র আকার ধারণ করে এবং ১৯৬৯ সালে গণঅভ্যুত্থানে রূপ নেয়। স্বৈরশাসক আইয়ুব খান পদত্যাগে বাধ্য হন। পরবর্তী শাসক ইয়াহিয়া খানও অব্যাহত চাপের মুখে পড়ে সাধারণ নির্বাচন অনুষ্ঠানের ঘোষণা দেন।১৯৭০ সালের নির্বাচন ছিল পাকিস্তান প্রতিষ্ঠার পর অনুষ্ঠিত প্রথম সাধারণ নির্বাচন। এ নির্বাচনে আওয়ামী লীগ কেন্দ্রীয় আইন পরিষদের ১৬৯টি আসনের মধ্যে ১৬৭টি আসন এবং প্রাদেশিক পরিষদে ৩০০টির মধ্যে ২৮৮টি আসন পেয়ে জয়লাভ করে। কিন্তু পাকিস্তান সরকার এই ফলাফল উপেক্ষা করে বাঙালির হাতে ক্ষমতা হস্তান্তর না করার ষড়যন্ত্র শুরু করে। পূর্ব পাকিস্তানের জনগণ বঙ্গবন্ধুর আহ্বানে পাকিস্তানি শাসকগোষ্ঠীর বিরুদ্ধে অসহযোগ আন্দোলনে নামে। এর পথ ধরেই আসে মুক্তিযুদ্ধ। পাকিস্তানি সেনাবাহিনীর সঙ্গে নয় মাসের রক্তক্ষয়ী লড়াইয়ের পর ১৯৭১ সালের ১৬ই ডিসেম্বর স্বাধীন বাংলাদেশ রাষ্ট্রের অভ্যুদয় ঘটে।উপরের আলোচনা থেকে তাই নিঃসন্দেহে বলা যায়, ভাষা আন্দোলন বাঙালি জাতীয়তাবাদের যে বিকাশ ঘটিয়েছিল ১৯৬৬ সালের ছয় দফা আন্দোলন এবং ১৯৭০ সালের নির্বাচনেই তার সবচেয়ে বড় বহিঃপ্রকাশ ঘটে।"},{"question":"\\"Алгандын бермейи бар\\" деген макалды түшүндүрүп берчи.","answer":"\\"Алгандын бермейи бар\\" деген макалды \\"бир нерсе алгандан кийин, бир нерсени кайтарып бериш керек\\" деп жөнөкөйлөштүрсө болот. Бул кимдир бирөөгө жакшылык, белек же пайда тийгенде ошого жараша ал адам бир нерсе кайтарып берет деп күтүлөт дегенди билдирет. Бул сөз мамиле курууда жана транзакцияларда кабыл алуу гана эмес, тең салмактуулукту жана калыстыкты сактоо менен кайра берүү керек деген коомдук норманы камтыйт. Бирок бул макал бир гана материалдык заттарга гана карата айтылган эмес. Адамдын ден-соолугу тубаса чың болгондугу, интеллекти тубаса жогору болгондугу берилген белек сыяктуу кабыл алынып, ошол кенчти өзүнүн жеке кызыкчылыгы гана үчүн эмес, курчап турган адамдарга карата кызмат же жардам аркылуу кайтарып берүү дагы күтүлөт дегенди билдирет."},{"question":"Nitori ọrọ buruku to sọ si Baba Adeboye, awọn pasitọ n binu si Buhari","answer":"Wẹrẹ bayii lọrọ ọhun bẹrẹ, nigba ti Baba Adeboye, olori ijọ Ridiimu, gba Aarẹ ilẹ wa, Muhammadu Buhari, nimọran lori atunto Naijiria, ṣugbọn tawọn ọmọ ẹyin ẹ kọlu baba naa, ti wọn si pe e ni ọta orilẹ-ede yii.Ọrọ ti wọn sọ yii lo bi Olori ijọ kan ti wọn n pe ni DayStar Christian Centre l’Ekoo, Sam Adeyẹmi, ninu. Ọkan lara awọn pasitọ ti wọn lorukọ nilẹ yii ni ni ọkunrin yii, o si ti bu ẹnu atẹ lu ọrọ buruku tawọn ọmọ ẹyin Buhari sọ si Baba Adeboye, bẹẹ lo sọ pe ki i ṣe ẹṣẹ rara ti eniyan ba sọ ero ọkan ẹ nipa orilẹ-ede ẹ fun ijọba.Ori ẹrọ ayelujara abẹyẹfo (twitter), ni Adeyẹmi gba ti sọ pe nigba wo lo di ki wọn maa dunkooko mọ araalu nitori ti wọn sọ ero ọkan wọn sita. O ni ẹtọ kaluku ni lati sọ ohun to yẹ fun ijọba nipa atunto orilẹ-ede yii. Ati pe niṣe ni olori gidi maa n tẹti lati gbọ ohun tawọn eeyan ẹ ba sọ, ki i ṣe idunkooko tabi ki wọn maa halẹ kiri.Bakan naa ni awọn iranṣẹ Ọlọrun mi-in, to fi mọ awọm ọmọ orileede yii ti n sọ pe ọrọ ti Garba sọ lorukọ Aarẹ ku diẹ kaato. Wọn ni lara ojuṣe iranṣẹ Ọlọrun ni lati tọ awọn aṣaaju wa sọna, ojuṣe yii ko yọ awọn ọmọ Naijiria paapaa silẹ, nitori awọn ni wọn yan wọn sipo, wọn si gbọdọ maa gbe amọran tabi akiyesi ti wọn ba fun wọn wo.Lana-an ni Ọgbẹni Garba Shehu, oluranlọwọ fun Aarẹ Muhammed Buhari lori eto iroyin bọ sita, ohun to si sọ ni pe ti a ba ri ẹnikan to ba n sọ nipa atunto Naijiria lasiko yii, ọta orilẹ-ede yii niru wọn. O sọ pe ko si ọrọ atunto kankan ninu iṣẹ to wa niwaju Muhammed Buhari, bẹẹ ni ko ni i ṣe e, wọn o baa pariwo ju bẹẹ lọ.Ohun to fa ibinu awọn eeyan ko ju pe, Baba Adeboye, olori ijọ Ridiimu, ṣẹṣẹ gba Muhammed Buhari niyanju ni, bi awọn eeyan si ṣe n ka iroyin ọhun lọwọ, ko pẹẹ ni Garba Shehu gbe tiẹ naa jade, ohun tawọn eeyan si n sọ ni pe dajudaju, Adeboye, Olori ijọ Ridiimu gan-an lawọn ọmọ Buhari n pe ni ọta ilu, wọn si mọ-ọn-mọ kan an labuku lori ọrọ to sọ ni."},{"question":"Por quem eram feitas missões religiosas com o objetivo de catequizar os povos indígenas no Brasil?","answer":"Pelos jesuítas."},{"question":"ਪੰਜਾਬ ਦੀਆਂ ਵਿਰਾਸਤੀ ਖੇਡਾਂ ਦੇ ਨਾਂ ਲਿਖੋ ।","answer":"ਲੂਣ-ਮਿਆਣੀ, ਬਾਂਦਰ-ਕਿੱਲਾ, ਭੰਡਾਭੰਡਾਰੀਆ, ਕੋਟਲਾ-ਛਪਾਕੀ, ਈਂਗਣ-ਮੀਂਗਣ, ਪਿੱਠੂ, ਗੁੱਲੀ-ਡੰਡਾ ਆਦਿ ਪੰਜਾਬ ਦੀਆਂ ਵਿਰਾਸਤੀ ਖੇਡਾਂ ਹਨ ।"},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'licin kerana minyak berminta, elok kerana kain berselang'?","answer":"Ia bermaksud sindiran untuk merendahkan seseorang yang angkuh atau sombong kerana harta atau barang yang dipinjam"},{"question":"வினா: இந்தியாவில் இரும்புப் பாலம் முதன் முதலில் எங்கு அமைக்கப்பட்டது?","answer":"விடை: லக்னோ"},{"question":"Là một học sinh cấp 2, hãy viết đoạn văn 200 chữ bàn về “Có ba cách để tự làm giàu mình: mỉm cười, cho đi và tha thứ”","answer":"Đã có khi nào bạn thử hỏi liệu cuộc sống của mình giàu có hay không? Và giàu có mà tôi muốn nói đến ở đây là giàu có về tinh thần. Có ý kiến cho rằng “Có ba cách để tự làm giàu mình: mỉm cười, cho đi và tha thứ” nhắn nhủ mỗi chúng ta về cách nuôi dưỡng tâm hồn. “Tự làm giàu mình” chính là tự nuôi dưỡng và bồi đắp nhân cách, tâm hồn bên trong. Và có ba cách để giúp ta làm việc đó: “mỉm cười” – biểu hiện của niềm vui, sự lạc quan, yêu đời; “cho đi” là biết quan tâm, chia sẻ với mọi người và “tha thứ” là khi ta bao dung, độ lượng với lỗi lầm của người khác. Tâm hồn con người sẽ trở nên trong sáng, giàu đẹp hơn nếu biết lạc quan, sống sẻ chia và rộng mở tấm lòng với mọi người. Ta vẫn quen với câu nói “Một nụ cười bằng mười thang thuốc bổ”.Lạc quan, yêu đời không chỉ giúp con người vượt lên khó khăn, thử thách mà còn tạo niềm tin về bản thân và giúp ta hướng đến khát vọng tốt đẹp. Và khi ta biết sẻ chia, quan tâm đến những người xung quanh là ta đã chiến thắng sự vô cảm, ích kỉ để sống giàu trách nhiệm và yêu thương hơn. Mang lại niềm vui cho người khác ta sẽ thấy thanh thản trong tâm hồn, được sự tin yêu, tôn trọng của mọi người và chắc chắn khi ta gặp khó khăn sẽ nhận được sự giúp đỡ của người khác. Và nếu muốn trút bỏ đau khổ, thù hận để sống thanh thản và mang lại niềm vui cho mọi người thì hãy bao dung, độ lượng hơn. Ngoài sự lạc quan, sẻ chia, độ lượng, con người còn có thể bồi đắp, nuôi dưỡng tâm hồn mình bang những ứng xử tốt đẹp. Hãy xem cách dân tộc Việt Nam tha thứ cho kẻ thù xâm lược để thấy được truyền thông nhân đạo, nhân ái của ông cha ta đáng khâm phục đến nhường nào. "},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਰਾਗੁ ਗਉੜੀ ੧੧ ॥ਆਸ ਪਾਸ ਘਨ ਤੁਰਸੀ ਕਾ ਬਿਰਵਾ ਮਾਝ ਬਨਾ ਰਸਿ ਗਾਊਂ ਰੇ ॥ਉਆ ਕਾ ਸਰੂਪੁ ਦੇਖਿ ਮੋਹੀ ਗੁਆਰਨਿ ਮੋ ਕਉ ਛੋਡਿ ਨ ਆਉ ਨ ਜਾਹੂ ਰੇ ॥੧॥ਤੋਹਿ ਚਰਨ ਮਨੁ ਲਾਗੋ ਸਾਰਿੰਗਧਰ ॥ਸੋ ਮਿਲੈ ਜੋ ਬਡਭਾਗੋ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਬਿੰਦ੍ਰਾਬਨ ਮਨ ਹਰਨ ਮਨੋਹਰ ਕ੍ਰਿਸਨ ਚਰਾਵਤ ਗਾਊ ਰੇ ॥ਜਾ ਕਾ ਠਾਕੁਰੁ ਤੁਹੀ ਸਾਰਿੰਗਧਰ ਮੋਹਿ ਕਬੀਰਾ ਨਾਊ ਰੇ ॥੨॥੨॥੧੫॥੬੬॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 338 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਭਗਤ ਕਬੀਰ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਵਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਸਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"(ਜਿਸ ਕ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਨ ਜੀ ਦੇ) ਆਸੇ ਪਾਸੇ ਤੁਲਸੀ ਦੇ ਸੰਘਣੇ ਬੂਟੇ ਸਨ (ਅਤੇ ਜੋ) ਤੁਲਸੀ ਦੇ ਜੰਗਲ ਵਿਚ ਪ੍ਰੇਮ ਨਾਲ ਗਾ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ ਉਸ ਦਾ ਦਰਸ਼ਨ ਕਰ ਕੇ (ਗੋਕਲ ਦੀ) ਗੁਆਲਣ ਮੋਹੀ ਗਈ (ਤੇ ਆਖਣ ਲੱਗੀ—) ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰੀਤਮ! ਮੈਨੂੰ ਛੱਡ ਕੇ ਕਿਸੇ ਹੋਰ ਥਾਂ ਨਾਹ ਆਈਂ ਜਾਈਂ ।੧।ਹੇ ਧਨੁਖਧਾਰੀ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! (ਜਿਵੇਂ ਉਹ ਗੁਆਲਣ ਕ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਨ ਜੀ ਤੋਂ ਵਾਰਨੇ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਸੀ ਤਿਵੇਂ ਮੇਰਾ ਭੀ) ਮਨ ਤੇਰੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਪ੍ਰੋਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਹੈਪਰ ਤੈਨੂੰ ਓਹੀ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈ ਜੋ ਵੱਡੇ ਭਾਗਾਂ ਵਾਲਾ ਹੋਵੇ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।ਹੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ! ਬਿੰਦ੍ਰਾਬਨ ਵਿਚ ਕ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਨ ਗਾਈਆਂ ਚਾਰਦਾ ਸੀ (ਤੇ ਉਹ ਗੋਕਲ ਦੀਆਂ ਗੁਆਲਣਾਂ ਦਾ) ਮਨ ਮੋਹਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਸੀ, ਮਨ ਨੂੰ ਧੂ੍ਰਹ ਪਾਣ ਵਾਲਾ ਸੀੇ ਤੇ ਹੇ ਧਨੁਖਧਾਰੀ ਸੱਜਣ! ਜਿਸ ਦਾ ਤੂੰ ਸਾਈਂ ਹੈਂ ਉਸ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਕਬੀਰ (ਜੁਲਾਹਾ) ਹੈ (ਭਾਵ, ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਦਾ ਮਨ ਕ੍ਰਿਸ਼ਨ ਜੀ ਨੇ ਬਿੰਦ੍ਰਾਬਨ ਵਿਚ ਗਾਈਆਂ ਚਾਰ ਕੇ ਮੋਹਿਆ ਸੀ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਲੋਕ ਗੋਕਲ ਦੀਆਂ ਗਰੀਬ ਗੁਆਲਣਾਂ ਆਖਦੇ ਹਨ । ਹੇ ਸਾਈਂ! ਮੇਰੇ ਤੇ ਤੂੰ ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰ, ਮੈਨੂੰ ਭੀ ਲੋਕ ਗਰੀਬ ਜੁਲਾਹਾ ਆਖਦੇ ਹਨ । ਤੂੰ ਗਰੀਬਾਂ ਉਤੇ ਜ਼ਰੂਰ ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈਂ) ।੨।੧੫।੬੬।\\""},{"question":"சுருக்கெழுத்தை கண்டுபிடித்தவர் யார்?","answer":"ஆங்கில எழுத்தாளரான சர் ஐசக் பிட்மேன் 1837 இல் ஒரு புதிய சுருக்கெழுத்து முறையை உருவாக்கினார், அது தற்போது பயன்படுத்தப்படுகிறது."},{"question":"Кандай жаңылмач билесиң ?","answer":"Белестеги беш кашка кой,Бешөө беш башка кой,Бешаласы кунан кой,Бешаласы дөнөн кой."},{"question":"බිම්බරක් යනු කොපමණද?","answer":"පෘථිවියේ එක්පසෙකට සෙනග හිටගත් විට අනෙක් පැත්ත උඩ යන තරම් ප්‍රමාණයක් , සේනාවක්, ඒ වගේ දස ගුණයක් සෙනග දසබිම්බරක් වේ .එකයි බිංදු 16 ක් වූ සංඛ්‍යාව ද බිම්බරක් ලෙස ද කිය වේ.මෙවැනිම සංඛ්‍යාවක් උම්මග්ග ජාතකයේ දැක්වේ, ඒ අටළොස් අක්ෂෞහිනියක් එය අර්ථ දක්වා තිබුණ තැනක ,හැට රියන් උණ ලී මිටි හැටක් මතින් සෙනගක් ගමන් ගත් කල්හි ඒ උණ මිටි සියල්ල දූවිලි මට්ටම ට කුඩු වෙන තරම් සිව්‍රරඟ සෙනගක් එක අක්ෂෞහිනියක් වේ ,ඒ වගේ 18 ගුණයක් ලෙස දක්වා තිබිණි ,මෙය ද ඇතුන්, අසුන් රථ , පාබල සෙනග නිශ්චිත සංඛ්‍යා වලින් දක්වා තිබෙනවා."},{"question":"கேள்வி:  தற்குறிப்பேற்ற அணியைச் சான்றுடன் விளக்குக.","answer":"பதில்: அணி விளக்கம்:இயல்பாக நிகழும் நிகழ்ச்சியின் மீது கவிஞர் தம் குறிப்பினை ஏற்றிக்கூறுவது தற்குறிப்பேற்ற அணி. எ.கா:அள்ளல் பழனத்து அரக்காம்பல் வாயவிழவெள்ளம் தீப் பட்ட(து) எனவெரீஇப்புன்ளினம்தம்கைச்சிறகால் பார்ப்பொடுக்கும் கவ்வை உடைத்தரோநச்சிலைவேல் கோக்கோதை நாடு.அணிப் பொருத்தம்:சேறுபட்ட, நீர்வளம் மிகுந்த வயல் பகுதிகளில், பொய்கைகளில் செவ்வாம்பல் மலர் விரிவது இயல்பான நிகழ்வு. இதைக் கண்ட நீர்ப்பறவைகள் வெள்ளத்தில் தீப்பிடித்து விட்டதாக எண்ணியதாக கவிஞர் தன் குறிப்பினை ஏற்றிக் கூறியதால் தற்குறிப்பேற்ற அணி ஆயிற்று.எடுத்துக்காட்டுகள்எ.கா.1:போருழந் தெடுத்த ஆரெயில் நெடுங்கொடிவாரல் என்பனபோல் மறித்துக் கைகாட்ட                                சிலப்பதிகாரம்விளக்கம்:கோவலனும் கண்ணகியும் மதுரை மாநகரத்திற்குள் நுழைய முற்படும்போது இயல்பாகக் காற்றிலாடும் தோரண வாயிற் கொடிகளைக் கவிஞர் தம் கற்பனையினால் கோவலன் மதுரையில் கொல்லப்படுவான் என்று முன்னமே அறிந்து வர வேண்டாம் என அக்கொடிகள் எச்சரிப்பதாகக் குறிப்பேற்றிக் கூறுவார்.எ.கா.2:தையல் துயர்க்குத் தறியா தம் சிறகால்கையால் வயிறலைத்து காரிருள் வெய்யோனைவாவு பரித் தேரேறி வாவென்றழைப்பது போல்கூவினவே கோழிக் குலம்.                                நளவெண்பாவிளக்கம்:நளன், தமயந்தியை நீங்கி, காட்டில் விட்டுச் சென்றான். அதிகாலையும் புலர, கோழிகளும் இயல்பாகக் கூவுகின்றன. இதைக் கண்ட புகழேந்தி, தமயந்தியின் தாங்கொணாத் துயர் கண்டே, கோழிகள் சூரியனை விரைவாக வரக் கதறுவதாகக் கூறுகிறார்.எ.கா.3:காதலியைக் காரிருளில் கானகத்தே கைவிட்டபாதகனைப் பார்க்கப் படாதேன்றோ - நாதம்அளிக்கின்ற ஆழிவாய் ஆங்கலவன் ஓடிஒளிக்கின்ற தென்னோ உரை.                                நளவெண்பாவிளக்கம்:நளன் கடலோரமாகச் செல்கின்றான். நண்டுகள்(\\"அலவன்\\") தம் வளையில் இருந்து வெளிப்பட்டு கடல் நாடிச் செல்கின்றன. இதைக் கண்ட புலவர், மனைவியைக் காட்டில் விட்டுச் சென்ற பாதகனைப் பார்க்கக் கூடாது என்றே நண்டுகள் வெளியேறிச் செல்கின்றன என்கிறார்."},{"question":"Ẹgbẹrun kan naira la ta ori awọn ọlọpaa mejeeji ta a gbe lọjọsi, aafaa kan n’Ilọrin lo fẹẹ fi wọn ṣoogun owo – Awọn afurasi ọdaran","answer":"Lẹyin ọsẹ mẹrin ti awọn ọmọ iṣọta ti dana sun ọlọpaa meji laduugbo Iwo Road, n’Ibadan, ti wọn si pin ẹran ara wọn jẹ bii ẹni jẹ suya laarin ara wọn, ọwọ awọn agbofinfro ti tun tẹ awọn ti wọn gbe koronfo agbari awọn ọlọpaa naa.Ọmọọdun mẹtadinlogun kan, Adewale Abiọdun ati Aliu Mubarak ti oun jẹ ẹni ọdun mẹrinlelogun ni wọn ṣiṣẹ ibi naa. Atawọn ati onịṣegun ibilẹ ti wọn ta a fun, Ọladipupọ Ifakorede, lawọn agbofinro jọ ṣa lọkọọkan nibi ti kaluku wọn fori pamọ si.Tẹ o ba gbagbe, l’Ọjọbọ, Tọsidee, ọjọ kejilelogun, oṣu kẹwaa, ọdun 2020 yii, lawọn ọmọ iṣọta dana sun awọn sajẹnti ọlọpaa meji kan, Ajibọla Adegoke ati Rotimi Ọladele, lasiko ti wọn n lọ sẹnu iṣẹ, wọn ni wọn fi mọto gba ọlọkada kan, iyẹn si ṣe bẹẹ jade laye.Ọga agba awọn ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Ọyọ, CP Joe Nwachukwu Enwonwu, ẹni to ṣafihan awọn afurasi ọdaran naa fawọn oniroyin lolu ileeṣẹ ọlọpaa ipinlẹ naa, fidi ẹ mulẹ pe lọjọ Abamẹta, Satide, ọjọ kẹẹẹdogun, oṣu kọkanla, ọdun 2020 yii, lọwọ awọn ọtẹlẹmuyẹ ọlọpaa ba awọn olubi eeyan naa.Ninu ifọrọwerọ ti awọn oniroyin ṣe pẹlu ẹ, eyi to n jẹ Abiọdun ninu awọn afurasi ọdaran yii sọ pe ọtọ nibi ti awọn n lọ lọjọ naa, iyẹn ọjọ Aje, Mọnde, ọjọ kejilelogun, oṣu kẹwaa, ọdun 2020, ti awọn fi ri i ti wọn n kun ẹran eeyan bii ẹni kun adiẹ, ti Murarak si sọ pe ki awọn lọọ gbe ori awọn oku eeyan naa.O ṣalaye pe “Nigba ta a de Iwo Road, a ri i pe gbogbo ọna ti di pa. Wọn dana soju titi. Awa naa sun mọ ibẹ lati mọ nnkan to n ṣẹlẹ, a waa ri i pe awọn eeyan meji kan ni wọn dana sun, wọn lọlọpaa lawọn mejeeji.“A ri i ti wọn n fi igi lu oku awọn ọlọpaa yẹn, bẹẹ ni wọn tun fa ẹya ara wọn yọ lọkọọkan, ti kaluku si n mu eyi to ba fẹ nibẹ.“Mubarak sọ pe oun naa fẹẹ lọọ mu diẹ ninu awọn ẹya ara yẹn. mo ni ki lo fẹẹ fi wọn ṣe, o loun mọ oniṣegun kan ti oun maa ta wọn fun. Bo ṣe gbe ori awọn ọlọpaa mejeeji niyẹn.“Oniṣegun kan (Ifakorede) ta a jọ n gbe adugbo la lọọ fun. Ẹgbẹrun kan Naira (N1,000) lo ra a, o ni ki i ṣoun loun fẹẹ lo o,  aafaa kan n’Ilọrin loun fẹẹ lọọ ko wọn fun, oun lo mọ bo ṣe n lo wọn fun oogun owo.“Apo meji aabọ (N500) ni wọn fun wa ninu owo yẹn. lẹsẹkẹsẹ lemi ati Mubarak ti lọọ fii jẹun. Ni nnkan bii aago mẹjọ alẹ ọjọ yẹn ni mo pada ri oniṣegun yẹn to fun mi ni apo meji aabọ yooku ti emi ati Mubarak si jọ pin in ni túú túú fifitì (N250)”.Alaye ti Mubarak naa ṣe ko yatọ si ti ọrẹ ẹ, o ni oun loun dabaa pe ki awọn ko ori awọn ọlọpaa ti awọn eeyan dana sun laduugbo Iwo Road ọhun nitori oun mọ pe owo ni kinni naa yoo yọ fawọn.Gẹgẹ bo ṣe sọ, “Mo wa ọra poli baagi kan, mo ko ori mejeeji si. A si gbe wọn lọ sile. Nigba to di aago marun-un irọlẹ la lọọ gbe e fun Ifakorede.“Oju ọna la ti pade ẹ, a waa sọ fun un pe a ni eegun agbari awọn ọlọpaa meji kan ta a fẹẹ ta fun wọn, o waa ni a ko gbọdọ sọ fẹnikankan o. O si fun wa ni apo meji aabọ ninu ẹgbẹrun kan Naira to sọ pe oun maa ra ori mejeeji. Lẹyin naa lo fun Abiọdun niyooku, ta a si jọ pin in dọgbandọgba.”Ifakorede, oniṣegun ibilẹ ti wọn ta awọn eegun agbari ọlọpaa mejeeji fun naa jẹwọ pe oun ni wọn taja okunkun ọhun fun loootọ, ati pe ẹgbẹrun mẹta Naira ni wọn da le awọn agbari naa ki oun too sọ oju abẹ nikoo pe oun ko le san ju ẹgbẹrun kan Naira lọ.Iwadii ṣi n tẹsiwaju lati ri awọn yooku ti wọn lọwọ ninu ọran naa mu gẹgẹ bi ọga agba awọn ọlọpaa ipinlẹ Ọyọ, CP Joe Nwachukwu Enwonwu ṣe fidi ẹ mulẹ."},{"question":"Awọn to n fẹhonu han nitori SARS ba mọto Igbakeji gomina Ogun jẹ","answer":"Ọlọrun nikan lo mọ ohun ti yoo gbẹyin ifẹhonu han awọn ti wọn fẹ kijọba fagi le SARS, pẹlu bawọn kan ninu wọn ṣe ba mọto Igbakeji gomina ipinlẹ Ogun, Onimọ-ẹrọ Nọimọt Salakọ, jẹ, ti wọn tun ṣe ọlọpaa kan leṣe laafin Olowu, l’Abẹokuta, lọjọ Abamẹta, Satide to kọja yii.Ayẹyẹ ọdun ọmọ Olowu tọdun yii lo n waye lọwọ laafin Olowu, Ọba Adegboyega Dosunmu, Oloye Oluṣẹgun Ọbasanjọ toun naa jẹ ọmọ Owu wa nibẹ pẹlu awọn alejo pataki, lara wọn si ni Igbakeji gomina, Onimọ-ẹrọ Nọimọt Salakọ.Inu ile ti wọn ti n ṣọdun naa ni awọn alejo pataki yii wa ti wahala fi ṣẹlẹ nita, awọn kan ti wọn n pariwo pe kijọba fopin si SARS ni wọn gbe iwọde naa de Aafin Olowu, ni wọn ba fẹẹ fagidi wọle, wọn ni Ọbasanjọ lawọn fẹẹ ba sọrọ lori SARS. Ọbasanjọ ba wọn sọrọ alaafia, ṣugbọn ko wọn wọn leti.Awọn ọlọpaa to wa lẹnu ọna ko fẹẹ ba wọn ja gẹgẹ ba a ṣe gbọ, ṣugbọn niṣe lawọn afẹhonu han naa bẹrẹ si i ba awọn nnkan jẹ, paapaa ju lọ mọto ti wọn paaki kalẹ, nibẹ ni wọn si ti kọlu mọto Igbakeji gomina yii, ti wọn fọ gilaasi ẹyin rẹ.Yatọ si eyi, awọn afẹhonu han naa tun fiya jẹ ọkan lara awọn ọlọpaa to wa nibẹ, nigba tawọn ọlọpaa yoo si fi bẹrẹ si i yinbọn soke lati le wọn lọ, wahala naa ti fẹju toto.Ọwọ pada ba mẹta ninu awọn to fa wahala naa. Ọlọpaa ti wọn ṣe leṣe ti n gba itọju nileewosan.Ṣe laaarọ kutu ọjọ Abamẹta naa lawọn kan ti kọkọ kora wọn jọ, ti wọn n wọde kiri nipa ọrọ SARS yii, koda, aṣọ oogun bii tawọn ologun ibilẹ ni awọn mi-in wọ ninu wọn. Panṣẹkẹ ni wọn ti bẹrẹ, wọn de Isalẹ-Igbẹhin, Ake atawọn adugbo mi-in l’Abẹokuta, ti wọn n pariwo ‘ENDSARS’ iyẹn ni pe kijọba apapọ pa SARS rẹ"},{"question":"Hoàn thiện đoạn văn sau: Trước đó, trong Tuyên bố chung về nâng cấp quan hệ Việt - Mỹ lên Đối tác chiến lược toàn diện, Tổng bí thư Nguyễn Phú Trọng và Tổng thống Joe Biden nhất trí tạo điều kiện thuận lợi và mở cửa thị trường hơn nữa cho hàng hóa, ","answer":"dịch vụ của mỗi nước, cùng nhau giải quyết các vấn đề như rào cản tiếp cận thị trường thông qua Hiệp định Khung về Thương mại và Đầu tư.Hai lãnh đạo ủng hộ việc tiếp tục củng cố hệ thống thương mại đa phương không phân biệt đối xử và dựa trên luật lệ, trong đó Tổ chức Thương mại Thế giới (WTO) đóng vai trò nòng cốt."},{"question":"Mayroong 15 spelling na salita sa pagsusulit. Ang unang mag-aaral ay nabaybay nang tama ng 9 na salita. Wastong nabaybay ni Miguel ang 8 salita. Ilang salita ang maling nabaybay ni Miguel?","answer":"8 na salita"},{"question":"ෆින්ලන්තයේ අගනුවර කුමක්ද?","answer":"ෆින්ලන්තයේ අගනුවර හෙල්සින්කි නුවරයයි."},{"question":"வினா:  பாரதியாரின் சிறப்பு பெயர் என்ன?","answer":"விடை: சுப்பையா "},{"question":"வினா  :   நூலகம், நூல்கள் ஆகியன குறித்து அண்ணாவின் வானொலி உரையில் வெளிப்படுகின்ற கருத்துகளை  தொகுத்து எழுதுக . ","answer":"விடை : முன்னுரை:மனிதனின் சிந்தனையைத் தூண்டுவது நூல்களே. இசையைப் போல மனதைப் பண்படுத்துவதும் நூல்களே எனில் மிகையாகாது. “வீட்டிற்கோர் புத்தகசாலை” என்னும் அண்ணாவின் வானொலி உரை மூலம், நூலகம், நூல்கள் குறித்து வெளிப்படும் கருத்துகள் குறித்து பார்ப்போம்.அறிஞர்  அண்ணா  சிறு அறிமுகம் : அண்ணாதுரை, சின்னகாஞ்சீபுரத்தில் வரகுவாசல் கைத்தறி நெசவாளர் நடராசன் முதலியார் - பங்காரு அம்மாள் என்பவருக்கு மகனாக  ஆவணித்திங்கள் 31ஆம் நாள் (1909 - செப்டம்பர் 15) பிறந்தார்.  சென்னை பச்சையப்பன் உயர் நிலைப் பள்ளியிலும், பின்னர் பச்சையப்பன் கல்லூரியிலும் கல்விக் கற்றார்.ஓர் இந்திய அரசியல்வாதியும், மதராஸ் மாநிலத்தின் கடைசி முதல்வரும், தமிழகத்தின் முதலாவது முதலமைச்சருமாவார். இவர் அறிஞர் அண்ணா எனவும் பேரறிஞர் அண்ணா எனவும் அழைக்கப்படுகிறார். இவர் இந்தியா குடியரசான பிறகு, ஆட்சி அமைத்த காங்கிரசல்லாத முதலாவது திராவிடக்கட்சித் தலைவரும், அறுதிப் பெரும்பான்மையுடன் ஆட்சி அமைத்தவரும் ஆவார்.  தமிழிலும் ஆங்கிலத்திலும் சிறப்பாகச் சொற்பொழிவாற்றவும் எழுதவும் வல்லவர்.இவர் பல முற்போக்கு, சீர்திருத்த நாடகங்களையும் எழுதியிருக்கிறார். அவற்றுள் சிலவற்றை இயக்கி இருக்கிறார்; சிலவற்றுள் நடித்திருக்கிறார். தமிழ்த் திரைப்படங்களுக்கு கதை, வசனம் எழுதியவரும் தன்னுடைய திராவிட சீர்திருத்தக் கருத்துக்களை அதன் மூலம் முதன்முதலாக பரப்பியவரும் இவரே.    நூலகம்:ஒரு நாட்டின் நிலை, உலக நிலைக்கேற்ப வளரவேண்டும் எனில் வீட்டு நிலை மாற வேண்டும். வீட்டிற்கோர் புத்தகசாலை [நூலகம்] வேண்டும். ஒரு நாட்டை உலகம் மதிப்பது அந்நாட்டு மக்களின் மனவளத்தைக் கண்டே ஆகும். நல்ல மனவளம் தருவது நூலகமே .“வீட்டிற்கோர் புத்தகசாலை” என்ற இலக்கினை நடைமுறைப்படுத்தினால் நமது சந்ததி நல்ல மனவளம் பெறுவர். நாடும் நலமும் வளமும் பெறும்.வீட்டில் அலங்காரப் பொருட்களுக்கு போகப் பொருள்களுக்கு முக்கியத்துவம் தரும் நிலை மாறவேண்டும். ஒவ்வொரு வீடுகளிலும் புத்தகசாலைக்கு இடம் தரப்பட வேண்டும். உணவும் உடையும் எவ்வாறு அடிப்படைத் தேவையோ அதைப் போலவே, நூலகமும் அடிப்படைத் தேவையாகும்.நூல்கள் :நாட்டை அறிய, உலகை அறிய, ஏன் ஒருவன் தன்னை அறிய ஏடுகள் (நூல்) வேண்டும். நிபுணத்துவம் தரும் ஏடுகள்தான் என்பதன்று, அடிப்படை அறிவை, உண்மையை உணர்த்தும் நூ ல்களையாவது கற்க முனையுங்கள்.பூகோள, சரித ஏடுகள் இருத்தல் வேண்டும். வீட்டிற்கோர் “திருக்குறள்” கட்டாயம் வேண்டும்.சங்க இலக்கியங்களின் சாரத்தைத் தீட்டித்தரும் நூல்களும் இருக்க வேண்டும். கற்க வேண்டும்.விஞ்ஞானக் கண்டுபிடிப்புகளைப் பற்றிய முக்கியமான தரவுகளைத் தரும் நூல்கள் படித்திடல் வேண்டும்.• நாட்டு விடுதலைக்கு உழைத்தவர்கள்• மக்களின் மனமாசு துடைத்தவர்கள்• தொலைதேசங்களைக் கண்டவர்கள்• வீரர்கள், விவேகிகள் வாழ்க்கைஆகிய நூல்கள் இருத்தல் வேண்டும் என்கிறார் பேரறிஞர் அண்ணா .முடிவுரை :கேட்டினை நீக்கிட வீட்டிலே புத்தகசாலை அமைப்போம்.“புனிதமுற்று மக்கள் புதுவாழ்வு வேண்டில்புத்தகசாலை வேண்டும் நாட்டில் யாண்டும்”என்ற பாவேந்தர் கூற்றுப்படி புத்தகசாலை அமைப்போம், புத்தகம் வாசித்துப் புதுவாழ்வு பெறுவோம்."},{"question":"如何清洗和保养乐高？","answer":"答：乐高积木可以用温水和中性肥皂清洗，但不建议用洗碗机或洗衣机清洗。清洗后，应将积木放在通风的地方自然干燥。为了保持积木的颜色和质地，不建议将它们暴露在阳光下过长时间。"},{"question":"Бул жомоктун уландысын жазып берчи: \\"Болбосо, колуң менен көмүп кеткин, Кыйналып өлүгүмө таппа кепин…\\"","answer":"Бул жомоктун уландысы мындай болушу мүмкүн: \\"Сен кетсең, кайрылышар теңиңди тап.  -Көрбөй кет куурал тарткан элдин четин.\\""},{"question":"Кошмо Штаттардын кызмат учурунда өлтүрүлгөн акыркы президенти ким болгон? ","answer":"Жон Кеннеди"},{"question":"Quem descobriu a existência da gravidade?","answer":"Isaac Newton."},{"question":"ਸ਼ੇਖ ਚਿੱਲੀ ਦੀ ਕਹਾਣੀ-ਤਰਬੂਜ ਚੋਰ","answer":"ਸ਼ੇਖ ਚਿੱਲੀ ਸੌਂ ਨਹੀਂ ਸਕਿਆ.ਫਾਤਿਮਾ ਬੀਬੀ ਨੇ ਉਸ ਸ਼ਾਮ ਸ਼ੇਖ ਦੀ ਮਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਤਰਬੂਜ਼ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਸੀ ਜੋ ਉਹ ਅਚਾਨਕ ਘਰ ਲਿਆਉਣਾ ਭੁੱਲ ਗਿਆ ਸੀ। ਸ਼ੇਖ ਸਿਰਫ ਉਸੇ ਤਰਬੂਜ ਬਾਰੇ ਸੋਚਦਾ ਰਿਹਾ.ਪਿਛਲੇ ਹਫ਼ਤੇ ਦੌਰਾਨ ਅੰਮੀ ਆਪਣੀ ਵੱਡੀ ਧੀ ਦੇ ਵਿਆਹ ਦੀ ਤਿਆਰੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਹਾਇਤਾ ਲਈ ਫਾਤਿਮਾ ਬੀਬੀ ਨੂੰ ਹਰ ਰੋਜ਼ ਕਈ ਘੰਟੇ ਮਿਲਣ ਆਉਂਦੀ ਸੀ ਅਤੇ ਹਰ ਸ਼ਾਮ ਅੰਮੀ ਫਾਤਿਮਾ ਬੀਬੀ ਦੁਆਰਾ ਸ਼ੇਖ ਨੂੰ ਦਿੱਤੀਆਂ ਚੀਜ਼ਾਂ ਲਿਆਉਂਦੀ ਸੀ.ਪਹਿਲੇ ਦਿਨ ਉਹ ਰਸੀਲੇ ਗੁਲਾਬ ਜਾਮੁਨ ਲੈ ਕੇ ਆਈ ਸੀ। ਉਸ ਤੋਂ ਬਾਅਦ ਖੀਰ ਅਤੇ ਫਿਰ ਕੇਲੇ.ਅੱਜ ਅੰਮੀ ਨੂੰ ਇੱਕ ਵੱਡਾ ਤਰਬੂਜ਼ ਮਿਲਿਆ.ਸ਼ੇਖ ਦੇ ਮੂੰਹ ਵਿੱਚ ਤਰਬੂਜ ਦੇ ਬਾਰੇ ਸੋਚਦੇ ਹੀ ਪਾਣੀ ਆਉਣ ਲੱਗ ਪਿਆ !  ਅੰਮੀ ਨੂੰ ਤਰਬੂਜ ਦਾ ਭਾਰ ਬਹੁਤ ਭਾਰੀ ਲੱਗਿਆ, ਇਸ ਲਈ ਉਸਨੇ ਇਸਨੂੰ ਫਾਤਿਮਾ ਬੀਬੀ ਦੇ ਘਰ ਦੇ ਵਿਹੜੇ ਵਿੱਚ ਛੱਡ ਦਿੱਤਾ। ਸ਼ੇਖ ਸਵੇਰੇ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਸੀ ਅਤੇ ਤਰਬੂਜ ਲਿਆ ਸਕਦਾ ਸੀ। ਪਰ ਉਹ ਸਿਰਫ ਤਰਬੂਜ ਖਾਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਸੀ। ਹੁਣ! ਤੁਰੰਤ! ਉਸ ਦਾ ਭੁੱਖਾ ਢਿੱਡ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੁਕਮ ਦੇ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ।ਸ਼ੇਖ ਉੱਠਿਆ। ਅੰਮੀ ਹੁਣੇ ਹੀ ਸੁੱਤੀ ਪਈ ਸੀ। ਉਹ ਰਾਤ ਦੇ ਹਨੇਰੇ ਵਿੱਚ ਅਤੇ ਪਿੰਡ ਦੀਆਂ ਸੁੰਨਸਾਨ ਗਲੀਆਂ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਚੁੱਪਚਾਪ ਫਾਤਿਮਾ ਬੀਬੀ ਦੇ ਘਰ ਵੱਲ ਤੁਰਨ ਲੱਗ ਪਿਆ। ਜਿਵੇਂ ਹੀ ਉਸਨੇ ਵਿਹੜੇ ਦੀ ਚਾਰਦੀਵਾਰੀ ਤੋਂ ਛਾਲ ਮਾਰੀ, ਉਸਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਤਰਬੂਜ ਨੂੰ ਉਸਦੇ ਸਾਹਮਣੇ ਪਿਆ ਵੇਖਿਆ। ਤਰਬੂਜ਼ ਕੋਲੇ ਦੇ ਦੇ ਉੱਪਰ ਪਿਆ ਸੀ। ਉਹ ਤਰਬੂਜ਼ ਚੁੱਕ ਕੇ ਤੁਰਨ ਹੀ ਵਾਲਾ ਸੀ ਕਿ ਉਸ ਨੇ ਘਰ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰੋਂ ਕੁਝ ਆਵਾਜ਼ਾਂ ਸੁਣੀਆਂ। ਉੱਥੇ ਕੌਣ ਹੋ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ ? ਘਰ ਖਾਲੀ ਸੀ। ਸਾਰਾ ਪਰਿਵਾਰ ਨੇੜਲੇ ਪਿੰਡ ਰਿਸ਼ਤੇਦਾਰੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਗਿਆ ਸੀ। ਕੀ ਉਹ ਸਾਰੇ ਜਲਦੀ ਵਾਪਸ ਆ ਗਏ? ਫਿਰ ਉਸਦੇ ਘਰ ਦੇ ਬਾਹਰ ਤਾਲਾ ਕਿਉਂ ਸੀ ? ਸ਼ੇਖ ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਸਾਰੀਆਂ ਗੱਲਾਂ ਬਾਰੇ ਸੋਚ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ ਜਦੋਂ ਉਸਨੇ ਕੁਝ ਪੈਰਾਂ ਦੀ ਆਵਾਜ਼ ਉਸਦੇ ਵੱਲ ਆਉਣ ਦੀ ਆਵਾਜ਼ ਸੁਣੀ। \\"ਹੈਲੋ ਰਾਮ\\" ਦੇ ਰੋਣ ਦੀ ਆਵਾਜ਼ ਆਈ.ਉਹ ਅਵਾਜ਼ ਲੱਲਨ ਦੀ ਸੀ। ਸ਼ੇਖ ਨੂੰ ਉਸਨੂੰ ਪਛਾਣਨ ਵਿੱਚ ਕੋਈ ਸਮੱਸਿਆ ਨਹੀਂ ਸੀ। “ਮੈਂ ਉਸ ਮੂਰਖ ਸ਼ੇਖ ਚਿੱਲੀ ਨੂੰ ਮਾਰ ਦਿਆਂਗਾ! ਇਹ ਉਸਦੇ ਕਾਰਨ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਮੇਰੇ ਪਿਤਾ ਨੇ ਮੈਨੂੰ ਇੰਨੀ ਬੁਰੀ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਮਾਰਿਆ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਮੇਰੀਆਂ ਹੱਡੀਆਂ ਦੁਖਦੀਆਂ ਹਨ! ਅਤੇ ਹੁਣ ਖਿੜਕੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਦਾਖਲ ਹੋਏ ਟੁੱਟੇ ਸ਼ੀਸ਼ੇ ਦੁਆਰਾ ਮੇਰਾ ਹੱਥ ਕੱਟ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ. ''\\"ਹੁਣ ਤੁਸੀਂ ਵੀ ਕੁਰਲਾਉਣਾ ਬੰਦ ਕਰੋ!\\" ਇੱਕ ਦਬਵੀਂ ਆਵਾਜ਼ ਆਈ. ਸ਼ੇਖ ਇਸ ਅਵਾਜ਼ ਨੂੰ ਪਛਾਣ ਨਹੀਂ ਸਕਿਆ। ਜਿਵੇਂ ਹੀ ਦੋ ਆਦਮੀ ਪ੍ਰਗਟ ਹੋਏ ਸ਼ੇਖ ਕੋਲੇ ਦੇ ਬੋਰੇ ਦੇ ਪਿੱਛੇ ਲੁਕ ਗਏ। ਉਹ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਕੋਇਲੇ ਦੀਆਂ ਬੋਰੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਵਿਚਕਾਰ ਚੀਰ ਕੇ ਵੇਖਦਾ ਰਿਹਾ। ਲੱਲਨ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਇੱਕ ਮੰਦੇ ਇਰਾਦੇ ਵਾਲਾ ਅਜਨਬੀ ਵੀ ਸੀ ਜਿਸਨੂੰ ਸ਼ੇਖ ਨੇ ਬਾਜ਼ਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਘੁੰਮਦੇ ਵੇਖਿਆ ਸੀ। ਲੱਲਨ ਬੈਗ ਵਿੱਚ ਕੁਝ ਲੈ ਕੇ ਜਾ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ।'ਜਲਦੀ ਕਰੋ, ਅਜਨਬੀ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ, “ਆਓ ਜਲਦੀ ਮਾਲ ਵੰਡ ਦੇਈਏ। ''ਜਦੋਂ ਅਜਨਬੀ ਬੋਰੀ ਦੇ ਸਾਹਮਣੇ ਆਪਣੀ ਪਿੱਠ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਬੈਠ ਗਿਆ, ਤਾਂ ਗਰੀਬ ਸ਼ੇਖ ਬਹੁਤ ਡਰਾਇਆ ਹੋਇਆ ਸੀ। ਅਜਨਬੀ ਨੇ ਲੱਲਨ ਤੋਂ ਬੈਗ ਖੋਹ ਲਿਆ ਅਤੇ ਇਸਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਸਾਰਾ ਸਮਾਨ ਜ਼ਮੀਨ ਤੇ ਡੋਲ੍ਹ ਦਿੱਤਾ। ਸੋਨੇ ਅਤੇ ਚਾਂਦੀ ਦੀਆਂ ਚੂੜੀਆਂ, ਚਾਂਦੀ ਦੇ ਗਲਾਸ ਅਤੇ ਸੋਨੇ ਦੇ ਸਿੱਕਿਆਂ ਦੇ ਹਾਰ ਚਾਨਣੀ ਰੌਸ਼ਨੀ ਵਿੱਚ ਚਮਕਣ ਲੱਗੇ। ਸ਼ੇਖ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਸਾਰੇ ਗਹਿਣਿਆਂ ਨੂੰ ਵੇਖਦਾ ਰਿਹਾ। ਉਹ ਜਾਣਦਾ ਸੀ ਕਿ ਫਾਤਿਮਾ ਬੀਬੀ ਨੇ ਉਸਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੀ ਧੀ ਦੇ ਵਿਆਹ ਲਈ ਇਕੱਠਾ ਕੀਤਾ ਸੀ। ਅੰਮੀ ਨੇ ਸ਼ੇਖ ਨੂੰ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਹਰ ਇੱਕ ਬਾਰੇ ਦੱਸਿਆ ਅਤੇ ਹੁਣ ਇਹ ਦੋ ਆਦਮੀ ਉਹ ਗਹਿਣੇ ਚੋਰੀ ਕਰ ਰਹੇ ਸਨ! “ਤੁਸੀਂ ਅੱਧੇ ਤੋਂ ਵੱਧ ਲਿਆ ਹੈ!” ਲੱਲਨ ਨੇ ਕਮਜ਼ੋਰ ਆਵਾਜ਼ ਵਿੱਚ ਵਿਰੋਧ ਕੀਤਾ। ਉਸ ਤੋਂ ਬਾਅਦ ਅਜਨਬੀ ਨੇ ਲੁੱਟ ਦਾ ਥੋੜਾ ਹੋਰ ਹਿੱਸਾ ਉਸ ਦੇ ਹਵਾਲੇ ਕਰ ਦਿੱਤਾ। “ਤੁਸੀਂ ਖੁਸ਼ਕਿਸਮਤ ਹੋ ਕਿ ਤੁਸੀਂ ਇੰਨਾ ਜ਼ਿਆਦਾ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਕਰ ਰਹੇ ਹੋ!” ਅਜਨਬੀ ਨੇ ਕੁਰਲਾਇਆ, \\"ਮੇਰੇ ਬਗੈਰ ਤੁਸੀਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਘਰ ਨੂੰ ਚੋਰੀ ਕਰਨ ਦੀ ਹਿੰਮਤ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰਦੇ! ''“ਇਹ ਘਰ ਭੂਤ -ਪ੍ਰੇਤ ਹੈ,” ਲੱਲਨ ਨੇ ਬੇਚੈਨੀ ਨਾਲ ਇਧਰ -ਉਧਰ ਵੇਖਦਿਆਂ ਕਿਹਾ। ਕੁਝ ਲੋਕ ਅਜੇ ਵੀ ਇਸ ਘਰ ਨੂੰ ਭੂਤ ਸਮਝਦੇ ਹਨ। \\"ਫਿਰ ਚਲੋ ਇੱਥੋਂ ਚਲੇ ਜਾਉ ਇਸ ਤੋਂ ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਕਿ ਭੂਤ ਸਾਨੂੰ ਫੜ ਲਵੇ!\\" ਅਜਨਬੀ ਹੱਸ ਪਿਆ। ਉਸਦੇ ਹਾਸੇ ਵਿੱਚ ਚਤੁਰਾਈ ਸੀ। “ਜੇ ਤੁਸੀਂ ਕੁਝ ਹੋਰ ਲੁੱਟਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦੇ ਹੋ, ਤਾਂ ਉਹ ਤਰਬੂਜ ਆਪਣੇ ਨਾਲ ਲੈ ਜਾਓ!ਅਜਨਬੀ ਨੇ ਬੈਗ ਵਿੱਚ ਸੋਨੇ ਅਤੇ ਚਾਂਦੀ ਦੇ ਤਿੰਨ ਚੌਥਾਈ ਹਿੱਸੇ ਭਰੇ। ਉਹ ਆਪਣੀਆਂ ਜੇਬਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਬਾਕੀ ਚੀਜ਼ਾਂ ਭਰਦੇ ਹੋਏ ਕੁਝ ਗੜਬੜ ਕਰ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ। ਲੱਲਨ ਨੇ ਖੜ੍ਹਾ ਹੋ ਕੇ ਤਰਬੂਜ਼ ਚੁੱਕਣ ਦੀ ਕੋਸ਼ਿਸ਼ ਕੀਤੀ। ਪਰ ਸ਼ੇਖ ਚਿੱਲੀ ਪਿੱਛੇ ਤੋਂ ਖੜ੍ਹਾ ਸੀ ਅਤੇ ਆਪਣੀ ਪੂਰੀ ਤਾਕਤ ਨਾਲ ਤਰਬੂਜ ਨੂੰ ਫੜ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ ! ਜਿਵੇਂ ਹੀ ਸ਼ੇਖ ਦੀਆਂ ਉਂਗਲਾਂ ਲੱਲਨ ਦੀਆਂ ਉਂਗਲਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਟਕਰਾ ਗਈਆਂ, ਲੱਲਨ ਨੂੰ ਉਸਦੀ ਜ਼ਿੰਦਗੀ ਦਾ ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਵੱਡਾ ਝਟਕਾ ਲੱਗਾ !ਭੂਤ! ”ਉਸਨੇ ਬੁੜਬੁੜਾਇਆ \\"ਜ਼ਮੀਨ .. ਭੂਤ !ਸ਼ੇਖ ਤਰਬੂਜ ਨੂੰ ਬੋਰੀ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਕੱਸ ਕੇ ਰੱਖਦਾ ਰਿਹਾ. ਦੋ ਕੋਲੇ ਅਚਾਨਕ ਪਲਟ ਗਏ ਅਤੇ ਲੱਲਨ ਅਤੇ ਅਜਨਬੀ ਉੱਤੇ ਡਿੱਗ ਪਏ। ਹੁਣ ਲੱਲਨ ਨੇ ਸਾਰੀ ਸਾਵਧਾਨੀ ਇੱਕ ਪਾਸੇ ਰੱਖ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਹੈ। \\"ਭੂਤ?\\" ਉਸਨੇ ਉੱਚੀ ਆਵਾਜ਼ ਵਿੱਚ ਚੀਕਿਆ। “ਭੂਤ!” ਇੱਕ ਡਰੇ ਹੋਏ ਸ਼ੇਖ ਚਿੱਲੀ ਨੇ ਵੀ ਉੱਚੀ ਆਵਾਜ਼ ਵਿੱਚ ਕਿਹਾ। '' ਦੁਸ਼ਟ ਆਤਮਾ! ਚਾਰ ਭੂਤ!ਦੋ ਚੋਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਭੱਜਣ ਤੋਂ ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਭੀੜ ਇਕੱਠੀ ਹੋ ਗਈ। ਕੋਲੇ ਦੀ ਧੂੜ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੋਵੇਂ ਚੋਰ ਕੋਤਵਾਲੀ ਲੈ ਗਏ। ਲੱਲਨ ਅਜੇ ਵੀ ਬੁੜਬੁੜਾ ਰਿਹਾ ਸੀ \\"ਭੂਤ! ਦੁਸ਼ਟ ਆਤਮਾ! ”ਇੱਕ ਗੁਆਂਢੀ ਫਾਤਿਮਾ ਬੀਬੀ ਦੇ ਪਰਿਵਾਰ ਦੇ ਵਾਪਸ ਆਉਣ ਤੱਕ ਲੁੱਟੇ ਹੋਏ ਗਹਿਣਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਰਾਖੀ ਕਰਦੀ ਰਹੀ। ਲੋਕ ਸ਼ੇਖ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਪਿਆਰੇ ਤਰਬੂਜ ਨਾਲ ਨਾਇਕ ਵਾਂਗ ਘਰ ਵਾਪਸ ਲੈਣ ਗਏ। "},{"question":"Beqil ma mbind mii:Ñu wax ne ko: \\"Yaw Aadama dëkkal ci àjjana yaak sa soxna, ngeen di fa lekkee na mu leen neexee, ca fa mu leen soobee; te bu leen jege garab gile: kon dey ngeen bokk ci way-tooñ ña\\".","answer":"Mbind mi jub a ngi nii:Ñu wàx ne ko: \\"Yaw Aadama dëkkal ci àjjana yaa'k sa soxna, ngéen di fa lekke na mu léen neexe, ca fa mu léen soobe; te buléen jege garab gile: kon dey ngéen bokk ci waytooñ ña\\"."},{"question":"Inona no ho avy amin'ny fikarohana habakabaka ara-barotra sy fizahan-tany an-habakabaka?","answer":"Mitombo ny fikarohana habakabaka ara-barotra miaraka amin'ireo orinasa tsy miankina mihevitra ny iraka ho any amin'ny Volana, Mars ary na dia ny fizahan-tany an-habakabaka ho an'ny sivily aza."},{"question":"Menene sunan babban garin Turkiya?","answer":"Ankara, wanda a da ake kira Ancyra da Angora, babban birnin Turkiyya ne, dake tsakiyar yankin Anatoliya."},{"question":"புதிர்:  நடக்கத் தெரியாதவன் நட்டுவனுக்கு வழி காட்டுகிறான் அவன் யார்?","answer":"விடை: கைகாட்டி"},{"question":" O que significa a expressão \\"feito cego em tiroteio\\"?","answer":"Significa estar desorientado."},{"question":"ਸਾਲ 2019 ਨੂੰ ਦੁਨੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਵੱਖ-ਵੱਖ ਮੁਲਕਾਂ ਨੇ ਕਿਵੇਂ ਕਿਹਾ ਖੁਸ਼ਾਮਦੀਦ।ਆਓ ਤਸਵੀਰਾਂ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਦੇਖਦੇ ਹਾਂ ਕਿ ਪੂਰੀ ਦੁਨੀਆਂ ਨੇ ਕਿਵੇਂ ਜੀ ਆਇਆਂ ਆਖਿਆ ਸਾਲ 2019 ਨੂੰ...ਮੱਧ ਲੰਡਨ ਦੇ ਮਸ਼ਹੂਰ ਲੰਡਨ ਆਈ ਉੱਤੇ ਪਾਇਰੋਟੈਕਨਿਕਸ ਨਾਲ ਸ਼ਾਨਦਾਰ ਆਤਿਸ਼ਬਾਜੀ ਕੀਤੀ ਗਈ।ਭਾਰਤ ਦੇ ਅਹਿਮਦਾਬਾਦ ਵਿੱਚ ਨਵੇਂ ਸਾਲ ਦੇ ਜਸ਼ਨ ਮੌਕੇ ਵਾਲਾ ਉੱਤੇ ਸੈਂਟਾ ਕਲੌਜ਼ ਬਣਾਉਂਦੇ ਹੋਈ ਇੱਕ ਕਲਾਕਾਰ। ਦੁੱਬਈ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੁਨੀਆਂ ਦੀ ਸਭ ਤੋਂ ਉੱਚੀ ਇਮਾਰਤ ਉੱਤੇ ਆਤਿਸ਼ਬਾਜ਼ੀ ਦਾ ਸ਼ਾਨਦਾਰ ਨਜ਼ਾਰਾ।ਮਲੇਸ਼ੀਆ ਵਿੱਚ ਕੁਆਲਾ ਲਾਮਪੁਰ ਦੇ ਪੈਟਰੋਨਸ ਟਾਵਰ ਉੱਤੇ ਹੋਈ ਆਤਿਸ਼ਬਾਜ਼ੀ ਨਾਲ ਆਸਮਾਨ ਵੀ ਲਾਲ ਰੰਗ ਵਿੱਚ ਰੰਗਿਆ ਨਜ਼ਰ ਆਇਆ।ਚੀਨ ਦੇ ਬੀਜਿੰਗ ਵਿੱਚ ਕੁਝ ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਜਸ਼ਨ ਮਨਾ ਕਾ ਨਵੇਂ ਸਾਲ ਦੀ ਕੀਤੀ ਸ਼ੁਰੂਆਤ।ਸਿੰਗਾਪੁਰ ਦੇ ਮਰੀਨਾ ਬੇਅ 'ਤੇ ਲੱਖਾਂ ਲੋਕਾਂ ਨੇ ਇਕੱਠੇ ਹੋ ਕੇ ਸਾਲ 2018 ਨੂੰ ਕੀਤਾ ਅਲਿਵਦਾ ਤੇ ਨਵੇਂ ਸਾਲ ਦਾ ਕੀਤਾ ਸੁਆਗਤ।ਆਸਟਰੇਲੀਆ ਦੇ ਸਿਡਨੀ ਹਾਰਬਰ ਬ੍ਰਿਜ ਉੱਤੇ 12 ਮਿੰਟ ਤੱਕ ਹੋਈ ਆਤਿਸ਼ਬਾਜ਼ੀ। ਰੂਸ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਾਲ 2018 ਦੀ ਆਖ਼ਰੀ ਸ਼ਾਮ ਨੂੰ ਇਸ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਕੀਤਾ ਅਲਵਿਦਾ ।ਫਿਲੀਪੀਂਸ ਦੇ ਕੇਜ਼ੋਨ ਸ਼ਹਿਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਨਵੇਂ ਸਾਲ ਦੀ ਆਮਦ ਮੌਕੇ 2019 ਨੂੰ ਦਰਸਾਉਂਦਾ ਚਸ਼ਮਾ ਪਹਿਨੇ ਇੱਕ ਕੁੜੀ।","answer":"ਨਵੇਂ ਸਾਲ ਦੀ ਆਮਦ ਨੇ ਦੁਨੀਆਂ ਭਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਰਾਤ ਨੂੰ ਰੁਸ਼ਨਾ ਦਿੱਤਾ, ਲੱਖਾਂ ਲੋਕਾਂ ਵੱਲੋਂ ਸ਼ਾਨਦਾਰ ਆਤਿਸ਼ਹਬਾਜ਼ੀ ਨਾਲ ਆਸਮਾਨ ਜਗਮਗਾ ਉਠਿਆ।"},{"question":"Саламат Садыкова ким?","answer":"Саламат Садыкова даңазалуу кыргыз ырчысы, комузчусу, аткаруучусу. Кыргызстан Республикасынын Эл артисти. Казакстан Республикасынын Эмгек сиңирген артисти."},{"question":"Dựa trên tiêu đề sau, hãy viết một đoạn văn tối đa 500 chữ: Nga 'dội lửa' miền nam Ukraine, giao tranh ác liệt ở Donbass","answer":"Trong một thông điệp đăng tải trên trang Telegram, Thống đốc vùng Mykolaiv Vitaliy Kim cho hay, Oleksiy Vadatursky, người sáng lập và cũng là chủ sở hữu công ty nông nghiệp Nibulon cùng vợ đã thiệt mạng tại nhà riêng do trúng đạn pháo. Đặt trụ sở tại Mykolaiv, một cảng chiến lược quan trọng giáp vùng Kherson đang nằm dưới sự kiểm soát của các lực lượng Moscow, công ty Nibulon chuyên sản xuất và xuất khẩu lúa mì, lúa mạch và ngô. Doanh nghiệp này có đội tàu vận tải và xưởng đóng tàu riêng. Tổng thống Volodymyr Zelensky mô tả cái chết của ông Vadatursky là \\"một tổn thất lớn đối với toàn đất nước Ukraine\\". Theo lãnh đạo Kiev, ông Vadatursky đang trong quá trình xây dựng một thị trường ngũ cốc hiện đại, bao gồm cả mạng lưới các bến trung chuyển và thang nâng. Phát biểu trên đài truyền hình quốc gia Ukraine, Oleksandr Senkevych, thị trưởng thành phố Mykolaiv nói, thêm 3 người khác cũng bị thương trong các vụ tấn công của quân Nga vào đây. Quan chức này nói, 12 quả tên lửa của đối phương cũng rơi trúng các ngôi nhà và cơ sở giáo dục trong thành phố. Ông nhận định, đây là có thể là vụ tập kích mạnh nhất vào đô thị này trong hơn 5 tháng chiến sự vừa qua. Ngoài ra, viết trên Telegram, Thống đốc Dnipropetrovsk Valentyn Reznichenko cáo buộc phía Nga đã nã tới 50 tên lửa Grad vào các khu dân cư ở Nikopol, một thành phố miền nam Ukraine khác sáng 31/7. Một người đã bị thương trong sự cố. Reuters thừa nhận không thể xác minh một cách độc lập các số liệu thống kê trên. Ukraine cảnh báo mất 1/2 sản lượng thu hoạch Cùng ngày, Tổng thống Zelensky cảnh báo Ukraine có thể thất thu tới 1/2 lượng nông sản thu hoạch năm nay vì xung đột với Nga. \\"Thu hoạch của Ukraine năm nay đang bị đe dọa giảm tới một nửa bình thường. Mục tiêu chính của chúng tôi là ngăn chặn khủng hoảng lương thực toàn cầu vì chiến dịch quân sự đặc biệt của Nga. Chúng tôi vẫn đang tìm cách vận chuyển các loại ngũ cốc\\", ông Zelensky viết trên Twitter. Ukraine đang vật lộn tìm cách chuyên chở các mặt hàng tới người mua thông qua các cảng bên bờ biển Đen của nước này. Kiev và Moscow đã ký kết một thỏa thuận hóa giải sự bế tắc dưới sự giám sát của Liên Hợp Quốc và Thổ Nhĩ Kỳ vào ngày 22/7, nhằm bảo đảm việc đi lại an toàn cho các tàu chở ngũ cốc rời khỏi 3 cảng miền nam Ukraine. Phát ngôn viên của Tổng thống Thổ Nhĩ Kỳ Tayyip Erdogan hôm 31/7 nhận định, khả năng cao là các tàu xuất khẩu ngũ cốc đầu tiên sẽ rời cảng của Ukraine vào ngày 1/8. Giao tranh tiếp diễn ác liệt ở miền đông Ukraine Tổng thống Zelensky lưu ý, hàng trăm nghìn người Ukraine vẫn đang phải đối mặt với tình trạng giao tranh ác liệt ở vùng Donbass, miền đông đất nước. Moscow đã công khai ý định giành quyền kiểm soát toàn bộ vùng đất hợp thành từ 2 tỉnh Donetsk và Luhansk kể từ giai đoạn 2 của chiến dịch quân sự đặc biệt tại nước láng giềng. \\"Nhiều người từ chối rời đi nhưng việc đó vẫn cần phải được thực hiện. Càng nhiều người rời Donetsk, càng ít người có nguy cơ thiệt mạng vì chiến sự\\", ông Zelensky nhấn mạnh. Theo báo Guardian, các phóng viên của một hãng thông tấn Pháp đã chứng kiến vụ bắn phá dữ hội vào thành phố Bakhmut, miền đông Ukraine, khiến một người mất mạng. Bakhmut là một trong những thành phố ít ỏi còn lại thuộc tỉnh Donetsk vẫn còn nằm dưới quyền quản lý của Kiev. Tuấn Anh"},{"question":"Sheeg garoonka kubada cagta ee Stadium Moqdisho dalkii dishay?","answer":"Garoonka kubada cagta ee Stadium Moqdisho waxa dhisay dalka shiinaha (China)."},{"question":"Completa quanto segue:\\"Roberto Baggio viene premiato ...\\"","answer":"\\"...  Pallone d'argento dei Mondiali, risultando il secondo miglior giocatore del torneo dopo il brasiliano Romário, che si laureò campione del mondo. Con 5 gol, Baggio si laurea inoltre vice capocannoniere del torneo, assieme a Romário, Kennet Andersson e Jürgen Klinsmann, superato solamente da Hristo Stoičkov e Oleg Salenko. Nel 1994 Baggio si classifica secondo nella classifica del Pallone d'oro e terzo in quella del FIFA World Player, e nello stesso anno gli viene assegnato l'Onze de Bronze.\\""},{"question":"Apakah resipi untuk ayam percik putih Terrenganu? Tunjukkan langkah-langkahn terperinci.","answer":"Bahan: 1 ekor ayam, 2 cawan santan pekat, 10 ulas bawang merah, 3 ulas bawang putih, 1 inci halia, 1 cm kunyit, 1 batang serai, 3 sudu besar cili kisar / cili boh, 1 sudu besar tepung beras/jagung (untuk memekatkan kuah), 1 keping asam gelugor, 1 sudu kecil garam, 1 sudu besar gulaCara penyediaan:1. Kisar bawang merah, bawang putih, kunyit, halia, serai, cili kering, garam dan gula dengan sedikit air.2. Potong ayam kepada empat bahagian atau lebih kecil. Bersihkan, kelar dan tuskan.3 Gaulkan ayam dengan bahan kisar dan perapkan selama sekurang-kurangnya setengah jam.Cara memasak:1.  Masukkan ayam bersama perapan ke dalam periuk. Tambah secawan air, kacau, tutup periuk dan rebus dengan api sederhana.2. Apabila ayam sudah masak, keluarkan ayam dari periuk untuk dipanggang.3. Masukkan santan, cili kisar, asam keping dan tepung beras ke dalam periuk berisi perapan tadi dan masak sehingga kuah pekat. Sentiasa kacau semasa kuah percik dimasak untuk mengelakkan santan berketul. Perasakan dengan garam dan gula sebelum diangkat. Keluarkan asam keping kalau dah cukup rasa masam.4. Panggang ayam di atas bara api, dalam oven atau menggunakan pemanggang ajaib. Apabila ayam sudahkeperangan, lumurkan kuah percik pada ayam dan teruskan memanggang hingga garing. Terbalikkanayam dan ulangi proses melumur kuah dan memanggang beberapa kali sehingga kuah melekat padaayam dan ia masak sekata.5. Angkat dan hidangkan."},{"question":"Inona no atao hoe demokrasia tsy liberaly?","answer":"Ny demokrasia tsy liberaly dia fitondrana misy ny fifidianana, saingy mety ho malemy ny zon'ny tsirairay sy ny andrim-panjakana demokratika."},{"question":"卡加利人口分佈如何？","answer":"卡加利人口60%為白人，少數族裔中，南亞人占大多數。"},{"question":"السؤال: ما نوع جمع الصلاة التي يجوز للمسلمين وقت المطر؟","answer":"الجواب: جمع التقديم فقط."},{"question":"「城塞」という意味がある、大統領府をはじめロシアの政治の中枢部があるモスクワの一地区といえばどこでしょう？","answer":"クレムリンです。"},{"question":"පහත ගීතය සම්පුර්ණ කරන්න.ලියතඹරා මල ඔබද ලදේමා වසඟයක් කැරූ","answer":"ලියතඹරා මල ඔබද ලදේමා වසඟයක් කැරූවිෂ බදුනක් ගෙන මධුවිතය කියාමා ගත සනසාලූඅවිහිංසක දෑසේ කඳුලැලි දැකමා ගැනවත් නොසිතාමිතුරන් කී බස් නොඅසා ඔබ ගැනසහසක් පැතුම් පතාපුද දුන් සෙනෙහස එතැනම මියැදීමා වූවා ද මුලාලියතඹරා මල ඔබද ලදේමා වසඟයක් කැරූවිෂ බදුනක් ගෙන මධුවිතය කියාමා ගත සනසාලූකෙනෙක් ඇසුරු කර තවකෙක් පතනාඔබ යයි මඟක මුලාසුපිපුණු හද මල් මෙලෙසින් සිඳ බිඳයන්නේ ඇයිද පෙලාමෙතුවක් බැඳි සෙනෙහස නාමෙන් හෝඔබ වෙතට දෙමි සමාලියතඹරා මල ඔබද ලදේමා වසඟයක් කැරූවිෂ බදුනක් ගෙන මධුවිතය කියාමා ගත සනසාලූ"},{"question":"ભૂમિતિ એટલે શુ ?","answer":"ભૂમિતિ ગણિતની એક શાખા છે. ભૂમિતિના વિષયમાં જુદા-જુદા આકારોનું વિશ્લેષણ થાય છે. દુનિયામાં જોવા મળતા આકારો ના મુખ્ય ત્રણ પ્રકાર છે. સુરેખ, સમતલ અને ઘન. આ વર્ગીકરણ તેમના પરિમાણના આધારે થયેલું છે. તેઓ અનુક્રમે ૧, ૨ અને ૩ પરિમાણ ધરાવે છે. પૂર્વધારણાઓ:ભૂમિતિના વિષયમાં મુખ્યતઃ પ્રમેયો સાબિત કરવામાં આવે છે. પરંતુ ભૂમિતિની શરૂઆત કેટલાક વિધાનોથી થાય છે જેમને સાબિતિ વિના માની લેવામાં આવે છે. આ વિધાનોને પૂર્વધારણા કહે છે. ભૂમિતિની મુખ્ય પૂર્વધારણાઓ આ મુજબ છે:1.બિંદુની પૂર્વધારણા2.રેખાની પૂર્વધારણા3.કિરણની પૂર્વધારણા"},{"question":"次の文章に書かれている内容に基づいて、少なくとも200語の段落を書いてください。： 東海道新幹線の中で弁当などをワゴンで売ることをやめる","answer":"東海道新幹線の「のぞみ」と「ひかり」の中では、弁当や飲み物などをワゴンにのせて売るサービスを行っています。JR東海は、このサービスを今年10月31日でやめます。新幹線の中ではなくて、駅の近くの店で買う人が増えたためです。新型コロナウイルスが広がる前の2018年の売り上げは、2008年の半分ぐらいになっていました。これから働く人が足りなくなりそうなことも理由です。会社は、「のぞみ」がとまる駅のホームなどで、飲み物やアイスクリームなどの自動販売機を多くすると言っています。"},{"question":"Descreva a bandeira de Ruanda.","answer":"A bandeira de Ruanda é composta por quatro faixas horizontais de igual tamanho, sendo a faixa superior azul, a faixa do meio amarela e as faixas inferiores verdes. No canto superior direito, há um emblema com uma letra \\"R\\" e um sol vermelho."},{"question":"Filenin sultanları 2023 antrenörü kimdir?","answer":"Daniele Santarelli"},{"question":"1975 වසරේ ලෝක ක්‍රිකට් ශූරතාවය හිමි කරගත් ජයග්‍රාහී බටහිර ඉන්දීය කොදෙව් කණ්ඩායමේ නායකයා කවුද?","answer":"ක්ලයිව් ලොයිඩ්"},{"question":"Fan mooy gëblag réewum Maldives?","answer":"Gëblag réewum Maldives mu ngi tudd Malé."},{"question":"కింది సామాన్య వాక్యాలను సంయుక్త వాక్యాలుగా మార్చి రాయండి.సీతమ్మ పెళ్ళికి ఏర్పాటు చేశారు. సీతమ్మ పెండ్లి పెటాకులయ్యింది. ","answer":"సీతమ్మ పెళ్ళికి ఏర్పాటు చేశారు కాని పెండ్లి పెటాకులయ్యింది. "},{"question":"文中の主な言葉を見つけて、その内容を説明しなさい。 アフガニスタンでは2021年からタリバンの政府になって、日本に留学したことがある人などが避難しています。NHKが調べると、日本の大学に留学したことがある33人が日本に来ています。宮崎県では、宮崎大学に留学していた7人と、その家族たちが生活しています。この中の男性1人が4月から、農業の会社で働くことが決まりました。男性は植物や農薬が専門で、アフガニスタンの大学で教えていました。男性は「国では自由や権利がなくて、希望をなくしていました。日本で働くことができてうれしいです」と話しました。今は大学が避難してきた人たちの世話をしていますが、働く場所が見つからないと、日本にいることができなくなる心配があります。宮崎大学の人は「アフガニスタンのことをたくさんの人に知ってもらって、どうしたら助けることができるか考えてほしいです」と話しています。","answer":"文にある主な言葉とその内容はこちらです。"},{"question":"デビュー曲は「箱根八里の半次郎」。演歌界の貴公子と言えば誰？","answer":"氷川きよしです。"},{"question":"Ijọba Eko yoo ṣi ileewe alakọọbẹrẹ ati girama lọjọ kọkanlelogun, oṣu kẹsan-an","answer":"Idunnu ti ṣubu lu ayọ fawọn akẹkọọ lawọn ile-ẹkọ jake-jado ipinlẹ Eko pẹlu bi Gomina ipinlẹ ọhun, Babajide Oluṣọla Sanwo-Olu, ṣe kede nirọlẹ ọjọ Abamẹta, Satide yii, pe gbogbo ile-ẹkọ nipinlẹ naa maa ṣi fun ikẹkọọ lakọtun ninu oṣu kẹsan-an ọdun yii.Nibi ipade pẹlu awọn akọroyin to waye nile ijọba to wa ni Marina, l’Ekoo, ni gomina ti sọrọ naa di mimọ.Sanwo-Olu ni: “Inu mi dun lati kede pe awọn ileewe giga wa yoo si fun ikẹkọọ bẹrẹ lati ọjọ kẹrinla, oṣu kẹsan-an, gbogbo ile-ẹkọ giga pata.”Lara awọn ile-ẹkọ naa ni fasiti, poli atawọn kọlẹẹji to kaakiri ipinlẹ ọhun.Gomina tun tẹ siwaju pe awọn ileewe pamari ati sẹkọndri yoo lanfaani lati bẹrẹ eto ẹkọ tiwọn naa pada lati ọjọ kọkanlelogun, oṣu kẹsan-an yii, kan naa, iyẹn lẹyin tawọn to n ṣe idanwo aṣekagba Wayẹẹki to n lọ lọwọ yii ba ti pari idanwo wọn lọjọ keji, oṣu ọhun."},{"question":"اختر العلاقة المناسبة بين الجملتين الأتيتين، توافق - تناقض - لا علاقة:الجملة الأولى: اعتذر سمير عن الذهاب لعمله اليوم.الجملة الثانية: تشاجر سمير مع زميله فى العمل اليوم","answer":"بالتأكيد، الجملة الثانية تناقض الجملة الأولى."},{"question":"खालील म्हणीचा सोप्या शब्दात अर्थ सांगा  चोरावर मोर","answer":"एखाद्या गोष्टीच्या बाबतीत दुसर्‍यावर कडी करणे."},{"question":"Waxaad Sheegtaa maalintii bishii iyo sanadkii la aasaasay Ciidanka Booliiska Soomaaliyeed?","answer":" Waxaa la aasaasay 20/12/1943kii."},{"question":"Ṣe àpilẹ̀kọ àyọkà fún àkòrí yìí: Ìdìbò tó ń bọ̀ kìí ṣé ìdìbo 'Èmi ló kán', ìdìbò àwọn ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà ní - Peter Obi","answer":"Olùdíje sípò ààrẹ lábẹ́ àṣíá ẹgbẹ́ òṣèlú Labour Party, Peter Obi, ti rọ àwọn ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè látí má ṣe rí ìdìbò tó ń bọ̀ gẹ́gẹ́ bíi ìdìbò \\"èmi ló kàn\\" nítorí àsìkò àwọn ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà ló kàn látí yan ààrẹ tí yóò wù wọ́n nínú gbogbo làásígbò tí wọ́n wà. Òbí sọ eléyìí nígbà tí òun pẹ̀lú igbákejì rẹ̀, Sẹ́nétọ̀ Datti Baba-Ahmed ń kópa nínú ìfọ̀rọ̀wérọ̀ kan pẹ̀lú Kadaria Ahmed lánàá. Ó sẹ ọ̀pọ̀lọpọ̀ ìlérí fún àwọn ọmọ Nàìjíríà pé tí wọ́n bá fún òun ní àyè látí ṣèjọba, ayípadà láì ní ẹgbẹ́ ni yóò dé bá orílẹ̀-èdè náà. Obi ní kí àwọn ọmọ Nàìjíríà má ṣe rí ìdìbò tó ń bọ̀ ọ̀hún gẹ́gẹ́ bíi ti ẹlẹ́yàmẹ̀yà tàbí ẹ̀sìn. “Àwa méjèèjì, èmi àti igbákejì mi ti rọ àwọn ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà pé ètò ìdìbò tó ń bọ̀ kò gbọdọ̀ dá lé ẹlẹ́yàmẹ̀yà, kò gbọdọ̀ dá l'órí ẹ̀sìn, kò gbọdọ̀ dá l'órí pé èmi ló kàn nítorí pé àsìkò àwọn ọmọ Nàìjíríà ló kàn látí gba ìṣèjọba orílẹ̀-èdè yìí. “Mo ń ṣe ìlérí pé màá yọ Nàìjíríà kúrò nínú oko ẹrú, tí àwa yóò sì bẹ̀rẹ̀ l'áti pèsè àwọn ǹkan tí a fẹ́ fún ara wa. “Ìṣẹ́ yóò dínkù pátápátá l'órílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà. A máa ri pé kò sí ẹnikẹni tó kọjá ìbáwí lábẹ́ òfin. “A fi ń dáa yín l'ójú pé ìwà ìbàjẹ́ èyí tó gbalẹ̀ l'órílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà yóò di ohun ìgbàgbé. A óò ri pé a pèse Nàìjíríà fún àwọn ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà. P\uFEFFeter Obi, ẹni tó jẹ́ igbákejì ààrẹ fún olùdíje sípò ààrẹ ẹgbẹ́ òṣèlú Alábùradà (PDP), Atiku Abubakar l'ọ́dún 2019, kúrò nínú ẹgbẹ́ ọ̀hún látí lọ díje fún ipò ààrẹ lábẹ́ àṣíá ẹgbẹ́ òṣèlú Labour fún ètò ìdìbò l'ọ́dún 2023."},{"question":"ආවර්තිතා වගුව යනු කුමක්ද","answer":"ආවර්තිතා වගුව යනු රසායනික මූලද්‍රව්‍යවල වගු සැකැස්මකි, ඒවායේ පරමාණුක ක්‍රමාංකය, ඉලෙක්ට්‍රෝන වින්‍යාසය සහ පුනරාවර්තන රසායනික ගුණාංග අනුව සංවිධානය වේ. විවිධ මූලද්‍රව්‍ය අතර සම්බන්ධතා අවබෝධ කර ගැනීමට, නව මූලද්‍රව්‍යවල ගුණ පුරෝකථනය කිරීමට සහ නව ද්‍රව්‍ය සැලසුම් කිරීමට එය විද්‍යාඥයින්ට ඉඩ සලසයි."},{"question":"महामुनी पराशर यांनी लिहिलेल्या कृषी कोषाचे नाव काय आहे ?","answer":"पराशर तंत्र"},{"question":"1977年に「私の先生」でデビューした、第一回ホリプロスカウトキャラバンの優勝者である「元祖巨乳アイドル」といえば誰でしょう？","answer":"榊原郁恵"},{"question":"Ta ni Mínísítà f'étò ọkọ̀ òfúrufú tí wọ́n ṣẹ̀ṣẹ̀ yàn lábẹ́ ìjọba Ààrẹ Bọ́lá Tinubu?","answer":"Festus Keyamo ni."},{"question":"Apakah nama festival yang diraikan masyarakat Sikh setiap April? Pilih jawapan yang betul dari pilihan berikut.  A. Deepavali B. Thaipusam C. Ponggal D. Vaisakhi","answer":"Jawapan yang betul adalah D. Vaisakhi.Vaisakhi diraikan sempena menandakan kelahiran Khalsa, komuniti yang menjadikan Sikhism sebagai kepercayaan."},{"question":"Euskal Herriko pintxo kultura: Zer da pintxo kultura eta zer nolako rola jokatzen du elkarbizitzan eta euskal gastronomian?","answer":"Pintxo kultura, Euskal Herriko tabernetan edo jatetxe txikietan jateko edo edari txikiak hartzean datza. Pintxoak, sukaldaritza sormenaren adibideak dira, zenbait osagai erabiliz sortutako janari txikiak. Elkarbizitzan, pintxo kultura momentu soziala da, lagunekin, familiarekin edo lankideekin denbora pasatzeko. Gastronomian, pintxoak euskal sukaldaritzaren kalitatea eta sormena erakusten du, mundu osoko sukaldaritzaren erreferente bihurtzen da."},{"question":"Địa phương nào của Việt Nam có hai sân bay đang hoạt động?","answer":"Theo Cục hàng không Việt Nam, địa phương duy nhất có hai sân bay là tỉnh Kiên Giang, với Cảng hàng không Quốc tế Phú Quốc và Cảng hàng không Rạch Giá."},{"question":"பதிவேற்றம் – இச்சொல்லின் பொருள் ……………………………அ) தகவல் ஆராய்தல்ஆ) தகவல் வரிசைப்படுத்துதல்இ) தகவல் பதிவு செய்தல்ஈ) தகவல் பெறுதல்","answer":"பதிவேற்றம் – இச்சொல்லின் பொருள்  ஈ) தகவல் பெறுதல்"},{"question":"Dame un ejemplo de trivia en está categoría : películas. ","answer":"¿Qué película dirigida por Steven Spielberg presenta a un parque temático de dinosaurios y se lanzó en 1993."},{"question":"चीनलाई छुने नेपालको प्रान्त कुन हो ?","answer":"प्रदेश नम्बर १, ३, ४, ६ र ७ चीनलाई छोने नेपालका प्रदेश हुन्।"},{"question":"Odpowiedz na pytanie: Czy filmy Triumph of the Will i The End of America powstały w tym samym roku?","answer":"Nie."},{"question":"2016年、スマートフォン向けゲームアプリとして大ヒットし、社会現象も引き起こした、現実世界を歩いてポケモンを捕獲し、育成するゲームを何という？","answer":"ポケモンGOです。"},{"question":"سوال کا جواب دیں: کینٹکی میں یو ایس روٹ 27 (یو ایس 27) ٹینیسی کی سرحد سے اوہائیو کی سرحد تک سینسیناتی ، اوہائیو میں کتنے میل چلتا ہے؟","answer":"روٹ 27 ۱۹۰.۷۸۵ میل چلتا ہے۔"},{"question":"Fan moy péeyum réwum Fidji","answer":"Péeyum réwum Fidji mu ngi tudu Suva"},{"question":"Quais são os impactos do tráfico transatlântico de escravos na Angola?","answer":"Angola desempenhou um papel central no tráfico de escravos, enviando milhões de africanos para as Américas. Esta história trágica deixou marcas profundas na sociedade angolana e nas suas relações com outras nações."},{"question":"Wqxaad  Sheegtaa  baarlabaankii ay ku Shiri jireen Kufaartii qureysheed maxaa la oran Jiray?","answer":" Waxa la oran Jiray baarlabaankaas (Daaru Nadwa)."},{"question":"\\"සාර්වත්‍රික දෘෂ්ටි කෝණය\\" කරුණාකර පැහැදිළි කර දෙන්න.","answer":"සියල්ල ඇතුළත් වන සේ සලකා බැලීම.අතීත, වර්තමාන, අනාගත යන කාල තුනටම ගැලපෙන ලෙස ලියනු ලබන කතා සර්ව කාලීන කතා වන අතර සියලු තැන්වලට/සියලු දෙනාට ගැළපෙන ලෙස ලියන ලද කතා සාර්වත්‍රිකදෘෂ්ටිකෝණයෙන් ලියන ලද කතා ලෙස සැලකේ."},{"question":"V6のメンバーの中で、三宅健・森田剛・岡田准一の3人のグループを特に何というでしょう？","answer":"Coming Century（カミセン）です。"},{"question":"هل الجملتين التاليتين لهما نفس المعنى؟\\"لقد حاولت كثيرا اجتياز الامتحان، ثم تمكنت من ذلك في النهاية.\\"\\"بعد العديد من المحاولات، تمكنت من اجتياز الاختبار بنجاح.\\"","answer":"نعم"},{"question":" Namanje awukafuni ukuthatha umfazi?'Uma ekhumbula kahle uBhekani sengathi uphendulile kodwa uyise wahwaqa,ekhombisa ukuthi impendulo ayimgculisi.'Cha, kuzofuneka ngiganwe.' Ukhuluma yedwa njalo uBhekani. 'Kodwa ngizoshadanobani?' Wayezibuza lo mbuzo, impendulo wagcina engayitholanga. Umqondowakhe wazulazula ethatha ebeka izintombi asake athandana nazo. Wayethi umaezifaka esikalweni, ezihlolisisa zonke zingafaneli ukumgana.Bayanda manje abantu lapha okumelwe khona amatekisi. Nakhu sekufika intokaziima eduze kukaBhekani. Athikaziseke emicabangweni yakhe. Abuke le ntokazi.Inhle. Imhlophe qwa.zinwele lezi zilungiswe ngobunono obukhulu. Zinhle, zihlangene zikanywe kahle.Athi uma eyibhekisisa abone ubuhwanqa obuphuphuzelayo obucishe busikazeizihlathi.Kanti zinjani zona izihlathi! Ungafunga uthi azigcotshwa kodwaziyapholishwa.Ezwe sengathi uyathatheka uBhekani yile ntokazi.1. Ngokubona kwakho iyiphi intombi eyabe ifanele uBhekani kulezi akeathandana nazo? Sekela impendulo yakho ngamaphuzu AMABI","answer":"ULindiwe√ ngoba: Amaphuzu AMABILI kwalandelayo: Wayethandwa ngabakubo kaBhekani. Wayenothando lweqiniso Wabuya wazoxolisa kuBhekani. Wayenomsebenzi oqondile futhi ohloniphekile njengoba ayenguthisha"},{"question":"நோபல் பரிசு பெற்ற முதல் இந்தியர் யார்?","answer":" ரவீந்திரநாத் தாகூர்"},{"question":"Crie um recado para Joana chamando ela para sair","answer":"Oie Joana,Quer sair comigo hoje? Podemos ir em um barzinho, cinema, restaurante, o que preferir! Se quiser pode chamar algum amigo também. Espero te ver hoje:)[Seu Nome]"},{"question":"La Roche sahtesi nasıl anlaşılır?","answer":"Ürün etiketi: Ürünün içeriği, kullanım talimatları ve üretim bilgileri net ve anlaşılır bir dilde, etiket üzerinde yer almalıdır. İsterseniz buradaki bilgileri La Roche-Posay web sitesine girerek, sitede yer alan bilgilerle de karşılaştırabilirsiniz."},{"question":"Hãy tiếp tục đoạn văn sau: Tối 28/8 (13/7 âm lịch), khuôn viên chùa Phước Duyên ở phường Hương Long, TP Huế chật kín phật tử về tham dự lễ Vu Lan do nhà chùa tổ chức. Trong đêm lễ, các phật tử đã cùng nhau tụng kinh Vu Lan báo hiếu với tâm thành kính. Tiếng kinh vang vọng khắp khuôn viên chùa, như một lời nhắc nhở về công ơn sinh thành dưỡng dục của cha mẹ.Vu Lan báo hiếu là ","answer":"một trong những nghi lễ quan trọng của đạo Phật. Lễ được tổ chức vào rằm tháng 7 hàng năm, xuất phát từ sự tích Bồ tát Mục Kiền Liên đại hiếu cứu mẹ khỏi kiếp ngạ quỷ bằng cách nghe lời Phật dạy.Rằm tháng 7 có thể nói là tháng đẹp nhất trong năm khi những người con hướng về cha mẹ, báo hiếu theo lời dạy của Phật. Đây cũng là thời điểm chư tăng kết thúc 3 tháng an cư tu tập và tỏa sáng công đức.Trong đêm lễ, không ít người con đã rơi nước mắt khi tưởng nhớ công ơn cha mẹ. Họ hứa sẽ luôn yêu thương, chăm sóc cha mẹ và làm những điều tốt đẹp để báo đáp công ơn sinh thành dưỡng dục.Lễ Vu Lan là dịp để những người con thể hiện lòng hiếu thảo với cha mẹ, đồng thời cũng là dịp để mọi người nhắc nhở nhau về trách nhiệm của con cái đối với cha mẹ."},{"question":"ما هو الحيوان الذي إذا تغير دمه أصبح طاهر؟","answer":"دم الغزال، إذا تغير أصبح مسك، وهو طاهر وذو رائحة ذكية."},{"question":"\\"How are you?\\" is in English. Translate it to Cebuano. ","answer":"Kumusta? "},{"question":"\\"प्रेम हुन केही गाह्रो छैन\\" भन्नुको तात्पर्य के हो ?","answer":"प्रेमले संस्कृति, भाषा, जाति, टाढानजिक, सुखदुःख जस्ता केही कुरा पनि हेर्दैन । मनसँग मन मिलेपछि तुरुन्त प्रेम हुन्छ भन्नुनै प्रेम हुन केही गाह्रो छैन भन्नुको तात्पर्य हो । "},{"question":"A lafazin kalma, wane wasali ke ganɗanta |g|?A)/a/B)/u/C)/o/D)/e/","answer":"D)/e/"},{"question":"No contexto de Linux, explique brevemente o termo \\"Distribution Release\\".","answer":"Uma Distribution Release é uma versão específica de uma distribuição Linux."},{"question":"د سړې جګړې لاملونه او پایلې څه وې؟","answer":"سړه جګړه له دویمې نړیوالې جګړې وروسته د امریکا او شوروي اتحاد تر منځ د ایډیالوژیکي اختلافاتو له امله راڅرګنده شوه. دا ژورې نړیوالې پایلې درلودې، نړیوالو اړیکو ته بڼه ورکول، د پراکسي جنګونو پیل کول، او په 1991 کې د شوروي اتحاد تر ړنګیدو پورې په سیاسي اتحادونو اغیزه کول."},{"question":"Beqil ma mbind mii:Nangeen gëm li Ma wàcce, te muy dëggal li ngeen yore; buleen doon ñi ko jëkk a weddi. Buleen jaay samay laaya ak njëg gu néew. Te nangeen ma ragal Man doŋ.","answer":"Mbind mi jub a ngi nii:Na ngéen gëm li Ma wàcce, te mu'y dëggal li ngéen yore; buléen doon ñi ko jëkk a weddi. Buléen jaay sama'y laaya ak njëg gu néew. Te na ngéen ma ragal Màn doŋŋ."},{"question":"ಐದು ಬೆಕ್ಕುಗಳು ಐದು ನಿಮಿಷಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ಐದು ಇಲಿಗಳನ್ನು ಹಿಡಿಯಬಹುದಾದರೆ, ಒಂದು ಬೆಕ್ಕು ಒಂದು ಇಲಿಯನ್ನು ಹಿಡಿಯಲು ಎಷ್ಟು ಸಮಯ ತೆಗೆದುಕೊಳ್ಳುತ್ತದೆ?","answer":"ಐದು ಬೆಕ್ಕುಗಳು ಐದು ನಿಮಿಷಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ಐದು ಇಲಿಗಳನ್ನು ಹಿಡಿಯಲು ಸಾಧ್ಯವಾದರೆ, ಪ್ರತಿ ಬೆಕ್ಕು ಐದು ನಿಮಿಷಗಳಲ್ಲಿ ಒಂದು ಇಲಿಯನ್ನು ಹಿಡಿಯುತ್ತದೆ ಎಂದು ಸೂಚಿಸುತ್ತದೆ.ಆದ್ದರಿಂದ, ಒಂದು ಇಲಿಯನ್ನು ಹಿಡಿಯಲು ಒಂದು ಬೆಕ್ಕು ಐದು ನಿಮಿಷಗಳನ್ನು ತೆಗೆದುಕೊಳ್ಳುತ್ತದೆ."},{"question":"Manana teny mikorotana ianao:\\"nohaim\\"Omeo ary teny marina .","answer":"Ny teny marina dia \\"mihaino\\"."},{"question":"Inona no hevitry ny teny hoe riba","answer":"  Ny teny hoe riba dia tenim-paritra midika hoe rindrina na fefy. "},{"question":"வினா:தமிழில் ஓரெழுத்து ஒரு மொழிகளின் பெருக்கம் குறித்து இளங்குமரனார் கூறும் செய்திகளைத் தொகுத்து எழுதுக?","answer":"விடை: இரா. இளங்குமரனார் :செந்தமிழ் அந்தணர் என்று அழைக்கப்படும் புலவர் இரா. இளங்குமரனார் (சனவரி 30, 1927 - சூலை 25, 2021) ஒரு தமிழ் அறிஞர். பள்ளி ஆசிரியராகப் பணியாற்றிய இவர், பின்னர் நூலாசிரியர், பாவலர், பதிப்பாசிரியர், உரையாசிரியர், தொகுப்பாசிரியர், இதழாசிரியர், உரையாளர் எனப் பலபணிகளையும் செய்துள்ளார்.ஓரெழுத்து ஒரு மொழிகளின் பெருக்கம் :முன்னுரை:மொழி என்பதற்குச் சொல் என்பதும் ஒரு பொருள். மொழியை (சொல்லை) ஓர் எழுத்து மொழி, ஈரெழுத்து மொழி, இரண்டுக்கு மேற்பட்ட எழுத்துகள் உடைய மொழி என மூன்று வகையாக்குவர்.ஓரெழுத்து ஒரு மொழி:உயிர் வரிசையில் ஆறு எழுத்துகளும், ம வரிசையில் ஆறு எழுத்துகளும், த, ப, ந என்னும் வரிசைகளில் ஐந்து ஐந்து எழுத்துகளும், க, ச, வ என்னும் வரிசையில் நான்கு நான்கு எழுத்துகளும், ய வரிசையில் ஒன்றும் ஆக நாற்பது நெடில்கள் ஓரெழுத்து ஒரு மொழியாக வரும் என்றார் நன்னூலார். நொ, து என்னும் குறில்களையும் சேர்த்து நாற்பத்து இரண்டு என்றார்.பூ-யா சொற்கள்:பூ என்பது ஓரெழுத்து ஒரு மொழி. கா என்பதும் ஓரெழுத்து ஒரு மொழி. இவை இரண்டையும் இணைத்துப் பூங்கா எனக் கலைச்சொல் ஆக்கி வைத்துள்ளனர். யா என்பது வினா. யாது, யாவர், யாவன், யாங்கு, யாண்டு, யார், யாவை என்றெல்லாம் வினாவுவதற்கு முன் வந்து நிற்கும் எழுத்து ‘யா’ தானே!‘மா’ சொல்:மா என்பதும் ஓரெழுத்து ஒரு மொழிகளுள் ஒன்று. நாட்டிலுள்ள பெருமக்கள் பெரிதும் கூடும் அவையை மாநாடு என்கிறோம். பல குறு நிலங்களை உள்ளடக்கிய பெருநிலத்தை மாநிலம் என்கிறோம். மா என்பது விலங்கையும் குறிக்கும். அரிமா, பரிமா, நரிமா, வரிமா, கரிமா என்றெல்லாம் வந்து விலங்கினப் பெயராகி நிற்கின்றது.ஈ-காரச் சொல்:ஈ என்னும் பொதுப் பெயர் ஓயாது ஒலி செய்யும் ஒலிக்குறிப்பைக் காட்டி நிற்கிறது. மாட்டு ஈ, தேன் ஈ எனப் பகுத்து வழங்கும் வழக்கம் உள்ளது. ஈ என்பது ஈக என்னும் பொருளில் வழங்குதல் வெளிப்படை. ஈ என்று பல்லைக் காட்டாதே என்று அறிவுரை கூறுவதும் உண்டு .கால மாற்றத்தில் கரைந்தவை:இன்னொரு வகையாகவும் பார்க்கலாம். ஆன் என்பது ஆ ஆகியது; மான் என்பது மா ஆகியது; கோன் என்பது கோ ஆகியது; தேன் என்பது தே ஆகியது; பேய் என்பது பே ஆகியது இவையெல்லாம் கால வெள்ளத்தில் கரைந்து தேய்ந்தவை.ஏகாரச் சொல்:எட்டத்தில் போகிற ஒருவனை ஏய் என அழைத்தனர். ஏய் என்பது என்னோடு கூடு, பொருந்து, சேர் என்னும் பொருளை உடையது. ஏய் என்பது ஏ என வழக்கில் ஊன்றிவிட்டது. அம்பை ஏவு என்பர். ஏவுதல் என்பது ‘அம்புவிடுதல்’ ஏவும் அம்பு ‘ஏ’ என்றாகியது. அம்பு விரைந்து செல்வது போலச் சென்று உரிய கடமை புரிபவன் ஏவலன் எனப்பட்டான். அம்புவிடும் கலையை ஏகலை என்றது தமிழ். அதில் வல்லவனை ஏகலைவன் என்று பாராட்டியது.முடிவுரை:தமிழில் ஓரெழுத்து ஒரு மொழிச் சொற்களின் பெருக்கம் நம் மொழியின் பழமை, உயிரோட்டம், பெருவழக்கு என்பனவற்றைக் கையில் கனியாகக் காட்டும்.  இவையே  ஓரெழுத்து ஒரு மொழிகளின் பெருக்கம் குறித்து இளங்குமரனார் கூறும்  செய்திகளாகும். "},{"question":"Naftaydaay gacalo, si kasta oo ay xaaladuhu u adkaadaan, ha luminin dareenkaaga xasilloonida jacaylka iyo rajada ah.","answer":"Naftaydaay gacalo:Mararka qaar Ilaahay innama siiyo wax aynu weyddiisannay, si uu inoogu beddelo wax kale oo ka sii wanaagsan. Marar badan ma garan karno sababta ducooyinkeenna qaar loo aqbalo kuwo kalena loo aqbali waayo. Waxa qudha ee aan ogahay waa in Ilaahay uu ina jecel yahay, qaddarkeennana uu inoojeexay isagu; marar badanna innaga oo aan xitaa fahansanayn sida ay wax u dhici doonaan waa in aynu ku kalsoonaannaa.Ku noolow noloshaada jacayl, oo ku kalsoonow Ilaahay si uu kuugu hanuuniyo waddada saxda ah.Wanaag badan ayaan kuu rajaynayaa naftaydaay."},{"question":"Inona avy ireo karazana rahona lehibe hita eny amin'ny lanitra?","answer":"Ny karazana rahona lehibe hita eny amin'ny lanitra dia cumulus, cirrus, stratus ary nimbus."},{"question":"Berikan resipi untuk lala masak pedas cili padi dengan langkah-langkah yang terperinci. ","answer":"Bahan: 1 kg lala, 5 ulas bawang putih, 4 biji bawang merah, 8 biji cili padi, 2 batang serai, 1 inci halia, 2 sudu makan sos cili, 2 sudu besar sos tiram, Sedikit air atau pes asam jawa, Garam dan gula secukup rasa, Minyak masak untuk menumisCara penyediaan:1. Rendam lala dalam air garam selama 10 minit untuk mengeluarkan pasir. Kemudian bersihkan dan bilas.2. Kisar bawang putih, bawang besar, halia, cili padi dan serai.Cara memasak:1. Panaskan minyak dalam kuali dan tumiskan bawang merah, bawang putih, serai dan cili padi sehinggawangi.2. Masukkan sos cili, sos tiram dan air asam jawa.3. Masukkan lala dan masak sehingga lala terbuka, dalam kira-kira 3-5 minit.4. Perasakan dengan garam, gula dan serbuk perasa jika perlu. Gaul rata. Tambahkan air sekiranya inginberkuah.5. Padamkan api dan angkat."},{"question":"ஆண்டுதோறும் திருமந்திரம் மாநாடு நடத்தும் மடம் எது?","answer":"ஆண்டுதோறும் திருமந்திரம் மாநாடு நடத்தும் மடம் திருவாவடுதுறை ஆதினம் ஆகும்.திருக்கயிலாய பரம்பரைத் திருவாவடுதுறை ஆதீனம் தென் இந்தியாவிலுள்ள சைவ ஆதீனங்களில் முதன்மையான ஆதீனமாகும். இது மயிலாடுதுறை மாவட்டம் குத்தாலம் வட்டத்தில் மயிலாடுதுறை-கும்பகோணம் சாலையில் திருவாலங்காட்டிலிருந்து சுமார் இரண்டு கிலோ மீட்டர் தொலைவில் அமைந்துள்ளது.திருக்கயிலாய பரம்பரை குருமரபில் தழைத்தோங்கி வருகின்ற இவ்வாதீனம் ஸ்ரீ மெய்கண்டாரின் வழிவழி சித்தர் சிவப்பிரகாசரிடம் ஞானோபதேசம் பெற்ற அருள்திரு நமசிவாய மூர்த்திகள் அவர்களால் கி.பி. 14-ஆம் நூற்றாண்டில் தோற்றுவிக்கப்பெற்றது. சித்தர் சிவப்பிரகாசர், அருள் நமசிவாயரிடம் தீட்சை பெற்றவர். அருள் நமச்சிவாயர், உமாபதி சிவாச்சாரியாரிடம் உபதேசம் பெற்றவர்."},{"question":"* ما هو العسجد؟","answer":"الذهب"},{"question":"O que significa o ditado popular: \\"Nem tanto ao mar nem tanto à terra\\"?","answer":"Esse ditado é utilizado para referir-se ao equilíbrio. É preciso fazer as coisas com moderação, sem exageros, nem muito para mais nem muito para menos.Exemplo: “Essa roupa tá adequada para a festa, nem tanto ao mar nem tanto à terra.”"},{"question":"Tulis satu karangan yang membincangkan cara-cara memupuk amalan gaya hidup yang sihat. ","answer":"Mutakhir ini, isu kesihatan seringkali menjadi topik perbincangan di kaca televisyen dan dada-dada akhbar. Kebanyakan anggota-anggota masyarakat kita menghidap penyakit yang menjejaskan kesihatan mereka sehingga boleh meragut nyawa. Malah Tinjauan Kebangsaan Kesihatan dan Morbiditi (NHMS) tahun 2019 menyatakan bahawa peratusan penghidap obesiti dalam kalangan dewasa di Malaysia adalah tertinggi di rantau Asia Tenggara. Fakta yang menggerunkan ini perlu diubah dengan menggalakkan seluruh masyarakat di tanah air ini untuk mengamalkan gaya hidup sihat. Mekanisme ini bukan sahaja dapat mengurangkan risiko menghidap obesiti tetapi ia juga menyumbang kepda pengurangan risiko menghidapi penyakit berbahaya lain seperti penyakit jantung, obesiti, darah tinggi dan kencing manis. Oleh itu, hal ini sangat penting untuk kita memupuk amalan gaya hidup yang sihat dalam kalangan masyarakat di Malaysia.Langkah pertama untuk mengamalkan gaya hidup yang sihat adalah dengan menjaga kebersihan diri dan persekitaran. Perkara asas seperti mandi, menggosok gigi, memakai pakaian yang bersih dan kemas serta mendapatkan tidur atau rehat yang cukup adalah mustahak untuk diamalkan. Disiplin ini sedikit sebanyak dapat mendorong kita untuk melakukan aktiviti gaya hidup seihat yang lain. Tambahan pula, menjaga kebersihan persekitaran khususnya di kawasan tempat tinggal kita dapat menghindari daripada penyakit-penyakit berjangkit seperti deman denggi dan keracunan makanan. Sebagai contoh, sebelum menjamu selera, kita hendaklah mencuci tangan dengan bersih dan menutup makanan atau lauk-pauk dengan betul supaya tidak dihinggapi lalat. Segelintir di antara ahli masyarakat bersikap sambil lewa apabila menjaga kebersihan sehingga membawa padah kepada diri dan juga masyarakat persekitaran. Tegasnya, menjaga kebersihan diri dan persekitaran adalah disiplin yang diperlukan untuk mengamalkan gaya hidup yang sihat.Inisiatif lain yang utama dalam mengamalkan gaya hidup sihat adalah dengan pemakanan yang seimbang. Semua sedia maklum bahawa makanan merupakan elemen penting dalam memastikan kesihatan kita berada di tahap yang terbaik. Berdasarkan piramid makanan yang disarankan oleh Kementerian Kesihatan Malaysia, kita digalakkan untuk memakan hidangan yang mengandungi kandungan karbohirat, sayur-sayuran dan buah-buahan yang tinggi. Manakala makanan yang mempunyai protein seperti ikan, ayam, daging serta produk tenusu dalam pula diambil dalam kandungan yang sederhana. Makanan yang mengandungi lemak, minyak, gula dan garam yang tinggi hendaklah dikurangkan. Dengan pengambilan zat dan nutrien yang cukup, nescaya tubuh badan kita akan menjadi lebih sihat dan cergas. Masyarakat hari ini lebih gemar untuk memakan makanan restoran segera serta makanan yang telah diproses kerana menjimatkan masa, tenaga dan mendapat hidangan yang sedap. Tetapi jika diambil dengan kerap, ia pasti menjejaskan kesihatan diri. Izharnya, pemakanan yang seimbang ialah ciri-ciri penting dalam amalan gaya hisup sihat.Pada masa yang sama, amalan gaya hidup sihat perlu dilengkapi dengan penyertaan dalam aktiviti sukan atau rekreasi. Apabila seseorang bersukan, ia dapat membantu individu tersebut membakar kalori dan lemak, mengeluarkan peluh atau toksin dari badan serta membina otot yang penting untuk pertumbuhan badan. Secara tidak langsung ia dapat meningkatkan imunisasi dan ketahanan diri. Setiap di antara kita hanya perlu meluangkan masa sekurang-kurangnya 30 minit sehari untuk beriadah atau bersukan. Pastikan anda melakukan aktiviti yang sesuai dengan kemampuan diri masing-masing di mana golongan warga emas boleh beriadah hanya dengan berjoging atau melakukan senam robik manakala golongan dewasa dan kanak-kanak boleh bersukan dan sebagainya. Jelas bahawa amalan gaya hidup sihat adalah penyertaan aktiviti sukan atau rekreasi yang memberikan pelbagai manfaat lain khususnya dari aspek kesihatan.Akhir sekali, kita digalakkan melakukan pemeriksaan kesihatan secara berkala sebagai amalan gaya hidup sihat. Umum mengetahui bahawa kita memiliki fasiliti kesihatan awam yang berpatutan dan wajar dimanfaatkan oleh semua lapisan masyarakat. Ibu dan bapa boleh membawa anak-anak untuk melakukan pemeriksaan kesihatan di klinik kesihatan yang dibina hampir di setiap daerah seluruh Malaysia. Pemeriksaan seperti tekanan darah, paras gula dalam darah dan tahap kolesterol serta pemeriksaan gigi boleh dilakukan enam bulan sekali atau dua kali setahun. Jika kita menghidapi penyakit tanpa sedar, tindakan ini dapat membantu kita untuk mengesan tanda-tanda awal dan merawatnya sebelum sakit yang lebih kronik menyerang. Persis kata peribahasa, ingat antara belum kena, hemat antara belum habis. Intihannya, melakukan pemeriksaan kesihatan adalah salah satu gaya hidup yang sihat.Kesimpulannya, banyak usaha dan cara untuk mengamalkan gaya hidup yang sihat oleh masyarakat pada hari ini. Kita perlu membuka mata dan melihat kepentingan dan kesan menjaga kesihatan kepada diri, keluarga, masyarakat dan juga negara. Sekiranya masyarakat berjaya mengamalkan gaya hidup sihat, pasti fasiliti kesihatan tidak dipenuhi pesakit sebaliknya fasiliti sukan dan rekreasi menjadi tumpuan dan pusat komuniti utama untuk negara. Selain itu, masyarakat yang sihat dari setiap aspek fizikal dan mental akan melahirkan individu yang berketrampilan tinggi dan disegani ramai. Hasilnya kelak, generasi masa hadapan kita mampu memacu negara ke arah yang lebih baik. Peribahasa melayu berkata, hendak seribu daya, tak hendak seribu dalih. Semoga setiap usaha untuk menjadikan amalan gaya hidup sihat sebagai satu rutin dalam diri setiap individu disokong dan memberikan hasil yang diingankan."},{"question":"Ba mhaith liom foghlaim conas a bheith ina ghrianghrafadóir? Cén cineál ceamara ba chóir dom a cheannach? ","answer":"Sílim go bhfuil tú ag dul chun féachaint ar ceamara digiteach a fháil, le scáthán SLR atá i ndáiríre éadrom, ionas gur féidir leat é a iompar leat cibé áit a théann tú. Molaim freisin lionsa mór-uillinn maith a cheannach, toisc gur lionsa coitianta é sin a úsáideann go leor grianghrafadóirí gairmiúla."},{"question":"Sheeg magaca jaziirada Afrika ugu weyn?","answer":"Waa jaziirada loo yaqaano Madagaskar"},{"question":"කමත් බසෙන් ඵළවෙනවා  යනු කුමක්ද?","answer":"පොත්ත ඉවත්වෙනවා "},{"question":"යාච්ඤාව යනු කුමක්ද?","answer":"යාච්ඤාවේ මූලිකම නිර්වචනය (විග්‍රහය) වන්නේ “දෙවියන්වහන්සේ සමඟ කතා කිරීම” යන්නයි. යාච්ඤාව භාවනාවක් හෝ නිෂ්ක්‍රීය පරාවර්තනයක් නොවේ; එය දෙවියන්වහන්සේට සෘජු ආමන්ත්‍රණයකි. එය ආත්මය මැවූ ස්වාමින්වහන්සේ සමඟ මිනිස් ආත්මය සන්නිවේදනය කිරීමයි. යේසුස් ක්‍රිස්තුස් වහන්සේ තුළ ඇදහිලිවන්තයෙකුට තම හැඟීම් සහ ආශාවන් දෙවියන්වහන්සේ සමඟ සන්නිවේදනය කිරීමට සහ දෙවියන්වහන්සේ සමඟ ඇසුරු කිරීමට ඇති මූලික මාර්ගය යාච්ඤාවයි. යාච්ඤාව යනු කිතුණුවකුගේ දෙවියන්වහන්සේ සමඟ සන්නිවේදනය කිරීමේ මාර්ගයයි. අපි දෙවියන්වහන්සේට ප්‍රශංසා කිරීමටත්, උන්වහන්සේට ස්තුති කිරීමටත්, අප උන්වහන්සේට කොතරම් ප්‍රේම කරනවාදැයි කියන්නටත් යාච්ඤා කරමු. උන්වහන්සේගේ පැමිණීම භුක්ති විඳීමට සහ අපගේ ජීවිතයේ සිදුවෙමින් පවතින දේ උන්වහන්සේට පවසන ලෙස අපි යාච්ඤා කරමු. ඉල්ලීම් කිරීමට සහ මඟ පෙන්වීම් ලබා ගැනීමට සහ ප්‍රඥාව ඉල්ලා සිටීමට අපි යාච්ඤා කරමු. දෙවියන්වහන්සේ තම දරුවන් සමඟ මෙම හුවමාරුවට ප්‍රිය කරයි, අප අපගේ දරුවන් සමඟ ඇති හුවමාරුවට ප්‍රිය කරනවා සේම. දෙවියන්වහන්සේ සමඟ ඇසුරු කිරීම යාච්ඤාවේ හදවතයි. බොහෝ විට යාච්ඤාව කෙතරම් සරල විය යුතුද යන්න අපට නොපෙනී යයි."},{"question":"इस श्रेणी में ट्रिविया का एक उदाहरण दीजिए: संगीत","answer":"एक उदाहरण संगीत से संबंधित ट्रिविया का है: गीत \\"हैप्पी बर्थडे टू यू,\\" विश्व में सबसे अधिक बार गाया जाने वाला और सबसे अधिक बजाया जाने वाला गीत माना जाता है।"},{"question":"다음 단락을 완성해주세요. 스탠윅스 요새는 1758년 8월 26일 식민지 시대에 영국군 존 스탠윅스 장군의 지휘로 오늘날의 뉴욕 로움에 지어지기 시작한 요새이다. 그러나 완공된 것은 4년 후인 1762년이었다. 처음에는","answer":"프렌치 인디언 전쟁 동안 ‘오나이다 수송지’(\\"Oneida Carrying Place\\")로 알려진 육로를 지키기 위해 건설되었다. 지금은 국립공원국에 의해 새로 지어진 스탠윅스 요새 국립 기념물이 그 자리를 차지하고 있다."},{"question":"أنشئ جملة جديدة استنادًا إلى الجملة التالية \\"لا أستطيع أن أصدق ذلك\\" . ","answer":"يصعب عليّ تصديق ذلك!."},{"question":"కింద ఇచ్చిన పదంతో వాక్య ప్రయోగం చెయ్యండి:శ్రద్ధాసక్తులు","answer":"చదువుపట్ల శ్రద్ధాసక్తులు ప్రదర్శించే వారు విజయాన్ని పొందుతారు."},{"question":"Que sont les taches solaires ?","answer":"Des régions du Soleil plus froides et plus sombres que le reste de la surface : voilà ce que sont les « taches » solaires. Il ne s'agit pas de « continents » comme ceux de la Terre : les taches changent d'aspect et de place au rythme de l'activité solaire. Le soleil arbore des taches parce qu'il se comporte comme un immense aimant. En agissant sur lui-même, il empêche certaines régions de sa surface de rayonner correctement leur lumière."},{"question":"Ali bin Yusuf yana ɗan shekara nawa ne a lokacin da ya gaji mahaifinsa?","answer":"Yana da shekaru 23 a duniya."},{"question":"Quais foram as principais contribuições de Ahmed Zewail para a química?","answer":"Ahmed Zewail recebeu o Prêmio Nobel de Química em 1999 por suas contribuições para o desenvolvimento da espectroscopia de femtossegundos, permitindo a observação de processos ultra-rápidos em escala atômica."},{"question":"Efe Ajagba gba ife-ẹyẹ kẹrinla lagbo ẹṣẹ kikan","answer":"Ọmọ ilẹ wa to n ṣe bẹbẹ lagbo ẹṣẹ kikan lagbaaye, Efe Ajagba, ti gba ami-ẹyẹ kẹrinla bayii lẹyin to na Jonnie Rice ilẹ Amẹrika lalẹ ana ni gbọngan The Bubble, to wa ni Vegas, nilẹ Amẹrika.Lẹyin ipele kẹwaa ija naa lawọn adajọ mẹtẹẹta, iyẹn Max DeLuca, Adalaide Byrd ati Dave Moretti, sọ pe Efe lo jawe olubori.Eyi nigba keji tawọn adajọ yoo fimọ ṣọkan lati fun ọkunrin ẹni ọdun mẹrindinlọgbọn naa lami-ẹyẹ, igba akọkọ ni ija to ba Ali Eren Demirezen ja loṣu keje, ọdun to kọja.Ṣugbọn ki i ṣe pe ija naa rọrun fun Efe rara, Jonnie naa fi gbogbo agbara ja, nnkan ko kan ṣẹnuure fun un ni.Oriire tuntun yii ni ija kẹrinla fun Efe, gbogbo ẹ lo si ti yege, bẹẹ lo fi ẹṣẹ gbe awọn alatako ẹ ṣubu nigba mọkanla."},{"question":"මාතර බලකොටුව ගැන විස්තරයක් කරන්න. ","answer":"මාතර බලකොටුව 1560 වර්ෂයේදී පෘතුගීසීන් විසින් ඉදිකරන ලද්දකි. ලන්දේසින් විසින් ගාල්ල අත්පත් කර ගැනීමෙන් අනතුරුව 1640 වසරේදීද බලකොටුව යලි ගොඩනැංවුණි"},{"question":"కింద ఇచ్చిన మొదటి పేరా మరియు చివరి పేరా అనుసరించు మధ్య పేరా రాయండి:మొదటి పేరా:సృజనాత్మకతకు అవధుల్లేవు : 1949 నుండి శంకర్స్ అంతర్జాతీయ విద్యార్థుల పోటీ ప్రతి ఏడాదీ జరుగుతుంది. శంకర్స్ పోటీలో 68 దేశాలకు చెందిన పిల్లలు పాల్గొన్నారు. వారు చిత్రించిన చిత్రలేఖనాలతో ఉన్న 55వ సంపుటిని కలాం చూసి ఆశ్చర్యపోయారు. ఆ పిల్లలు తమ చిత్రలేఖనాల్లో, కవితల్లో, కథల్లో, వ్యాసాల్లో చూపించిన ప్రతిభ ఆయన్ని అబ్బురపరచింది. ప్రపంచంలో పెద్దవాళ్లు, వయోజనులు దేశాల గురించి, సరిహద్దుల గురించి, కులాల గురించి, మతాల గురించి, పేదల గురించి, ధనికుల గురించి మాట్లాడుతుండగా పిల్లలు చేసిన కృషి మాత్రం సరిహద్దులకూ, అవధులకూ అతీతంగా ఆయనకు కనిపించింది.చివరి పేరా:పదమూడేళ్ల అర్ధాకృష్ణ తన ఆలోచన అనే ఆకాశంలో స్వేచ్ఛగా విహరించింది. క్రీ.శ. 3000 సంవత్సరంలో ఈ భూమి ఎలా ఉంటుందో ఊహించే ప్రయత్నం చేసింది. అప్పుడు ఈ ప్రపంచ పౌరులు, అంగారక గ్రహానికి వలసపోయి అక్కడొక కొత్త నాగరికతను నిర్మించుకుంటారనీ, అంతలో బృహస్పతి గ్రహంనుండి అంగారకుడి మీదికి రాబోయే ఒక ఏస్టరాయడ్ వల్ల మొత్తం మానవాళి నశించే ప్రమాదమేర్పడుతుందనీ ఆమె ఊహించింది. అప్పుడు అంగారకగ్రహంమీద ఉండే శాస్త్రవేత్తలు తమమీద విరుచుకుపడబోతున్న ఏస్టరాయడును అణుశరపరంపర ద్వారా విచ్ఛేదపరుస్తారని ఆమె చెప్పింది. ఆవిధంగా క్రీ.శ. 3000 లలో అంగారక నాగరికత ప్రాకృతిక ఆగ్రహానికి ఎదురు నిలిచి జీవించగలుగుతుందనీ ఆమె విశ్వాసం ప్రకటిస్తుంది. అర్ధాకృష్ణ శాస్త్రీయ ఆలోచన ఎంత సుందరంగా కొత్తగా ఉంది అని అబ్దుల్ కలాం గుర్తు చేసుకున్నారు.","answer":"పిల్లల హృదయం అత్యంత పరిశుద్ధంగా, అన్ని విభజనశీల మనస్తత్వాలకూ అతీతంగా కనిపించింది. మానవాళి భవిష్యత్తుకు మనలో ఆశను పెంచేది పిల్లల ప్రపంచం మాత్రమే అని, వాళ్ల చేతుల్లో ఈ భూగోళం భద్రంగా ఉండగలదని వారికి నమ్మకం కలిగింది."},{"question":" Inona no biby mampinono an-dranomasina lehibe indrindra?","answer":"Ny trozona manga no biby mampinono an-dranomasina lehibe indrindra."},{"question":"Ilang oras dapat pakuluan ang nilagang itlog?","answer":"Pwedeng pakuluan ang itlog ng mga 5-6 minuto kung gusto ng malambot na pula ng itlog o 10-12 minuto kung gusto ng matigas sa gitna."},{"question":"दिवाली के अवसर पर आपको एक छोटा सा निबंध लिखना है।  ","answer":"दिवाली के इस विशेष त्योहार के लिए हिंदू धर्म के लोग बहुत उत्सुकता से इंतजार करते हैं। यह बच्चों से लेकर बड़ों तक के लिए हर किसी का सबसे महत्वपूर्ण और पसंदीदा त्यौहार है। दीवाली भारत का सबसे महत्वपूर्ण और मशहूर त्यौहार है। जो पूरे देश में साथ-साथ हर साल मनाया जाता है। रावण को पराजित करने के बाद, 14 साल के निर्वासन के लंबे समय के बाद भगवान राम अपने राज्य अयोध्या में लौटे थे। लोग आज भी इस दिन को बहुत उत्साहजनक तरीके से मनाते हैं। भगवान राम के लौटने वाले दिन, अयोध्या के लोगों ने अपने घरों और मार्गों को बड़े उत्साह के साथ अपने भगवान का स्वागत करने के लिए प्रकाशित किया था। यह एक पवित्र हिंदू त्यौहार है जो बुरेपन पर अच्छाई की जीत का प्रतीक है। यह सिखों द्वारा भी मुगल सम्राट जहांगीर द्वारा ग्वालियर जेल से अपने 6 वें गुरु, श्री हरगोबिंद जी की रिहाई मनाने के लिए मनाया जाता है।इस दिन बाजारों को एक दुल्हन की तरह रोशनी से सजाया जाता है ताकि वह इससे एक अद्भुत त्यौहार दिख सके। इस दिन बाजार बड़ी भीड़ से भरा होता है, विशेष रूप से मीठाई की दुकानें। बच्चों को बाजार से नए कपड़े, पटाखे, मिठाई, उपहार, मोमबत्तियां और खिलौने मिलते हैं। लोग अपने घरों को साफ करते हैं और त्योहार के कुछ दिन पहले रोशनी से सजाते हैं। हिन्दू कैलेंडर के अनुसार सूर्यास्त के बाद लोग देवी लक्ष्मी और भगवान गणेश की पूजा करते हैं। वे अधिक आशीर्वाद, स्वास्थ्य, धन और उज्जवल भविष्य पाने के लिए भगवान और देवी से प्रार्थना करते हैं। वे दिवाली त्यौहार के सभी पांच दिनों में खाद्य पदार्थों और मिठाई के स्वादिष्ट व्यंजन बनाते हैं। लोग इस दिन पासा, कार्ड गेम और कई अन्य प्रकार के खेल खेलते हैं। वे अच्छी गतिविधियों के करीब आते हैं और बुरी आदतों को दूर करते हैं।पहले दिन धनतेरस या धन्त्ररावदाशी के रूप में जाना जाता है जिसे देवी लक्ष्मी की पूजा करके मनाया जाता है। लोग देवी को खुश करने के लिए आरती, भक्ति गीत और मंत्र गाते हैं। दूसरे दिन नरका चतुर्दशी या छोटी दिवाली के रूप में जाना जाता है जिसे भगवान कृष्ण की पूजा करके मनाया जाता है क्योंकि उन्होंने राक्षस राजा नारकसुर को मार डाला था। तीसरे दिन मुख्य दिवाली दिवस के रूप में जाना जाता है जिसे शाम को रिश्तेदारों, दोस्तों, पड़ोसियों और जलती हुई फायर क्रैकर्स के बीच मिठाई और उपहार वितरित करते हुए देवी लक्ष्मी की पूजा करके मनाया जाता है। चौथे दिन भगवान कृष्ण की पूजा करके गोवर्धन पूजा के रूप में जाना जाता है। लोग अपने दरवाजे पर पूजा करकेगोबर के गोवर्धन बनाते हैं। पांचवें दिन यम द्वितिया या भाई दौज के रूप में जाना जाता है जिसे भाइयों और बहनों द्वारा मनाया जाता है। बहनों ने अपने भाइयों को भाई दौज के त्यौहार का जश्न मनाने के लिए आमंत्रित करती हैं।"},{"question":"Cari aspek dan polaritas sentimen dari kalimat ulasan di bawah ini. Berikan jawaban beserta penjelasan atau pointer kalimat atau frasa (bagian kalimat) dari tiap-tiap aspek sentimen tersebut.Kalimat ulasan:Restoran Sunda yang sangat recommended di tengah Kota Bandung. Suasananya sangat menyenangkan, terasa nuansa Sunda-nya.Pilihan makanan dan minumannya sangat banyak dengan rentang harga yang bervariasi juga. Rasa makanannya pun enak, kaya bumbu, dan porsi nya besar.Jawaban:","answer":"1. aspek: lokasi - sentimen: positifKalimat: Restoran Sunda yang sangat recommended di tengah Kota Bandung.Frasa: sangat recommended di tengah Kota Bandung2. aspek: suasana - sentimen: positifKalimat: Suasananya sangat menyenangkan, terasa nuansa Sunda-nya.Frasa: Suasananya sangat menyenangkan3. aspek: makanan - sentimen: positifKalimat: Rasa makanannya pun enak, kaya bumbu, dan porsi nya besar.Frasa:- pilihan makanan dan minumannya sangat banyak- Rasa makanannya pun enak- kaya bumbu- porsi nya besar4. aspek: harga - sentimen: positifKalimat: Pilihan makanan dan minumannya sangat banyak dengan rentang harga yang bervariasi juga.Frasa: rentang harga yang bervariasi"},{"question":"l = 3 విలువ గల ఆర్బిటాళ్ళలో నిండగల గరిష్ఠ ఎలక్ట్రాన్ల సంఖ్యA) 6B) 10C) 14D) 18","answer":"C) 14"},{"question":"Escreva uma continuação para este parágrafo - Embora originalmente sendo predominantemente um estereótipo americano, a cultura tem crescido em todo o mundo e é agora mais aceitável e comum do que nunca. Os eventos australianos, como Oz Comic Con, uma grande convenção de histórias em quadrinhos e cosplay, e Supanova Expo, são eventos incrivelmente populares entre a cultura de pessoas que se identificam como nerds. Em 2016,","answer":"a Oz Comic Con em Perth viu quase 20.000 cos-players e fãs de quadrinhos se reúnem para comemorar o evento."},{"question":"以下の段落に関連する内容を記入しなさい： 日本では、お葬式などで、亡くなった人が入ったひつぎの近くに行ってお別れをすることがあります。 消費者庁によると、ひつぎの中に顔を入れた人が亡くなる事故が3件ありました。ひつぎの中を冷やすために入れるドライアイスは、気体の二酸化炭素になります。消費者庁は、この二酸化炭素を吸ったため中毒になって事故が起こったと考えています。","answer":"国民生活センターが、ひつぎに10kgのドライアイスを入れて実験をしました。ふたを閉めると、二酸化炭素は20分で、吸うと意識がなくなる濃度になりました。 そのあと、ふたを開けても、なかなか濃度は下がりませんでした。 このため消費者庁は、お別れのときに、ひつぎに顔を入れないように言っています。部屋の空気を十分に入れ替えることにも気をつけてほしいと言っています。"},{"question":"Sebutkan 3 jenis enzim yang dihasilkan oleh pankreas beserta fungsinya!","answer":"Tiga jenis enzim yang dihasilkan oleh pankreas adalah sebagai berikut:•\\tLipase = reaksi pengubahan lemak menjadi asam lemak dan gliserol•\\tTripsin = reaksi pengubahan pepton menjadi asam amino•\\tAmilase = reaksi pengubahan amilum menjadi maltosa"},{"question":"පහත වචනයට අදාළ විරුද්ධ පද කුමක්ද?ආරාධිත ","answer":"අනාරාධිත"},{"question":"පහත  නාම පදයට අදාළ ස්ත්‍රී ලිංග නාම පාදක කුමක්ද?මොනරා ","answer":"සෙබඩ "},{"question":"Give me an example of trivia in this category: sports","answer":"Sure! Here's an example of a sports trivia question:Who holds the record for the most home runs hit in a single season in Major League Baseball?A) Babe RuthB) Barry BondsC) Mark McGwireD) Sammy SosaCorrect answer: B) Barry Bonds (73 home runs in the 2001 season)"},{"question":"Fan mooy gëblag réewum Serbi","answer":" Gëblag réewum Serbi mu ngi tudd Belgraad"},{"question":"Inona no mozika klasika malaza noforonin'i Ludwig van Beethoven ary antsoina matetika hoe \\"Symphony of Destiny\\"?","answer":"Ny mozika klasika malaza noforonin'i Ludwig van Beethoven ary antsoina matetika hoe \\"Symphony of Destiny\\" dia ny \\"Symphony No. 5\\"."},{"question":"Kailangan ba mag pa checkup kung nag fever?","answer":"Depende sa kundisyon sa patiente, pwede ra ma ayo ang fever pama-agi sa pagpahulay ug mag-tumar ug tambal.Hinundumi na kailangan magpa konsulta ug duktor."},{"question":"What is Fertility?","answer":"Getting pregnant can be an exciting time. For some, getting pregnant seems to happen simply by talking about it. For others, getting pregnant takes patience and perhaps a bit of luck.Understanding when you're most fertile can make getting pregnant easier. It's also important to consider the simple dos and don'ts of conception. For example, maintain a healthy weight and have sex regularly, especially near the time of ovulation. Don't smoke or drink alcohol. Of course, healthy sperm counts, too.With frequent unprotected sex, most healthy couples conceive within one year. If you have trouble getting pregnant, don't go it alone. A fertility specialist or other health care provider might be able to help. Infertility affects men and women equally, and treatment is available."},{"question":"كم مرة ذكر اسم جبريل عليه السلام في القرآن الكريم؟.\\t","answer":"ثلاث مرات."},{"question":"Choisissez 3 villes pour des vacances d'une semaine en Italie.","answer":"Voici trois villes pour passer 1 semaine de vacances en Italie, toutes situées dans la même région géographique :Rome:La capitale de l'Italie est riche en histoire, en art et en monuments emblématiques. Vous pouvez explorer le Colisée, le Forum romain, la Cité du Vatican (y compris la basilique Saint-Pierre et la chapelle Sixtine) et déguster une cuisine italienne authentique dans de charmantes trattorias.Florence:Florence est réputée pour son art et son architecture de la Renaissance. Vous pouvez visiter la Galerie des Offices, voir le David de Michel-Ange à la Galerie de l'Académie, vous promener sur le Ponte Vecchio et explorer les charmantes places de la ville.Venise :Venise est célèbre pour ses canaux uniques, son architecture historique et son atmosphère romantique. Vous pouvez faire une promenade en gondole le long du Grand Canal, visiter la place et la basilique Saint-Marc, explorer le palais des Doges et vous perdre dans les charmantes ruelles."},{"question":"\\"Ny epistilin'i Paoly ho an'ny Romana dia ampahany amin'ny Testamenta Vaovao ary miresaka lohahevitra teolojika lalina momba ny fahasoavana, ny finoana ary ny fanamarinana.\\"Inona ny fanontaniana azo tsogaina amin'io andian-teny io?","answer":"Fanontaniana: Iza no mpanoratra ny Romana ao amin'ny Testamenta Vaovao?"},{"question":"Sheeg astaamaha xanuunka qaaxada (TB) Iyo dadka u nugul ?","answer":"Qaaxo waa xanuun kamid ah kuwo ugu khatarta badan xanuunada faafa. Xanuun kaan waxaa uu saameeyaa in badan oo kamid ah dadka dunida ku nool gaar ahaan wadamada soo koroya. Difaaca jirka oo daciifa ayaa ah sabab kamid ah in loo nuglaado xanuunka qaaxada. Dadka qaba xanuunka Aids-ka ayaa ugu nugul, sababtoo ah feyruska HIV ayaa la dagaalama difaaca jirka kaasoo hoos udhiga awooda uu isaga celin karo waxyaabaha soo weerara jirka sida bakteeriyada ama fayrusyada.Qaaxada waxaa sababa bagteeriya loo yaqaano mycobacterium tuberculosis. Bakteeriyadan ayaa ah mid la isugu gudbiyo hawada, qofka qaba qaaxada sanbabada oo aan la daweyn ayaa ugugudbin kara qof kale sida hindhisada, qufaca iyo hadalkaba. Waxaa jirta qaaxo aan darneyn  oo si sahal ku faafta. Waxaa dhixi kara in qofku uu la nool yahay bakteeriyada sababta xanuunkaan laakin aan weli sababin wax astaamo ah, xiligan qaaxadu ma ahan mid faafta. Hadii aan la daweyn waxay isu badasha qaaxo leh astaamaheeda.Halista fududeysa in qaaxada waxaa ka mid ah, dadka qaba xanuunada la dagaalama difaaca jirka sida, aidska, kansarrada sonkoroowga/macaanka, fashilka kilyaha ku yimaada iyo daawooyinka loo isticmaalo kaankarada, daawooyinka la qaato markii xubin laga badalo bukaanka laguna talaalo xubin kale iyo nafaqa daradaba.Waa maxay astaamaha qaaxada?Astaamaha lagu garto xanuukaan waxaa kamid ah;Dhidid xiliga habeenkii ahQufac raaga ilaa 3 todobaad kaasoo mararka qaar uu dhiig la socdoXabad xanuunItaal yariQandhoQarqaryoCunada oo qofka ka hortimaadaMiisaanka oo yaraadaXanuun la dareemo marka neef la qaadanayo ama la qufacayo.Qaaxadu waxay kaloo saamaysaa xubno kala duwan oo jirka ah sida, xangulaha, kelyaha, maskaxda iyo xataa hab tarankaba. Astaamaha ay sababto xiliyadan waxay ku xiran tahay hadba xubinta ay saamaysay, tusaale hadii ay xungulaha saamayso waxaa qofku dareemaa dhabar xanuun.Bakteeriyada sababta xanuunka qaaxada ayaa qaar kamid ah daawooyinka awood u leh inay iska caabiso, taasoo aan si sahal ah loo ciribtiri karin. Inta badan waxaa lagu daweeyaa daawooyin soconaya ilaa saddex isbuuc ilaa 6 bilood si loo ciribtiro bakteeriyada.Talo:Waxaa aad u hagaag san in qofka qaba xanuun kaan laga ilaaliyo inuu dhex galo bulshada ama xubnaha qoyskiisa ilaa ay daawadu u dhamaanayso ama uu wado ugu yaraan 2 todobaad. Hadaad isku aragto wax calaamad ah oo muujinaya xanuunkaan fadlan booqo dhakhtar."},{"question":"UC Merced的校园环境如何？","answer":"答：UC Merced位于加利福尼亚州中部，校园环境优美，周围有许多自然风光和户外活动场所。"},{"question":"\\"උගත්කමට ආඩම්බර වීම තරම් නූගත්කමක් නැත.\\"මෙම ප්‍රකාශය කරන ලද්දේ කවුරුන් විසින්ද?","answer":"ඉහත ප්‍රකාශය සිදු කරන ලද්දේ හිටපු ඇමරිකානු ජනාධිපතිවරයෙකු වන ඒබ්‍රහම් ලින්කන් විසිනි."},{"question":"පහත තේරවිල්ල විසඳන්න.ගසට නමකි මල පිපුනම වෙන නමකිගැටයට නමකි ලොකු වෙනකොට නමකිගෙඩියට නමකි ගෙඩි ඉදුනම වෙන නමකිමෙතුන් පදේ තෝරාලා කියන් සකි","answer":"ගසට කොස් කියයි මලනම් පනා  නොවේදෝගැටයට පොලොස් ලොකු වෙනකොට නිකිනි නොවේදෝගෙඩියට කොස් ඉදුනම වරකා  නොවේදෝමෙතුන් පදේ තේරුවෙ මෙලෙස නොවේදෝ"},{"question":" வினா : அரசியல் தத்துவத்தின் தந்தைஎன  அழைக்கப்படுபவர் யார்?","answer":"விடை :  பிளேட்டோ                    "},{"question":"Энчилүү жана жалпы зат атоочтор булар ... ","answer":"Бардык зат атооч сөздөр заттарды атоо касиети боюнча энчилүү жана жалпы аттар болуп экиге бөлүнөт.   ❕__Жалпы аттар__ бир тектеги заттарды, жан-жаныбарларды жалпы жонунан атайт: киши, бала, небере, карышкыр, шаар, китеп   ❕__Энчилүү аттар__ бир тектеш заттардын, жан-жаныбарлардын ичинен бирөөнү бөлүп көрсөтөт. Башкача айтканда, затка, жаныбарга, көбүнчө адамга энчиленип коюлат.   ❕Энчилүү зат атоочторго адамдардын, жер -суу, адабий чыгармалардын, тарыхый чыгармалардын, жаныбарлардын аттары жана географиялык аттар да кирет.     ❗️Жазууда энчилүү аттар менен жалпы аттар бири-биринен айырмаланышат. Энчилүү аттар сүйлөмдүн кайсы жеринде келбесин (башына, ортосуна, аягына) дайыма баш тамга менен жазылат.   ❗️__Географиялык татаал энчилүү аттар өз өзүнчө жазылат:__   Ала-Арча, Ала-Бука, Ак-Талаа, Ысык-Көл, Ысык-Ата.    ❗️__Географиялык жөнөкөй энчилүү аттар баш тамга менен жазылат:__   Алай, Ноокат, Каракол, Нарын ж.б   ❗️__Географиялык энчилүү аттарга ошол жерлик экендигин туюнтуучу -лык мүчөсү уланып айтылса, ал сөз кичине тамга менен жазылат:__Ысык-Көл//ысык-көлдүк, Нарын//нарындык.     ‼️Китеп, журнал, газета, сүрөт, күү, кино ж.б аттары баш тамга менен жазылып, тырмакчага алынат. "},{"question":"ෆුකුෂිමා: චීනයේ විරෝධය මැද ජපානය පිරිපහදු කළ න්‍යෂ්ටික ජලය මුහුදට මුදා හරී","answer":"ජපානය ෆුකුෂිමා න්‍යෂ්ටික බලාගාරයේ සිට පැසිෆික් සාගරයට පිරිපහදු කළ අපජලය මතභේදාත්මක ලෙස මුදා හැරීම ආරම්භ කිරීමත් සමග කලාපය තුළ විරෝධතා මතුව ඇති අතර චීනය විසින් ජපානයෙන් මුහුදු ආහාර ආනයනය සම්පූර්ණයෙන් නතර කරනු ලැබ තිබේ.එක්සත් ජාතීන්ගේ න්‍යෂ්ටික නිරීක්ෂණ ආයතනය වන ජාත්‍යන්තර පරමාණුක බලශක්ති ඒජන්සිය (IAEA) විසින් අනුමතකර තිබියදීත්, මෙම සැලැස්ම ජපානයේ ගැඹුරින් මතභේදයට තුඩු දී ඇති අතර ස්වදේශික ජනතාවද සාගර දූෂණය පිළිබඳ කනස්සල්ල පළ කර තිබේ.ජපානයේ ධීවර කර්මාන්තයේ නියැළෙන කණ්ඩායම් සහ ඒ ආසන්න පුළුල් කලාපයම සිය ජීවනෝපය ගැන කනස්සල්ලට පත්ව සිටින්නේ, පාරිභෝගිකයන් විසින් මුහුදු ආහාර මිලට ගැනීම නතර කරනු ඇතැයි යන බිය නිසාවෙනි.ජපානය විසින් සාගරය \\"පෞද්ගලික කුණුකාණුවක්\\" ලෙස සලකන බවට චීනය චෝදනා කරන අතර, ජාත්‍යන්තර පරමාණුක බලශක්ති ඒජන්සිය (IAEA) ද \\"ඒක පාර්ශවීය\\" ලෙස කටයුතු කරන බවට විවේචනය කරයි. දකුණු කොරියාවේ රජය සැලැස්මට විරෝධයක් නැතැයි ප්‍රකාශ කළ නමුත් එරට බොහෝ පුරවැසියෝ එයට විරෝධය දක්වති."},{"question":"Ku Malawi kuli madotolo angati?","answer":"Komanso, bungwe la ActionAid UK linanena kuti kuchokera ku kafukufuku waposachedwapa, apeza kuti m'dziko lonse la Malawi muli madokotala pafupifupi 600 omwe ali ndi anthu onse ogwira ntchito zachipatala. Achipatala okwana 600 wa m'Malawi muno ndiwo amayang'anira anthu 16 miliyoni a Malawi."},{"question":"Wọn tun n bakan bọ: Wọn ni ọga ọlọpaa pata ni yoo maa dari eto Amọtẹkun o","answer":"O da bii pe gbogbo eto yoowu ti awọn gomina ilẹ Yoruba ba ṣe lori ikọ Amọtẹkun ko ni i ṣiṣẹ bi ki i baa ṣe pe wọn tẹle ilana ti ọga awọn ọlọpaa patapta ba la kalẹ fun wọn. Ileeṣẹ aarẹ lo sọ bẹẹ, lati ọdọ ọkan ninu awọn agbẹnusọ ibẹ, Garba Shehu.Ọkunrin naa ni eto ti wa nilẹ ti ijọba Buhari ṣe fun awọn ọlọpaa ibilẹ, labẹ eto awọn ọlọpaa ibilẹ yii si ni ikọ bii ti awọn Amotẹkun bọ si, ohun yoowu ti ọga olopaa pata ba si ti la kalẹ fun wọn ni wọn yoo tẹ le, ẹnikẹni ti ko ba si tẹ le e yoo da ara rẹ lẹbi. Bẹẹ ni Garba wi.Bi ẹ ba ranti, lati igba tawọn ijọba ilẹ Yoruba gbogbo ti ronu Amọtẹkkun ti wọn si ti gbe eto rẹ jade ni awọn eeyan ijọba apapọ ko fi taratara fẹ kinni ọhun, ohun to si i fa a ti wọn fi sare da ohun ti wọn pe ni ọlọpaa ibilẹ silẹ ree, ti wọn ni awọn gangan ni araalu nilo, ki iṣe awọn Amọtẹkun kankan. Ọsẹ to kọja yii ni Buhari gbe owo bii bilionu mẹtala kalẹ pe ki wọn fi bẹrẹ eto agbekalẹ awọn olọpaa ibilẹ yii, to si jẹ awọn gomina ni yoo pada maa sanwo oṣu fawọn ti wọn ba gba siṣẹ ọhun.Bi Amọtẹkun yoo ṣe ṣiṣẹ labẹ eto ọlọpaa ibilẹ ati ọga ọlọpaa patapata lẹni kan ko ti i le sọ."},{"question":"文中の主な言葉を見つけて、その内容を説明しなさい。 大阪で2025年に、世界の国が文化や産業などを紹介する「大阪・関西万博」があります。万博に参加する56の国や地域は、万博で使う建物を自分たちで作る予定です。しかし、準備が遅れていて、工事を始めるために必要な書類を出したのは韓国だけです。博覧会協会は7日、建物の工事をする会社を集めて説明会を開きました。そして、どの会社に工事を頼むか決めた国や、会社と話し合いをしている国は、アメリカやカナダなど10ぐらいだと言いました。工事をする会社が決まらないのは、建物の形が複雑なためだと言われています。材料の値段や働く人の給料が上がっていることも、原因になっているようです。協会は、建物の形を変えたり工事に使うお金を増やしたりするように参加する国に言って、早く工事が進むようにしたいと考えています。","answer":"文にある主な言葉とその内容はこちらです。- 参加: 1）仲間に入ること。- 地域: 1）ある範囲に区切られた土地。- 工事: 1）建物・道路・橋などを造ったり、直したりすること。また、その仕事。- 書類: 1）書き物。必要なことを書き記した書きつけ。文書。- 話し合い: 1）話し合うこと。相談。- 材料: 1）物を作るもとになるもの。多くは、元の形や性質が残っている場合にいう。2）研究・表現などのもとになるもの。- 給料: 1）やとい主が、働いた人にはらうお金。給与。サラリー。- 協会: 1）ある目的のために、会員が力を合わせて作り、運営している会。- 増やし: 1）多くする。"},{"question":"واش حلال على المسلم يتزوج بنصرانية؟","answer":"نعم حلال عليه ولكن بالكراهة"},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਬ੍ਰਹਮ ਗਿਆਨੀ ਏਕ ਊਪਰਿ ਆਸ ॥ਬ੍ਰਹਮ ਗਿਆਨੀ ਕਾ ਨਹੀ ਬਿਨਾਸ ॥ਬ੍ਰਹਮ ਗਿਆਨੀ ਕੈ ਗਰੀਬੀ ਸਮਾਹਾ ॥ਬ੍ਰਹਮ ਗਿਆਨੀ ਪਰਉਪਕਾਰ ਉਮਾਹਾ ॥ਬ੍ਰਹਮ ਗਿਆਨੀ ਕੈ ਨਾਹੀ ਧੰਧਾ ॥ਬ੍ਰਹਮ ਗਿਆਨੀ ਲੇ ਧਾਵਤੁ ਬੰਧਾ ॥ਬ੍ਰਹਮ ਗਿਆਨੀ ਕੈ ਹੋਇ ਸੁ ਭਲਾ ॥ਬ੍ਰਹਮ ਗਿਆਨੀ ਸੁਫਲ ਫਲਾ ॥ਬ੍ਰਹਮ ਗਿਆਨੀ ਸੰਗਿ ਸਗਲ ਉਧਾਰੁ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਬ੍ਰਹਮ ਗਿਆਨੀ ਜਪੈ ਸਗਲ ਸੰਸਾਰੁ ॥੪॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 273 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਬ੍ਰਹਮਗਿਆਨੀ ਇਕ ਅਕਾਲ ਪੁਰਖ ਉਤੇ ਆਸ ਰੱਖਦਾ ਹੈ; ਬ੍ਰਹਮਗਿਆਨੀ (ਦੀ ਉੱਚੀ ਆਤਮਕ ਅਵਸਥਾ) ਦਾ ਕਦੇ ਨਾਸ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੁੰਦਾ ।ਬ੍ਰਹਮਗਿਆਨੀ ਦੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਗਰੀਬੀ ਟਿਕੀ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਦੂਜਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਭਲਾਈ ਕਰਨ ਦਾ (ਸਦਾ) ਚਾਉ (ਚੜ੍ਹਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ) ਹੈ ।ਬ੍ਰਹਮਗਿਆਨੀ ਦੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ (ਮਾਇਆ ਦਾ) ਜੰਜਾਲ ਨਹੀਂ ਵਿਆਪਦਾ, ਉਹ ਭਟਕਦੇ ਮਨ ਨੂੰ ਕਾਬੂ ਕਰ ਕੇ (ਮਾਇਆ ਵਲੋਂ) ਰੋਕ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਜੋ ਕੁਝ (ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਵਲੋਂ) ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਬ੍ਰਹਮਗਿਆਨੀ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਭਲਾ ਪ੍ਰਤੀਤ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਦਾ ਮਨੁੱਖਾ ਜਨਮ ਚੰਗੀ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਕਾਮਯਾਬ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਬ੍ਰਹਮਗਿਆਨੀ ਦੀ ਸੰਗਤਿ ਵਿਚ ਸਭ ਦਾ ਬੇੜਾ ਪਾਰ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! ਬ੍ਰਹਮਗਿਆਨੀ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ ਸਾਰਾ ਜਗਤ (ਹੀ) (ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ) ਜਪਣ ਲੱਗ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੪।\\""},{"question":"Fan moy péeyum réwum Maldives","answer":"Péeyum réwum Maldives mu ngi tudu Malé"},{"question":"Inona no niandohan'ny Revolisiona Madagasikara tamin'ny 1972, antsoina koa hoe Revolisiona Orange?","answer":"Ny Revolisiona Madagasikara tamin’ny 1972, antsoina koa hoe Revolisiona Orange noho ny loko mifandray amin’io hetsika io, dia hetsika lehibe teo amin’ny tantara politika teto Madagasikara. Ny disadisa ara-politika, ara-toekarena ary ara-tsosialy izay nitombo teo ambany fitondran’ny filoha Philibert Tsiranana no nahatonga izany.Anisan’ny niandohan’ny Revolisiona ny firongatry ny fahasorenan’ny vahoaka Malagasy amin’ny kolikoly, ny tsy rariny ara-toe-karena ary ny tsy fitantanam-panjakana. Nanomboka nanohitra ny fitondrana ny mpianatra, ny mpiasa ary ny vondrona hafa tamin'ny 1971, ary nahatratra ny fara tampony ny fihetsiketsehana tamin'ny 1972.Nanaraka izany ny famoretana feno habibiana nataon'ny governemanta, ka an'arivony no maty sy tsy hita popoka. Henjana ny vokatry ny Revolisiona, niaraka tamin'ny vanim-potoanan'ny famoretana ara-politika, ny sivana ary ny fifehezana henjana ny fiaraha-monina. Nametra-pialana i Tsiranana tamin’ny 1972, nanamarika ny fiafaran’ny fitondrany.Ny Revolisiona 1972 dia namela takaitra lalina teo amin'ny fitadidian'i Madagasikara ary nisy fiantraikany maharitra teo amin'ny politika sy ny fiarahamonina Malagasy. Izy io koa dia nanampy tamin'ny famolavolana ny fitarihana ara-politikan'ny firenena tamin'ny taona nanaraka, ary nisy vokany maharitra ho an'ny tantaran'i Madagasikara."},{"question":"a que categoria pertenece la siguiente pregunta: ¿Quién era el segundo hijo del segundo presidente de los EE. UU.?.","answer":"La categoría pertenece a Historia de EE.UU"},{"question":"Inona no fiantraikan'ny sakafo amin'ny fitondran-tena sy ny fihetseham-po?","answer":"Ny sakafo dia mety hisy fiantraikany amin'ny fitondran-tena sy ny fihetseham-po amin'ny fitaomana ny famokarana singa misy fiatraikany eo amin'ny ati-doha. Ny sakafo voalanjalanja misy otrikaina tena ilaina dia afaka manampy amin'ny fahasalamana ara-pihetseham-po tsara kokoa."},{"question":"लक्ष्मी प्रसाद देवकोटाको \\"नाटिप्नु हेर कोपिला\\" कविता लेख्नुहोस्।","answer":"नटि प्नु हेर कोपिलानचुँड्नु पाप लाग्दछनच्यात्नु फुल नानी होदया र धर्म भाग्दछनछोप्नु है चरी बरीसराप आँसु लाग्दछनमा र्नु जन्तु है कुनैबसेर काल जाग्दछन घाउ चोट लाउनूसडेर चित्त पाक्दछधुलो नफेक्नु नानी होउडेर भित्र ढाक्दछहिलो नखेल्नु फोहरीखराब दाग लाग्दछन चित्त है दुखाउनुडसेर आँसु बग्दछबनेर फुलझैँ सधैँहँसा उनू सुवास दीसधैँ रमाउनू जगत्रमेर नित्य आसदीजता ततै छ ईश रेछ सुन्नु त्यो विचार रेछकाउने लुकाउनेनराख भाव क्यै गरे"},{"question":"ఇచ్చిన ప్రశ్నకు జవాబు ఇవ్వండి: భూమికి ఒక పెద్ద సహజ ఉపగ్రహం ఉందా?","answer":"చంద్రుడు"},{"question":"ဆူနီဆာ ကာဝရွန်ဂရောင်း (၂၉ ဇန်နဝါရီ ၁၉၇၂ မွေးဖွားသည်)  ထိုင်းနိုင်ငံမှ မာရသွန်ပြိုင်ပွဲဝင်တစ်ဦး ဖြစ်သည်။ သူမသည် အမျိုးသမီး ၄ × ၁၀၀ မီတာ လက်ပတ်ပြိုင်ပွဲတွင် ဝင်ရောက်ယှဉ်ပြိုင်ခဲ့သည်။","answer":"၁၉၉၆ နွေရာသီ အိုလံပစ်မှာပေါ့။"},{"question":"કવિ દલપતરામ લિખીત એક પદ અથવા વાતા જેવી કહેવતોના ઉદાહરણ આપો.","answer":"એક પદ અથવા વાતા જેવી કહેવતોના નીચે મુજબ છે:- પોતાની માને કોઅ ડાકણ ન કહે.- પોથી માઅલાં રીંગણાં- પોપટ બોલવા શીખીને બંધીખાંને પડે.- ફરેતે ચરે.- ફાટલ લુઘડાં ને ગરીબ માબાપથી લજાવું નહીં.- ફુઈને મુછો હોઅતો કાકો કહેવાઅ.- ફુંક, માર ને ગહરકો એ ત્રણ જાતનાં વાંજાં.- ફુવડને ઘેર જોડ કમાડ ઊઘાડે કોણ ને અડકાવે કોણ.- બકરું કહાડતાં ઊંટીઊ પેઠું.- બગાસું ખાતાં સાકરનો ગાંગડો આવીઓ.- બલીઆના બે ભાગ.- બલતું ઘર કરશનાપણ.- બઊ તાંતર બલીઊં."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਆਸਾ ਮਹਲਾ ੫ ਅਸਟਪਦੀਆ ਘਰੁ ੨ੴ ਸਤਿਗੁਰ ਪ੍ਰਸਾਦਿ ॥ਪੰਚ ਮਨਾਏ ਪੰਚ ਰੁਸਾਏ ॥ ਪੰਚ ਵਸਾਏ ਪੰਚ ਗਵਾਏ ॥੧॥ਇਨੑ ਬਿਧਿ ਨਗਰੁ ਵੁਠਾ ਮੇਰੇ ਭਾਈ ॥ਦੁਰਤੁ ਗਇਆ ਗੁਰਿ ਗਿਆਨੁ ਦ੍ਰਿੜਾਈ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਸਾਚ ਧਰਮ ਕੀ ਕਰਿ ਦੀਨੀ ਵਾਰਿ ॥ਫਰਹੇ ਮੁਹਕਮ ਗੁਰ ਗਿਆਨੁ ਬੀਚਾਰਿ ॥੨॥ਨਾਮੁ ਖੇਤੀ ਬੀਜਹੁ ਭਾਈ ਮੀਤ ॥ਸਉਦਾ ਕਰਹੁ ਗੁਰੁ ਸੇਵਹੁ ਨੀਤ ॥੩॥ਸਾਂਤਿ ਸਹਜ ਸੁਖ ਕੇ ਸਭਿ ਹਾਟ ॥ਸਾਹ ਵਾਪਾਰੀ ਏਕੈ ਥਾਟ ॥੪॥ਜੇਜੀਆ ਡੰਨੁ ਕੋ ਲਏ ਨ ਜਗਾਤਿ ॥ਸਤਿਗੁਰਿ ਕਰਿ ਦੀਨੀ ਧੁਰ ਕੀ ਛਾਪ ॥੫॥ਵਖਰੁ ਨਾਮੁ ਲਦਿ ਖੇਪ ਚਲਾਵਹੁ ॥ਲੈ ਲਾਹਾ ਗੁਰਮੁਖਿ ਘਰਿ ਆਵਹੁ ॥੬॥ਸਤਿਗੁਰੁ ਸਾਹੁ ਸਿਖ ਵਣਜਾਰੇ ॥ਪੂੰਜੀ ਨਾਮੁ ਲੇਖਾ ਸਾਚੁ ਸਮ੍ਹਾਰੇ ॥੭॥ਸੋ ਵਸੈ ਇਤੁ ਘਰਿ ਜਿਸੁ ਗੁਰੁ ਪੂਰਾ ਸੇਵ ॥ਅਬਿਚਲ ਨਗਰੀ ਨਾਨਕ ਦੇਵ ॥੮॥੧॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 430 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਰਜਨ ਦੇਵ ਜੀ ਇਹਨਾਂ ਬਾਣੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਹਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ! ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੂੰ ਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ ਗਿਆਨ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਉਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਸਰੀਰ-ਨਗਰ ਵਿਚ ਸਤ ਸੰਤੋਖ ਦਇਆ ਧਰਮ ਧੀਰਜ—ਇਹ) ਪੰਜੇ ਪ੍ਰਫੁਲਤ ਕਰ ਲਏ, ਤੇ, ਕਾਮਾਦਿਕ ਪੰਜੇ ਨਾਰਾਜ਼ ਕਰ ਲਏ, (ਸਤ ਸੰਤੋਖ ਆਦਿਕ) ਪੰਜ (ਆਪਣੇ ਸਰੀਰ ਨਗਰ ਵਿਚ) ਵਸਾ ਲਏ, ਤੇ, ਕਾਮਾਦਿਕ ਪੰਜੇ (ਨਗਰ ਵਿਚੋਂ) ਕੱਢ ਦਿੱਤੇ ।੧।ਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ (ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੂੰ) ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦੀ ਸੂਝ ਪੱਕੀ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਦੇ ਦਿੱਤੀ (ਉਸ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰੋਂ) ਵਿਕਾਰ-ਪਾਪ ਦੂਰ ਹੋ ਗਿਆ, ਤੇ, ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਵੀਰ! ਇਸ ਤਰੀਕੇ ਨਾਲ ਉਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਦਾ ਸਰੀਰ-ਨਗਰ ਵੱਸ ਪਿਆ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ! ਜਿਸ ਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ ਗਿਆਨ ਬਖ਼ਸ਼ਿਆ, ਉਸ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਸਰੀਰ-ਨਗਰ ਦੀ ਰਾਖੀ ਵਾਸਤੇ) ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਨਿੱਤ ਦੇ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦੀ ਵਾੜ ਦੇ ਲਈਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਗਿਆਨ ਨੂੰ ਸੋਚ-ਮੰਡਲ ਵਿਚ ਟਿਕਾ ਕੇ ਉਸ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਖਿੜਕ (ਗਿਆਨ-ਇੰਦ੍ਰੇ) ਪੱਕੇ ਕਰ ਲਏ ।੨।ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਿੱਤਰ! ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਭਾਈ! ਤੁਸੀ ਵੀ ਸਦਾ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਲਵੋ, ਸਰੀਰ-ਪੈਲੀ ਵਿਚ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਬੀਜਿਆ ਕਰੋਸਰੀਰ-ਨਗਰ ਵਿਚ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦਾ ਸੌਦਾ ਕਰਦੇ ਰਹੋ ।੩।ਹੇ ਭਾਈ! ਜੇਹੜੇ (ਸਿੱਖ-) ਵਣਜਾਰੇ (ਗੁਰੂ-) ਸ਼ਾਹ ਦੇ ਨਾਲ ਇੱਕ-ਰੂਪ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਸਾਰੇ ਹੱਟ (ਸਾਰੇ ਗਿਆਨ-ਇੰਦ੍ਰੇ) ਸ਼ਾਂਤੀਆਤਮਕ ਅਡੋਲਤਾ, ਤੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਆਨੰਦ ਦੇ ਹੱਟ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।੪।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ! ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ ਗਿਆਨ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਸਰੀਰ-ਨਗਰ ਵਾਸਤੇ) ਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਦਰ ਤੋਂ ਪਰਵਾਨ ਹੋਈ ਹੋਈ ਮਾਫ਼ੀ ਦੀ ਮੋਹਰ ਬਖ਼ਸ਼ ਦਿੱਤੀਕੋਈ (ਪਾਪ ਵਿਕਾਰ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਹਰਿ-ਨਾਮ ਸੌਦੇ ਉਤੇ) ਜਜ਼ੀਆ ਡੰਨ ਮਸੂਲ ਨਹੀਂ ਲਾ ਸਕਦਾ (ਕੋਈ ਵਿਕਾਰ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਦੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਵਿਚ ਕੋਈ ਖ਼ਰਾਬੀ ਪੈਦਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਦਾ) ।੫।ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਮਿੱਤਰ! ਹੇ ਮੇਰੇ ਭਾਈ! ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਸਰਨ ਪੈ ਕੇ ਤੁਸੀ ਭੀ ਹਰਿ-ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦਾ ਸੌਦਾ ਲੱਦ ਕੇ (ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦਾ) ਵਪਾਰ ਕਰੋ(ਉੱਚੇ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦਾ) ਲਾਭ ਖੱਟੋ ਤੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਟਿਕਾਣਾ ਪ੍ਰਾਪਤ ਕਰੋ ।੬।(ਹੇ ਭਾਈ! ਨਾਮ ਦਾ ਸਰਮਾਇਆ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਪਾਸ ਹੈ) ਗੁਰੂ (ਹੀ ਇਸ ਸਰਮਾਏ ਦਾ) ਸਾਹੂਕਾਰ ਹੈ (ਜਿਸ ਪਾਸੋਂ ਆਤਮਕ ਜੀਵਨ ਦਾ) ਵਣਜ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲੇ ਸਿੱਖ ਹਰਿ-ਨਾਮ ਦਾ ਸਰਮਾਇਆ ਹਾਸਲ ਕਰਦੇ ਹਨ(ਜਿਸ ਸਿੱਖ ਨੂੰ ਗੁਰੂ ਨੇ ਗਿਆਨ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਦੇ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਹੈ ਉਹ) ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਵਿਚ ਸਾਂਭ ਕੇ ਰੱਖਦਾ ਹੈ (ਇਹੀ ਹੈ) ਲੇਖਾ-ਹਿਸਾਬ (ਜੋ ਉਹ ਨਾਮ-ਵਣਜ ਵਿਚ ਕਰਦਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ) ।੭।ਉਹ ਇਸ (ਐਸੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ-) ਘਰ ਵਿਚ ਵੱਸਦਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ਜੋ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਸਤੇ (ਵਿਕਾਰਾਂ ਵਿਚ) ਕਦੇ ਨਾਹ ਡੋਲਣ ਵਾਲੀ ਨਗਰੀ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ! (ਆਖ—ਹੇ ਭਾਈ!) ਪੂਰਾ ਗੁਰੂ ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੂੰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੀ ਸੇਵਾ-ਭਗਤੀ ਦੀ ਦਾਤਿ ਬਖ਼ਸ਼ਦਾ ਹੈ \\""},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'hutang kayu ara'?","answer":"Ia bermaksud jikalau meminjamkan wang kepada orang besar jangan diharap akan kembali"},{"question":"السؤال: ماهو اسم مولى أبي بكر الذي أمره أن يعتني بأغنامه وقت هجرة الرسول صلى الله عليه وسلم وأبي بكر للمدينة؟","answer":"الإجابة: عامر بن فهيرة"},{"question":"Nitori SARS, awọn ọdọ ṣe iṣọ-oru nita gbangba n’Ibadan","answer":"Awọn ọdọ tun gbe iwọde wọn gba ọna ara lalẹ ọjọ Abamẹta, Satide, to kọja, pẹlu bi wọn ṣe rọ da si gbangba títì Iwo Road lalẹ pẹlu abẹla lọwọ kaluku wọn, wọn lawọn n ṣe iṣọ oru ni iranti awọn ẹgbẹ awọn ti awọn ọlọpaa yinbọn pa niluu Ogbomọṣọ ni. Oriṣiiriṣii orin aro ni wọn kọ pẹlu abẹla lọwọ. A gbọ pe niṣe ni wọn si ṣe iwọde ọhun di nnkan bii aago marun-un idaji ọjọ Aiku, Sannde, ọsẹ yii."},{"question":" Sheeg Sanadkii Uu Dhashay General Maxamed Faarax Ceydiid","answer":" General Maxamed Faarax Ceydiid Wuxu Dhashay Sanadkii 1934-Tii, Isla SanadkaanWaxaa Dhashay Cabdullaahi Yuusuf Axmed."},{"question":"Ilan ang terminal ng Ninoy Aquino International Airport?","answer":"Sa ngayon, may apat na terminal ang Ninoy Aquino International Airport o NAIA. Ginagamit ang Terminal 1 at 3 para sa mga international na flights, habang ginagamit naman ang Terminal 2, 3 at 4 para sa mga domestic o lokal na flights. Matatagpuan ang lahat ng mga terminal sa lungsod ng Parañaque at Pasay sa Metro Manila."},{"question":"Kto otrzymał Nagrodę Nobla z Literatury w 1997 roku?","answer":"W 1997. roku Nagrodę Nobla z dziedziny literatury otrzymał: Dario Fo ( Włochy) otrzymał ją jako ten, który rywalizuje z błaznami średniowiecznymi w krytykowaniu władzy oraz popieraniu godności uciskanych."},{"question":"警方还询问了歌手Rimi Tomy和演员Kavya Madhavan, 这两人都是Siddique和他的妻子Dileep的亲密朋友, 句子2: 警方还询问歌手Rimi Tomy和演员Kavya Madhavan, 这两位是Siddique和他的妻子Dileep的亲密朋友, 问题:第一句和第二句表达相同的意义吗? 相同还是不同?","answer":"相同"},{"question":"Bùkọ̀lá Awóyẹmí","answer":"Bùkọ́lá Àwoyẹmí tí gbogbo ènìyàn mọ̀ sí Arugbá, tí wọ́n bí lọ́dún 1988 jẹ́ gbajúmọ̀ òṣèrébìnrin ọmọ bíbí ìpínlẹ̀ Kwara lórílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà. Òun ni ìyàwó gbajúmọ̀ òṣèré mìíràn tí ó ń jẹ́ Dàmọ́lá Ọlátúnjí. Ó gba orúkọ ìnagijẹ rẹ̀, Arugbá látàrí ipa tí ó kó nínú sinimá àgbéléwò kan tí ògbóǹtarìgì òní-sinimá, Túndé Kèlání gbé jáde lọ́dún 2008.Wọ́n bí Bùkọ́lá Arugbá ní ìpínlẹ̀ Kwara lọ́dún 1988. Láti ìgbà èwe ni Bùkọ́lá tí fẹ́ràn láti di eléré tíátà. Ó kàwé gbàwé ẹ̀rí nínú ìmọ̀ iṣẹ́ Tíátà ní ifáfitì ìjọba àpapọ̀ ní Ìlọrin, University of Ilorin. Nígbà tí ó ń kẹ́kọ̀ọ́ ló ti ń gbìyànjú láti máa ṣeré tíátà, ṣùgbọ́n ìràwọ̀ rẹ̀ kò tàn àfi ìgbà tí ó kópa nínú sinimá àgbéléwò tí Túndé Kèlání dárí lọ́dún 2008,tí àkọ́lé rẹ̀ ń jẹ́ Arugbá. Lẹ́yìn náà o tún kópa nínú \\"Poisonous Affair\\" àti àwọn sinimá-àgbéléwò gbankọgbì mìíràn lédè Yorùbá. \\"Ìgbà Ǹ Bá Jó\\" ni sinimá àgbéléwò àkọ́kọ́ tí Bùkọ́lá Àwoyẹmí ṣe agbátẹrù rẹ̀ fún ara rẹ̀ lọ́dún 2013."},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"ada bakat\\"? Berikan satu contoh ayat bagi peribahasa tersebut. ","answer":"Ia bermaksud berkebolehan dalam sesuatu lapangan seperti melukis, mengarang dan sebagainya. Contoh ayat: Izzah ada bakat menjadi penulis novel."},{"question":"ව්‍යුත්පත්තිය යනු කුමක්ද?","answer":"ජීවන තක්ෂලාවෙන් ලබන පරිණත බුද්ධියත් පොත් පත් පරිශීලනයෙන් හා  ශ්‍රවණය කිරීමෙන් ලබන බහුශ්‍රැතභාවයත් ව්‍යුත්පත්තිය යි."},{"question":"豊臣秀吉の義兄を父に持つ武将で、関ヶ原の戦いでは裏切りによって東軍勝利の立役者となったのは誰でしょう？","answer":"小早川秀秋"},{"question":"එක්සත් ජාතීන්ගේ මානව හිමිකම් කවුන්සිලයේ සාමජික රටවල් ගණන  ?","answer":"එක්සත් ජාතීන්ගේ මානව හිමිකම් කවුන්සිලයේ සාමජික රටවල් ගණන 47"},{"question":"පහත මාතෘකා ව ඇති කතාව ලියා  දක්වන්න. (ඉඟිය: මෙය රසවාහිනීයේ එන කතාවකි)වෙස්සා මිත්තාවගේ කථාව","answer":"දඹදිව කොසඹෑ නුවර කොසඹෑ රජතුමාගේ අග බිසව වෙස්සාමිත්තාය. බුදුරජාණන් වහන්සේ ද කොසඹෑ නුවර මෙසමයෙහි විසූ සේක. වෙස්සාමිත්තාවෝ රජතුමා සමඟ විහාරයට ගොස් බුදුරජාණන් වහන්සේ බුද්‍ධ ලීලාව දැක පැහැදී සරණ සිල්හි පිහිටියාය. පසු කාලයක පිටිසර බද රජෙක් රජුට විරුද්ධව පැමිණ රාජ්‍යය හෝ යුද්ධය කියා සන්දේශයක් එවා තිබුණි. මෙයැසූ රජතුමා සේනාව පිරිවරාගෙන මෙහෙසියත් සමඟ යුද බිමට ගොස් ඇයට මෙසේ කීයේය. ‘දේවීනි, යුද්ධය ගැන කීමට අපහසුය. මා යම් විධියකින් පරදින බව පෙනී ගියොත් කඳවුරෙහි රතු කොඩියක් ඔසවමි. ඒ සලකුණෙන් ඔබට කොසඹෑ නුවරට යා ගැනීමට හැකි වන්නේය.” රජතුමාට යුද්ධයෙන් පරාජය පෙනෙනු බැවන් දේවියට දැන ගැනීමට කඳවුරෙහි රතු කොඩියක් ඔසවා යුද කොට පරාජයට පත්විය. දේවිය සලකුණෙන් පරාජය දැන කොසඹෑ නුවරට යන අතර පසල් දනව් රජුගේ ආරක්‍ෂකයන්ට අසුවී ඔවුහු ඇය රජුට ඉදිරිපත් කොළෝය. රජතුමා ඇයට තමන්ගේ අග බිසොව වන්න යයි ආරාධනා කළේය. ඕ එය ප්‍ර‍තික්‍ෂේප කළා. නැවත නැවතත් අග බිසෝ වීම ප්‍ර‍තික්‍ෂේප කළ නිසා රාජාඞ්ගනයෙහි දර සෑයක් කරවා එයට ගිනි දී ගින්නට පනින මෙන් ඇයට නියෝග කළේය. ඕ නොයෙක් යුක්ති කියමින් එයින් ගැලවීමට උත්සාහ කළත් කිසි ප්‍රයෝජනයක් නොවීය. පසුව දැල්වෙන ගින්නට බලහත්කාරයෙන් ඇය දැම්මවීය. මේ මොහොතේ ඇය බුදුරජුන් සරණය ගැන උස් හඬින් කියා සිටියාය. පුදුමයකි! ඒ ගිනි දැල් ඇගේ ලෝම කූපයක් දැවීමට අසමත් විය. මේ පුදුමය දුටු රජතුමා වහා පැන ඔසවාගෙනවිත් ආසනයක තබා ඇඳිලි බැඳගෙන මේ නොදැවීමට හේතු විචාළේය. බිසව් තොමෝ තමා බුදුන්, දහම්, සඟුන් සරණ ගිය උපාසිකාවක් බවත්, ඒ බෙලෙන් නොදැවී ගිය බවත් ප්‍ර‍කාශ කළාය. ඇගේ මේ බණ කථාව අසා අතිශයින් සතුටට පත්ව ඇය මව් තනතුරෙහි තබා ගත්තේය. රජතුමාත්, බොහෝ සේනාවත් මෙහිදී තුනුරුවන් සරණ ගියෝය."},{"question":"*ما الصوت الذي يصدره المريض ؟","answer":"أنين"},{"question":"من مخضرمي العصر الجاهلي والإسلامي..؟","answer":"النابغة الجعدي"},{"question":"هل مشاعر الجملة التالية سلبية ، إيجابية ، أم محايدة : \\"جودة الخدمة عالية، خدمة الافطار ممتازة. وخدمات الموظفين جيدة و في قمة الاحترام. والغرف موقعها استراتيجي. الفندق ممتاز ونظيف. و بصراحة جيد و .ممتاز من جميع النواحي. يستأهل 4 أو 5 نجوم. نحب أن نراه لمرة ثانيه.  و نتمنى أن يكون على نفس المستوى العالي.\\"","answer":"مشاعر الجملة السابقة إيجابية. هذا واضح من العديد من التعبيرات الايجابية القوية مثل \\"جودة الخدمة عالية\\" و \\"خدمة الافطار ممتازة\\" و \\"خدمات الموظفين جيدة و في قمة الاحترام\\" و أيضاً \\"الفندق ممتاز ونظيف\\""},{"question":"पंढरपूर शहर कोणत्या नदीकाठी आहे?","answer":"भीमा नदीकाठी. महाराष्ट्राची काशी म्हणतात असे म्हटले जाते."},{"question":"Kudirat Kekere-Ekun","answer":"Kudirat Motonmori Olatokunbo tí gbogbo ènìyàn mọ̀ sí Kudirat Kekere-Ekun CFRCFR (ọjọ́ ìbí: ọjọ́ keje oṣù karùn-ún ọdún 1958) jẹ́ ọmọ orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà tí ó jẹ́ adájọ́ ilé-ẹjọ́ tó ga jùlọ ní orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà.A bí Kekere Ekun ní ọjọ́ keje oṣù karùn-ún ọdún 1958 ní ìlú London, United Kingdom. Ní ọdún 1980, ó gba òye (bachelor's degree) nípa òfin ní Yunifásítì Èkó àti pé ó gba ilé-ìgbìmọ̀ (Nigeria Bar ) ní ọjọ́ kẹwàá oṣù keje ọdún 1981, lẹ́hìn tí ó ti jáde ní ilé-ẹ̀kọ́ òfin Nàìjíríà ṣáájú kí ó tó lọ sí 'London School of Economics' níbití ó ti gba òye másítà ní Òfin ní oṣù kọkànlá ọdún 1983.Ní oṣù kẹwàá ọdún 2022, olá orílẹ̀-èdè Nàìjíríà kan ti Alákoso ti Àṣẹ ti ìjọba àpapọ̀ (CFR) ni a fún un ní láti ọ̀dọ̀ Ààrẹ Muhammadu Buhari.Kudirat darapọ̀ mọ́ ètò ìdájọ́ ní ìpínlẹ̀ Èkó gẹ́gẹ́ bí Adájọ́ Àgbà kejì, ó sì di ipò adájọ́ ilé-ẹjọ́ gíga ìpínlẹ̀ náà. Ó sìn gẹ́gẹ́ bí Alága Ìgbìmọ̀ Ìjà jilè àti Ìbọn, (Zone II, Ikeja) láàrín oṣù kọkànlá ọdún 1996 sí oṣù karùn-ún ọdún 1999. Wọ́n yàn án sí ìjókòó ilé ẹjọ́ kòtẹ́milọ́rùn ní Nàìjíríà lọ́dún 2004 kí wọ́n tó yàn án gẹ́gẹ́ bí Adajọ́ Ilé Ẹjọ́ Gíga Jù lọ ti Nàìjíríà ní oṣù keje ọdún 2013."},{"question":"Waan Uga Toosay!!","answer":"Waan Uga Toosay!!Waar\uFEFF\uFEFF\uFEFF ninyahow anigoo makhaayad kula sheekaysanaya mid\uFEFF aannu saaxiibbo nahay oo dhinca kale ah oo\uFEFF yera taataabanaya musuqmaasuqa \uFEFF\uFEFFwasaaradaha ka jira sow mid xoog weyn oon ogahay inuu wasaarada dhan keligii liqay afka ilama soo gelin, kaddibna laba askari oo meesha fadhiyey igumay soo kicin”“Haye”\uFEFF \uFEFF“Dabaeeto\uFEFF labada askari kii weynaa oon is idhi tu horuu ka hadhay baa igu soo haliilay oo la iga qaban kari waayey. Wuxu iila soo baxay qori, nin meesha joogay baa qabtay oo qasnaddii ka saaray, haddana bastoolad buu la soo baxay, haddana katiinad…, haddana waxa haw igu soo yidhi askarigii yaraa oon is idhi tii horuu gaadhayaa”\uFEFF \uFEFF“Adiga yaa musuqmaasuqa wasaaradaha ka sheekee ku yidhi ma wax kalood ka hadashaad weyday sowka waddanku wada musuqmaasuqa ah”.\uFEFF“Dee miyey igu simeenba, sow maan doonayn inaan ka hadlo musuqmaasuqa hayadaha, ganacsatada iyo meel walba, ma anaa meelba ka tegayey”\uFEFF \uFEFF“Haaye maxaad\uFEFF ka wasaaradaha ugu bilowday, miyaad wax kale ku bilowdid?” “Anigu ma madaxdii qarankaan caayey mise kuwii aalaha maxay igu haystaan wax jira uun baan sheegee?”\uFEFF “Dee markaa maxaad yeeshay?” \uFEFF“Dee waan\uFEFF uga toosay” “Yaah!! Maxaad tidhi, waan uga toosay? Sidee ahaan?” “Dee hurdadii baan uga\uFEFF toosay oo halkii bay igaga hadheen, ma si kalay kaaga hadhayaan inaad uga toosto mooyee, miyaanan abaalkood ka waraabin?”“Oo miyaad hurudday?”“Haddaa miyaan soo jeeday? Haddaan soo jeedo miyaannu nimankanba isku iman lahayn”“Oo waxan aad ka sheekaynaysaaba ma riyaa?”“Haddaa hee… riyadii baa lagaga nabadgeli laayahee ma soo jeed baa lagaga nabad geli”“Sow markay soo toosaan ku soo raadsan maayaan”“soo jeedkaba waan u dayn, toosiba maayo”“Oo sow haddana markaa riyoon maysid?”“Seexanba maayo, waan iska soo jeedi”“Oo markaa miyaad aamusi afkaa lagaa falee” “Haa oo weligay soojeed dawlad kuma xaman, shicibka uun baan soojeedka ku xantaa, waan is ilaaliyaa markaan soo jeedo laakiin markaan seexdo isma ilaalin karo intaasay iyana ka faa’iidaysanayaan oo hurdaday ila eeganayaan”.. “Oo maxay kugu haystaan haddaad huruddo, mindhaa inaad soo jeeday moodayeen?” “Dib dambeba u seexan maayo intay wax isbeddelayaan” “ Siday wax isu beddelayaan”“Kollay ammaan la heli maayee intay imanayaan kuwo soo jeedka dadka ku qabsanaya oon hurdada ku qabsanayn” “Oo sow markaana lagu xidhi maayo?”“Sowtaan ku idhi soojeedka wax kuma xanto”“Dee qaar kaloo soo jeedka wax ku xantaba sow la qabsan maayo illayn dadku keligaa maahee” “Waa runtaa.. oo haddaa maxaan yeelnaa?.”“Dee kuwan riyada wax ku qabsanaya maxaad ku haysataa sow kama darna kuwa soo jeedka wax ku qabsanayaa, markaa miyaanay ahayn in kuwan riyada kugu qabsanaya la iska daayo ha joogaane”“Maya..maya..maya…ma rkaa cidiba seexan maysee, dadka ma hurdo la’aan baad ku dilaysaa”“Dee haddaa kuwa soojeedka ku qabsanaya ma keennaa?”Maya..maya..maya, sow markaana dadku wada seexan maayo, cidiba toosi maysee yaa dalka u shaqayn?” “Dee haddaa meeshaba aynu qabsanno illayn innagu soojeed iyo riyo cidna wax ku qabsan maynee”“Ma sidaasaa?”“Ma si kalaa jirta”“Waa talo wanaagsan”.."},{"question":"Title: ਵਿਸ਼ਵ ਜੰਗ ਦੇ ਉਸ ਜਾਂਬਾਜ਼ ਸਿੱਖ ਪਾਇਲਟ ਬਾਰੇ ਜਾਣੋ, ਜਿਸ ਦਾ ਯੂਕੇ ਵਿੱਚ ਬੁੱਤ ਲੱਗ ਰਿਹਾ।","answer":"ਭਾਰਤੀ ਸਿੱਖ ਪਾਇਲਟ ਹਰਦਿੱਤ ਸਿੰਘ ਮਲਿਕ ਨੇ ਪਹਿਲੀ ਵਿਸ਼ਵ ਜੰਗ ਵਿੱਚ ਲੜਾਕੂ ਜਹਾਜ਼ ਉਡਾਏ ਸਨ ।ਹੁਣ ਸਦੀਆਂ ਬਾਅਦ, ਇਸ ਜੰਗੀ ਨਾਇਕ ਦਾ ਬੁੱਤ ਇੰਗਲੈਂਡ ਦੇ ਸਾਊਥਹੈਂਪਟਨ 'ਚ ਲਗਾਇਆ ਜਾ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ।ਭਾਰਤੀ ਭਾਈਚਾਰਾ ਹੈਰਾਨ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਦੋ ਵਿਸ਼ਵ ਜੰਗਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਆਪਾ ਵਾਰਨ ਵਾਲਿਆਂ ਲਈ ਪਹਿਲਾਂ ਹੀ ਕੋਈ ਯਾਦਗਰ ਕਿਉਂ ਨਹੀਂ ਬਣਾਈ ਗਈ।ਸਿੱਖ ਭਾਈਚਾਰੇ ਨੇ 15 ਮਾਰਚ ਨੂੰ ਸਿਟੀ ਕਾਉਂਸਲ ਨਾਲ ਯੋਜਨਾ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਚਾਰ ਵਟਾਂਦਰਾ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਮੀਟਿੰਗ ਕੀਤੀ ਸੀ। ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਉਮੀਦ ਹੈ ਕਿ 2023 ਦੀ ਬਸੰਤ ਰੁੱਤ ਆਉਣ ਤੱਕ ਬੁੱਤ ਸਥਾਪਿਤ ਹੋ ਜਾਵੇਗਾ।"},{"question":"What year was the movie Titanic released?","answer":"1997"},{"question":"Far Cry 3 açık dünya mı?","answer":"Far Cry 3, Ubisoft Montreal'in Ubisoft Massive, Ubisoft Red Storm ve Ubisoft Shangai stüdyolarıyla birlikte geliştirdiği Ubisoft'un yayımladığı açık dünya birinci şahıs nişancı video oyunudur."},{"question":"ما هي لغة الجملة الأتية:\\"C'est la vie\\"","answer":"الجملة \\"C'est la vie\\" مكتوبة باللغة الفرنسية."},{"question":"Shin gaskiya ne cewa: Turkiyya kasa ce daga nahiyoyi, da ta ratsa Turai da Asiya. (a) Gaskiya (b) Ƙarya","answer":"Amsa: Gaskiya"},{"question":"ادامه این پاراگراف را بنویسید: واکنش بین‌المللی به جنگ اوستیای جنوبی ۲۰۰۸ بسیاری از کشورها و سازمان‌های غیر دولتی را در برگرفت. با وجود آغاز این جنگ دبیر کل ناتو اعلام داشت که تعهد این سازمان مبنی بر عضویت آتی گرجستان در این سازمان همچنان به قوت خود باقی است. وی افزود ناتو، به درخواست‌های گرجستان برای کمک، به صورت اضطراری رسیدگی می‌کند.دولت روسیه با تمایل گرجستان برای پیوستن به ناتو به شدت مخالف است. دولت روسیه آمریکا رامتهم به آموزش و حتی شرکت در این جنگ کرد","answer":" ولی آمریکا ضمن رد این اتهامات اعلام کرد که مستشاران نظامی آمریکا برای آموزش آن دسته از سربازان گرجی که طبق برنامه قرار است به عراق اعزام شوند، درگرجستان بوده‌اند. همچنین پس از رسیدن به آتش بس شکننده در این جنگ شماری از اعضای اتحادیه اروپا خواهان اعزام نیروهای پاسدار صلح به اوستیای جنوبی، در چارچوب واحدی از پاسداران بین‌المللی صلح شدند."},{"question":"Negara kita turut menerima tempias akibat wabak selesema burung dan penyakit Sindrom Pernafasan Akut yang Teruk (SARS) yang berlaku di kebanyakan negara di dunia baru-baru ini.Jelaskan langkah-langkah yang perlu diambil oleh negara kita dan negara-negara yang terlibat.","answer":"Industri pelancongan negara terjejas sedikit akibat wabak selesema burung dan penyakit Sindrom Pernafasan Akut yang Teruk (SARS) yang berlaku di kebanyakan negara di dunia baru-baru ini. Namun demikian, wabak penyakit itu berjaya dikawal dan tidak memberikan kesan yang serius terhadap industri pelancongan dan kesihatan rakyat negara kita. Hal ini dikatakan demikian kerana pihak kerajaan telah mengambil langkah-langkah yang berkesan untuk menangani penyakit tersebut. Berdasarkan langkah mencegah lebih baik daripada mengubati, penyakit tersebut tidak merebak kepada rakyat negara kita. Namun begitu, rakyat negara ini perlu berwaspada dan berasa bimbang akan wabak yang menular di seluruh dunia itu. Terdapat beberapa langkah yang boleh diambil untuk menangani masalah tersebut.     Negara kita dan negara-negara yang terlibat sepatutnya mengambil langkah seperti mengasingkan pesakit yang menghidap wabak tersebut. Dengan perkataan lain, pesakit perlu dikuarantin dan diasingkan daripada orang awam agar penyakit tersebut tidak merebak kepada orang lain iaitu sebelum nasi menjadi bubur. Jika tindakan ini diambil sudah pasti penyakit ini dapat dikawal dan tidak akan disebarkan kepada orang lain dan juga ke negara-negara lain. Seterusnya, keadaan ini bukan sahaja tidak akan memudaratkan kesihatan manusia malahan industri pelancongan juga tidak terjejas.     Langkah lain yang perlu dijalankan ialah anggota masyarakat hendaklah mengelakkan diri daripada melancong ke negara-negara yang terlibat. Rakyat negara kita atau negara lain perlu membatalkan rancangan buat sementara waktu untuk pergi melancong ke negara-negara yang sedang dilanda wabak itu seperti negara China, Hong Kong, dan Indonesia. Langkah yang dikatakan sebagai menyediakan payung sebelum hujan, diharapkan dapat mengelakkan seseorang itu daripada dijangkiti oleh penyakit yang berbahaya terebut.     Pihak berkuasa setiap negara juga perlu membuat pemeriksaan yang ketat dan menyediakan alat pengimbas di pintu-pintu masuk utama negara masing-masing. Sebagai contohnya, alat pengimbas tersebut perlu diletakkan di lapangan-lapangan terbang antarabangsa seperti di KLIA, Kuching, dan Bayan Lepas. Alat pengimbas tersebut berupaya untuk mengesan pelancong yang memasuki negara kita sekiranya mereka dijangkiti oleh penyakit itu. Sekiranya mereka telah dijangkiti oleh penyakit tersebut, maka mereka perlu dibawa ke hospital untuk diberikan rawatan dan dikuarantin.     Pihak berkuasa perlu menyediakan ubat-ubatan dan vaksin yang boleh melawan virus H5N1 dan mencegah virus tersebut daripada menyerang manusia. Seseorang yang perlu ke luar negara atas urusan yang penting perlu diberikan suntikan vaksin yang dapat mencegah seseorang itu daripada dijangkiti penyakit tersebut. Hal ini dikatakan demikian kerana vaksin yang berkesan akan berupaya untuk melawan virus penyakit itu daripada menyerang mangsanya. Orang yang sudah dijangkiti oleh penyakit itu pula, perlu diberikan rawatan yang rapi dengan ubat-ubatan yang benar-benar berkesan untuk mengubati pesakit tersebut.     Langkah seterusnya ialah pihak berkuasa perlu memusnahkan haiwan yang telah dijangkiti dan menjadi punca penyakit itu merebak kepada manusia pula. Unggas seperti burung dan ayam yang telah dijangkiti perlulah dihapuskan segera agar wabak tersebut tidak menjangkiti manusia pula. Hal ini perlu dilakukan kerana penyakit ini sebenarnya berpunca daripada unggas seperti ayam dan burung yang dijangkiti oleh virus tersebut. Seterusnya, virus itu berpindah kepada manusia yang memeliharanya atau terlibat secara langsung dengan unggas tersebut setiap hari.     Sebagai kesimpulannya, pihak kerajaan dan rakyat hendaklah peka terhadap keadaan di sekeliling mereka dan mengambil langkah yang berkesan untuk menangani masalah tersebut. Aspek penjagaan kebersihan dan kesihatan perlulah diberikan perhatian yang utama dalam kehidupan seharian. Janganlah sudah terhantuk baru nak tengadah kerana sekiranya aspek kebersihan diabaikan sudah pasti penyakit itu akan mudah menyerang mangsanya. Jadi, langkah awal penting untuk menghindarkan seseorang itu daripada dijangkiti oleh wabak yang berbahaya ini. Selain itu, tindakan tersebut juga akan dapat meyakinkan pelancong yang hendak melancong ke negara kita dan industri pelancongan tidak akan terjejas. Kita berharap agar masalah itu dapat ditangani dengan berkesan demi kesihatan dan kesejahteraan rakyat negara ini."},{"question":"Tôi đi làm được 4 năm, có hơn 300 triệu tiền nhàn rỗi, một nửa bỏ vào kênh chứng khoán, một nửa gửi tiết kiệm ngân hàng. Cổ phiếu giai đoạn này được giới chuyên gia cảnh báo rủi ro nên tôi đã rút vốn khỏi kênh này. Với khoản tiền từ 150 đến 200 triệu, tôi có nên chuyển qua kênh trái phiếu? Cần lưu ý gì khi tham gia kênh này, nhờ chuyên gia tư vấn giúp.","answer":"Trước hết, tôi muốn nói rằng, việc chọn được một trái phiếu doanh nghiệp tốt để đầu tư, ngay cả với nhà đầu tư chuyên nghiệp, cũng không phải dễ dàng.Để ra quyết định đầu tư trái phiếu của một doanh nghiệp nào đó, bạn cần đánh giá được tình hình tài chính hiện tại, cũng như tương lai của doanh nghiệp đó. Dòng tiền để doanh nghiệp chi trả các khoản nợ, bao gồm cả khoản nợ trái phiếu, sẽ đến từ đâu, từ hoạt động kinh doanh cốt lõi, hay từ các hoạt động huy động vốn trên thị trường tài chính.Nếu doanh nghiệp không có khả năng thực hiện các nghĩa vụ chi trả của mình, có tài sản gì được cầm cố/thế chấp cho các chủ sở hữu trái phiếu, chất lượng của tài sản đó thế nào?Đó là những gạch đầu dòng đầu tiên bạn phải nắm được về doanh nghiệp trước khi muốn mua trái phiếu do họ phát hành.Với khoản tiền dưới 200 triệu đang dự tính, bạn thường chỉ có thể mua trái phiếu của một hay hai doanh nghiệp và khó có một danh mục đa dạng.Hiện nay, các trái phiếu doanh nghiệp được chào bán trên thị trường, theo tôi được biết, có mức lãi suất rất chênh lệch, từ trên dưới 8% tới trên dưới 10%, phụ thuộc vào chất lượng của trái phiếu.Nếu là nhà đầu tư không chuyên nghiệp, việc đánh giá chất lượng trái phiếu sẽ gặp nhiều khó khăn. Đầu tư trái phiếu của các doanh nghiệp có tình hình tài chính không lành mạnh sẽ khiến bạn gặp rủi ro mất toàn bộ phần vốn đầu tư khi doanh nghiệp phát hành trái phiếu mất khả năng chi trả. Từ trước tới nay, chưa phát sinh trường hợp tổ chức phát hành các trái phiếu được phân phối cho nhà đầu tư cá nhân mất khả năng thanh toán. Nhưng điều đó không có nghĩa là rủi ro này sẽ không xảy ra trong tương lai.Trường hợp của bạn, tôi không khuyến khích việc tự đầu tư.Nếu có nhu cầu đầu tư các sản phẩm tài chính cho lợi tức cố định, với số tiền dưới 200 triệu đồng mà lại không nhà đầu tư chứng khoán chuyên nghiệp, tôi nghĩ bạn nên lựa chọn sản phẩm của các công ty quản lý quỹ chuyên nghiệp.Đầu tư vào các quỹ mở trái phiếu là một lựa chọn. Lợi tức sẽ thấp hơn tương đối so với việc trực tiếp sở hữu các trái phiếu doanh nghiệp, nhưng khoản tiền của bạn sẽ được quản lý bởi các nhà đầu tư chuyên nghiệp, hạn chế tối đa rủi ro mất vốn, đồng thời đảm bảo tính thanh khoản do bạn có thể bán lại các chứng chỉ quỹ này bất kỳ lúc nào.Thị trường trái phiếu doanh nghiệp cũng như thị trường cổ phiếu, không phải là sân chơi của các nhà đầu tư không chuyên nghiệp. Việc tiếp cận được đầy đủ thông tin cũng như việc có đủ hiểu biết để đánh giá về khả năng tài chính của tổ chức phát hành là hết sức quan trọng trong việc hạn chế rủi ro mất vốn. Việc tổ chức phát hành cam kết thanh toán trái tức và vốn gốc không đồng nghĩa với việc họ sẽ thực hiện các nghĩa vụ này trong tương lai."},{"question":"次の段落にマッチするタイトルをつけてください： アメリカの雑誌「タイム」は4年前から、いろいろな分野で活躍している若い人を「次世代の100人」に選んでいます。今年は、五ノ井里奈さんが選ばれました。五ノ井さんは自衛隊にいたときに、同じ部隊の人たちから性被害を受けたと訴えました。タイムは、五ノ井さんの行動で、自衛隊でハラスメントの調査が始まって、ほかの女性たちも話をするようになったと言っています。そして「日本では、性暴力について話すことが長い間タブーになっていました。しかし、五ノ井さんの勇気がドアを開けました」と紹介しています。国会議員の英利アルフィヤさんも選ばれました。英利さんは、両親が中国の新疆ウイグル自治区の出身で、日本銀行や国連で働いていました。タイムは、男性がとても多くて平均年齢が高い日本の国会で、英利さんは特別な人だと言っています。","answer":"タイムの「次世代の100人」　五ノ井里奈さんが選ばれた"},{"question":"xi, fi, విలువలు పెద్ద సంఖ్యలు అయినపుడు సగటు కనుగొనుటకు ఈ క్రింది వానిలో సరియైన పద్ధతి ఏది?A) ప్రత్యక్ష పద్ధతిB) సోపాన విచలన పద్దతిC) ఊహించిన సగటు పద్ధతిD) ఏదీకాదు","answer":"B) సోపాన విచలన పద్దతి"},{"question":"Korona ti tun pa ẹni kan l’Ekiti, bẹẹ lawọn to lugbadi ẹ ti kọja igba","answer":"Ipinlẹ Ekiti ti padanu ẹni kẹta sọwọ arun Koronafairọọsi pẹlu bi awọn to lugbadi arun naa ṣe di mẹrinlenigba (204) nipinlẹ naa bayii.Lọsan-an ọjọ Aiku, Sannde, nijọba ipinlẹ naa kede pe eeyan mẹrin ninu awọn ti wọn ṣẹṣẹ ṣayẹwo ni wọn ti ko arun ọhun, eyi si ti sọ awọn to wa nibudo itọju bayii di mejidinlaaadọfa (108).Nitori bi arun yii ṣe n tan kalẹ diẹdiẹ nipinlẹ naa nijọba ṣe mu ofin tita kete sira ẹni ati lilo ibomu lọkun-un-kundun, awọn alakalẹ yii si mulẹ gidigidi.Lọwọlọwọ bayii, eeyan mẹtalelaaadọrun-un (93) lo ti ri iwosan l’Ekiti, eyi to din diẹ ni ida aadọta awọn to ti ko arun naa nipinlẹ ọhun."},{"question":"Pregunta: ¿Quién hace cumplir la Carta de Derechos y Libertades de Canadá? Respuesta:","answer":"Los tribunales."},{"question":"Les habitants autochtones du Groenland se nomment Inuit au Canada et Kalaalleq (pluriel Kalaallit), Groenlandais, au Groenland. Here is the same text in Wolof:","answer":"Ni dëkk ci Greenland ñoo'y woohe séen bopp Inuit ci Canada ak Kalaalleq (bu bàree Kalaallit), benn Greenlander, ci Greenland."},{"question":"සාමජයේ ජීවත්වන සියල්ලන්ට නිදහස තිබිය යුතු ආකාර කිහිපයක් නම් කරන්න.","answer":"සාමජයේ ජීවත්වන සියල්ලන්ට නිදහස, ආර්ථික නිදහස, දේශපාලන නිදහස, සමාජීය නිදහස ආදී වශයෙන් විවිධාකාර ය."},{"question":"هل صامطة هي عاصمة السعودية؟","answer":"لا، عاصمة المملكة العربية السعودية هي الرياض."},{"question":"ഇനിപ്പറയുന്ന ചോദ്യത്തിന് ഉത്തരം നൽകുക.ചോദ്യം: ഏത് സാഹിത്യ പുരസ്കാരമാണ് \\"കയർ\\" നേടിയത്?","answer":"ഉത്തരം: 'കൈർ' സാഹിത്യപുരസ്കാരമായ 'ജ്ഞാനപീഠ അവാർഡ്' നേടി.പ്രശസ്ത മലയാളം എഴുത്തുകാരൻ തകഴി ശിവശങ്കരപ്പിള്ള എഴുതിയ നോവലാണ് കയർ. 1978-ൽ പ്രസിദ്ധീകൃതമായ ഈ നോവൽ 1997-ൽ ഇംഗ്ലീഷിലേയ്ക്ക് മൊഴിമാറ്റം ചെയ്യപ്പെട്ടിട്ടുണ്ട്. ഡി.സി. ബുക്സ് ആയിരുന്നു പ്രസാധകർ."},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"air lalu, kubangan tohor\\"?","answer":"Ia bermaksud upah atau wang yang diterima habis dibelanja (untuk membayar hutang)"},{"question":"É um dos maiores nomes da literatura brasileira Ucraniana, em 2020 faria 100 anos De quem estamos falando?a) Lygia Fagundes Tellesb) Clarice Lispectorc) Cecília Meirelesd) Rachel de Queiroze) Svetlana Aleksiévitch","answer":"Alternativa b: Clarice Lispector.Clarice Lispector nasceu na Ucrânia, no dia 10 de dezembro de 1920. Com um estilo inconfundível, a obra de Clarice é considerada um marco na literatura."},{"question":"Ta đã biết 3/5 là một phân số. Vậy -3/5 có phải là phân số không?","answer":"Lời giải:-3/5 cũng là một phân số."},{"question":"Answer the following question with \\"Yes\\" or \\"No\\" or \\"None\\" if none of the first two answers apply.Question: 2015లో కంబోడియా దేశ అధ్యక్షుడు ఎవరు?Topic: కంబోడియాArticle: ప్రవేశికకంబోడియా (కంపూచియా), ఆధికారికంగా కంపూచియా సామ్రాజ్యము అని గుర్తించబడే ఈ దేశం ఆగ్నేయ ఆసియా లోని ఇండోనీషియా ద్వీపకల్పానికి దక్షిణంగా ఉంది. ఈ దేశం మొత్తం భూ వైశాల్యం 181,035 చదరపు కిలోమీటర్లు. కాంబోడియా వాయవ్య సరిహద్దులలో థాయ్ లాండ్, ఈశాన్యంలో లావోస్ తూర్పున వియత్నాం, ఆగ్నేయంలో థాయ్ లాండ్ జలసంధి ఉన్నాయి. 1.48 కోట్ల జనాభా కలిగిన కంబోడియా ప్రపంచంలో జనసాంద్రతలో 68వ స్థానంలో ఉంది. కంబోడియా అధికార మతం \\" తెరవాడ బౌద్ధమతం\\". తెరవాడ బౌద్ధమతాన్ని దేశ జనాభాలో 95% ప్రజలు అనుసరిస్తున్నారు. దేశంలోని అల్పసంఖ్యాకులు వియత్నామీయులు, చైనీయులు, చాములు మరియు 30 రకాల గిరిజనులు మొదలైన వారు. దేశరాజధాని మరియు దేశంలోని అతి పెద్ద నగరమైన \\" నాంఫెన్\\" కాంబోడియా సాంస్కృతిక, రాజకీయ మరియు ఆర్థిక కేంద్రమని చెప్పవచ్చు. రాచరిక విధానం అనుసరిస్తున్న దేశమిది. రాజ సింహాసన మండలి చేత ఎన్నుకొనబడిన అధిపతి రాజ్యనిర్వహణ బాధ్యత వహిస్తాడు. ప్రభుత్వ అధ్యక్షుడు అయిన \\" హన్ సెన్\\" కంబోడియాను 25 సంవత్సరాల నుంచి పాలన చేస్తూ, దక్షిణాసియాలోనే దీర్ఘకాల పాలకుడిగా ప్రసిద్ధి చెందాడు.కంపూచియా పురాతన నామము \\" కాంభోజ\\". 802 లో రెండవ జయవర్మ స్వయంగా తనకు తాను రాజుగా ప్రకటించుకోవడంతో ఖైమర్ సామ్రాజ్యం అంకురించింది. ఖైమర్ సామ్రాజ్యం దిగ్విజయంగా సమర్థులైన రాజులతో 600 సంవత్సరాల కాలం కొనసాగింది. ఖైమర్ సామ్రాజ్య కాలంలో కేంద్రీకృత అధికారం మరియు విస్తార సంపదలతో కంబోడియా దక్షిణాసియా దేశాలలో ఆధిపత్యం సాధించింది. ఆంకర్ వాట్ వంటి హిందూరాజుల కాలంలో ప్రపంచ ప్రసిద్ధ దేవాలయాల నిర్మాణం జరిగింది. దక్షిణాసియాలో హిందూమతం విస్తరణకు ఈ ఆలయాలు తార్కాణంగా నిలిచాయి. తరువాత ఇక్కడ బౌద్ధమతం విస్తరించింది. 15 వ శతాబ్దంలో ఆంకర్ పతనమై \\"ఆయుధాయ\\" సామ్రాజ్యం అవతరించిన తరువాత కంబోడియా 19 శతాబ్దం మధ్యకాలంలో ఫ్రెంచి వలసలు ఆరంభం అయ్యే వరకు పొరుగు రాజ్యాలతో కలిసి సామంతరాజ్యంగా ఉండిపోయింది. 1953 లో కంబోడియా స్వతంత్ర రాజ్యంగా అవతరించింది.వియత్నాం యుద్ధం కంపూచియాయా వరకు విస్తరించిన తరువాత అవతరించిన \\" ఖేమర్ రోగ్ \\" పార్టీ, 1975 నాటికి కంబోడియాను వశపరచుకుకుంది. కొన్ని సంవత్సరాల తరువాత కంబోడియా తిరిగి సోషలిస్ట్ భావ ప్రభావితమైన \\" పీపుల్స్ రిపబ్లిక్ ఆఫ్ కంబోడియా\\"తో విలీనమైంది. 1993 వరకూ ఇలా కొనసాగిన తరువాత, ఏకాంతం వీడి 1993 లో యుద్ధవినాశిత దేశమైన కంబోడియా సమైక్య సామ్రాజ్యంగా అవతరించింది. ","answer":"None"},{"question":"ராஜ்ய சபாவில் நியமிக்கப்படும் உறுப்பினர்கள் எத்தனை பேர்? \\t1. 82. 103. 124. 14","answer":"3. 12"},{"question":"كمل الفقرة:وكان حاملو الأعلام الفلسطينية الرئيسيون، من المنتمين لما يعرف، بـ\\"اللواء الأخضر\\" وهو مجموعة \\"ألتراس\\" تشكلت عام 2006، وتشتهر بنزعتها الجمهورية الأيرلندية ودعمها الثابت للقضية الفلسطينية.وطالما كان","answer":"هناك قسم من مشجعي سلتيك مرتبطين بالقضية الفلسطينية، حيث سبق أن تعرض النادي لعقوبات من جانب يويفا بسبب رفع الجماهير لافتات أو أعلام تظهر الدعم لفلسطين."},{"question":"Inona no dikan'ny \\"fady\\" eo amin'ny kolontsaina Malagasy?","answer":"Ny fady, eo amin'ny kolontsaina Malagasy, dia midika zavatra tsy azo atao na fandrarana ara-kolontsaina maro izay miovaova isaky ny faritr'i Madagasikara."},{"question":"عطني سؤال في تاريخ دولة مع اجابته","answer":"ما هي العاصمة الأولى للولايات المتحدة وأشهر ولاية أيضا؟ نيويورك"},{"question":"සුප්‍රකට \\" මෝල්ටා දූපත \\" පිහිටා ඇති මුහුද කුමක්ද ?","answer":"මධ්‍යධරණී මුහුද "},{"question":"Кыргыз тилинде  сөздөрдү ташымалдоодо, үндүүлөр арасында айтылган эки окшош үнсүз тыбышты чогуу койбостон, бири- биринен ажыратып ташымалдоо керек. ","answer":"   Ооба, дал ошондой. Сөздөрдү ташымалдоодо, үндүүлөр арасында айтылган эки окшош үнсүз тыбышты чогуу койбостон, бири- биринен ажыратып ташымалданат. Буга карата мындай мисал келтирейин карап көр, мисалы: мас-са, кас-са, тон-на, салтанат-туу, кат-та, жээк- ке жана башка ушул сыяктуу сөздөрдү келтирүүгө болот."},{"question":"Mungano yechirungu yemukundi anonzi Ragnorak, hondo yekupedzisira yaakarwa yakafambasei?","answer":"Mungano inotaura nezvemukundi anonzi Ragnorak, hondo yekupedzisira yakange iine vamwe vakundi vanosanganisira Ordin, Lor  na Thor. Nyika yakange yasvika kumagumo, zviitiko zvinoshamisa zvakange zvakazara mudenga, pasi panga paparadzwa nemoto  nematombo. Ragnorak nevamwe vake vakarwa nesimba vaive nechishuvo chekuti, kana hondo iyi ikapera, pasi rose pangazove nerunyararo, vanhu votangidza patsva, kurarama zvakanaka."},{"question":"fenoy by banga :\\"Valala sasatra ny miaina : _. \\"","answer":"\\"Valala sasatra ny miaina : mandry an-tanàna be olona\\""},{"question":"బాల్యవివాహాలు తగ్గుముఖం పట్టడానికి ఏమేమి తోడ్పడతాయి?","answer":"అతి బాల్యవివాహాలు ఈనాడు చెదురు మదురుగానే అక్కడక్కడ జరుగుతున్నాయి. నేడు అది ఒక పెద్ద సమస్యగా పరిగణించదగినంతగా జరగడం లేదు. ఈ పరిణామం సాధ్యం కావడానికి ప్రభుత్వం చేసిన ‘శారదా శాసనం’ ఒక్కటే కారణం అని అనుకోలేము. బాల్యవివాహాలు అనే దురాచారాన్ని రూపుమాపడానికి ఎందరో మహానుభావులూ సంఘసంస్కర్తలు, కృషి చేశారు. వారి కృషి ఫలితంగా, ప్రజలలో బాల్యవివాహాల పట్ల కలిగిన ఏవగింపు ఈ దురాచార నిర్మూలనకు ముఖ్య కారణం."},{"question":"(… ehlise inkomishi ayibeke esosweni.) Siyezwa nje bekhulumangokufaka itiyela emgwaqeni, ukufaka ompompi bamanzi kanyenokufaka ogesi abazokhanyisa ucoshe inaliti phansi endlini.Dlamini! Dlamini, ngaphi kokuthi abantu bafuyile? Phela imfuyo yethuizogugelwa yizinselo.Wena Ndabezitha ukhaliswa wubala. Ngubani ozokhokha amaleyithi?Iyovelaphi imali yamaleyithi lawo emakhaya?(alule isandla esinenkomishi sakukhomba uDlamini) Kukini Dlamini.Phela mina nginezinduna ezixegelwa ngamakhanda, abantu bamibayokhokha baze bangakwazi nokuthenga ukudla.(anikine ikhanda) Ngeke Ndabezitha! Ngeke bakubone lokho. Kantingekabani le ndawo esesizoyikhokhela?1. Bhala isizathu sikaShandu sokungafuni ukuvele alichithe nje ikhansela","answer":"Uthi kuyosuke kube sengathi akawuhloniphi umbuso, uphikisana nezinqumozikaHulumeni."},{"question":"Wie zijn de grote drie agentschappen in de kpop industrie?","answer":"De drie agentschappen die bekend staan als de voornaamste en invloedrijkste kpop agentschappen van Zuid Korea zijn YG entertainment, SM entertainment en JYP entertainment. "},{"question":"भारत में कौन सा खेल अमेरिकी खेल बेसबॉल जैसा है?","answer":"क्रिकेट एक ऐसा खेल है जो भारत में बहुत लोकप्रिय है। अमेरिकी खेल बेसबॉल की तरह, क्रिकेट भी एक मैदान में खेला जाता है और विजेता का फैसला रन बनाकर किया जाता है। क्रिकेट बल्ले और गेंद से भी खेला जाता है। इन दोनों खेलों के नियम उन्हें बेहद अलग बनाते हैं, लेकिन जो तत्व समान हैं वे अक्सर उन्हें तुलना का विषय बनाते हैं।"},{"question":"මිනෝවාසීන් කවුද, ඔවුන් ජීවත් වූයේ කොහේද?","answer":"Minoans යනු ක්‍රි.පූ. 3000 සිට 1600 දක්වා කාලය තුළ ක්‍රීට් දූපතේ සමෘද්ධිමත් වූ පුරාණ ශිෂ්ටාචාරයකි. ඔවුන්ගේ සමාජය එහි සංකීර්ණත්වය සඳහා ප්‍රසිද්ධ වූ අතර, ඔවුන් දක්ෂ ලෙස නිර්මාණය කර සකස් කරන ලද ඇඳුම් ඇතුළු පොහොසත් කලාත්මක උරුමයක් ඉතිරි කළහ. මිනෝවන් ඇඳුම් පිළිබඳ අපගේ අවබෝධය මූලික වශයෙන් මෙම කාල පරිච්ඡේදයේ සිට සොයා ගන්නා ලද කලා කෘති, විශේෂයෙන් බිතුසිතුවම් වලින් පැමිණේ."},{"question":"Msomba ya batala imapezeka kwambiri ku boma lanji mu Malawi?","answer":"Nsoma ya batala imapezeka kwambiri mu boma la Nkhata Bay. Boma la Nkhata Bay lili m'mphepete mwa nyanja ya Malawi (yomwe kale inali Nyanja ya Nyasa), kum'mawa kwa Mzuzu, ndipo ndi limodzi mwa madoko akuluakulu a Nyanja ya Malawi.[2] Chiwerengero cha anthu ku Nkhata Bay chinali 14,274 malinga ndi kalembera wa 2018. Nkhata Bay ili pamtunda wa makilomita 413 (257 mi) kuchokera ku Lilongwe, likulu la dziko la Malawi, komanso makilomita 576 kuchokera ku Blantyre, mzinda wachiwiri paukulu m’Malawi. Nkhata Bay ndi malo achiwiri \\"otanganidwa kwambiri\\" pa Nyanja ya Malawi.Nkhata Bay ndi tauni ya ku Malawi yomwe ili m'mphepete mwa nyanja ya Lake Malawi. Doko lake lochititsa chidwi lili ndi malo otetezedwa okhala ndi nkhalango, miyala yamwala. Kum'mwera kwa chilumbachi, Chikale Beach ili ndi madzi oyera okhala ndi nsomba zokongola za mbuna. "},{"question":"క్రింది వానిలో ఫారడే విద్యుత్ అయస్కాంత ప్రేరణ నియమాన్ని అనుసరించనిది ……..A) ATM కార్డుB) ఇండక్షన్ స్టవ్C) టేప్ రికార్డర్D) ఇస్త్రీ పెట్టె","answer":"B) ఇండక్షన్ స్టవ్"},{"question":"Inona no volana aorinan'ny Jona","answer":"Jolay no volana aorinan'ny Jona"},{"question":"ماهي الفئة التي ينتمي له النص التالي: من هو أصغر من حقق بطولة كبرى؟.","answer":"ينتمي السؤال السابق إلى فئة الرياضة."},{"question":"Манас эпосундагы Чоң Билгичтин минген аты?а) Ниянкор б) Кер в) Кулунсур г) Куносур","answer":"Манас эпосундагы Чоң Билгичтин минген аты Кер.Ошентип, туура жообу:б) Кер"},{"question":"Vygaudas Ušackas, Žygimantas Pavilionis, Audrius Brūzga, Stasys Sakalauskas, Alfonsas Eidintas – visi šie žmonės anksčiau buvo Lietuvos ambasadoriai tai pačiai šaliai. Kokia tai šalis?","answer":"Jungtinės Amerikos Valstijos. Lietuvos ambasados Vašingtone pirmaisiais asmenimis buvo penki diplomatai: Alfonsas Eidintas (1993–1997), Stasys Sakalauskas (1997–2001), Vygaudas Ušackas (2001–2006), Audrius Brūzga (2007–2010) bei Žygimantas Pavilionis (2010—2015)."},{"question":"السؤال: ما أكثر البلدان من حيث نسبة الانتحار في العالم؟","answer":"الإجابة: تعتبر غيانا الريفية التي موقعها في الطرف الشمالي الشرقي في أمريكا الجنوبية، يسكنها نحو 740,000 شخص. سجلت أعلى معدلات الانتحار في العالم"},{"question":"\\"फोटोसिंथेसिस का अवधारणा समझाएं।\\"","answer":"\\"फोटोसिंथेसिस वह प्रक्रिया है जिसमें पौधों को उनके विकास और वृद्धि के लिए राशि और ऑक्सीजन के रूप में केमिकल ऊर्जा मिलती है। इस प्रक्रिया के दौरान, कार्बन डाइऑक्साइड और पानी को सूरज की किरणों और क्लोरोफिल का उपयोग करके ग्लूकोज और ऑक्सीजन में परिवर्तित किया जाता है।\\""},{"question":"Maxay (API) u taagan tahay?","answer":"API waa soo gaabinta ereyga Codsiga Isugeynta Barnaamijyada (API). API waa nidaam joogto ah, hab-maamuusyo, iyo qalab loogu talagalay dhisidda barnaamijyada ku-saleysan mareegaha iyo moobilka. API-gu wuxuu qeexayaa sida aad u xaqiijin karto (ikhtiyaar), codsiga iyo uga heli karto xogta server-ka API."},{"question":"Yaa tiriyey Gabeyga Orod Xoogso?","answer":"Waxaa tiriyay gabayga Orad Xoogso abwaan Mohamud Mohamed Barre."},{"question":"Ọdún wo ni wọ́n gbé eré Bàbá Ajasco jáde?","answer":"1996"},{"question":"Манас өлгөндөн кийин ак пейил туулган Абыке Бакайга кан өлгөндө баары өлүп, өрт өчкөндөй болбойлук. Төмөнкү үч кан элинде эр өлтүрүшкөн кыргын болуптур. Калыстык менен элдештирип кайталык, – дегенде Бакай эмне дейт?а) “Манас мен өлгөндө топко барбай жүр, кан өлгөндө карысы төөгө жакын болуучу, жети-миңдин төөсүн кайтар” -деген Абыке тобуңузга барбаймын -деп мындан ары бийликке катышпасын билдиретб) Манас “мен өлгөндөн кийин элди сен башкар, кан шайланып душмандардан журтубузду корго” деген макул барайын-дейтв) Бакай -башкаруу менин ишим эмес, өзүңөр элди башкаргыла кааласаң өзүң, же агаң Көбөш кан болсун-дейтг) “Манас өлгөндөн кийин мага эч нерсенин кереги жок, бул жерлерден баш алып кетемин”-дейт","answer":"Туура жообу:а) “Манас мен өлгөндө топко барбай жүр, кан өлгөндө карысы төөгө жакын болуучу, жети-миңдин төөсүн кайтар” -деген Абыке тобуңузга барбаймын -деп мындан ары бийликке катышпасын билдирет"},{"question":"文中の主な言葉を見つけて、その内容を説明しなさい。 法務省は、子どもが学校や家族のことなどで悩んでいるとき、電話やLINEで相談できるようにしています。夏休みが終わるころは、悩んだり心配な気持ちになったりする子どもが多くなりやすいです。このため、法務省は8月23日から29日まで相談できる時間を長くします。月曜日から金曜日までは午前8時30分から午後7時までです。いつもは休みの土曜日と日曜日も午前10時から午後5時まで相談できるようにします。電話番号は0120-007-110で、お金はかかりません。LINEは「LINEじんけん相談」を「友だち」にすると、メッセージを送ることができます。（LINE: @snsjinkensoudan）文部科学省の永岡大臣も「相談は恥ずかしいことではありません。1人で悩まないで相談してください」と言いました。","answer":"文にある主な言葉とその内容はこちらです。- 法務省: 1）裁判や法律に関した仕事をする、国の役所。- 悩ん: 1）心の中で思って苦しむ。心配する。2）痛みなどで苦しむ。- メッセージ: 1）伝言。2）挨拶の言葉。声明文。- 文部科学省: 1）教育や文化についての仕事や、科学技術を発展させる仕事をする国の役所。文科省。- 大臣: 1）内閣を構成し、国の政治で、もっとも責任のある役。また、その役の人。総理大臣と国務大臣とがある。2）昔、天皇のもとで政治を行った、いちばん上の役。また、その人。"},{"question":"ప్రశ్న : నిత్య జీవితంలో అయస్కాంతాలను ఎక్కడెక్కడ వినియోగిస్తారో రాయండి.","answer":"మన నిత్య జీవితంలో చాలా సందర్భాలలో అయస్కాంతాలు ఉపయోగిస్తాము.రేడియో మరియు టి.వి. స్పీకర్లలో అయస్కాంతాలు వాడతారు.ఎలక్ట్రిక్ మోటార్ లో అయస్కాంతాలు వాడతారు.ఇంటి తలుపులు, షోకేలో అయస్కాంతాలు వాడతారు.ఆఫీస్ బల్లపై గుండుసూదుల పెట్టెలో అయస్కాంతం ఉంటుంది.గాలిలో ప్రయాణించే ఎలక్ట్రిక్ ట్రైన్లలో అయస్కాంతం వాడతారు.సెల్ ఫోన్ కవర్, హాండ్ బాగ్ లో అయస్కాంతాలు ఉంటాయి.కొన్ని ఆటబొమ్మలలో అయస్కాంతం ప్రధాన ఆకర్షణ.సముద్ర నావికులు వాడే దిక్సూచిలో అయస్కాంతం ఉంటుంది."},{"question":"క్రింద ఇచ్చిన మొదటి పేరా మరియు చివరి పేరా అనుసరించి మధ్య పేరా రాయండి:మొదటి పేరా:కుచేలుడు శ్రీకృష్ణుని బాల్యమిత్రులు – వారిరువురు సాందీపుని సన్నిధిలో విద్యాభ్యాసం చేశారు. తరువాత శ్రీకృష్ణుడు ద్వారకా నగరాధిపతియైనాడు. కుచేలుడు దుర్భరమైన దారిద్య్ర బాధ అనుభవించాడు. కుచేలుని భార్య మహాపతివ్రత, అభిమనవతి. ఆ ఇల్లాలు దారిద్య్ర బాధతో పిల్లలు మలమలమాడిపోబడం చూచి – భర్తను, శ్రీకృష్ణుని ఆయన అనుగ్రహంతో తమను కాపాడుమని ప్రార్థించు సన్నివేశంతో కథ ప్రారంభమగుచున్నది.చివరి పేరా:మహాపతివ్రతయు, క్రుంగికృశించి పోయినది. యునైన కుచేలుని భార్య దుర్భరమైన దరిద్రపీడచే అలమటించుచు, పిల్లలు ఆకులు, గిన్నెలు పట్టుకొని. తల్లి వద్దకు వచ్చి పట్టెడన్నము పెట్టుమని యడిగిరి. వారి మాటలు వినినంతనే పట్టరాని దుఃఖముతో భర్త కడకరిగి “ప్రాణేశ్వరా ! ఇంటిలో దారిద్ర్యము తాండ వించుచున్నది. దానిని తొలగించుటకు మార్గమును ఆలోచింపరైతిరి.","answer":"భర్తకు కర్తవ్యోపదేశము చేసిన అర్ధాంగిగా కుచేలుని భార్య ఎంతటి దుర్భరమైన దారిద్ర్యము అనుభవించినను నోరు తెరచి సహాయమును అర్థింపని అభిమనధనుడుగా కుచేలుడు – అవధులు ఆదరాభిమానాలతో బాల్య మిత్రునికి సర్వ సంపదలను అనుగ్రహించిన ఆర్తజన రక్షకుడిగా శ్రీకృష్ణుడు మనకు ఈ పాఠ్యభాగములో సాక్షాత్కరిస్తారు. కుచేల శ్రీకృష్ణుల మధురమైన స్నేహానికి, శ్రీకృష్ణుని భక్తజన వాత్సల్యమునకు కుచేలోపాఖ్యానం నిదర్శనంగా నిలుస్తుంది."},{"question":"ਰਿਤਿਕ ਰੌਸ਼ਨ  ‘ਡਾਨ-2’ ‘ਚ ਮਹਿਮਾਨ ਭੂਮਿਕਾ ਨਿਭਾਅ ਕੇ ਆਲੋਚਕਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਖ਼ੁਸ਼ ਕਰਨ ਵਾਲਾ ਰਿਤਿਕ ਰੌਸ਼ਨ  ‘ਅਗਨੀਪੱਥ’ ਨਾਲ ਵੀ ਕੁਝ ਅਜਿਹਾ ਹੀ ਕਰ ਦਿਖਾਉਣ ਲਈ ਤਿਆਰ ਹੈ। ਹਾਲਾਂਕਿ ‘ਕਾਈਟ’ ਨਹੀਂ  ਸੀ ਚੱਲੀ ਪਰ ‘ਕ੍ਰਿਸ਼-2’ ਲਈ ਰਿਤਿਕ ਰੌਸ਼ਨ ਤਕ ਤਿੰਨ ਚੋਟੀ ਦੀਆਂ ਅਭਿਨੇਤਰੀਆਂ ਨੇ ਪਹੁੰਚ  ਕੀਤੀ ਹੈ। ਰਿਤਿਕ ਰੌਸ਼ਨ ਦੀ ਖ਼ੂਬੀ ਇਹ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਉਹ ਹਰ ਕੰਮ ਜਨੂੰਨ ਨਾਲ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਹਰ  ਫ਼ਿਲਮ ਲਈ ਦਿਨ-ਰਾਤ ਇੱਕ ਕਰ ਦਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ।‘ਜ਼ਿੰਦਗੀ ਨਾ ਮਿਲੇਗੀ ਦੁਬਾਰਾ’ ਚਾਹੇ ਬਹੁਤੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਚੱਲੀ ਪਰ ਅੱਜ ਵੀ ‘ਕੋਈ ਮਿਲ ਗਿਆ’,  ‘ਕਹੋ ਨਾ ਪਿਆਰ ਹੈ’ ਉਸ ਦੀਆਂ ਫ਼ਿਲਮਾਂ ਲੋਕ ਚੇਤੇ ‘ਚ ਹਨ। ‘ਅਗਨੀਪੱਥ’ ਤੋਂ ਬਾਅਦ ਉਸ ਦਾ  ਸਾਰਾ ਧਿਆਨ ‘ਕ੍ਰਿਸ਼-2’ ਵੱਲ ਹੈ। ਹੁਣ ਰਿਤਿਕ ਨੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਜਿਸਮ ਦੀ ਬਣਤਰ ‘ਕ੍ਰਿਸ਼-2’ ਲਈ  ਬਦਲਣੀ ਸ਼ੁਰੂ ਕੀਤੀ ਹੈ। ਚਾਰ ਵਰ੍ਹਿਆਂ ਤੋਂ ਉਸ ਦੇ ਦਿਮਾਗ ‘ਚ ਕ੍ਰਿਸ਼ ਹੀ ਹੈ ਰਿਤਿਕ  ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਪਿਤਾ ਦਾ ਪੂਰਾ ਸਾਥ ਮਿਲ ਰਿਹਾ ਹੈ।ਰਿਤਿਕ ‘ਕ੍ਰਿਸ਼’ ਲਈ ਕਾਫ਼ੀ ਪਤਲਾ ਹੋਣਾ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹੈ। ਸਭ ਕੁਝ ਸਹੀ ਹੈ ਪਰ ਕਦੇ-ਕਦੇ ਪਿੱਠ  ਦੀ ਦਰਦ ਜ਼ਰੂਰ ਸਤਾਉਂਦੀ ਹੈ। ਰਿਤਿਕ ਐਨਾ ਕੁ ਤੰਦਰੁਸਤ ਹੋਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ ਕਿ  ਮਾੜੀ-ਮੋਟੀ ਦਰਦ ਦਾ ਪਤਾ ਹੀ ਨਾ ਚੱਲੇ। ਅੱਜ-ਕੱਲ੍ਹ ਰਿਤਿਕ ਦੀ ਚਹੇਤੀ ਮਾਡਲ ਸੌਰਯ  ਚੌਹਾਨ ਹੈ ਜੋ ‘ਕਿੰਗ ਫਿਸ਼ਰ’ ਦੀ ਮਾਡਲ ਬਣ ਕੇ ਬਾਲੀਵੁੱਡ ਲਈ ਆਕਰਸ਼ਣ ਬਣੀ ਹੋਈ ਹੈ।  ‘ਕ੍ਰਿਸ਼-2’ ‘ਚ ਰਿਤਿਕ ਹੁਣ ਸੌਰਯ ਚੌਹਾਨ ਨਾਲ ਵਧੀਆ ਤਾਲਮੇਲ ਬਿਠਾ ਕੇ ਇੱਕ ਹੋਰ ਨਵੀਂ  ਹਿੱਟ ਜੋੜੀ ਦੇਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ।ਪ੍ਰਸ਼ਨਃ ਸੌਰਯ  ਚੌਹਾਨ ਕੌਣ ਹੈ?","answer":"ਉੱਤਰਃ ਸੌਰਯ  ਚੌਹਾਨ  2006 ਲਈ ਕਿੰਗਫਿਸ਼ਰ ਕੈਲੰਡਰ ਦੀ ਮਾਡਲ ਸੀ"},{"question":"Kysymys: Kuka näyttelijä näyttelee Venomia kyseisestä sarjakuvasta tehdyissä elokuvissa?","answer":"Pääosaa, eli Venomia näyttelee Tom Hardy."},{"question":"Dựa trên tiêu đề sau, hãy viết một bài báo nói về chủ đề này: HLV từng vô địch World Cup dẫn dắt tuyển futsal Việt Nam. Nội dung chính của đoạn văn là về Giustozzi Diego Raul, một HLV người Argentina, người đã đưa Argentina vô địch Futsal World Cup - Colombia 2016 và có nhiều thành tích ấn tượng khác trong lịch sử futsal. Raul hiện là HLV của đội tuyển futsal Việt Nam và đang kỳ vọng đưa đội tuyển đến những thành công mới. Đoàn tuyển Việt Nam dự kiến sẽ tham gia các giải đấu quốc tế và chuẩn bị cho vòng chung kết châu Á 2022 với các đối thủ mạnh như Iran, Morocco, Phần Lan, Angola, Thái Lan, Hàn Quốc, Saudi Arabia và Nhật Bản.","answer":"Giustozzi Diego Raul, sinh năm 1978, từng đưa Argentina vô địch Futsal World Cup - Colombia 2016. Đấy cũng kỳ World Cup lần đầu tiên trong lịch sử futsal Việt Nam, khi đó được dẫn dắt bởi HLV Bruno Garcia Formoso. Bên cạnh chức vô địch World Cup 2016, Raul còn đưa Argentina đến ngôi á quân đại hội thể thao Nam Mỹ 2014, đánh bại Brazil ở giải Tứ hùng sau đó và đăng quang tại giải Continental Cup lần thứ ba. Ở cấp CLB, chiến lược gia người Argentina từng đưa CLB ElPozo Murcia (Tây Ban Nha) đến vị trí á quân giải Futsal UEFA Champions League 2019-2020. Raul được kỳ vọng sẽ mang đến làn gió mới cho futsal Việt Nam, trước mắt là thi đấu thật tốt tại vòng chung kết châu Á 2022, sau đó là hướng tới mục tiêu cạnh tranh suất dự vòng chung kết World Cup 2024. Do mới tiếp quản đội tuyển, tân HLV Raul đã đặt niềm tin vào lực lượng do các cộng sự trong ban huấn luyện giới thiệu, trong đó đa phần là những gương mặt dạn dày kinh nghiệm như thủ thành Hồ Văn Ý, Fixo Trần Văn Vũ, Khổng Đình Hùng, Phạm Đức Hòa, Ala Lê Quốc Nam, Trần Thái Huy, Pivo Nguyễn Minh Trí... Bên cạnh đó là một số gương mặt trẻ xuất sắc như Nguyễn Văn Hiếu, Châu Đoàn Phát, Nhan Gia Hưng... Theo kế hoạch, tuyển Việt Nam sẽ tập luyện tại Nhà thi đấu Thái Sơn Nam (quận 8, TP HCM) từ ngày 1/8 đến ngày 8/9. Sau đó, thầy trò HLV Raul sang Thái Lan dự giải futsal quốc tế từ ngày 9/9 đến 17/9. Tại giải đấu này, Việt Nam có cơ hội gặp các đối thủ chất lượng như Iran, Morocco, Phần Lan, Angola và chủ nhà Thái Lan. Đội tuyển sau đó trở về nước để tiếp tục hoàn thiện khâu chuẩn bị cuối cùng trước khi sang Kuwait ngày 24/9 để tham dự vòng chung kết châu Á 2022. Tại đó, đội gặp Hàn Quốc, Saudi Arabia và đương kim á quân Nhật Bản."},{"question":"Su’aal: Sheeg magacii hore ee loo-yaqaanay magaalada Qaahira (Cairo) ee dalka Masar (Egypt)?","answer":"Jawaab: Waxaa loo-yaqaanay Fusdaad (Fusdad)."},{"question":"බුදු දහමේ එන  උපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය ගැන විස්තර කරන්න.","answer":"චිත්ත චෛතසික ඇති වීමට ලැබිය යුතු වූ එක් විය යුතු වූ අනේක ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය ධර්මයන් අතර ඵල ධර්මයට අතිශයින් උපකාර වූ දනැතිව ම බැරි වූ ද බලවත් වූ ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය උපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය නම් වේ. එය කම්කරුවන්ට වැටුප් දී ගෙයක් සාදවන ගේ හිමියකු මෙන් දත යුතුය. ගේ හිමියාය කම්කරුවෝය යන සියල්ලෝ ම ගෙය ඇති කරන්නෝය. එහෙත් කම්කරුවන්ගෙන් ඇතැමුන් නැති වුව ද ගෙය තැනීම සිදු වන්නේ ය. ඔවුනට වැටුප් දෙන කර්මාන්තයට ද්‍ර‍ව්‍ය සපයන ගේ හිමියා නැති වුව හොත් ගෙය නො කෙරෙන්නේ ය. එබැවින් ගෙය නමැති ඵලය ඇති කිරීමේ ප්‍ර‍ධාන උපකාරකයා ගේ හිමියා ය. ගේ හිමියාගේ සම්බන්ධය නැතහොත් ගෙය නො කරන්නා වූ කම්කරුවෝ ගෙය තැනීමේ අප්‍ර‍ධානයෝ ය. චිත්ත චෛතසිකයන් ඇති වීමට තිබිය යුතු වූ උපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යයෙන් අන්‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යයන්, ගෙය තනන කම්කරු පිරිසි මෙන් දත යුතු ය.ආරම්මණෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය, අනන්තරෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ය, ප්‍ර‍කෘතෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය යි උපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය ත්‍රිවිධ වේ. ලෝකයා විසින් හොඳය කියා ගරු කරනු ලබන අරමුණු ආරම්මණෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය වේ. ගරු කරනු ලබන අරමුණු නිසා ඒ ඒ දෙයට ගරු කරන්නා වූ පුද්ගලයන් කෙරෙහි බොහෝ චිත්ත චෛතසිකයෝ උපදිති. රුවන්වැලි මහා සෑය ලෝකයා ගරු කරන වස්තුවකි. එබැවින් එය දැකීමට වැඳීමට බොහෝ මනුෂ්‍යයෝ යති. ඔවුන් තුළ ඒ සඳහා ඇති වන චිත්ත චෛතසික සියල්ල ඇති වන්නේ ගරු කළ යුතු වූ රුවන්වැලි සෑය නිසා ය. රුවන්වැලි මහ සෑය ඒ සිත් ඇති වීමේ බලවත් හේතුව ය. එබැවින් ඒ සිත්වලට රුවන්වැලි මහ සෑය ආරම්මණෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය වේ. ලෝකයා ඇලුම් කරන ශෝභන ස්ත්‍රී පුරුෂ රූපාදිය අකුශල චිත්ත චෛතසිකයන්ට ආරම්මණෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය වේ.ඒ ඒ සන්තානවල ඒ ඒ සිතට කලින් ඉපද නිරුද්ධ වූ චිත්තය අනන්තරෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය වේ. සිත් උපද වන හේතූන් කොතෙක් එක් වුව ද ඒ හේතූහු කලින් සිතක් නූපන් තැනක සිත් ඉපද වීමට සමත් නො වෙති. සිතක් ඉපද පවත්නා තැන තවත් සිතක් ඉපද වීමට ද සමත් නො වෙති. ආරම්මණාදි හේතූන්ට සිත් ඉපදවිය හැකි වීමට කලින් සිත් ඉපද නිරුද්ධ වූ තැනක් ලැබිය යුතු ය. කලින් ඉපද නිරුද්ධ වූ සිත පසුව උපදනා සිතට ඉපදීමට බලවත් හේතුවක් වේ. එබැවින් උපදනා සිත ළඟ ම කලින් ඉපද නිරුද්ධ වූ සිත පසු උපදනා සිතට අනන්තරෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යයයි කියනු ලැබේ.රූප ශෝභාව ඇති කාන්තාවක් දැක මෑ ලක්ෂණය, හොඳය කියා යම් කිසිවකු ගේ සන්තානයෙහි රාගය උපත හොත් ඒ තැනැත්තා ඒ කාන්තාව නැවත නැවත සිහි කරයි. ඒ කාන්තාව දක්නට යයි. ඇය හා කථා කරයි. ඇය සතුටු කරවීමට ඇගේ සිත් ගැනීමට නොයෙක් ක්‍රියා කරයි. රාගය ඇති වූ කාන්තාව සිහි කිරීම් ආදි වශයෙන් ඒ පුද්ගලයා කෙරෙහි බොහෝ චිත්ත චෛතසිකයෝ උපදිති. ඒ පුරුෂයා කෙරෙහි කාන්තාව පිළිබඳ රාගය කලින් ඇති නො විණි නම් අන් කොතෙක් හේතූන් ඇතත් කාන්තාව සම්බන්ධයෙන් පසු කාලයේ දී ඇති වන ඒ චිත්ත චෛතසිකයන්ගෙන් එකකුදු ඇති නො වේ. ඒ චිත්ත චෛතසික සමූහය ඇති වීමට රාගය ම බලවත් හේතුව වේ. ප්‍ර‍ධාන හේතුව වේ. වරක් ඇති වූ රාගය නිසා පසු කාලයේ බොහෝ චිත්ත චෛතසිකයන් ඇති වන්නාක් මෙන් සත්ත්ව සන්තානයේ උපදනා වූ අන්‍ය ක්ලේශයන් නිසා ද, ශ්‍ර‍ද්ධා ප්‍ර‍ඥාදි ශුක්ල ධර්මයන් නිසා ද, සත්ත්ව සන්තානයේ ඇති වන සුඛ දුඃඛ වේදනා දෙක නිසා ද, සේවනය කළ පුද්ගලයන් නිසා ද, වළඳන ආහාර පානයන් නිසා ද, වාසය කරන ස්ථාන නිසා ද, ශීතෝෂ්ණාදිය නිසා ද, කළ හොඳ නරක ක්‍රියා නිසා ද, පසු කාලයේ දී ඒ ඒ සන්තානයන්හි බොහෝ චිත්ත චෛතසිකයෝ උපදිති. එසේ උපදින්නා වූ චිත්ත චෛතසිකයන්ට ඒ ඒ කරුණු බලවත් හේතූහු වෙති. ප්‍ර‍කෘතෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය යි කියනුයේ රාග ශ්‍ර‍ද්ධාදි වූ ඒ බලවත් හේතූන්ට ය. පකතූපනිස්සය යන මෙහි “පකත” යනුවෙන් කියැවෙන්නේ ඉහත කී රා ශ්‍ර‍ද්ධාදි කරුණුය. පකත යන වචනයෙන් ගැනෙන කියැවෙන ඉහත කී බලවත් හේතු සමූහය ප්‍ර‍කෘතෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය නම් වේ. මෙය බොහෝ ධර්ම ඇති මහත් වූ ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යයෙකි.උපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යයේ ත්‍රි රාශියඋපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය ආරම්මණෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යයය, අනන්තරෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය, ප්‍ර‍කෘතෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය යි තෙවැදෑරුම් වේ. එයින් ආරම්ණෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යයේ ත්‍රි රාශිය ආරම්මණාධිපති ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යයේ ත්‍රි රාශිය මෙනි. අනන්තරෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යයේ ත්‍රි රාශිය අනන්තරප්‍ර‍ත්‍යයේ ත්‍රි රාශිය මෙනි. ප්‍ර‍කෘතෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යයේ ත්‍රි රාශිය මෙසේ ය.එකුන් අනූ චිත්තයය, චෛතසික දෙපනසය, රූප අට විස්සය, ඇතැම් ප්‍ර‍ඥප්තීහුය යන මොහු ප්‍ර‍කෘතෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යය ධර්මයෝ ය.එකුන් අනූ චිත්තයය, චෛතසික දෙපනසය යන මොහු ප්‍ර‍කෘතෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යයේ ප්‍රත්‍යයෝත්පන්න ධර්මයෝ ය.චිත්තජ රූපය, ප්‍ර‍තිසන්ධි කර්මජ රූපය, බාහිර රූපය, ආහාරජ රූපය, සෘතුජ රූපය, අසංඥ සත්ත්ව කර්මජ රූපය, ප්‍ර‍වෘත්ති කර්මජ රූපය යන මොහු ප්‍ර‍කෘතෝපනිඃශ්‍ර‍ය ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යයේ ප්‍ර‍ත්‍යනීක ධර්මයෝ ය."},{"question":"لدينا السؤال التالي: من هي الحيوانات التي تتمكن من تغيير اللون ؟. أجب عليه بإستخدام النص التالي: وهكذا يستطيع هذا الكائن الحي أن يبدل ويغير لون جسده بالاستعانة بانقباض العضلات التي تفرز الألوان العديدة وعلى هذا النحو تستطيع كائنات حية مثل الحرباء والرخويات أن تغير الألوان والنماذج التي على سطحها الخارجي..","answer":"لقد قمت بقراءة النص. الإجابة هي الحرباء."},{"question":"\\"Багалчагын чагуу\\" деген эмнени түшүндүрөт?","answer":"Жазалоо, бирди көрсөтүү. М: Багалчагын чаккыла Барлык сырын уккула («Эр Табылды»)"},{"question":"14 ayar altın değerli midir?","answer":"14 ayar altın genellikle takı yapımında kullanılır ve daha uygun fiyatlı bir seçenek olarak kabul edilir. Daha saf altın türlerine göre daha dayanıklı olabilir, ancak aynı zamanda daha az değerli olarak kabul edilir."},{"question":"ساقه گیاهان من قهوه‌ای و شل شده‌اند و برگ‌های آنها پژمرده شده‌اند. مشکل چیست؟","answer":"گیاهان شما ممکن است دچار پوسیدگی شده باشند که علت این مشکل افراط در آبیاری می‌باشد. در این صورت تنظیم میزان آبیاری کمک کننده است."},{"question":"ఇచ్చిన పద్యానికి భావం రాయండి:చ|| కరమున నిత్యదానము, ముఖంబున సూనృతవాణి, యౌఁదలంగురుచరణా భివాదన, మకుంఠిత వీర్యము దోర్యుగంబునన్వరహృదయంబునన్ విశదవర్తన, మంచితవిద్య వీనులన్సురుచిరభూషణంబులివి శూరులకున్ సిరి లేనియప్పుడున్ – సుభాషిత రత్నావళి","answer":"పౌరుషవంతులకు సిరిలేక పోయినప్పుడు కూడా చేతులకు దానం చేసే గుణం, నోటికి నిజం చెప్పడం, గురువుగారి పాదాలకు నమస్కరించడం శిరస్సుకు, భుజాలకు మొక్కవోని బలం, శ్రేష్ఠమైన హృదయంలో మంచి ప్రవర్తన, చెవులకు ఒప్పిదమైన విద్య అనేవి మంచి కాంతివంతమైన ఆభరణాలు."},{"question":"سوال: توهان هڪ فوسيل کي ڇا ٿا چئو جيڪو ڪڏهن به ڪم نه ڪندو آهي؟ جواب: هڪ سست هڏا! توهان جي خيال ۾ مٿين مذاق جي پينچ لائن ڇا آهي؟","answer":"وضاحت: فوسل هڪ جيئري شيءِ جا حصا آهن جيڪي محفوظ ڪيا ويا آهن، يا هڪ تمام ڊگهي وقت کان پوءِ، شايد 10 هزار سال يا وڌيڪ اڳ جا نشان ڇڏي ويا آهن. انساني ڪُلَ، جيڪا تازو مينيسوٽا ۾ ملي، ان کي فوسيل نه چيو ويو، شايد ان ڪري جو اها صرف 8000 سال پراڻي هئي. هڏا هڪ تمام عام قسم جا فوسل آهن ڇاڪاڻ ته اهي زنده شين جي نرم حصن کان وڌيڪ عرصي تائين رهندا آهن. ڇاڪاڻ ته فوسل زنده شين مان ايندا آهن جيڪي گهڻو وقت کان مري چڪا آهن، اهي ڪو به ڪم نه ڪندا آهن. هڪ سست هڏا هڪ شخص آهي جيڪو سست آهي، جيڪو مدد نه ڪندو آهي، جيڪو گهڻو ڪجهه نه ڪندو آهي. تصور ڪريو ڪو ماڻهو اهو ڪم اڪيلو ڪري رهيو آهي ۽ ٻئي شخص کي چئي رهيو آهي، \\"ايڏو سست نه هجو. مون کي هن کي حاصل ڪرڻ ۾ مدد!  هي مذاق مزيدار آهي ڇاڪاڻ ته اهو هڏن ۽ فوسيلن جي خيال سان راند ڪري ٿو، گڏوگڏ قديم هڏن کي سست هجڻ سان. ڊائنوسار فوسلز ڪيئن ٺهيل آهن اهو ڳولڻ لاءِ هتي ڏسو:"},{"question":"O que significa o ditado popular: \\"Roupa suja se lava em casa\\"?","answer":"Este ditado indica que as pessoas devem discutir ou brigar somente entre membros da família, não na frente de desconhecidos."},{"question":"ਕਿਰਪਾ ਕਰਕੇ ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ ਵਿਸਥਾਰ ਵਿੱਚ ਦੱਸੋ ਕਿ ਹੇਠਾਂ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਦਾ ਕੀ ਅਰਥ ਹੈ।\\"ਮਾਝ ਮਹਲਾ ੩ ॥ਮੇਰਾ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਨਿਰਮਲੁ ਅਗਮ ਅਪਾਰਾ ॥ਬਿਨੁ ਤਕੜੀ ਤੋਲੈ ਸੰਸਾਰਾ ॥ਗੁਰਮੁਖਿ ਹੋਵੈ ਸੋਈ ਬੂਝੈ ਗੁਣ ਕਹਿ ਗੁਣੀ ਸਮਾਵਣਿਆ ॥੧॥ਹਉ ਵਾਰੀ ਜੀਉ ਵਾਰੀ ਹਰਿ ਕਾ ਨਾਮੁ ਮੰਨਿ ਵਸਾਵਣਿਆ ॥ਜੋ ਸਚਿ ਲਾਗੇ ਸੇ ਅਨਦਿਨੁ ਜਾਗੇ ਦਰਿ ਸਚੈ ਸੋਭਾ ਪਾਵਣਿਆ ॥੧॥ ਰਹਾਉ ॥ਆਪਿ ਸੁਣੈ ਤੈ ਆਪੇ ਵੇਖੈ ॥ਜਿਸ ਨੋ ਨਦਰਿ ਕਰੇ ਸੋਈ ਜਨੁ ਲੇਖੈ ॥ਆਪੇ ਲਾਇ ਲਏ ਸੋ ਲਾਗੈ ਗੁਰਮੁਖਿ ਸਚੁ ਕਮਾਵਣਿਆ ॥੨॥ਜਿਸੁ ਆਪਿ ਭੁਲਾਏ ਸੁ ਕਿਥੈ ਹਥੁ ਪਾਏ ॥ਪੂਰਬਿ ਲਿਖਿਆ ਸੁ ਮੇਟਣਾ ਨ ਜਾਏ ॥ਜਿਨ ਸਤਿਗੁਰੁ ਮਿਲਿਆ ਸੇ ਵਡਭਾਗੀ ਪੂਰੈ ਕਰਮਿ ਮਿਲਾਵਣਿਆ ॥੩॥ਪੇਈਅੜੈ ਧਨ ਅਨਦਿਨੁ ਸੁਤੀ ॥ਕੰਤਿ ਵਿਸਾਰੀ ਅਵਗਣਿ ਮੁਤੀ ॥ਅਨਦਿਨੁ ਸਦਾ ਫਿਰੈ ਬਿਲਲਾਦੀ ਬਿਨੁ ਪਿਰ ਨੀਦ ਨ ਪਾਵਣਿਆ ॥੪॥ਪੇਈਅੜੈ ਸੁਖਦਾਤਾ ਜਾਤਾ ॥ਹਉਮੈ ਮਾਰਿ ਗੁਰ ਸਬਦਿ ਪਛਾਤਾ ॥ਸੇਜ ਸੁਹਾਵੀ ਸਦਾ ਪਿਰੁ ਰਾਵੇ ਸਚੁ ਸੀਗਾਰੁ ਬਣਾਵਣਿਆ ॥੫॥ਲਖ ਚਉਰਾਸੀਹ ਜੀਅ ਉਪਾਏ ॥ਜਿਸ ਨੋ ਨਦਰਿ ਕਰੇ ਤਿਸੁ ਗੁਰੂ ਮਿਲਾਏ ॥ਕਿਲਬਿਖ ਕਾਟਿ ਸਦਾ ਜਨ ਨਿਰਮਲ ਦਰਿ ਸਚੈ ਨਾਮਿ ਸੁਹਾਵਣਿਆ ॥੬॥ਲੇਖਾ ਮਾਗੈ ਤਾ ਕਿਨਿ ਦੀਐ ॥ਸੁਖੁ ਨਾਹੀ ਫੁਨਿ ਦੂਐ ਤੀਐ ॥ਆਪੇ ਬਖਸਿ ਲਏ ਪ੍ਰਭੁ ਸਾਚਾ ਆਪੇ ਬਖਸਿ ਮਿਲਾਵਣਿਆ ॥੭॥ਆਪਿ ਕਰੇ ਤੈ ਆਪਿ ਕਰਾਏ ॥ਪੂਰੇ ਗੁਰ ਕੈ ਸਬਦਿ ਮਿਲਾਏ ॥ਨਾਨਕ ਨਾਮੁ ਮਿਲੈ ਵਡਿਆਈ ਆਪੇ ਮੇਲਿ ਮਿਲਾਵਣਿਆ ॥੮॥੨॥੩॥\\"","answer":"ਇਹ ਸ੍ਰੀ ਗੁਰੂ ਗ੍ਰੰਥ ਸਾਹਿਬ ਜੀ ਦੇ ਪੰਨਾ 110 ਤੋਂ ਲਿਆ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਗੁਰੂ ਅਮਰਦਾਸ ਜੀ ਇਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਵਾਰਾਂ ਦੇ ਲਿਖਾਰੀ ਸਨ।ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਹੇਠ ਲਿਖੇ ਅਨੁਸਾਰ ਵਿਖਿਆਨ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ,\\"ਪਿਆਰਾ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਆਪ ਪਵਿਤ੍ਰ-ਸਰੂਪ ਹੈ ਅਪਹੁੰਚ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਬੇਅੰਤ ਹੈ । ਉਹ ਤੱਕੜੀ (ਵਰਤਣ ਤੋਂ) ਬਿਨਾ ਹੀ ਸਾਰੇ ਸੰਸਾਰ ਦੇ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਦੇ ਜੀਵਨ ਨੂੰ ਪਰਖਦਾ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ (ਹਰੇਕ ਜੀਵ ਦੇ ਅੰਦਰ ਵਿਆਪਕ ਰਹਿ ਕੇ) । (ਇਸ ਭੇਤ ਨੂੰ) ਉਹੀ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਸਮਝਦਾ ਹੈ ਜੋ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਸਨਮੁਖ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ (ਗੁਰੂ ਦੀ ਰਾਹੀਂ) ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੇ ਗੁਣ ਉਚਾਰ ਕੇ ਗੁਣਾਂ ਦੇ ਮਾਲਕ-ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਵਿਚ ਲੀਨ ਹੋਇਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ ।੧। ਮੈਂ ਸਦਾ ਉਹਨਾਂ ਤੋਂ ਸਦਕੇ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹਾਂ, ਜੋ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦਾ ਨਾਮ ਆਪਣੇ ਮਨ ਵਿਚ ਵਸਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ । ਜੇਹੜੇ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਵਿਚ ਲਿਵ ਲਾਈ ਰੱਖਦੇ ਹਨ, ਉਹ ਹਰ ਵੇਲੇ ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਹੱਲਿਆਂ ਵਲੋਂ ਸੁਚੇਤ ਰਹਿੰਦੇ ਹਨ, ਤੇ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਰਹਿਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਦੀ ਹਜ਼ੂਰੀ ਵਿਚ ਸੋਭਾ ਪਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।੧।ਰਹਾਉ।ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਆਪ ਹੀ (ਸਭ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਦੀ ਅਰਦਾਸ) ਸੁਣਦਾ ਹੈ ਤੇ ਆਪ ਹੀ (ਸਭ ਦੀ) ਸੰਭਾਲ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ । ਜਿਸ ਜੀਵ ਉੱਤੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਮਿਹਰ ਦੀ ਨਜ਼ਰ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹੀ ਮਨੁੱਖ (ਉਸਦੇ ਦਰ ਤੇ) ਕਬੂਲ ਹੁੰਦਾ ਹੈ । ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੂੰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਆਪ ਆਪਣੀ ਯਾਦ ਵਿਚ ਜੋੜੀ ਰੱਖਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹੀ ਜੁੜਿਆ ਰਹਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਸਨਮੁਖ ਹੋ ਕੇ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਨਾਮ ਸਿਮਰਨ ਦੀ ਕਮਾਈ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ ।੨। (ਪਰ) ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੂੰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਆਪ ਗ਼ਲਤ ਰਸਤੇ ਪਾ ਦੇਵੇ, ਉਹ (ਸਹੀ ਰਾਹ ਲੱਭਣ ਵਾਸਤੇ) ਕਿਸੇ ਹੋਰ ਦਾ ਆਸਰਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਲੈ ਸਕਦਾ । ਪੂਰਬਲੇ ਜਨਮ ਵਿਚ ਕੀਤੇ ਕਰਮਾਂ ਦੇ ਸੰਸਕਾਰਾਂ ਦਾ ਲੇਖ ਮਿਟਾਇਆ ਨਹੀਂ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ (ਤੇ ਉਹ ਲੇਖ ਕੁਰਾਹੇ ਪਾਈ ਰੱਖਦਾ ਹੈ) ।ਜਿਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਮਨੁੱਖਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪੂਰਾ ਗੁਰੂ ਮਿਲ ਪੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਵੱਡੇ ਭਾਗਾਂ ਵਾਲੇ ਜਾਣੋ । ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਪੂਰੀ ਮਿਹਰ ਨਾਲ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਆਪਣੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਮਿਲਾਈ ਰੱਖਦਾ ਹੈ ।੩। ਜੇਹੜੀ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਇਸ ਲੋਕ ਵਿਚ ਹਰ ਵੇਲੇ ਮਾਇਆ ਦੇ ਮੋਹ ਦੀ ਨੀਂਦ ਵਿਚ ਮਸਤ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ।ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਖਸਮ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਨੇ ਭੁਲਾ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਆਪਣੀ ਭੁੱਲ ਦੇ ਕਾਰਨ ਛੁੱਟੜ ਹੋਈ ਪਈ ਹੈ । ਉਹ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਹਰ ਵੇਲੇ ਦੁਖੀ ਭਟਕਦੀ ਫਿਰਦੀ ਹੈ, ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਪਤੀ ਦੇ ਮਿਲਾਪ ਤੋਂ ਬਿਨਾ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਆਤਮਕ ਸੁਖ ਨਹੀਂ ਮਿਲਦਾ ।੪। ਜਿਸ ਜੀਵ-ਇਸਤ੍ਰੀ ਨੇ ਪੇਕੇ ਘਰ ਵਿਚ ਸੁਖ ਦੇਣ ਵਾਲੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਪਤੀ ਨਾਲ ਡੂੰਘੀ ਸਾਂਝ ਪਾਈ ਰੱਖੀ। ਜਿਸ ਨੇ (ਆਪਣੇ ਅੰਦਰੋਂ) ਹਉਮੈ ਦੂਰ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਸ਼ਬਦ ਵਿਚ ਜੁੜ ਕੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਪਤੀ ਨੂੰ ਪਛਾਣ ਲਿਆ । ਉਸ ਦੇ ਹਿਰਦੇ ਦੀ ਸੇਜ ਸੋਹਣੀ ਬਣ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ, ਉਹ ਸਦਾ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ-ਪਤੀ ਦਾ ਮਿਲਾਪ ਮਾਣਦੀ ਹੈ, ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਨਾਮ ਨੂੰ ਉਹ ਆਪਣੇ ਜੀਵਨ ਦਾ ਸ਼ਿੰਗਾਰ ਬਣਾ ਲੈਂਦੀ ਹੈ ।੫। ਪਰਮਾਤਮਾ ਨੇ ਚੌਰਾਸੀ ਲੱਖ ਜੂੁਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਬੇਅੰਤ ਜੀਵ ਪੈਦਾ ਕੀਤੇ ਹੋਏ ਹਨ । ਜਿਸ ਜੀਵ ਉੱਤੇ ਉਹ ਮੇਹਰ ਦੀ ਨਜ਼ਰ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਗੁਰੂ ਮਿਲਾ ਦੇਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।(ਗੁਰੂ-ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਜੁੜੇ ਹੋਏ) ਬੰਦੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਪਾਪ ਦੂਰ ਕਰਕੇ ਸਦਾ ਪਵਿਤ੍ਰ-ਜੀਵਨ ਵਾਲੇ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ, ਤੇ ਸਦਾ-ਥਿਰ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਦਰ ਤੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਦੇ ਨਾਮ ਦੀ ਬਰਕਤਿ ਨਾਲ ਸੋਭਾ ਪਾਂਦੇ ਹਨ ।੬।(ਅਸੀ ਜੀਵ ਸਦਾ ਭੁੱਲਣਹਾਰ ਹਾਂ) ਜੇ ਪ੍ਰਭੂ (ਸਾਡੇ ਕੀਤੇ ਕਰਮਾਂ ਦਾ) ਹਿਸਾਬ ਮੰਗਣ ਲੱਗੇ, ਤਾਂ ਕੋਈ ਜੀਵ ਹਿਸਾਬ ਨਹੀਂ ਦੇ ਸਕਦਾ (ਭਾਵ, ਲੇਖੇ ਵਿਚ ਪੂਰਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਉਤਰ ਸਕਦਾ) ।(ਆਪਣੇ ਕੀਤੇ ਕਰਮਾਂ ਦਾ) ਲੇਖਾ ਗਿਣਾਇਆਂ (ਭਾਵ, ਲੇਖੇ ਵਿਚ ਸੁਰਖ਼ਰੂ ਹੋਣ ਦੀ ਆਸ ਤੇ) ਕਿਸੇ ਨੂੰ ਆਤਮਕ ਆਨੰਦ ਨਹੀਂ ਮਿਲ ਸਕਦਾ । ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਆਪ ਹੀ ਮਿਹਰ ਕਰਕੇ (ਆਪਣੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ) ਮਿਲਾ ਲੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੭। (ਸਭ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਵਿਆਪਕ ਹੋ ਕੇ) ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਆਪ ਹੀ (ਸਭ ਕੁਝ) ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ ਅਤੇ ਆਪ ਹੀ (ਪ੍ਰੇਰਨਾ ਕਰ ਕੇ ਜੀਵਾਂ ਪਾਸੋਂ) ਕਰਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ । ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਆਪ ਹੀ ਪੂਰੇ ਗੁਰੂ ਦੇ ਸ਼ਬਦ ਵਿਚ ਜੋੜ ਕੇ ਆਪਣੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਮਿਲਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।ਹੇ ਨਾਨਕ ! ਜਿਸ ਮਨੁੱਖ ਨੂੰ (ਉਸ ਦੇ ਦਰ ਤੋਂ ਉਸ ਦਾ) ਨਾਮ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈ, ਉਸ ਨੂੰ (ਉਸ ਦੀ ਹਜ਼ੂਰੀ ਵਿਚ) ਆਦਰ ਮਿਲਦਾ ਹੈ, ਪ੍ਰਭੂ ਆਪ ਹੀ ਉਸ ਨੂੰ ਆਪਣੇ ਚਰਨਾਂ ਵਿਚ ਜੋੜ ਲੈਂਦਾ ਹੈ ।੮।੨।੩।\\""},{"question":"చదరంగం గురించి రాయండి.","answer":"చదరంగం. భారత జాతీయ క్రీడ. ప్రపంచానికి చదరంగం ఆటను ప్రసాదించినది భారతదేశమే ! పూర్వం దీనిని అష్టాపదమని పిలిచేవారు. మనదేశం నుండి ఈ ఆట పర్షియా, అరేబియా, తూర్పు చైనా దేశాలకు వ్యాపించింది. – 10వ శతాబ్దం చివరిలో అరబ్బులు ఈ ఆటను స్పెయిన్ దేశానికి తీసుకుపోయారు. 11వ శతాబ్దంలో ఐరోపాకు పరిచయం అయింది. ఈ ఆటను పూర్వం ఉన్నత కులాలవారు మాత్రమే ఆడేవారు. విజయనగర ప్రభువు కృష్ణదేవరాయలు ఈ ఆటను అమితంగా ప్రేమించారు.ఆయన బొడ్డుచర్ల తిమ్మనతో ప్రతిరోజూ ఆడేవారట. రాయల తరపున ఎందరు ఆడినా ఒక్కడే ఉండి తిమ్మన విజయం సాధించేవాడట. పూర్వం యుద్ధమునకు వెళ్ళే సమయాన ఈ ఆటను ఆడి ఎత్తులకు పై ఎత్తులు వేసేవారని చరిత్ర తెలియజేస్తుంది. ఈనాడు చదరంగం ప్రపంచ క్రీడలలో చేరింది. ఇప్పటికి కూడా ముందుగానే చెప్పి ఆట కట్టించగల క్రీడాకారులు. తెలుగుదేశాన ఎందరో ఉన్నారు."},{"question":"misitu ina umuhimu gani?","answer":"katika uhai wa binadamu hifadhi ya misitu ina umuhimu sana, na leo tuangalie baadhi ya faida za hifadhi ya miti kwa binadamu. kwanza, miti huleta hewa nyingi na safi kwa mazingira ya binadamu. pili, hifadhi za miti huleta tija kibiashara kwa kuzalisha mbao ambazo hutumika kutengeneza viti, meza, nyumba, madirisha na kadhalika."},{"question":"رسيدات څه شی ده ؟","answer":"ځواب: رسيدات هغه دفتر ده چي د هغه له مخي د واردې او صادرې د ک تاب صادر شوي مکتوب نمبر ، تاریخ ، مرسل او مرسل اليه مرجع رسېږي . د مرسل مرجع په مقابل کي له شخص یا تسليموونکې ادارې څخه لاسلیک اخيستل کېږي ."},{"question":"මැලේසියාවේ අගනුවර කුමක්ද?","answer":"ක්වාලාලම්පූර්"},{"question":"Inona no fiantraikan'ny fanamafisana amin'ny psikolojia?","answer":"Ny fiantraikan'ny fanamafisana ao amin'ny psikolojia dia manondro ny fironan'ny olona mitady, mandika ary mitadidy vaovao amin'ny fomba manamafy ny finoany efa nisy teo aloha."},{"question":"Apakah jawapan untuk teka-teki berikut: Saya boleh dijumpai di atas air, tetapi saya tidak tahu berenang dan bergerak. Siapakah saya?","answer":"Jawapannya ialah jambatan. Jambatan adalah satu struktur yang dibina untuk menyeberangi jurang atau rintangan seperti sungai, landasan keretapi ataupun jalan raya. Ia dibina untuk membolehkan laluan pejalan kaki, pemandu kenderaan atau keretapi di atas halangan itu."},{"question":"“اقامة رائعه”. كل ما في الفندق رائع. ماهي مشاعر المراجعة السابقة؟","answer":"الجملة تحتوي على مشاعر ممتازة."},{"question":"یک نامه استعفای رسمی برایم بنویس که اعلام کند من در تاریخ ۱ آبان ۱۴۰۲ قصد ترک شرکت x را دارم.","answer":"با سلام و درودبه استحضار آن مقام محترم می‌رساند اینجانب (نام) از مورخه (تاریخ) در واحد (نام واحد) در اختیار مجموعه x بوده‌ام.بنا به دلایلی از مورخه ۱ آبان ۱۴۰۲ قادر به ادامه همکاری با این شرکت نخواهم بود.از اینکه در این مدت فرصت همکاری با آن مجموعه را داشتم، بسیار خرسندم. امیدوارم حضور بنده در این مجموعه مفید بوده باشد.مراتب و اقدامات لازم جهت پیگیری حضورتان ارسال خواهد شد.ارادتمند شما:نام و نام خانوادگی / امضا"},{"question":"Laburtu artikulua: By . Associated Press eta Daily Mail Reporter . ARGITARATUA: . 16:41 EST, 2013ko uztailaren 10a. | . EGUNERATU: . 09:34 EST, 2013ko uztailaren 11. Itsas Armadak ehiza-hegazkin baten tamainako drone bat lehorreratu du asteazkenean lehen aldiz hegazkin-ontzi batean, militarrek programa informatiko batek pilotuari eskatzen zaion zeregin zailenetako bat egiteko duen gaitasuna erakutsiz. X-47B hegazkin esperimentalaren lurreratzeak esan nahi du Armadak bere planekin aurrera egin dezakeela tripulatu gabeko beste hegazkin bat garatzeko, hegazkin tradizionalekin batera flotan batuko dena, zaintza zaintza eskaintzeko, eta eraso ahalmena ere badu. Gainera, bidea irekiko luke AEBek tripulaziorik gabeko hegazkinak abiaraz ditzaten, beste herrialde batzuei beren oinarriak erabiltzeko baimenik lortu beharrik gabe. Joan behera bideoa ikusteko. Aireratzea: X47-B Armadako drone bat USS George HW Bush hegazkin-ontziaren bizkarretik jaurti zen asteazkenean. X-47B hegazkin esperimentala Maryland-eko Patuxent River Naval Air Station-etik atera zen USS George HW Bushera hurbildu baino lehen, Virginiako kostaldean ari dena. Droneak lur hartu zuen itsasontzian hari bat harrapatu eta azkar geldiarazi zuen isats-gantxo bat zabalduz, ehiza-hegazkin arruntek egiten duten bezala. Hegaldia egitea: X-47B ez da inoiz funtzionamenduan jarriko, baina Armadako funtzionarioei etorkizuneko garraiolarietan oinarritutako droneak garatzen lagunduko die. Maniobra atxilotutako lurreratzea bezala ezagutzen da eta lehenago droneak bakarrik egin zuen Patuxent ibaian lurrean. Hegazkin-ontziaren atzean dagoen aire nahasietan nabigatzean etengabe mugitzen den itsasontzi batean lurreratzea maniobra zailagoa dela ikusten da. «Zure bilobak eta birbilobak eta nireak gertaera historiko honi buruz irakurriko dute beren historia liburuetan. Hau ez da hutsala, ezta arin gertatu den zerbait ere&#39;, esan zuen Mat Winter-ek, Armadako programako ofizial exekutiboak, tripulaziorik gabeko hegazkintzarako eta greba-armeetarako. X-47B ez da inoiz funtzionamenduan jarriko, baina Armadako funtzionarioei etorkizuna garatzen lagunduko die...","answer":"Itsas Armadak hegazkin-ontzi batean lurreratu du ehiza-hegazkin baten tamainako drone bat, X-47B hegazkin esperimentala, militarrak bere software aurreratuak pilotu batek egin beharko luketen maniobra zailean ahal izango duela frogatuz. Drone honek bere lurreratzeak AEBek tripulaziorik gabeko hegazkinak erabil ditzakeela erakusten du, beste herrialdeen oinarriak erabil beharrik izan gabe. X-47B Maryland-eko Patuxent River Naval Air Station-etik abiatu zen eta USS George HW Bush hegazkin-ontzian lurreratu zen isats-gantzo baten bidez. Hala ere, X-47B inoiz ez da funtzionamenduan jarriko, baina etorkizuneko droneen garapenean erabiliko da. Mat Winter, Armadako ofizial exekutiboak, honen garrantzia nabarmendu du, esanez gertaera historiko bat dela."},{"question":"Quem é o deus grego da terra fértil?","answer":"Deméter."},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'intan itu jika terbenam dalam pelimbahan sekalipun tidak akan hilang cahayanya'?","answer":"Ia bermaksud kebenaran akan ternyata juga walaupun cuba disembunyikan oleh orang lain"},{"question":"අඩසඳ මෝරන මැදියම්  අහසින්  බිළිඳු  හදට කිරි දියර ගලයි.මෙහි අදහස පැහැදිලි  කර දෙන්න","answer":"මෙහිදි පවසන හා  දැකිය හැකි දෙයක් තියනවා සඳ මේරීම යනු වැඩි වීමයි එය මැදියම් රාත්‍රිය දනවයි ඒ මොහොතේත් දරුවන්ගේ මනස ගුණ නුවණින් පිරවීමට දෙමාපියන් කටයුතු කරයි හදට කිරි දියර ගැලීම යනු හදවත් ගුණයෙන් පිරවීමයි.ඒ අතරම දිවා කාලය පුරාවට දරුවන් වෙනුවෙන් තම ශ්‍රමය කැපකළ දෙමාපියන් මැදියම් රැයේවත් නිදි නැත ඔවුන් දරුවන්ගේ හීනෙන් දක්වන සිනහව දැක සතුටුවන අතර තමන් දරුවන්ට හෙට දිනට ගොඩ නඟන සුන්දර ලෝකය දකිමින් සතුටු වන බව දක්වයි.දෙමාපියන් දහවල් පමණක් නොව මැදියම් රෑ පවා දරුවන් වෙනුවෙන්ම කැපවන බව දක්වයි."},{"question":"ලොව උසම කඳු 10 මොනවද?","answer":"ලොව උසම කඳු 10 උසත් සමඟ අනුපිළිවෙලින් පහත දැක්වේ.1. එවරස්ට් කන්ද(මීටර් 8848)2. k2 කන්ද(මීටර්  8611)3. කාංචන් චුන්ගා කන්ද(මීටර් 8586) 4. ලොට් සී කන්ද(මීටර් 8516)5. මකාලු කන්ද(මීටර් 8485)6. චොයු කන්ද(මීටර් 8188)7. ධවලගිරි I කන්ද(මීටර් 8167)8. මනස්ලු කන්ද(මීටර් 8163)9. නන්ගාපාර්බත් කන්ද(මීටර් 8126) 10. අන්නාපූර්නා I කන්ද(මීටර් 8091)"},{"question":"ब्रिटीश ईस्ट इंडिया कंपनीची स्थापना केव्हा झाली ?","answer":"इ.स. 1600 मध्ये"},{"question":"De quais materiais é feito o vidro?","answer":"O vidro é feito da mistura básica de areia de sílica, sódio e cálcio. O material passa por vários processos até se torna o vidro como conhecemos."},{"question":"Ìmòye","answer":"Ìmòye (Philosophia; Philosophy) ni igbeka awon isoro gbogbo ati pipilese lori ohun bi iwalaye, imo, iyi, ironu, emi ati ede. O yato si awon ona idojuko ibere pipilese (bi Iseawo, itan-abiso tabi awon iseona) nipa ona oniyewo, ati ni gbogbo ona sistemu ati igbokan le re lori iyan alalaye. \\"Philosophy\\" (filosofi) wa lati ede Griki φιλοσοφία (philosophia), to tumo si \\"ife oye\\".Ìwọ̀nyí ni àwọn ẹ̀ka ti won je gbigbeka ju lo:Oro-adanida ni igbeka eda wiwa ati aye. Awon eka re ni oro-igbeaye and oro-iwalaaye.oro-ijinle nje mo eda ati ise imo, atipe boya imo se e se. Ninu re ni ti ri isoro iseiyemeji ati ibasepo larin ooto, igbagbo, ati idalare.Iwawiwu, tabi \\"imoye oniwayiyeni\\", bere bawo ni eni gbodo se huwa tabi boya iru ibere bahun gan ni idahun. Awon eka re ni oro-iwawiwu, ìṣe iwawiwu, ati imulo iwaiwu. oro iwawiwu nda lori eda ero oniwa, afiwe orisi awon sistemu oniwuwa, boya awon ooto oniwawiwu kedere wa, ati bi iru ooto bayi se le je mimo. Bakanna iwawiwu je jijose mo arowa ijeiwatoyeni. Awon iwe dialogi Plato ti bere mupo iwadi fun itumo idara.Imoye olselu ni igbeka ijoba ati ibasepo awon enikookan ati awon agbajo mo orileijoba. O mupo awon ibere nipa idajo, ohun didara, ofin, ini ati awon eto ati ojuse omoilu.Oro-ewa da lo ri ewa, ona, igbadun, awon iyi sensory-emotional, ihansi, ati nipa iwu ati italara.Ogbon je igbeka awon iru ijiyan afesemule. Lati opin orun 19th, awon onimo mathimatiki bi Frege teju si fifi mathimatiki se ogbon, loni oro nipa ogbon pin si meji: ogbon mathimatiki (formal symbolic logic; ogbon ami-idamo) ati eyi ti a mo loni bi ogbon onimoye.Ìmòye ẹ̀mí nda le eda emi ati ibasepo re mo ara, o se pataki nitori ijiyan larin ìṣeẹ̀mí meji ati iseohunaye. Apa imoye yi na tun ni ibasepo mo sayensi oloye.Imoye ede n se awari eda, ibere ati ilo ede.Imoye esin ni apa imoye to un bere awon ibere nipa esin."},{"question":"මලක කොටස් කීයක් තිබේද?","answer":"බොහෝ මල් වල ප්‍රධාන කොටස් හතරක් ඇත: සීපල්(sepals), පෙති(petals), රේණු (statemens) සහ කාපල්(carpels). රේණු යනු පිරිමි කොටස වන අතර කාපල් යනු මලෙහි කාන්තා කොටසයි. බොහෝ මල් හර්මෆ්‍රොඩයිට්(hermaphrodite) වන අතර එහි පිරිමි සහ ගැහැණු කොටස් දෙකම අඩංගු වේ."},{"question":"Cách đây 10 tháng tôi đã phẫu thuật bong võng mạc mắt, và do nguyên nhân bị đục thủy tinh thể, nên tôi đã phẫu thuật đặt mắt nhân tạo cách đây 6 năm. Hiện tại mắt đã phẫu thuật của tôi vào ban đêm nhìn ko được rõ lắm. Cho tôi hỏi bác sĩ, hiện mắt tôi có thể đeo kính cận thị được không? Tôi đã phẫu thuật bong vong mạc thì có được chơi đá bóng ko? Tôi xin chân thành cảm ơn bác sĩ.","answer":"Chào bạn, mắt sau khi phẫu thuật nếu cần đeo kính để nhìn rõ hơn (kể cả cận thị, viễn thị hay loạn thị) bạn đều có thể đeo được. Tuy nhiên số kính nên được kiểm tra chính xác vì sự thích nghi trên mắt đã mổ bong võng mạc không dễ như mắt chưa qua phẫu thuật. Bạn không nên chơi đá bóng hoặc các môn thể thao mang tính chất đối kháng vì võng mạc có thể bong tái phát, gây hậu quả nặng nề cho mắt, khó điều trị hơn rất nhiều so với lần đầu."},{"question":"普通のテレビの走査線は５２５本ですが、ハイビジョンの走査線の数は何本あるでしょう？","answer":"１１２５本です。"},{"question":"Nọ́mbà gidi","answer":"Nínú Ìmọ̀ Ìṣirò nọ́mbà gidi (real number) ni a mọ̀ sí àwọn nọ́mbà tí a Ko lè gé, gẹ́gẹ́ bí nọ́mbà oníyemẹ́wàá (decimals) tí kò lópin. Fún àpẹẹrẹ 2.4871773339…. Àwọn nọ́mbà gidi jẹ́ nọ́mbà oníìpín, nọ́mbà bí 42 àti −23/129, àti nọ́mbà aláìníìpín, nọ́mbà gbòngbò alágbára-méjì]] 2 (square root) tí wọ́n sì ṣeé fihàn gẹ́gẹ́ bí ojúàmì (point) ní orí ìlà nọ́mbà tó gùn ní àìlópin.A ń pe àwọn nọ́mbà gidi bẹ́ẹ̀ láti lè ṣèyàtọ̀ sí àwon nọ́mbà tósòro (complex number). Ní ayé àtijọ́ àwọn onímọ̀ ìṣirò mọ nọ́mbà tó rújú gẹ́gẹ́ bí nọ́mbà afòyemọ̀ (imaginary number).Nọ́mbà gidi lè jẹ́ onípìín tàbí aláìnípìín; Ó lè jẹ́ nọ́mbà Ọ̀jíbírà tàbí nọ́mbà t tí kò ní ònkà (transcendental number); bẹ́ẹ̀ sì ni wọ́n lè jẹ́ nọ́mbà tódájú, ni odi tàbí kí wọ́n jẹ́ òdo.A n fi nomba gidi se iwon awon opoiye to je wiwapapo (continuous). O se se ka fi won han gege bi nombamewa to ni itelentele (sequence) eyonomba (digit) ti ko lopin lapa otun ojuami nombamewa (decimal point); a le fi won han bayi 324.823211247…. Awon ami bintin meta to wa leyin nomba yi tumosi pe awon eyonomba miran si n bo leyin.Bakanna, awon nomba gidi tun ni idamo meji ti papa elesese (ordered field) ni, be ni won si ni idamo ti a mo si ipari l'oke tokerejulo (least upper bound). Akoko so fun wa pe awon nomba gidi ni papa kan, pelu aropo, isodipupo ati isepinpin pelu awon nomba ti ki se odo ti won le je elesese lapapo ni ori ila nomba lona to ni ibamu po mo aropo ati isodipupo. Ekeji so fun wa pe ti akojopo nomba gidi ti ki se ofo (empty) ba ni ipari l'oke (upper bound), o gbudo ni ipari l'oke tokerejulo. Awon mejeji yi lapapo ni won se'tumo nomba gidi patapata. Lati inu won ni awon idamo nomba gidi yioku ti jade wa. Fun apere a le fihan pe gbogbo polynomial (alamipupo) alagbara nomba siseku pelu nomba ibamulo (coefficient) gidi yio ni gbongbo gidi; ati pe ti a ba s'aropo gbongbo alagbarameji idin okan (minus one) po mo nomba gidi lati fun wa ni nomba tosoro, esi yi ni a n so pe o je titi ninu aljebra.A n se iwon ninu Imo Sayensi Alagbamu (physical science) gege bi won ba n sunmo nomba gidi to. Bo tile je pe awon nomba ti a n lo fun eyi je ida nombamewa (decimal fraction) ti won duro fun awon nomba oniipin, nipa kiko won sile gege bi nombamewa fihan pe won n sunmo nomba gidi kan.A n so pe nomba gidi se sesiro ti igbese isiro ti a mo si Algorithm ba wa ti yio mu eyonomba re wa. Nitoripe bo tile wu ki awon algorithm re o po to, won niye pato (countable), sugbon awon nomba gidi ko niye (uncountable), nitori eyi opo ninu awon nomba gidi ni won ko se sesiro.Ero onka Komputa le sunmo nomba gidi nikan. L'apapo won le s'oju fun awon inuakojopo (subset) awon nomba oniipin pato kan, nipa lilo nomba ojuami tonlefo (floating point) tabi nomba ojuami soso (fixed point), be sini awon nomba oniipin yi n je lilo lati sunmo awon iye gidi ti won sunmo won.Awon onimo isiro n lo ami R (tabi �{displaystyle mathbb {R} } tabi Unicode ℝ) lati se'duro fun akojopo gbogbo nomba gidi. Ami ikosile Rn n tokasi aaye elegbe-n pelu ipoidojuko (coordinate) gidi won. Fun apere awon iye R3 je nomba gidi meta ti won tokasi ipo kookan ninu aaye elegbe meta (3 dimension).A lé mú nomba gidí wa gégé bí àkótán àwon nomba oniìpín ni ònà tó jé pé ìtèntèle nomba kan se fẹsíwájú pèlú nombámèwa tàbí nombáméjì (binary) báyí {3, 3.1, 3.14, 3.141, 3.1415,...} f'enuko sí nomba pàtò gidí kan.E je ki R ki o duro fun akojopo gbogbo nomba gidi. Nitorie:Akojopo R je papa kan. Eyi tumosi pe a le se aropo ati isodipupo ninu re.Papa R je elesese. Eyi tumosi pe a ni apapo elesese ≥ to je pe, fun gbogbo nomba gidi x, y ati z:ti x ≥ y nitorie x + z ≥ y + z;ti x ≥ 0 ati y ≥ 0 nitorie xy ≥ 0.Eseese yi je akotan Dedekind. Eyi tumosi pe gbogbo abeikojopo S (subset) ti ki se ofo, fun R pelu ipari l'oke ninu R ni ipari l'oke tokerejulo (least upper bound or supremum) kan ninu R.Idamo to gbeyin yi lo seyato larin nomba gidi ati nomba oniipin. Fun apere akojopo awon nomba oniipin ti alagbarameji won din si 2 ni nomba oniipin ipari l'oke (apere 1.5) sugbon won ko ni nomba onipin ipari l'oke tokerejulo, nitoripe gbongbo alagbarameji 2 ko se pin.TitanIdi pataki ti a tun se seyato awon nomba gidi ni pe won ni gbogbo opin (limit). A le so pe won \\"\\"tan\\". Eyi tumosi bawonyi:Itelentele kan (xn) nomba gidi ni a n pe ni ìtẹ̀léntẹ̀lé Cauchy to je pe fun ε > 0, nomba odidi N kan wa to je pe ijinnasi (distance) |xn − xm| kere ju ε eyun to ba je pe n ati m tobi ju N lo. Ni ede mi, itelentele je itelentele Cauchy ti awon afida (element) xn re ba sunmo ara won gbagba.Itelentele (xn) foriko po si opin x to ba je pe fun ε > 0, nomba odidi N kan wa to je pe ijinnasi |xn − x| kere ju ε lo, to ba je pe n tobi ju N lo. Ni ede miran, itelentele kan ni opin x ti awon afida (element) re ba sunmo x gbagbagba.A ri bayi pe gbogbo itelentele ti o n foriko si oju kanna ni itelentele Cauchy.Gbogbo itelentele Cauchy fun nomba gidi je eyi to n foriko si oju kanna.Bayi wipe awon nomba gidi \\"tan\\".S'akiyesi pe awon nomba onipin ko lo tan o. Fun apere itelentele 1, 1.4, 1.41, 1.414, 1.4142, 1.41421, …) je ti Cauchy sugbon won ko foriko si nomba oniipin. (Eyi yatosi nomba gidi ti won foriko si gbongbo alagbarameji 2).Nitoripe awon opin wa fun awon itelentele Cauchy ni isiro Kalkulosi fi se e se, ti o si wulo. Ona kan ti a fi le sewadi boya itelentele kan ni opin ni ki a yewo boya o je itelentele Cauchy, nitoripe a ko le mo opin yi tele.Eyi fihan pe itelentele Cauchy ni o je. A ti mo bayi pe itenlentele ohun foriko si opin kan bi a ko ba ti e le so opin ibi ti o foriko si."},{"question":"فیلم چهارشنبه‌سوری ساخته چه سالی است و چه کسی آن را کارگردانی کرده است؟","answer":"چهارشنبه‌سوری محصول سال ۱۳۸۴ است و کارگردان آن اصغر فرهادی فرهادی است."},{"question":"Sheeg sanadkii uu soo islaamay halyeey-gii cumar bin khadaab RC?","answer":"Sanadkii uu soo islaamay halyeey-gii cumar bin khadaab RC waa sanadkii 6-aad ee Nabinimada rasuulka (N.N.K.H) loo-soo saaray."},{"question":"வினா:இரட்டைக் காப்பியங்கள் என அழைக்கப்படுபவைஅ) நீலகேசி, குண்டலகேசிஆ) உதயணகுமாரகாவியம், நாககுமார காவியம்இ) சிந்தாமணி, சூளாமணிஈ) சிலப்பதிகாரம், மணிமேகலை","answer":"விடை: சிலப்பதிகாரம், மணிமேகலைசிலப்பதிகாரம் முன்னோட்டம்இக்காப்பியத்தில் இயல், இசை, நாடகம் என்னும் மூன்றனையும் காணலாம். கி. பி. இரண்டாம் நூற்றாண்டில் எழுதப்பட்டது என்பர். ஏனைய நூல்கள் அரசனையோ தெய்வங்களையோ பாட்டுடைத் தலைவனாகக் கொண்டிருக்க சிலப்பதிகாரம் கோவலன் என்ற குடிமகனைப் பாட்டுடைத் தலைவனாகக் கொண்டதால் இதனை ‘குடிமக்கள் காப்பியம்’ என்றும் கூறுவர். இன்பியலும் துன்பியலும் கலந்து எழுதப்பட்ட இந்நூலை இயற்றியவர் இளங்கோ அடிகள் என்பவராவார். இவர் புகழ் பெற்ற சேரமன்னன் செங்குட்டுவனுடைய தம்பி எனக் கருதப்படுகின்றது.சிலப்பதிகாரத்தின்  காலம்சிலப்பதிகாரமும் மணிமேகலையும் இரட்டைக் காப்பியங்கள் . நற்றிணைப் பாடல் கண்ணகி வரலாற்றைக் குறிப்பிடுகிறது மலையாள மொழி கி.பி. ஆறாம் நூற்றாண்டில் தோன்றியது. மணிமேகலை வஞ்சி மூதூர் சென்று பல்வேறு சமயங்களின் கருத்துக்களைக் கேட்டறிந்தது மலையாளத்தில் அன்று. தமிழில். எனவே மணிமேகலை காலம் ஆறாம் நூற்றாண்டுக்கு முந்தையது. புகார் நகரத்தில் சிவன்கோயில் இருந்ததாகச் சிலப்பதிகாரம் குறிப்பிடுகிறது. 276 ஊர்களிலிருந்த சிவன்கோயில்களைக் குறிப்பிடும் தேவாரம் இதனைக் குறிப்பிடவில்லை. எனவே புகார் நகரைக் கடல் கொண்டது தேவாரம் தோன்றிய 7 ஆம் நூற்றாண்டுக்கு முந்தியது.புகார் நகரத்தில் பலராமனுக்கும், கண்ணனுக்கும் தனித்தனிக் கோயில்கள் இருந்ததைச் சிலப்பதிகாரம் குறிப்பிடுகிறது. எனவே இரட்டைக் காப்பியங்களான சிலப்பதிகாரம், மணிமேகலை ஆகிய காப்பியங்களின் காலம் கி.பி. இரண்டாம் நூற்றாண்டு.சிலப்பதிகாரத்தின்  நூலமைப்புகாப்பியங்களுக்கான இலக்கண அமைப்பு அனைத்தும் பொருந்தி வரும்படி இயற்றப்பட்ட காப்பியமாகும். காவிரி, வைகை முதலான ஆறுகளும் புகார், உறந்தை, மதுரை , வஞ்சி முதலான நகரங்களும், குரவைக் கூத்து முதலிய கூத்துகளும், திருமால் முதலிய தெய்வங்களும், அடர்ந்து வளர்ந்த பெருங்காடுகளும் இந்நூலில் நன்கு வர்ணிக்கப்பட்டுள்ளன. அக்காலத் தமிழ் மக்களின் வாழ்க்கை பற்றிய செய்திகள் இதில் இடம் பெற்றுள்ளன. சிலப்பதிகாரப் பதிகம் இதனை உரையிடையிட்ட பாட்டுடைச் செய்யுள் எனக் குறிக்கின்றது. இடையிடையே உரைகளும் வரிப்பாட்டுகளும் கலந்து வந்துள்ளன. பொருட்செறிவு, தெளிவான இனிய எளிய நடையுடன், அணிகள் பல பொதிந்த தமிழின் வளமான நூலாகும். இறையனார் களவியல் உரைகாரர், இளம்பூரனார் போன்ற உரையாசிரியர்களால் மேற்கோளாக எடுத்தாளப்பட்ட பெருமை உடையது. தமிழறிஞர்களால் மிகுதியாக ஆய்வுக்கு உட்பட்ட நூல் இதுவேயாகும். சிலப்பதிகாரம் , நூல் முகத்தில் உரைப் பாட்டினையும், கானல் வரி, வேட்டுவ வரி, ஆற்றுவரி, ஊசல்வரி, கண்புகுவரி என்னும் இசைப்பாட்டுகளும் நிறைந்தது. புகார்க் காண்டம், மதுரைக் காண்டம் மற்றும் வஞ்சிக் காண்டம் எனும் உட்பகுப்புகளால் பிரிக்கப்பட்டுள்ளது."},{"question":"Em 2021, qual foi o IDH da Eslovênia?","answer":" Em 2021, o Índice de Desenvolvimento Humano (IDH) da Eslovênia foi de 0,918, o que a coloca em uma categoria de alto desenvolvimento humano."},{"question":"Inona no toetra tsy mifandray amin'ny rano?    1-Tsy misy fofona ny rano.    2-Ny rano dia fitambarana simika.    3-Ny rano dia metaly.","answer":"Ny safidy diso dia ny safidy 3-Ny rano dia metaly."},{"question":"கேள்வி :  பாரதியாரின் புகழ்மிக்க  மேற்கோள் ஒன்றினை எழுதவும்.","answer":"பதில்:  பாரதியாரின் புகழ்மிக்க  மேற்கோள் : சொல்லில் உயர்வு தமிழ்ச் சொல்லே - அதைத் தொழுது படித்தடடி பாப்பா.பாரதியார் ஒரு தமிழ் எழுத்தாளர், கவிஞர், பத்திரிகையாளர், இந்திய சுதந்திர ஆர்வலர், சமூக சீர்திருத்தவாதி மற்றும் பலமொழியாளர். கவிதையில் சிறந்து விளங்கியதற்காக அவருக்கு \\"பாரதி\\" என்ற பட்டம் வழங்கப்பட்டது."},{"question":"Ọjọ́ mélòó ni Odùduwà àti àwọn ènìyàn rẹ̀ fi rìn láti mẹ́kà kí wọ́n tó dé ilé ifẹ̀","answer":"Àádọ́rùn-ún ọjọ́ "},{"question":"Dapọ Abiọdun kilọ fawọn to n da rogbodiyan silẹ ni Yewa","answer":"Latari rogbodiyan to mu ẹmi lọ to n waye lawọn àgbegbe Yewa, nipinlẹ Ogun, lasiko yii, Gomina Dapọ Abiọdun ti kilọ fawọn to wa nidii iṣẹlẹ naa. O ni ijọba oun ko ni i faaye gba palapala bẹẹ. Ẹni tọwọ ba si ba nidii ẹ yoo jẹ buruku iya.Ọjọbọ, ọjọ kọkanla, oṣu keji yii, ni gomina kilọ bẹẹ, ninu atẹjade kan lati ọfiisi Akọwe iroyin ẹ, Ọgbẹni Kunle Ṣomọrin.Ṣe lọjọ naa ni iroyin jade pe awọn Fulani paayan ni Owode-Ketu, pe wọn tun daamu awọn eeyan Igan -Alade, Eegua ati Igbogila. Yatọ si ikilọ yii, ikọ alaabo ti i ṣe ọlọpaa, fijilante, otelemuye atawọn ẹṣọ mi-in nijọba làwọn ti da sawọn agbegbe ti rogbodiyan ti n ṣẹlẹ, awọn agbegbe bíi Ariwa Yewa, Ìmẹ̀kọ-Afọn ati Guusu Yewa.Wahala naa pọ lawọn agbegbe yii to bẹẹ ti wọn ti ileewe ati ọpọlọpọ ibi pa. Eyi lo fa a ti Gomina fi ni ki iwadii bẹ̀rẹ̀ kia lori awọn to lọwọ si ikọlu to mu ẹmi lọ naa, wọn ni ijọba yoo gbe ẹni tọwọ ba tẹ pe o lọ́wọ́ si wahala naa lọ si kootu kíá ni.“Gbogbo ohun to ba gba la maa fun un lati mu alaafia duro nipinlẹ Ogun, koda bo gba ifiyajẹni gidi, a o ni i woju ẹnikẹni ka too lo o lati mu ifọkanbalẹ wa nipinlẹ yii”Bẹẹ ni apa kan atẹjade naa wi."},{"question":"\\"Simon a pris des cours de français avec Adam, car _ voulait parler français couramment.\\" Dans la phrase précédente, \\"_\\" fait-il référence à \\"Simon\\" ou \\"Adam\\" ?","answer":"Le \\"_\\" fait référence à Simon."},{"question":"ጥያቄ፡- ሦስቱ የሙቀት መለኪያ መለኪያዎች ምንድ ናቸው? መልስ፦","answer":"ለአጠቃላይ አጠቃቀም, ሶስት የሙቀት መለኪያዎች አሉ. የሴልሺየስ (° ሴ) ልኬት የመለኪያ ሥርዓትን ተግባራዊ ባደረጉ አብዛኞቹ አገሮች ውስጥ መደበኛ አሃድ ነው። በሁሉም የሳይንስ ዘርፎች ውስጥ በሰፊው ተቀጥሯል. የፋራናይት (°F) ልኬት በዩናይትድ ስቴትስ እና በጥቂት እንግሊዝኛ ተናጋሪ አገሮች ውስጥ በጣም የተለመደ ነው። የኬልቪን (ኬ) የሙቀት መለኪያ ለሳይንሳዊ የሙቀት ስሌት እንደ ዓለም አቀፍ መደበኛ አሃድ ይታወቃል።"},{"question":"Waze wasiyala uHulumeni ngale mithetho yakhe esikhwezaabafokazana emakhanda amakhosi.Uqinisile baba, oDuma abasazikhohliwe bengamakhosi. NgempelauDuma ungekhohlwe sekunguye inkosi kule ndawo. Kukhona nabantuasebemkhulekela. Eqinisweni nje, lo Hulumeni wayecabangeni nje azeashaye umthetho onje?(ubuso buhwaqabala) Kwakunani nje ukuthi bavotiseabasemadolobheni kuphela? Thina makhosi basivikele ngokushayaumthetho othi masifundiswe ngokusebenzisana nabantu ekuletheniintuthuko. Buka nje manje, abantu sebenezimpawana zokuhlukanaphakathi. Kukhona asebengibuka njengento engathi shu. Abanyebazonda uDuma egameni lokuthi usethathe isikhundla samiengasinikwa uMvelingqangi kanye nobabamkhulu.(ahebeze ngezandla sakuphika) Cha! Cha! Noma ngabe lo mthethoushaywe ePitoli noma eKapa inkosi iyohlale iyinkosi. Angifundileokuyaphi kepha ngiyazi ukuthi ngaphambi kokushaya umthetho,kudingeka kube nocwaningo. Phela kumele bacwaninge ngosikompilolwama-Afrika kuqala ze bakwazi ukushaya umthetho ongachithiokukhona ngoba bakwethu, kuse-Afrika lapha.(aneke izandla sakuzivula, okukaMfundisi eshumayela)Ngivumelana nawe MaNgema. Uyazi kuyasho ukuthi walunguzaesikoleni. Futhi-ke nje akukhona ukulunguza ukufunda uze ubenguthisha. Phela uhleli nje ungafundisi ngoba yimi kanye nobabaesanquma ukuba ube yinkosikazi yenkosi egcwele. Wawungeke ubeyiyo egcwele ube ufundisa. Cabanga nje inkosikazi yenkosi idelelwayizingane zabafokazana. Okubi kakhulu-ke nawe utholakale ulawulwanguthishanhloko ongumfokazana.1. UDuma wayengaphumelela ukuletha intuthuko endaweni ngaphandle kosizolukaMbandlwa. Fakazela lesi sitatimende ngalokho okushiwo endabeni.","answer":"Yebo wayengaphumelela ngoba emva kokushona kukaMbandlwa, uDumawabambisana nenkosi ukuze basebenzisane, balethe intuthuko endaweni."},{"question":"Ǹ jẹ́ òrìṣà Buddha jẹ́ èyàn láyé rí?","answer":"bẹ́ẹ̀ni"},{"question":"दिइएको वाक्यमा आवश्यक ठाउँमा आवश्यक चिह्न प्रयोग गर्नुहोस् ।हरि तिमी के गर्दै छौ","answer":"हरि! तिमी के गर्दै छौ ? "},{"question":"以下の段落に関連する内容を記入しなさい： ドローンを飛ばすときのルールが去年12月に変わりました。操縦している人からドローンが見えなくても、家などがある場所の上でドローンを飛ばすことができるようになりました。","answer":"このため、日本郵便はドローンで手紙や荷物を届けるサービスを2023年度から始める予定です。使うドローンは、ポストのような赤い色で、大きさは1m50cmぐらいです。全部で5kgの荷物を、35km離れた所まで運ぶことができます。山が多い所や島など、荷物を運ぶ人が足りない所からサービスを始める予定です。"},{"question":"یک نظر مثبت در مورد یک رستوران بنویس.","answer":"این رستوران محیط خیلی قشنگ و تمیزی داشت. غذا ها با کیفیت و خوشمزه بودند. برخورد گرسنل بسیار محترمانه بود. سرویس دهی مرتب و سریع بود."},{"question":"Tohizo ity ohabolana ity :  “Ny omby matin’ny taviny, ...............................”","answer":"   “Ny omby matin’ny taviny, ny hazo matin’ny hitsiny.”"},{"question":" are some great explorers that navigated the world","answer":"Throughout history, there have been numerous great explorers who embarked on voyages to navigate and chart the world. These explorers played crucial roles in expanding knowledge about geography, trade routes, and cultures. Here are some of the most notable explorers:Christopher Columbus (1451-1506): An Italian explorer sponsored by Spain, Columbus completed four voyages across the Atlantic Ocean, opening the way for widespread European exploration and the eventual colonization of the Americas.Ferdinand Magellan (1480-1521): A Portuguese explorer sailing under the Spanish flag, Magellan led the first successful expedition to circumnavigate the globe. Although he did not survive the journey, his fleet completed the circumnavigation in 1522.Marco Polo (1254-1324): An Italian merchant and traveler, Marco Polo is famous for his journey along the Silk Road to China. His travelogue, \\"The Travels of Marco Polo,\\" had a significant impact on European exploration and trade with Asia.Vasco da Gama (c. 1460-1524): A Portuguese explorer, da Gama was the first to sail directly from Europe to India, opening an important sea route for trade and exploration between Europe and Asia.Zheng He (1371-1433): A Chinese mariner and diplomat, Zheng He led seven large expeditions to Southeast Asia, South Asia, the Middle East, and Africa during the early Ming Dynasty.Roald Amundsen (1872-1928): A Norwegian explorer, Amundsen was the first person to reach the South Pole in 1911 and also led the first successful expedition to traverse the Northwest Passage.Hernán Cortés (1485-1547): A Spanish conquistador, Cortés led the expedition that resulted in the fall of the Aztec Empire in present-day Mexico.Sir Ernest Shackleton (1874-1922): An Anglo-Irish explorer, Shackleton is best known for his leadership during the ill-fated Imperial Trans-Antarctic Expedition. Despite the failure to cross Antarctica, his leadership ensured the safe return of his crew.These explorers and many others made significant contributions to the exploration and mapping of the world, leaving behind a lasting legacy in the fields of geography, navigation, and global understanding."},{"question":"من هو مؤسس مدينة فاس عام 808 ميلادياً لتكون أول عاصمة إسلامية في المغرب الأقصي ؟","answer":"الإجابة هي : إدريس الثاني ."},{"question":"Patikrinkite žemiau pateiktą eilutę ir atsakykite į klausimą, pateiktą toje pačioje kalba, kaip ir eilutė:  Liūtai priklauso egzotiškų gyvūnų grupei, kuri nuo XVIII a. pabaigos buvo pagrindinė zoologijos sodo eksponatų dalis; šios grupės nariai visada yra dideli stuburiniai gyvūnai tokie kaip: drambliai, raganosiai, hipopotamai, dideli primatai ir kitos didelės katės; zoologijos sodai stengiasi surinkti kuo daugiau šių rūšių. Nors daugelis šiuolaikinių zoologijos sodų savo eksponatų parenka labiau selektyviai, zoologijos soduose ir laukinių gyvūnų parke visame pasaulyje yra daugiau kaip 1000 Afrikos ir 100 Azijos liūtų. Jie laikomi turizmo, švietimo ir išsaugojimo tikslais. Liūtai nelaisvėje gali išgyventi daugiau kaip 20 metų. 2007 m. rugpjūčio mėn. 22 metų amžiaus mirė zoologijos sode Honolulu, Havajų valstijoje, gyvenęs liūtas Apollo. Jo dvi seserys, gimusios 1986 m., dar buvo gyvos 2007 m. rugpjūčio mėn. Senovės Egipto miestuose Taremu ir Per-Bast buvo šventyklos, skirtos Egipto liūto deivėms Sekhmet ir Bast, o Taremu buvo šventykla, skirta dievo Maaheso sūnui, liūto princui, kur buvo laikomi liūtai ir jiems buvo leidžiama vaikščioti šventykloje. Graikai miestą vieną mietą pavadino Leontopolis (\\"Liūto miestas\\") ir užrašė apie tai.  Klausimas: Koks yra bendras Afrikos liūtų skaičius zoologijos soduose?","answer":"daugiau kaip 1000 Afrikos ir 100 Azijos liūtų"},{"question":"Miisa firy ny tongotry ny hala?","answer":"Ny hala dia matetika manana tongotra valo."},{"question":"வினா: அலி பாதுஷா என்ற  நாடக நூலின்  ஆசிரியர் யார்? ","answer":"விடை:  வண்ணக் களஞ்சியப் புலவர் 1.  வண்ணக்களஞ்சியப் புலவர் என அழைக்கப்படும் புலவர் நாகூரைச் சேர்ந்த ஹமீது இப்ரகீம் என்பவர்     ஆவார். 2.  இவர் சுலைமன் ரபியின் கதையைக் கூறும் 'இராசநாயகம்' என்ற (46 படலங்களில் 2240 பாக்கள்)     காவியச் சுவை ததும்பும் நூலையும், முகைதீன் புராணம், தீன் விளக்கம் போன்ற புராணங்களையும்     இயற்றியுள்ளார். 3.  சந்தப் பாக்களும் வண்ணப்பாக்களும் பாடுவதில் வல்லமை பெற்றுத் திகழ்ந்ததால்     வண்ணக்களஞ்சியப் புலவர் என வழங்கப்பட்டார்.4.  நாகூர் தர்க்காவில் வாழ்ந்த சாது ஒருவரின் அருமை பெருமைகளை விளக்கி, முகைதீன் புராணம்     என்னும் நூலை எழுதி நாகூரில் அரங்கேற்றினார்.5.   இந்நூலின் இனிமையில் மகிழ்ந்த அன்பர் ஒருவர் இவர் விரும்பிய தன் மகளை இவரைத் தேடிப் பிடித்து     மணமுடித்து வைத்துள்ளார்."},{"question":"Manomeza ohabolana malagasy iray momba ny zanaka.","answer":"Ny zanaka hendry mahafaly ny ray, fa ny zanaka adala manome halahelo ny reny."},{"question":"請回答這個問題：地球上最古老的舞台劇是哪一部？","answer":"答案：古希臘的《俄狄浦斯王》"},{"question":"Su’aal: Sheeg Xayawaanka Kaliya ee lab Iyo dhidig ey Isku egyihiin?","answer":"Jawaab: Waa xayawaanka loo-yaqaano Dhurwaaga (Waraabe)."},{"question":"Wie is Ernest Rutherford?","answer":"Ernest Rutherford, 1e Baron Rutherford of Nelson (Brightwater, 30 augustus 1871 – Cambridge (Verenigd Koninkrijk), 19 oktober 1937) was een Nieuw-Zeelands-Britse natuur- en scheikundige. Hij wordt ook wel de vader van de kernfysica genoemd. Hij pionierde de baantheorie van het atoom door de ontdekking van de verstrooiing van Rutherford. "},{"question":" Inona no maha-zava-dehibe ny fananana toe-tsaina tsara?","answer":" Ny fananana toe-tsaina tsara dia mety hanatsara ny fahasalamantsika ara-pihetseham-po, hanamafy ny fifandraisantsika, hampitombo ny faharetantsika manoloana ny zava-tsarotra, ary hampiroborobo ny fomba fijery feno fanantenana eo amin’ny fiainana."},{"question":"*من هو الملك الموكل بتوزيع الأرزاق ؟","answer":"سيدنا ميكائيل"},{"question":"தமிழரின் வாழ்வியல் கருவலமாகக் கருதப்படுவது………………….அ) அகநானூறுஆ) புறநானூறுஇ) பதிற்றுப்பத்துஈ) கலித்தொகை","answer":"ஆ) புறநானூறுபுறநானூறு என்னும் தொகைநூல் நானூறு பாடல்களைக் கொண்ட புறத்திணை சார்ந்த ஒரு சங்கத் தமிழ் நூலாகும். புறம், புறப்பாட்டு, நந்தா விளக்கம் என்றும் வழங்கப்படும். இது சங்க காலத் தமிழ் நூல் தொகுப்பான எட்டுத்தொகை நூல்களில் புறநூல்களுள் ஒன்று. இந்நூலைத் தொகுத்தவர் பெயரும், தொகுப்பித்தவர் பெயரும் தெரியவில்லை. இந்நூலின் பாக்கள் 4 அடி முதல் 40 அடி வரையிலான ஆசிரியப்பாவால் அமைந்து உள்ளன. சிறுபான்மையாக வஞ்சி அடிகளும் விரவி வரும். புறநானூற்றின் பாடல்கள் சங்ககாலத்தில் ஆண்ட அரசர்களைப் பற்றியும் மக்களின் சமூக வாழ்க்கை பற்றியும் எடுத்துரைக்கின்றன. இதனை ஜி. யு. போப் ஆங்கிலத்தில் மொழிபெயர்த்துள்ளார்.பாடியவர்கள்:இந் நூலில் அடங்கியுள்ள பாடல்கள் பல்வேறு புலவர்களால் பல்வேறு காலங்களில் பாடப்பட்டவை. அகவற்பா வகையைச் சேர்ந்த இப்பாடல்கள், 150க்கும் மேற்பட்ட புலவர்களால் எழுதப்பட்டவை. இந்நூலில் அதிக பாடல்களைப் பாடியவர் ஔவையார் (33 பாடல்கள்) ஆவார். அவரை அடுத்து அதிக பாடலைப் பாடியவர் கபிலர் (28 பாடல்கள்) ஆவார். இந்நூலில் இடம்பெறும் புலவர்கள் அனைவரும் ஒரே சமூகத்தையோ நாட்டையோ சார்ந்தவர்கள் அல்லர்,அரசன் முதல் எளிய குயவன்மகள் வரை பல்வேறு நிலைகளில் இருந்த ஆடவரும் பெண்டிருமான புலவர்கள் பாடியுள்ளனர். நூல் அமைப்பு:இந்நூலில் பாடல்கள் தொகுக்கப்படும்போது ஒருவகை இயைபு கருதி, முதலில் முடிமன்னர் மூவர், அடுத்து குறுநில மன்னர், வேளிர் ஆகியோரைப் பற்றிய பாடல்களும் அதனை அடுத்துப் போர்ப் பற்றிய பாடல்களும் கையறுநிலைப்பாடல், நடுகல், மகளிர் தீப்பாய்தல் என்று தொகுத்துள்ளனர். புறப்பொருள் கருத்துகளைத் தழுவிப் பாடப்பட்ட இந்நூலில் ஒவ்வொரு பாடலின் இறுதியிலும் திணை, துறை, பாடினோர், பாடப்பட்டோர், பாடப்பட்ட சூழல் போன்ற குறிப்புகள் உள்ளன.புறநானூறு வழி அறியலாகும் செய்திகள்:   அக்காலத் தமிழ் மக்களின் அரசியல், சமூகம், பொருளாதாரம், கல்வி, நாகரிகம், கலை வளர்ச்சி, வீரம், கொடை, ஆடை, அணிகலன், பழக்க வழக்கங்கள், வாணிபம் போன்ற பல செய்திகளைப் புறநானூறு வழி அறியலாம்."},{"question":"O que é um número ímpar na matemática?","answer":"Um número ímpar é um número natural que não é divisível por 2. Exemplos incluem 3, 7 e 11."},{"question":"வால்ட்விட்மனின் உலகப்புகழ் பெற்ற கவிதைநூல் எது?","answer":"‘புல்லின் இதழ்கள், வால்ட் விட்மனின் உலகப்புகழ் பெற்ற கவிதை நூல்."},{"question":"පහත  නාම පදයට අදාළ ස්ත්‍රී ලිංග නාම පාදක කුමක්ද?හංසයා ","answer":"හංස ධේනුව "},{"question":"Inona no niandohan’ny Ady Mangatsiaka teo amin’i Etazonia sy ny Firaisana Sovietika?","answer":"Ny ady mangatsiaka dia ady ara-jeopolitika sy ideolojika izay naharitra hatramin'ny nifaranan'ny Ady Lehibe II tamin'ny 1945 ka hatramin'ny fandravana ny Firaisana Sovietika tamin'ny 1991. Ny niandohan'ny Ady Mangatsiaka dia tao anatin'ny disadisa teo amin'ny fanjakana -Etazonia sy ny Firaisana Sovietika. , firenena matanjaka roa nanana firehan-kevitra ara-politika nifanohitra, dia ny kapitalisma ho an'i Etazonia ary ny kominisma ho an'ny Firaisana Sovietika.Lalina ny vokatry ny Ady Mangatsiaka. Nitarika hazakazaka fitaovam-piadiana niokleary izany, fizarazarana an'i Eoropa ho vondrona roa, ny OTAN tarihin'i Etazonia sy ny Fifanarahana Warsaw notarihan'ny Firaisana Sovietika, ary ny fifandonana isam-paritra manerana izao tontolo izao, anisan'izany ny ady tany Vietnam sy ny ady tany Afghanistan. Izy io ihany koa no namolavola ny politikan'ny raharaham-bahiny roa tonta, miaraka amin'ny fotoanan'ny détente sy ny fiaraha-miasa narahin'ny vanim-potoanan'ny disadisa.Nifarana tamin’ny fandravana ny Firaisana Sovietika ny Ady Mangatsiaka tamin’ny 1991, izay nanamarika ny fiafaran’ny fifandrafiana teo amin’ireo firenena matanjaka roa ireo. Ny vokatry ny Ady Mangatsiaka dia maro, anisan'izany ny fiafaran'ny bipolarity maneran-tany, ny fampiraisana an'i Alemaina, ny faharavan'ny URSS ho fanjakana mahaleo tena maromaro, ary ny fivoaran'ny fifandraisana iraisam-pirenena tao anatin'ny tontolo taorian'ny Ady Mangatsiaka. Namela lova maharitra ihany koa izy amin'ny politika ivelany, ny filaminana eran-tany ary ny fifandraisana iraisam-pirenena."},{"question":"Maansada Maxaa Loo Qaybiyaa ?","answer":"Waxa loo qaybiyaa labo oo kala ah 1. Toox-gab iyo 2. Toox-dheer."},{"question":"Me kalmar \\"pen\\" take nufi a harshen Hausa?","answer":"Kalmar \\"pen\\" a turanci na nufin \\"alkalami\\" a harshen Hausa."},{"question":"Isi tempat kosong dengan jawapan yang paling sesuai.  Remaja yang diculik itu ditemui sedang bersembunyi ketakutan di __ kampung itu.. Pilihan:  A) jalan belakangB)  gigi hutanC) hilang akal D)  jejak bara","answer":"Jawapan yang betul ialah B)  gigi hutan. Gigi hutan bermaksud pinggir atau tepi hutan."},{"question":"في أي عام إلقيت القنبلة الذرية على هيروشيما؟","answer":"عام 1945م"},{"question":"س154- كم تبلغ مساحة الكرة الأرضية؟","answer":"ج154- 510210000 كم مربع"},{"question":"هل يمكنك اخباري باللون الذي سوف ينتج من خلط اللون الأزرق مع اللون الأحمر؟","answer":"بالتأكيد. عند خلط اللونين الأزرق والأحمر ينتج اللون البنفسجي."},{"question":"Apakah resipi untuk kuih cara manis? Tunjukkan langkah-langkah secara terperinci. ","answer":"Bahan:  2 cawan tepung gandum, 3 cawan santan cair, 2 biji telur, 1 sudu teh garam, 3 helai daun pandan, Pewarna hijau - opsyenal, Gula pasir untuk inti, Minyak masak untuk sapuanCara penyediaan:1. Potong daun pandan dan kisar bersama santan, kemudian tapis. Bersihkan blender.2.  Satukan santan pandan, tepung gandum, telur, garam dan pewarna hijau di dalam blender dan kisar. Kemudian tapis masuk ke dalam jag atau sebarang bekas bermuncung.Cara memasak:1. Panaskan acuan kuih cara di atas dapur dengan api sederhana kecil.2. Sapukan minyak pada setiap lubang menggunakan paper towel atau daun pandan yang disimpul dan dicarik-carikkan hujungnya.3. Tuangkan adunan sehingga hampir penuh ke dalam setiap lubang. Kemudian letak anggaran ½ sudu teh gula pasir pada setiap adunan. Tutup acuan dengan tudung.4. Apabila masak (dalam 2-3 minit), cungkil keluar kuih dari acuan dan sejukkan.5. Ulang langkah 2 - 4 hingga habis adunan.6. Lekatkan kuih secara berpasangan kemudian hidang."},{"question":"கேள்வி :  அம்பேத்கரின் மேற்கோள் ஒன்றை தரவும்.","answer":"பதில் : பிரம்மா, விசுணு மற்றும் மகேசுவரன் ஆகியோர் மீது நான் நம்பிக்கை கொள்ளவோ அல்லது அவர்களை வழிபடவோ மாட்டேன்.கடவுளின் மறுபிறப்பாக நம்பப்படுகின்ற, ராமன் மற்றும் கிருசுணன் ஆகியோர் மீது நான் நம்பிக்கை கொள்ளவோ அல்லது அவர்களை வழிபடவோ மாட்டேன்.கௌரி, கணபதி மற்றும் இந்துக்களின் ஏனைய ஆண் மற்றும் பெண் கடவுளர் மீது நான் நம்பிக்கை கொள்ளவோ அல்லது அவர்களை வழிபடவோ மாட்டேன்.கடவுளின் மறுபிறப்பில் நான் நம்பிக்கை கொள்ள மாட்டேன்.புத்தர் விசுணுவின் மறுபிறப்பு என நான் நம்பவோ கருதவோ மாட்டேன். இது ஒரு அடிமுட்டாள்த்தனம் என்றும் பொய்ப் பரப்புரை எனவும் நான் நம்புகிறேன்.நான் சிரார்த்தமளிக்கவோ, பிண்டமளிக்கவோ மாட்டேன்.நான் புத்தரின் கொள்கைகள் மற்றும் போதனைகளை மீறும் வகையில் நடக்க மாட்டேன்.பிராமணர்களால் ஆற்றப்படும் எந்த நிகழ்வுகளையும் நான் செய்ய மாட்டேன்.நான் மனிதர்கள் அனைவரும் சமமானவர்கள் என நம்புகிறேன்.நான் சமத்துவத்தை நிலைநாட்டுவதற்குப் பெருமுயற்சி எடுப்பேன்.நான் புத்தரின் உன்னதமான எண்வகை மார்க்கங்களைப் பின்பற்றுவேன்.நான் புத்தரால் முன்மொழியப்பட்ட பத்துப் பாரமிதாக்களைப் பின்பற்றுவேன்.நான் அனைத்து உயிர்களிடமும் இரக்கமும் அன்பும் செலுத்துவதோடு அவற்றைப் பாதுகாப்பேன்.நான் திருட மாட்டேன்.நான் பொய்யுரைக்க மாட்டேன்."},{"question":"Crie um verso contendo a palavra: Harmonia","answer":"Verso: Na harmonia da música, notas em perfeição,Ecos da alma, uma doce sensação."},{"question":"ਵਿਸ਼ਾਃ  ਉੱਤਰ ਭਾਰਤ ਦੇ ਕਈ ਇਲਾਕਿਆਂ 'ਚ ਭੁਚਾਲ ਦੇ ਝਟਕੇ। ","answer":"ਇੰਡੀਅਨ ਮੀਟਿਯੋਰੋਲੌਜਿਕਲ ਵਿਭਾਗ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਭੁਚਾਲ ਦਾ ਕੇਂਦਰ ਉਤਰਾਖੰਡ ਦਾ ਰੂਦਰਪ੍ਰਯਾਗ ਜ਼ਿਲਾ ਸੀ। ਰਾਤ ੮ ਵੱਜ ਕੇ ੪੯  ਮਿੰਟ 'ਤੇ ੫.੫ ਤੀਵਰਤਾ ਵਾਲੇ ਭੁਚਾਲ ਦੇ ਝਟਕੇ ਮਹਿਸੂਸ ਕੀਤੇ ਗਏ। ਅਮਰੀਕਾ ਵਿੱਚ ਭੁਚਾਲ ਤੇ ਨਜ਼ਰ ਰੱਖਣ ਵਾਲੀ ਏਜੰਸੀ ਯੂਐਸਜੀਐਸ ਨੇ ਕਿਹਾ ਕਿ ਉਤਰਾਖੰਡ ਦੇ ਪੀਪਲ ਕੋਟੀ ਪਿੰਡ ਦੇ ਉੱਤਰ ਪੱਛਮ ਤੋਂ ੩੪ ਕਿਲੋਮੀਟਰ ਦੂਰ ਭੁਚਾਲ ਦਾ ਕੇਂਦਰ ਸੀ। ਅਮਰੀਕੀ ਏਜੰਸੀ ਮੁਤਾਬਕ ਇਸਦੀ ਡੂੰਘਾਈ ੧੦ ਕਿਲੋਮੀਟਰ ਸੀ।ਭੁਚਾਲ ਸਬੰਧੀ ਤਫ਼ਸੀਲ ਸਹਿਤ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਦਾ ਇੰਤਜ਼ਾਰ ਹੈ। ਹਾਲੇ ਤਕ ਨੁਕਸਾਨ ਦੀ ਕੋਈ ਪੁਖ਼ਤਾ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਨਹੀਂ ਮਿਲੀ।ਖ਼ਬਰ ਏਜੰਸੀ ਪੀਟੀਆਈ ਮੁਤਾਬਕ ਹਿਮਾਚਲ ਦੀਆਂ ਪਹਾੜੀਆਂ ਨਾਲ ਲੱਗਿਆ ਉਤਰਾਖੰਡ ਭੁਚਾਲ ਦੇ ਲਿਹਾਜ਼ ਤੋਂ ਸੰਵੇਦਨਸ਼ੀਲ ਮੰਨਿਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ। ਲੋਕ ਸੋਸ਼ਲ ਮੀਡੀਆ 'ਤੇ ਭੁਚਾਲ ਦੇ ਝਟਕੇ ਮਹਿਸੂਸ ਕਰਨ ਦੇ ਤਜਰਬੇ ਸਾਂਝਾ ਕਰ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ। (ਬੀਬੀਸੀ ਪੰਜਾਬੀ ।)"},{"question":"በዓለም ከሚገኙ ሰው ሰራሽ ሐይቆች ትልቁ የቱ ነው?","answer":"ቮልታ ሐይቅ"},{"question":" Umuntu ohloniphayo ubonakala ngazo lezizimpawu. Pho yini engingathi ngiyayifuna kumuntu wesifazane ngoba yiyoinhlonipho ebalulekile.'Akunjalo-ke Bhuti. Ukuyizwa kwami into oyishoyo, akusho ukuthingiyayemukela. Ngeke ngivele ngamukele into efana nalena kumuntuengingamazi. Ngikholwa wukuthi akulula ukwamukela into enjena kumuntuoqalayo ukuxoxa naye. Angikholelwa neze kuleyo nto. Ngiyakuzonda ukubauthathekile. Ngiyalesaba ihlazo.''Hhayi, kahle Zodwa. Musa ukuyibeka kabi le nto. Ukwamukela into eshiwowumuntu oqalayo ukuxoxa naye, akusho ukuthi ungumuntu owuthathekile.'1. Ngabe IQINISO noma UMBONO ukuthi wonke amadoda ashadileawathembekile kumakhosikazi awo? Sekela impendulo yakho.","answer":"Umbono.Yiphuzu ELILODWA kwalandelayo:• Abanye abantu besilisa bayazihlonipha bona kanyenamakhosikazi abo.• Basekhona abantu besilisa abaqotho nabanothandolweqiniso.• Abanezindandatho zomshado bahlezi bezifakile emnweni."},{"question":"ما هو المعدن الذي يتميز بوزنه الخفيف؟","answer":" معدن الليثيوم."},{"question":"Sheeg magacyada Arbihii iyo Qalanjadii Riwaayaddii “Qabrigii Jacaylka”?","answer":"Waxa ay kala ahaayeen Salaad Derbi iyo Seynab Cige."},{"question":"Waxaad sheegtaa timirta faaidooyinka ay ledahay?","answer":"BAL ILA EEG FA'IIDOYINKA TIMIRTA KUJIRA E AN MOOGNAHAY MISANA WAXTARKA LEH Waxtarka Timirta (WAA DAWO LA MOOGYAHAY)TIMIRTATijaabo iyo cilmi baadhis lagu sameeyay timirta waxaa lagu ogaaday in timirta laga helo faaiido iyo waxtar iyo dheef badan oo aan la koobi karin. Waxaad hoos ka akhrisataan waxtarka badan ee timirtu leedahay. Waxaa la odhan karaa timirtu waxay daawo u tahay wax kasta. Waana cuntadii Rasuulku (scw) ugu jeclaa.Waxaa ka mid ah iyadoo dhinta ama yaraysa kalastaroolka dhiigga ku jira sabatoo ah waxaa timirta laga helaa maaddo la dhaho Pectin oo halbowlaha dhiigga ka ilaalisa inuu isku dhego ama xidhmo kadibna uu joogsado wareegga dhiiggu.Sidoo kale, timirta waxaa ku jira maaddo kale oo la dhaho fluorine (fluoride) taasoo ilkaha ka dhawrta inuu suus galo.Timirtu waxay jidhka (jirka) ka difaacdaa ama ka dhawrtaa sunta waayo timirta waxaa laga helaa saddex maaddo oo caafimaadka u roon kuwaasoo kala ah sodium iyo potassium iyo weliba vitamin C.Timirta waxaa ku jira saddex maaddo oo kala ah iron iyo copper iyo vitamin B. Kuwaasina waxay daawo u yihiin aniimiyada ama dhiig yaraanta (anemia).Timirta waxaa kale ku jira labo maaddo oo kala ah calcium iyo phosphorous iyo vitamin A. Kuwaasina waxay daawo u yihiin cudurka carruurta ku dhaca ee loo yaqaan (rickets) kaasoo lafahooda ka dhiga jiljileec iyo tamar darri ka dhalatay vitamin D la’aan.Timirta waxaa ku jira maadada magaceedu yahay potassium taasoo daawo u ah oon diidnimada ama rabitaan la’aanta cuntada iyo weliba marka qofku fakerkiisa meel isugu keeni kari waayo (lack of concentration).Timirta waxaa ku jira maadada la dhaho magnesium taasoo daawo u ah daciifnimada iyo tabar-darrida iyo boodboodka ama garaaaca wadnaha.Waxaa kalee timirta ku jira maaddo loo yaqaan boron taasoo daawo u ah cudurka tufta ama lafo xanuunka (rheumatism) iyo cudurka kaansarka ee maskaxda gala.Timirtu waxay baajisaa oo ka hortagtaa cudurka kaansarka ee ku dhaca mindhicirka ama xiidmaha.Waxay kalee timirtu ka hortagtaa cudurka bawaasiirta isla markaana waxay yaraysaa in xammeetida dhagxanyo ku samaysmaan. Sidoo kale waxay fududaysaa marxaladaha uuraysiga ama uur bixinta iyo dhalinta iyo muddada umuluhu ku jiraan umulbixinta. Sidaasna waxaa u sabab ah timirta waxaa ku jira maaddo miraha laga helo oo dheef-shiidka cuntada sahal ka dhigta.Timirta waxaa ku jirta maaddo la dhaho boron taasoo waxtar wayn u leh ragga ay ku dhacdo awood darri iyo hawlgabnimo ku saabsan raganimada iyo galmada.Timirtu waxay daawo u tahay jidhka engaga iyo indho habeenada ama qofka aan waxba arki karin waqtiga habeenimada.Waxaa kalee timirta laga helaa vitamin B2 taasoo daawo u ah dheef-mareenka ama (digestive system).Waxaa intaas sii dheer, timirtu waxay daawo u tahay timaha daata iyo indho-daalka iyo cirrid-dhiiga ka dhasha fiitamiin C la’aan iyo weliba xiiqda iyo lafo jileeca.Timirta waxaa laga samayn karaa daawooyin iyo fiitaamiino iyo kiniini dila jeermiska iyo baakteeriyada cudurada keenta kuwaasoo lagu daawayn karo cudurada kor ku xusan..Faaiidooyinka kor lagu sheegay ayay timirtu leedahay ee markaa yaan loo daymo la’aan."},{"question":"what important event is this text about: Основними причинами війни стали політичні суперечності, породжені недосконалою Версальською системою та агресивна експансіоністська політика нацистської Німеччини, Японської імперії та Італії. 1 вересня 1939 року гітлерівські війська вторглися в Польщу. 3 вересня Велика Британія та Франція оголосили Німеччині війну. Упродовж 1939-41 років завдяки серії успішних військових кампаній та низки дипломатичних заходів Німеччина захопила більшу частину континентальної Європи. У той же час Радянський Союз анексував (повністю або частково) території сусідніх європейських держав: Польщі, Румунії, Фінляндії та країн Балтії, що відійшли до його сфери впливу на підставі Пакту Молотова-Ріббентропа. Після початку бойових дій в Північній Африці та падіння Франції в середині 1940 року війна тривала насамперед між країнами Осі та Великою Британією, ВПС якої зуміли відбити німецькі повітряні атаки. У цей же час бойові дії поширились на Балканський півострів та Атлантичний океан. Японія окупувала частину Китаю та Південно-Східної Азії, взявши під контроль важливі джерела сировини.","answer":"Друга світова війна — глобальний збройний конфлікт, що тривав від 1 вересня 1939 до 2 вересня 1945 року."},{"question":"Meeqo ayaa Loo qeybiyaa Pharmacy?","answer":"Waxaa loo qeybiyaa afar qeybood:-1. Pharmaceutics : waa cilmiga lagu barto sidda loo sameyo dawada ama sidda loo cusbooneysiiyo dawada.2. Pharmacognosy : waa cilmiga lagu barto sidda dawada loogu soo dharan dhariyo gedaha .3. Pharmcology : waa cilmiga lagu barta dawada sidda ay jirka ula falgasho ayna falcelin uuga soo saarto.4. Medicinal chemistry: waa cilmiga lagu barto kiimikal foormulada ay yeeelaneyso dawo kasta. "},{"question":"ጣልያን ኢትዮጵያን ለመውረር ድጋሚ የመጣበት ዓመት መቼ ነው?","answer":"በ1928"},{"question":"在加拿大，G2（第二阶段）驾驶员，驾驶时酒精在血液中的含量（酒精度）不能超过？","answer":"0.00%"},{"question":"வினா:தொல்காப்பியத்தில் நாடகப் பாங்கிலான உணர்வுகளுக்கு இலக்கணம் வருந்த இயல்(1) மரபியல்                                                             (2) பொருளியல்(3) மெய்ப்பாட்டியல்                                          (4) களவியல்","answer":"விடை :(3) மெய்ப்பாட்டியல்    "},{"question":"Jawab soalan teka-teki berikut:  Daunnya nampak koyak rabak, buahnya menggerutu.","answer":"Jawapannya ialah buah peria"},{"question":"A wane ƙarni ne Musulunci ya shigo Najeriya?","answer":"ƙarni na 11"},{"question":"福特汽车在电动汽车市场的发展如何？","answer":"近年来，福特汽车也开始积极布局电动汽车市场。它推出了全新的Mustang Mach-E电动SUV，以及即将推出的全电动版F-150皮卡。这些产品表明，福特汽车正在努力适应汽车业的电动化趋势。"},{"question":" క్రింది ప్రశ్నకి ఒక్కమాటలో జవాబునివ్వండి. భారతదేశంలో అత్యంత పొడవైన కాలువ ఏది?","answer":"ఇందిరాగాంధీ కాలువ."},{"question":"Apa pitakonan kanggo jawaban ing ngisor iki? Ing Bumi, ana pitung lempeng-lempeng utama lan lempeng-lempeng sing luwih cilik. Topike yaiku lempeng tektonik.Pitakonan:","answer":"Pitakonan kanggo jawaban lan topik ing ndhuwur yaiku:Pira lempeng tektonik ing lapisan Litosfer Bumi?"},{"question":"Taariikhda Khadra Daahir Cige!","answer":"Taariikhda Khadra Daahir Cige!Khadra Daahir Cige (Af Ingiriis : Kadra Daher Igeh; Af Carabi : ar‎) waa fanaanad weyn oo ku heesta af-Soomaaliga taasi oo leh suugaan iyo heeso aad u badan. Heesaha ay qaado fanaanadani oo u badan wadani, goobaabin, talo-siin, dhiiri-gelin iyo wanaag darteed ayaa Khadra loo siiyay magaca weyn ee Boqorada Fanka Soomaaliyeed. Intaasi waxaa dheer, Khadra Daahir waxaa ay leedahay naanays ay ku kasbatey kartideeda iyo hanaan-wanaageeda, waxaana lagu naanaysaa Khadra Qaali.Khadra Daahir Cige waxay ku dhalatey magaalada Hargeysa ee gobolka Waqooyi, ee deegaanada Waqooyiga Soomaaliya maanta loo yaqaano Somaliland.Ka dib, qiyaastii sanadkii 1979kii ilaa 80meeyihii ayaa Khadra ku soo biirtay fanka wakhtigaasi oo lagu sheego ineey jacayl dartii u biloowday ineey heesto.Fanaanada Khadra Daahir waxay leedahay tiro badan oo heeso ah, kuwaasi oo iskugu jira wadani, jacayl, guubaabin, dhiirigelin, haasaawe, amaan, duco, wacyi, wargelin iyo wax-sheeg.Fanaanadu waxay ka tirsanayd Hobolada Waaberi ee hogaanka u ahaa fanka iyo suugaanta Soomaaliyeed.Heesaha fanaanada Khadra qaado waxaa ugu caansan oon soo qaadan karnaa:Heesta JaleeloHeesta Caashaqu Sadweeye: heestani waxa si talantaali ah u wada qaada Khadro Daahir iyo Saalax QaasimWar hooy ka joogHeesta Ma Gudho Caashaqaygu"},{"question":"Weer/yi","answer":"month/s\\t"},{"question":"Strafor köpük soğuğu keser mi?","answer":"Strafor (EPS) hem sıcağa hem soğuğa karşı binanızı koruyan kapalı gözenekli çok iyi bir ısı yalıtım malzemesidir. Bu özelliği tanecikler içine sıkıştırılmış hava sağlamaktadır."},{"question":"Alin sa mga sumusunod ang hindi kabilang sa mga pangkaraniwang sangkap ng paggawa ng halo-halo?A. leche flanB. sagingC. kalamansiD. ube","answer":"Base sa mga pagpipilian, ang kasagutan ay c. kalamansi. Maasim ang kalamansi, samantalang matatamis naman ang leche flan, saging, at ube na karaniwang sangkap sa paggawa ng halo-halo."},{"question":"Namna ya kua mama bora","answer":"Kuwa mama bora kunahitaji upendo usio na kipimo, uvumilivu, na uongozi wenye busara. Kwa kujali na kusikiliza wanawe, kutoa mwongozo wa maadili na elimu, na kuwapa fursa za kujifunza na kukua, mama bora huunda mazingira ya upendo na usalama ambayo hufanya watoto wao wakue kuwa watu wema na wenye furaha. Kuwa mama bora pia kunahitaji kujitunza mwenyewe ili uweze kuwa mfano mzuri kwa watoto wako na kutoa msaada wa kimwili na kihisia wanapohitaji"},{"question":"現在はお祭りなどでおこなわれる、走る馬の上から的に向かって矢をいることをなんと言う？","answer":"やぶさめです。"},{"question":"W oparciu o poniższy fragment, odpowiedz na poniższe pytanie. Według autora, Douglasa Hofstadtera, jaki jest temat przewodni książki \\"Gödel, Escher, Bach\\"? W odpowiedzi na zamieszanie związane z tematem książki, Hofstadter podkreślił, że \\"Gödel, Escher, Bach\\" nie dotyczy relacji matematyki, sztuki i muzyki, ale raczej tego, jak poznanie wyłania się z ukrytych mechanizmów neurologicznych. W pewnym fragmencie książki przedstawiono analogię tego, jak poszczególne neurony w mózgu koordynują się, tworząc jednolite poczucie spójnego rytmu, porównując go do organizacji społecznej charakterystycznej, na przykład w koloniach mrówek.","answer":"Według Hofstadtera, głównym tematem Gödela, Eschera, Bacha jest to, jak zrozumienie świata wynika z ukrytych mechanizmów neurologicznych."},{"question":"sheeg Magaca Buurta ugu dheer Afrika?","answer":"buurta ugu dheer afrika Waa Kalaminjaaro."},{"question":"「ｎＷｏジャパン」「チーム２０００（トゥーサウザント）」などのグループを率いたこともある、新日本プロレス所属の人気レスラーは誰でしょう？","answer":"蝶野正洋"},{"question":"Jawab teka-teki lawak berikut : Mee apa paling berat dalam dunia?","answer":"Jawapan: Mee wantan. Ini kerana sebutan wantan mirip \\"one\\" tan. Unit tan ialah unit ukuran berat yang bersamaan dengan 2240 lb. Maka ia dikatakan sangat berat.  "},{"question":"Em que clube o jogador de futebol Bruno Guimarães foi revelado?","answer":"O jogador Bruno Guimarães foi revelado no Audax."},{"question":"எண்ணத்தை வெளியிடுவதற்கும், சிந்தனையாற்றல் பெருகுவதற்கும் தாய் மொழியே துணை நிற்கும். இதனை வலியுறுத்தி பின்வரும் குறிப்புகளைக் கொண்டு கட்டுரை எழுதுக. தாய்மொழிக் கல்வியின் தேவைதாய்மொழிச் சிந்தனை – அறிஞர்களின் பார்வை – கற்கும் திறன் – பயன் – இன்றைய நிலை.","answer":"முன்னுரை:“தாய்மொழி கண் போன்றதுபிறமொழி கண்ணாடி போன்றது”நமது எண்ணங்களைப் பிறருக்கு வெளிப்படுத்த உதவுவது மொழியே. மொழி ஒரு கருவி. மனிதன் மொழியால்தான் வாழ்கின்றான். மொழியால்தான் கருத்துப் பரிமாற்றமும் செய்கின்றான். தனது எண்ணத்தை வெளியிடுவதற்கும் சிந்தனையாற்றலைப் பெருக்கவும் துணையாக இருக்கும் தாய்மொழி வழிக் கல்வியின் சிறப்புகள் பற்றி இக்கட்டுரையில் காண்போம்.தாய்மொழிக் கல்வியின் தேவை :மனிதனின் அடையாளம் அவனது தாய்மொழிதான். கல்வி என்பது தாய்மொழி வழியாக மட்டுமே கற்பிக்க பட வேண்டும். மனிதனின் சிந்தனையும் கற்பனையும் தாய்மொழியில்தான் உருவாகின்றன. எனவே, மனிதனின் சிந்தனை வளர்ச்சிக்குத் தாய்மொழிக் கல்வியே சிறந்தது. சிந்திக்கின்ற மொழியிலே பயிற்றுவிக்கப்படுகின்ற கல்வி சிந்தனையைக் கூட்டுகின்றது. நுணுக்கங்களையும் அறிவியல் படைப்புகளையும் உருவாக்க மனிதர்களைத் தயார்ப்படுத்துகின்றது.தாய்மொழிச் சிந்தனை :தாய்மொழிதான் சிந்திக்கும் திறனின் திறவுகோலாக இருக்கின்றது. எத்தனை மொழிகள் கற்றாலும் எந்த மொழியைக் கற்றாலும் ஒருவனின் சிந்தனை உருவெடுப்பது தாய்மொழியில்தான். தாய்மொழியால் சிந்தனை பெருகும். மனிதர்களின் மனவெழுச்சி வாழ்விற்கு அடிப்படை. அத்தகைய மனவளர்ச்சியைத் தாய்மொழியால் மட்டுமே கொடுக்க இயலும். தாய்மொழியில் சிந்திப்பதால் உயர்ந்த கருத்துக்களைச் சிறந்த சொற்களைக் கொண்டு உணர்த்த முடியும்.அறிஞர்கள் பார்வை :உலகில் வாழ்ந்த பல அறிஞர்கள் தாய்மொழிக்கல்வியின் அவசியத்தைக் கூறியிருக்கின்றார்கள். காந்தியடிகள் கூறும் போது ஜெகதீஷ் சந்திர போஸ், பி.சி. இராய் முதலியோரின் சாதனைகளைக் கண்டு நாம் மகிழ்ச்சியடைகிறோம். ஆனால், தாய்மொழி மூலம் நமக்குக் கல்வி அளிக்கப்பட்டிருந்தால் நம்மிடையே பல போஸ்களும், இராய்களும் தோன்றியிருப்பார்கள் என்கிறார். சாகித் ஹுசைன் (1938-ஆம் ஆண்டு) குழு தாய்மொழியில் கற்றுக்கொடுத்தலை வலியுறுத்துகிறது, டி.எஸ். கோத்தாரி குழுவும் (1964) தேசியக்கல்விக் கொள்கையில் தாய்மொழி கல்வியை வலியுறுத்தியது.கற்கும் திறன் :தாய்மொழியைப் போற்றி வீழ்ந்த நாடும் இல்லை. தாய்மொழியைப் புறக்கணித்து வாழ்ந்த நாடும் இல்லை. தாய்மொழி மூலமாகவே ஒருவர் தான் கூற விரும்பும் கருத்தைத் தெளிவாகவும் முழுமையாகவும் ஆழமாகவும் தெரிவிக்க முடியும். கற்கும் திறன் அதிகரிப்பது தாய்மொழி வழியாகவே, தாய்மொழி வழியாகக் கற்கும் போது சிந்தனைத்திறன் அதிகமாகும்.தாய்மொழிக் கல்வியின் பயன் :“கருவில் உள்ள குழந்தை ஏழு மாதத்திலேயே மூளை முதிர்ச்சிப் பெற்று ஒலிகளைக் கேட்கிறது” என்கின்றனர். மருத்துவ அறிஞர்கள், குழந்தை வளரும் சூழல் மொழித்தாக்கத்திற்கு அடிப்படையாக அமைகிறது. அக்குழந்தைகள் தாய்மொழி வழியாகக் கற்கும் சூழல் ஏற்பட்டால் மிகச் சிறந்த அறிஞர்களாக, மேதைகளாக அக்குழந்தைகள் வளரும். குழந்தைகள் தாய்மொழி வழியாகக் கல்விக் கற்றால் தரமான கல்வியைப் பெறுவார்கள்.இன்றைய நிலை :இன்று தாய்மொழி வழியில் கல்விச் கற்பதைக் கௌரவக் குறைச்சலாகவும், கேவலமாகவும் நினைக்கின்றனர். தாய்மொழியில் கல்விக் கற்றவர்களைத் தரம் குறைந்தவர்களாகப் பார்ப்பது சமூகத்தில் நிலவி வரும் அவலங்களுள் ஒன்றாகும். தாய்மொழியில் கல்விக் கற்போருக்கு அரசுப் பணிகளில் முன்னுரிமை வழங்குதல் வேண்டும்.முடிவுரை :மொழி என்பது ஒரு தகவல் தொடர்புச் சாதனம் மட்டுமன்று. ஒரு பண்பாட்டின், ஒரு இனத்தின் அடையாளம் என்பதை யாவரும் உணர்ந்தாலே தாய்மொழியை அழிவிலிருந்து காக்கலாம்."},{"question":" Sheeg Goorma Ayuu Dhacay Dagaalkii Qanda","answer":" Wuxu Dhacay Sanadkii 8-Aad Ee Hijriyada."},{"question":"Ngiyakuzwela Sipho. Icala lakho kuthiwa yini ngempela?Kwavele kwathiwa ngonisa wena emzini. Ngikwenza ube nenkani.Awusasho yini ukuthi wawulamula, ungaqonde kugwaza muntu.Abanginikanga ithuba elide lokuchaza. Okubi-ke futhi ngangingenayeufakazi.Awusasho ngani ukuthi abangibize?Ngabona ukuthi ngizokwandisela izinkinga. Ukuba kuya ngami ngabengithi mgane uDumisani lowo.Kahle Sipho bo. Sekwenzenjani futhi.Kwathiwa ngiyophuma uma seniganene.Kanti awuboshelwe lona icala lakho owalenza. Kwenzelwa ukubangigane uDumisani?Ngendlela engihlezi kabuhlungu ngayo lapha mngani wami, impelashintsha umqondo. Mhlawumbe uthando lukaDumisani luzobuyeluvele.Ngeke Sipho. Ngeke. Uyazi esikhundleni sokuba kuqale uthandolukaDumisani uya ngokuya eba yisitha. Ngizogcina ngimenzakalisile.1. Yisiphi isifundo esitholakala kulo mdlalo? Bhala ngamaphuzu AMABILI","answer":"Amaphuzu AMABILI kwalandelayo: Umbhali ufuna ukusikhombisa ukuthi kwesinye isikhathi kukhonaukushayisana phakathi kwamalungelo kanye nesiko. Umbhali ufuna sibone ukuthi basekhona abesifazaneabasacindezelekile. Ufuna abantu bazi ukuthi amanye amasiko asephelelwe isikhathi."},{"question":"Siapakah pengarah filem Laila Majnun? Pilih jawapan yang betul dari pilihan berikut.  A) B S Rajhans B) P Ramlee C) Praboo Ariva D) Hassan Muthalib","answer":"Jawapan yang betul adalah A) B S Rajhans.Laila Majnun arahan B.S Rajhan merupakan filem pertama yang diterbitkan di Tanah Melayu iaitu pada 1933."},{"question":"Waxaad Sheegtaa meydka Kaliya ee aan la-dhaqin?","answer":"Meydka kaliya ee aan ladhaqin waa Meydka Shahiidka."},{"question":"Beschrijf in een paar woorden wat de kenmerken zijn van een goede leider.","answer":"Een goede leider is gemotiveerd, zelfverzekerd, overtuigend, inspirerend, georganiseerd en betrouwbaar."},{"question":"Inona ary izao : \\"Homan-tsy matavy ilay tsy misy vavany.\\"","answer":"Valiny : antsy. Milaza ny pozin'ilay antsy."},{"question":"Fenoy ny banga :\\"Ny te hanana tsy ___\\"","answer":"\\"Ny te hanana tsy mahaleo ny ambinina.\\""},{"question":"දීඝජානු කෝලිය අරබයා බුදුහිමියන් දේශනාකල පරිදි, පුද්ගලයෙකුගේ මෙලොව යහපත පිණිස හේතුවන කරුණු (සම්පදා) 4 මොනවාද ?","answer":"දීඝජානු කෝලිය අරබයා බුදුහිමියන් දේශනාකල පරිදි, පුද්ගලයෙකුගේ මෙලොව යහපත පිණිස හේතුවන කරුණු (සම්පදා) 4 පහත දැක්වේ.1. උට්ඨාන සම්පදා ( උත්සාහ සම්පත්තිය )2. ආරක්ඛා සම්පදා ( ආරක්ෂා සම්පත්තිය )3. කල්‍යාණ මිත්තතා ( යහපත් මිතුරු සම්පත්තිය )4. සමජීවිකතා ( ආදායමට අනුව වියදම / ජීවිකාව."},{"question":"Trả lời 2 ý sau:a) Số 8 có phải là ước chung của 24 và 56 không? Vì sao?b) Số 8 có phải là ước chung của 14 và 48 không? Vì sao?","answer":"Lời giải:a) Ta có: 24 và 56 đều chia hết cho 8 (vì 24 : 8 = 3; 56 : 8 = 7) nên 8 vừa là ước của 24 vừa là ước của 56. Do đó 8 là ước chung của 24 và 56. b) Ta có: 14 : 8 = 1 (dư 6); 48 : 8 = 6 nên 8 là ước của 48 nhưng không là ước của 14. Do đó 8 không phải là ước chung của 14 và 48. "},{"question":"Da tôi thường tiết nhiều dầu nhờn, mặt bóng nhẫy vào mùa hè, có phải do thừa độ ẩm và không cần dưỡng ẩm mỗi ngày? ","answer":"Thời tiết mùa hè và ánh nắng mặt trời khiến da đổ nhiều mồ hôi và tuyến bã nhờn hoạt động mạnh dẫn đến mụn hoặc làm tình trạng mụn nặng hơn. Ngồi điều hòa liên tục cũng khiến da khô, lão hóa nhanh do mất nước. Do đó, dù da dầu, da khô hay da hỗn hợp, vẫn cần dùng kem dưỡng ẩm hàng ngày.Nên thoa dưỡng ẩm cho da hai lần mỗi ngày vào sáng và tối. Nếu sợ bí da hoặc thường xuyên đeo khẩu trang, có thể dùng dưỡng ẩm một lần vào buổi tối trước khi đi ngủ.Lượng kem dưỡng ẩm phù hợp nhất vào mùa hè là khoảng hai hạt đậu (3-5 ml) cho khuôn mặt nhỏ và ba hạt đậu (5-7 ml) cho khuôn mặt lớn hoặc vuông. Dùng quá nhiều hay quá ít có thể làm mất hoặc giảm tác dụng của việc dưỡng ẩm."},{"question":"Dê um exemplo de uma pergunta trivia da categoria: livros","answer":"Shakespeare escreveu quantas peças? 37"},{"question":"Xikmad ama murti?","answer":"#XIKMADFulayadu waxa ay dhintaan marar badan ka hor dhimashadooda; geesiyaduna hal mar uun mooye ma dhadhamiyaan geerida!"},{"question":"Buatlah paragraf eksplanasi dan kronologis singkat dari pertanyaan berikut.Topik: Sejarah Indonesia, Masa Orde Baru (1966-1998).Pertanyaan: Dalam sejarah orde baru, apa itu peristiwa Malari? Jawaban:","answer":"Peristiwa Malari merupakan salah satu peristiwa kelam di zaman Orde Baru. Malari adalah singkatan dari Malapetaka Limabelas Januari. Peristiwa Malari ini terjadi pada tanggal 15 Januari 1974 ketika para mahasiswa melakukan demonstrasi atas kedatangan Perdana Menteri Jepang Tanaka Kakuei ke Jakarta, Indonesia (14–17 Januari 1974). Mahasiswa demostran menolak kedatangan Tanaka karena dianggap sebagai simbol modal asing yang harus dienyahkan. Mahasiswa merencanakan menyambut kedatangannya pada 14 Januari dengan berdemonstrasi di Bandar Udara Internasional Halim Perdanakusuma. Karena penjagaan yang ketat, rombongan mahasiswa tidak berhasil untuk menerobos masuk pangkalan udara. Keesokan harinya, tanggal 15 Januari, mahasiswa melakukan aksi berupa long march dari Salemba menuju Universitas Trisakti di Grogol, Jakarta. Mahasiswa mengusung tiga tuntutan, yakni pemberantasan korupsi, perubahan kebijakan ekonomi modal asing, dan pembubaran lembaga Asisten Penasehat Pribadi (ASPRI) presiden (sumber: nasional.tempo.co). Namun, aksi yang diikuti ratusan ribu orang itu kemudian berujung rusuh.  Menurut ketua Dewan Mahasiswa Universitas Indonesia sekaligus pimpinan, Hariman Siregar, mengatakan unjuk rasa mahasiswa telah berakhir pukul 14.30 WIB. \\"Sedangkan kerusushan terjadi satu jam kemudian,\\" katanya dikutip dari Majalah Tempo Edisi 4 Februari 2008.Massa yang mengaku dari kalangan buruh itu melakukan penjarahan serta membakar mobil produksi Jepang dan toko-toko. Sore itu, Jakarta telah menjadi karang abang. Belasan orang tewas, ratusan luka-luka, hampir seribu mobil dan motor dirusak dan dibakar, serta 160 kilogram emas sejumlah toko perhiasan hilang. Bahkan, saking mencekam Soeharto harus mengantar Tanaka menumpang helikopter ke bandara Halim sebelum pulang ke negaranya (sumber: nasional.tempo.co)."},{"question":"Tukarkan ayat pasif berikut kepada ayat aktif tanpa mengubah maksud asalnya.Ayat pasif: Bantuan kepada mangsa gempa bumi di Sumatera kami hulurkan. ","answer":"Ayat aktif yang betul ialah 'Kami menghulurkan bantuan kepada mangsa gempa bumi di Sumatera.'"},{"question":"Bada misalan Almarar Wasa Ƙwaƙwalwa?","answer":"Wata rana, wata budurwa ta je zance wajen saurayinta da ya ke wani gari. Da suka gama zance, dare ya yi, sai ya tafi zai raka ta. A tsakanin waɗannan garuruwa guda biyu, akwai wani kogi. Da suka isa bakin wannan kogi, sai saurayin ya ce budurwar ta dakata, ya iya ruwa, shi zai fara haura kogin ya ɗauko kwale-kwale don ya haye da ita. Sai ya shiga ruwa, sai da ya je tsakiyar ruwan, sai wani ƙaton kada ya biyo shi zai kama shi, da ƙyar ya samu ya haye. Bayan ya haye, sai ya hango kura ta rugo da gudu za ta cinye wannan budurwar tasa. To, wai idan kai ne wannan saurayin ya zaka yi? Za ka shigo ruwa kada ya cinye ka ne, ko kuwa za ka tsaya kura ta cinye budurwar taka?"},{"question":"LLMs අනිසි ලෙස භාවිතා කිරීම වැළැක්වීම සඳහා සමහර ප්‍රවේශයන් මොනවාද?","answer":"LLMs අනිසි ලෙස භාවිතා කිරීම වැලැක්වීම සඳහා ප්‍රවේශයන් කිහිපයක් මෙන්න: 1. පරිශීලකයින්ට අපවාදාත්මක වාක්‍ය ඛණ්ඩ අඩංගු විමසීම් ඉදිරිපත් කිරීමෙන් වළක්වන්න (සරල මූල පද තහනමක් මේ සඳහා ක්‍රියා කළ හැකිය). 2. පළමු කරුණට සමානව, සරල මූල පද තහනමක් මත පදනම් වූ අපවාදාත්මක වාක්‍ය ඛණ්ඩ අඩංගු ප්‍රතිචාර ආපසු ලබා දීමෙන් LLM වළක්වන්න. 3. ප්‍රතිපෝෂණ රැස් කිරීම සඳහා LLM වෙතින් ප්‍රතිචාර ඉහළ/පහළ කිරීමට සහ සලකුණු කිරීමට පරිශීලකයින්ට විකල්පය ලබා දෙන්න. නුසුදුසු ලෙස සලකුණු කරන ලද ප්‍රතිචාර පිළිබඳ අමතර වර්ගීකරණ ආකෘතියක් පුහුණු කළ හැකි අතර පසුව පරිශීලකයා ඒවා දැකීමට පෙර අනාගතයේදී LLM වෙතින් ගැටලුකාරී ප්‍රතිචාර හඳුනා ගැනීමට සහ පෙරීමට භාවිතා කළ හැක."},{"question":"ചോദ്യം: ഒരു ചോക്ലേറ്റ് കേക്ക് എങ്ങനെ ചുടാം?","answer":"ഉത്തരം:1. ഓവൻ നിശ്ചിത ഊഷ്മാവിൽ ചൂടാക്കുക.2. മൈദ, പഞ്ചസാര, കൊക്കോ പൗഡർ, മുട്ട, പാൽ, വെണ്ണ തുടങ്ങി കേക്കിന് ആവശ്യമായ എല്ലാ ചേരുവകളും ശേഖരിക്കുക.3. ഒരു മിക്സിംഗ് പാത്രത്തിൽ, ഉണങ്ങിയ ചേരുവകൾ (മാവ്, പഞ്ചസാര, കൊക്കോ പൗഡർ) യോജിപ്പിച്ച് നന്നായി ഇളക്കുക.4. ഉണങ്ങിയ ചേരുവകളിലേക്ക് മുട്ട, പാൽ, ഉരുകിയ വെണ്ണ എന്നിവ ചേർത്ത് കുഴമ്പ് മിനുസമാർന്നതുവരെ ഇളക്കുക.5. കേക്ക് പാൻ ഒട്ടിപ്പിടിക്കുന്നത് തടയാൻ വെണ്ണയോ കുക്കിംഗ് സ്പ്രേയോ ഉപയോഗിച്ച് ഗ്രീസ് ചെയ്യുക.6. തയ്യാറാക്കിയ പാത്രത്തിലേക്ക് കേക്ക് ബാറ്റർ ഒഴിച്ച് തുല്യമായി പരത്തുക.7. മുൻകൂട്ടി ചൂടാക്കിയ ഓവനിൽ പാൻ വയ്ക്കുക, നിർദ്ദിഷ്ട സമയത്തേക്ക് ചുടേണം, സാധാരണയായി ഏകദേശം 30-35 മിനിറ്റ്.8. കേക്ക് മധ്യഭാഗത്ത് ടൂത്ത്പിക്ക് തിരുകിക്കൊണ്ട് ചെയ്തതാണോയെന്ന് പരിശോധിക്കുക; വൃത്തിയായി വന്നാൽ കേക്ക് തയ്യാർ.9. ബേക്ക് ചെയ്തുകഴിഞ്ഞാൽ, കേക്ക് അടുപ്പിൽ നിന്ന് മാറ്റി കുറച്ച് മിനിറ്റ് പാനിൽ തണുപ്പിക്കട്ടെ.10. ഫ്രോസ്റ്റിംഗ് അല്ലെങ്കിൽ സേവിക്കുന്നതിന് മുമ്പ് പൂർണ്ണമായും തണുക്കാൻ കേക്ക് ഒരു വയർ റാക്കിലേക്ക് മാറ്റുക."},{"question":"Iza ilay Indiana voalohany nahavita nilomano nanapaka ranomasina fito lehibe ? ","answer":"I Bula Chaudhury no anaran'ilay Indiana voalohany nahavita nilomano nanapaka ranomasina fito lehibe. "},{"question":"உலகின் மிகப்பெரிய பீடபூமி எது?","answer":"கிங்காய்-திபெத்திய பீடபூமி உலகின் மிக உயரமான மற்றும் மிகப்பெரிய பீடபூமி ஆகும்."},{"question":"Төмөндөгү жомокту улантып берчи:Кыштын бир күнү Кыргоол бадалдан койкоюп чыгып, чаңкаганын кандырыш үчүн ойдогу сууга кирет. Каптаган көк музду кыдырып жүрүп күбүрдү араң таап, муздак суудан иче баштайт. Ошондо булайган куйругу музга чап жабышып, чыкпай калат.","answer":"Төмөндөгү жомоктун уландысы  мындай болушу мүмкүн:– Ой-эй, Көк Муз! Дүйнөдө сенден күчтүү эч ким жокпу дейм. Заматта куйругумду куп кармапсың,- дейт Кыргоол Музга.– Жок, Кыргоол. Менден Жамгыр күчтүү. Ал жаап келгенде тымтыракайым чыгып, эрип кетем. Ал сөздү угуп калган Жамгыр шатыратып келип:"},{"question":"Hãy chọn đáp án đúng nhất cho câu hỏi sau:Tỉnh nào của Tây Nguyên được đặt tên theo một tộc người?a. Gia Laib. Đăk Nôngc. Đăk Lăk","answer":"đáp án là Gia LaiGia Lai bắt nguồn từ chữ Jarai, tên gọi của một tộc người bản địa có dân số đông nhất trong tỉnh. Cách gọi này vẫn còn giữ trong tiếng của người Eđê, Bana, Lào, Thái Lan và Campuchia để chỉ vùng đất này là Jarai, Charay, Ya-Ray, có nghĩa là vùng đất của người Jarai, ám chỉ vùng đất của Thủy Xá và Hỏa Xá thuộc tiểu quốc Jarai xưa.Gia Lai nằm ở phía bắc cao nguyên Trung Bộ thuộc vùng Tây Nguyên Việt Nam."},{"question":"\`பிரமிடு கோவில் நாடு' என்று அழைக்கப்படுவது?","answer":"பர்மா பிரமிட் கோயில் என்று அழைக்கப்படுகிறது "},{"question":"هل فرانكفورت عاصمة كنتاكي؟","answer":"نعم"},{"question":"ගුරුතුමිය සිසුන් රැකීම පිණිස නීති පැනවී ය. යන්නෙහි රැකීම පිණිස අපර ක්‍රියා ගණයට අයත් වේ ද?","answer":"එතැන පිණිස යන්න නිපාතයක් ලෙස යෙදී ඇත.ගුරුතුමිය සිසුන් රකින්නට/රකිනුව නීති පැනවීය.මේ ලෙස තිබුණොත් අපර ක්‍රියා වේ.මෙතැන පිණිස(පිණිසාර්ථයේ නිපාත)."},{"question":"Inona no hevitra fonosin' ny fametrahan’ny mpiara-monina ny tsihy any ambany kidoro rehefa manao famadihana?","answer":"Ny fametrahan’ny mpiara-monina ny fianakaviana dia midika ho fanamafisana ny fihavanana sy ny firaisan-kina. "},{"question":"एक दिलचस्प विचारशील व्यक्ति की कहानी लिखें, जो जीवन को नया दृष्टिकोण देते हैं।","answer":" वह व्यक्ति हमेशा नये और सर्वोत्तम दृष्टिकोण को ध्यान में रखते थे और उनकी दृष्टि ने न केवल उनके अपने जीवन को परिवर्तित किया, बल्कि उन्होंने अपने आसपास के लोगों को भी प्रेरित किया।"},{"question":"人気ユニットの氣志團（きしだん）、オレンジレンジ、ＥＸＩＬＥ（エグザイル）といえば、ともに何人グループでしょう？","answer":"６人です。"},{"question":"MuTesitamende yekare, ibhuku ripi rinouya pakati paObadia naMika?","answer":"MuTestamente Yekare yeBhaibheri, bhuku rinouya pakati paObhadhiya naMika iBhuku raJona. Mabhuku matatu aya chikamu chechikamu chinozivikanwa seVaporofita Vadiki, rinova boka remabhuku mapfupi echiporofita muTestamente Yekare. Jona ibhuku rakasiyana nemamwe muchikamu chino, sezvo richinyanya kutaura nyaya yemuprofita Jona nezvaakasangana nazvo, pane kungotaura nezvemashoko echiporofita chete."},{"question":"Naon nu dimaksud jeung lapisan ozon jeung naha éta penting?","answer":"Lapisan ozon nyaéta lapisan gas dina atmosfér Bumi anu ngajaga urang tina radiasi ultraviolét anu ngabahayakeun jeung tiasa ngaruksak kulit sareng kaséhatan urang."},{"question":"ஐம்பெருங்காப்பியங்களுள் பொருந்தாததை தேர்க.அ) யசோதர காவியம் ஆ) சிலப்பதிகாரம் இ) மணிமேகலை ஈ) சீவக சிந்தாமணி ","answer":"விடை: அ) யசோதர காவியம் "},{"question":"অর্থের সময় মূল্য বিষয়টি ব্যাখ্যা করো।","answer":"অর্থের সময় মূল্য বলতে বুঝায় আজকের প্রাপ্ত অর্থের মূল্য এক বছর পরে প্রাপ্ত অর্থের মূল্য থেকে বেশি। পক্ষান্তরে, ভবিষ্যতে প্রাপ্ত একটি নির্দিষ্ট পরিমাণ অর্থ বর্তমানে প্রাপ্ত অর্থের চেয়ে কম মূল্যবান। অর্থাৎ, ভবিষ্যতে প্রাপ্য পরিমাণ একই অর্থের মূল্যের চেয়ে বর্তমানে প্রাপ্ত অর্থ অধিকতর মূল্যমানের নীতিকে অর্থের সময় মূল্য বলে।যদি আমরা ১০০ টাকা এখন গ্রহণ করি, তাহলে আমরা এই ১০০ টাকা বিনিয়োগ করে ১ বছর পর সুদসহ অধিক পরিমাণ অর্থ ফেরত পাব। কিন্তু যদি আমরা ১০০ টাকা ১ বছর পর গ্রহণ করি তাহলে বিনিয়োগ করার সুযোগ থাকবে না। ফলে কোন সুদ অর্জিত হবে না । ফলে আমরা ১০০ টাকা ১ বছর পর অর্থাৎ ভবিষ্যতে গ্রহণ করার চাইতে এখন বা বর্তমানে গ্রহণ করতে অধিক পছন্দ করব।সুতরাং বলা যায়, সময় পরিবর্তনের সঙ্গে সঙ্গে বর্তমান নগদ অর্থের ভবিষ্যত মূল্য পরিবর্তিত হয়ে থাকে এবং ভবিষ্যত অর্থের মূল্যও বর্তমানে পরিবর্তন হয়ে থাকে। অর্থের এই পরিবর্তনজনিত মূল্যকেই অর্থের সময় মূল্য বলা হয়। সংক্ষেপে বলতে গেলে সময়ের পরিবর্তনের সাথে সাথে অর্থের মূল্যের যে পরিবর্তন ঘটে তাকেই অর্থের সময় মূল্য বলে। "},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'kera terlalu makan, tupai di julai timpa perasaan'?","answer":"Ia bermaksud orang besar-besar yang bersuka ria, orang kecil-kecil menepilah dengan irinya"},{"question":"Joxeel péeteg waat yi ci kàddu gii: Te bi ñu xoolee ne siif àmut, xoqtal àmut, li wàroon moo'y, bàyyi Usmaan Sónko te bàñ koo toppe dàra.","answer":"Waat yi nekk ci kàddu gii di \\"Te bi ñu xoolee ne siif àmut, xoqtal àmut, li wàroon moo'y, bàyyi Usmaan Sónko te bàñ koo toppe dàra.\\" ak séen i péete ñoo di:Te: CCONJbi: SCONJñu: PRONxoolee: VERBne: SCONJsiif: NOUNàmut: VERB,: PUNCTxoqtal: NOUNàmut: VERB,: PUNCTli: PRONwàroon: VERBmu: PRONa: AUX'y: AUX,: PUNCTbàyyi: VERBUsmaan: PROPNSónko: PROPNte: CCONJbàñ: VERBko: PRONa: PARTtoppe: VERBdàra: PRON.: PUNCT"},{"question":"ప్రశ్న : ఆహారపు గొలుసులో ఉత్పత్తిదారుల పాత్రను నీవు ఎలా అభినందిస్తావు?","answer":"మొక్కలను ఉత్పత్తిదారులు అని పిలుస్తారు. ఎందుకంటే అవి తమ ఆహారాన్ని సొంతంగా తయారు చేసుకుంటాయి. పర్యావరణ వ్యవస్థలోని అన్ని జీవులకు ఆహారాన్ని అందించే ఏకైక జీవులు ఈ మొక్కలే.పర్యావరణ వ్యవస్థలో, ఉత్పత్తిదారులు అన్నీ ఆహార గొలుసు యొక్క ఆధారం.మొక్కలు ఆహారాన్ని మాత్రమే కాకుండా భూమికి ఆక్సిజన్‌ను కూడా అందిస్తాయి.భూమిపై జీవితాన్ని కొనసాగించడానికి మొక్కలు విలువైనవి."},{"question":"ஜமீலா ஹம்மாமி ஐக்ஸ்-மார்சேய் பல்கலைக்கழகத்தில் கல்வி பயின்றார். இவர் 2002இல் சர்வதேச செஞ்சிலுவை சங்கத்தில் பணியாற்றத் தொடங்கினார். 2008ஆம் ஆண்டில் சவுதி அரேபியாவிலிருந்து திருப்பி அனுப்பப்பட்ட 62 ஈராக்கிய வீரர்களின் குடும்பங்களைக் கண்டுபிடிக்க ஈராக் அதிகாரிகளுக்கு இவர் அழைப்பு விடுத்தார். அந்த ஆண்டின் பிற்பகுதியில் ஈரான்-ஈராக் போரில்","answer":"கொல்லப்பட்ட கிட்டத்தட்ட 250 வீரர்களின் உடல்களை சர்வதேச செஞ்சிலுவை சங்கத்தின் மூலம் பரிமாற்றம் செய்ய ஏற்பாடு செய்தார். 2010 மற்றும் 2011 ஆம் ஆண்டுகளில் இவர் காத்மாண்டுவில் பணிபுரிந்து வந்தார். நேபாள உள்நாட்டுப் போரில் தப்பியவர்களுக்கு இடைக்கால நிவாரணம் அளித்தார். 2014-5 ஆம் ஆண்டில் , லெபனானின் திரிப்போலியில் சர்வதேச செஞ்சிலுவை சங்கத்தின் குழுத் தலைவராக இருந்தார். சிரிய உள்நாட்டுப் போரிலிருந்து பரவிய ஆயுத வன்முறையால் பாதிக்கப்பட்ட சமூகங்களுடன் இணைந்து பணியாற்றினார்."},{"question":"கேள்வி :  2011ஆம் ஆண்டு செண்டாய், சப்பானில் நிகழ்ந்த நிலநடுக்கம் சிறு  குறிப்பு   வரைக  .","answer":" பதில் :        ஒரு நிலநடுக்கத்தின் அளவுக்கு வரையறை ஏதுமில்லை என்றாலும் வரலாற்றில் பதிவான மிக பெரிய நிலநடுக்கங்கள், 9.0 ரிக்டருக்கும் கூடுதலானவை பெரும் பாதிப்பை ஏற்படுத்துவன ஆகும்.   இத்தகைய மிக அண்மையில் நிகழ்ந்த நிலநடுக்கமானது 2011ஆம் ஆண்டு செண்டாய், சப்பானில் நிகழ்ந்த நிலநடுக்கமாகும். பதிவு செய்யப்பட்ட நிலநடுக்கங்களுல் சப்பானில் பதிவான வலுவான நிலநடுக்கம் இதுவாகும். ஆழமற்ற நிலநடுக்கங்களே அதிக ஆபத்தை விளைவிக்கக்கூடியவை ஆகும்."},{"question":"පළමු ලෝක යුද්ධයේ වරදකරු බවට පත්කරමින් , ජර්මනියට එරෙහිව දඬුවම් නියමකළ ගිවිසුම කුමක්ද ?","answer":"පළමු ලෝක යුද්ධයේ වරදකරු බවට පත්කරමින් , ජර්මනියට එරෙහිව දඬුවම් නියමකළ ගිවිසුම වන්නෙ වර්සෙල්ස් ගිවිසුම යි.."},{"question":"Kedụ ìhè bụ ọrịa Obi?","answer":"Ọrịa obi nke kacha emetụta ụmụnwoke bụ nke a kpọrọ 'coronary heart disease' na Bekee.Ihe na-akpata ya bụ mgbe ọbara anaghị erucha n'obi mmadụ otu o kwesịrị.Ọtụtụ ihe na-akpata mkpọnwụ ahụ (stroke) bụkwa ha na-akpata ọrịa obi.Nnyocha gosiri na ọrịa obi na-aka ejitu ụmụnwoke karịa ndị nwaanyị.Ụzọ kacha mfe e si agwọta ọrịa obi bụ ma a chọpụta ya n'oge.Ya kpatara ime nnyocha kwa mgbe kwa mgbe ji dị ezigbo mkpa."},{"question":"Hãy đặt một tiêu đề phù hợp với đoạn văn sau: Trên trang cá nhân, Trương Mỹ Nhân xả kho bộ ảnh cùng con gái. Đây là lần đầu tiên người đẹp công khai việc sinh con đầu lòng trước công chúng khiến khán giả không khỏi bất ngờ. Trương Mỹ Nhân hạnh phúc chia sẻ: \\"Gửi con gái của mẹ! Chúc mừng sinh nhật tròn 2 tuổi của con, Bona. Hôm nay mẹ viết ra những dòng này vì mẹ biết với bản tính của mẹ thì chắc nơi đây là nơi lưu trữ tốt nhất. Mẹ mong những dòng tâm sự này sau khi con lớn lên có thể đọc được và xem là kỷ niệm thật ngọt ngào.   Trương Mỹ Nhân rất bất ngờ khi mình được bước vào hành trình làm mẹ đầy thiêng liêng. Bởi trước đó, cô bị đa nang buồng trứng, bác sĩ thông báo tỉ lệ có con là rất khó. Người đẹp nghẹn ngào: \\"Con được sinh ra bằng một tình yêu đẹp. Những ngày đầu con mới đến, mẹ đã rất bất ngờ. Lúc trước, bác sĩ nói mẹ bị đa nang buồng trứng nên rất khó có thai. Trước năm 25 tuổi, mẹ không dám nghĩ mình sẽ có con. Với mẹ, con như điều kỳ tích, là điều may mắn mà ông trời ưu ái dành cho mẹ. Dù mẹ vụng về, mẹ có nhiều lúc thật trẻ con nhưng được làm mẹ của Bona đã mang đến cho mẹ hạnh phúc quá lớn. Mẹ cám ơn Bona. Mẹ không hiểu tại sao ông trời có thể ban cho mẹ 1 em bé hiểu chuyện, ngoan ngoãn ngay từ khi còn nằm trong bụng mẹ. Lúc mang bầu con, mẹ chịu nhiều áp lực. Nhưng từ lúc con chào đời, con đã tiếp thêm cho mẹ sức mạnh. Con mạnh mẽ, ít khi khóc quấy, tình cảm và đặc biệt là lúc nào cho mẹ cảm giác mẹ là người đặc biệt nhất với con.   Bona ơi, con tuyệt vời như chòm sao Sư tử của con vậy đó. Từ bé, con đã luôn âu yếm mẹ, hôn mẹ, nắm lấy tay mẹ, nhìn vào gương mặt của mẹ để thể hiện cảm xúc. Nhiều khi mẹ nghĩ rằng không phải con mới 2 tuổi đâu, Bona à, mẹ ngốc quá phải không con. Bây giờ con thêm tuổi mới rồi, cũng đã dần bộc lộ tính cách và cái tôi của mình hơn. Mẹ yêu sao những lần đi đâu con cũng về cất dép ngăn nắp, những lần gặp người lớn là con ngoan ngoãn cúi đầu chào. Con lại còn biết cám ơn, xin lỗi và hờn dỗi nữa chứ. Con 2 tuổi rồi, đã biết chọn xem chương trình con thích, mặc bộ quần áo mà con yêu. Mẹ luôn tôn trọng những điều con chọn, con hãy chia sẻ cùng mẹ mọi điều con nhé.  Mẹ biết, khi mẹ viết những dòng này, sẽ có nhiều anh chị hỏi mẹ về con lắm. Nhưng con gái của mẹ quá là xinh xắn, đáng yêu mà, mẹ phải tự hào nói về con chứ. Mẹ đang rất hạnh phúc, khi được ở bên con. Và mẹ muốn cho cả thế giới biết rằng Bona của mẹ tuyệt vời đến thế nào\\". Trương Mỹ Nhân hạnh phúc khi thiên thần nhỏ xuất hiện trong cuộc đời mình, Bona là động lực lớn của cô lúc này. Thậm chí cô đánh đổi cả sự nghiệp để lựa chọn việc có con. Trương Mỹ Nhân kể: \\"Nếu quay lại những ngày mới mang thai con, mẹ vẫn sẽ chọn Bona. Mẹ thầm biết ơn bản thân vì đã quyết định đúng đắn. Mẹ có thể đi chậm 1 chút, có thể rơi vài nhịp trên con đường sự nghiệp nhưng mẹ không thể không có Bona. Nếu ngày đó mẹ không đủ mạnh mẽ thì thiên thần nhỏ của mẹ đã chẳng được nhìn thấy ánh mặt trời. Nếu ngày đó mẹ chọn sự nghiệp, mẹ sẽ không bao giờ biết được nụ cười của con ấm áp, rạng rỡ đến chừng nào. Nếu ngày đó mẹ chọn sự nghiệp, có thể mẹ sẽ bước nhanh hơn 1 chút nhưng chắc chắn rằng cả đời này mẹ sẽ ân hận, hối tiếc lắm.  Phải chi mẹ tính toán được nhiều hơn, sẵn sàng hơn trong việc chào đón con thì có thể con đã có nhiều điều tốt đẹp hơn. Mẹ xin lỗi Bona vì đôi khi mẹ vụng về, mẹ lúng túng, mẹ chưa làm 1 người mẹ thật tốt nhưng mẹ sẽ cố gắng nhiều hơn. Con giúp mẹ cảm thấy cuộc đời này đẹp quá, tích cực quá. Mẹ bây giờ sống có mục đích hơn, con cho mẹ trách nhiệm cùng niềm tin rằng chỉ cần có con bên cạnh, mẹ sẽ làm được mọi thứ. Không gì quý giá hơn được nhìn thấy con cười với mẹ mỗi ngày. Sinh nhật 2 tuổi rồi, Bona hãy mau ăn chóng lớn, khỏe mạnh và mãi đáng yêu nhé. Mẹ yêu con lắm, Bona của mẹ\\".","answer":"Á quân The Face 2017 bất ngờ công khai con đầu lòng sau thời gian giữ kín"},{"question":"सर्बनाम भनेको के हो ?","answer":"नामको सट्टामा प्रयोग हुने शब्दलाई सर्वनाम भनिन्छ । सर्वनामको प्रयोग नाम, पदावली र वाक्यको सट्टामा पनि हुनेगर्दछ। सर्वनाम पाँच प्रकारका हुन्छन्‌ :- (१) पुरुषवाचक सर्वनाम (२) दर्शकवाचक सर्वनाम (३) सम्बन्धवाचकसर्वनाम (४) प्रश्नवाचक सर्वनाम (५) निजबाचक सर्वनाम ।"},{"question":"Nitori Sunday Igboho, Oluwoo bẹ Buhari, o lo ti kẹkọọ pe Naijiria ko ṣe e pin","answer":"Oluwoo ti ilu Iwo, Ọba Abdulrosheed Adewale Akanbi, ti rawọ ẹbẹ si Aarẹ Muhammadu Buhari lati sinmi lilepa Oloye Sunday Adeyẹmọ, ẹni ti gbogbo eeyan mọ si Sunday Igboho, kaakiri.Ninu lẹta kan ti Akọwe iroyin Oluwoo, Alli Ibraheem, kọ ranṣẹ si Buhari lorukọ Kabiesi ni Oluwoo ti sọ pe ọmọde ki i mọ ẹkọ ọ jẹ ko ma ra a lọwọ ni ọrọ wahala ti Igboho ko ara rẹ si yii.O ni ọpọlọpọ ori-ade lo gba a nimọran nigba to bẹrẹ ijijagbara rẹ pe dandan ni ki Orileede Oodua da duro, ṣugbọn to kọ eti ikun si imọran awọn agba.Oluwoo ṣalaye pe pẹlu bi gbogbo nnkan ṣe waa da bayii, Sunday Igboho ti kẹkọọ pe Naijiria ko ṣee pin si wẹwẹ lasiko ti a wa yii, ati pe ko sẹni to le doju ija kọ ijọba.Kabiesi sọ siwaju pe “Gẹgẹ bii Musulumi, gbogbo wa la mọ pe ọjọ idariji ni ọjọ Jimọh jẹ, idi niyi ti mo fi n bẹ Aarẹ Muhammadu Buhari lati fori jin Sunday Adeyẹmọ.“A kilọ fun un to. Ẹni to ba mọ itan wahala to mu ẹmi awọn eeyan bii Moshood Kaṣimawo Ọlawale Abiọla ati Kensaro Wiwa lọ yoo mọ pe ninu iṣọkan ni agbara wa wa.“Sunday Adeyemo di gbajugbaja nipasẹ jija fun awọn ti wọn ba fọwọ ọla gba loju lawujọ, mo si maa n ba a sọrọ nigbakuugba ti mo ba gbọ ohunkohun nipa rẹ. O wa si aafin mi lọdun 2018, mo si gba a nimọran, ṣugbọn ko mọ iyatọ laarin didoju ija kọ ijọba ati jija fun ẹya ẹni.“O to asiko kan to bẹrẹ si i bu gbogbo eeyan, mo wa lara awọn to kọkọ fẹsun kan nitori ipolongo ki orileede yii wa lọkan ti mo n ṣe. Gẹgẹ bii baba, mo ti dariji i, mo wa n bẹ Aarẹ Buhari pe ko foriji ọmọ wa ologo yii.“Ope ni ninu nnkan to jẹ mọ tijọba. Ẹbun pataki lo jẹ fun iran Yoruba. O ti ṣeleri lati feti si imọran wa. Mo bẹ Aarẹ lati paṣẹ fun awọn agbofinro lati tuukanna lẹyin ọrun rẹ. Mo gbagbọ pe ṣiṣe bẹẹ yoo tun mu ki iṣọkan Naijiria tẹsiwaju. Mo ṣeleri lati mu Igboho wa fun ipade alaafia nitori oju rẹ ti ri to, yoo si maa kiyesi ihuwasi rẹ latoni lọ.”Oluwoo wa gboṣuba fun Buhari lori ọna to n gba lati gbogun ti iwa igbesunmọmi ati awọn iwa janduku lorileede yii pẹlu bo ṣe n mu idagbasoke ba gbogbo ẹkajẹka."},{"question":"Onde está localizado o menor osso do corpo humano?","answer":"O estribo é considerado o menor osso do corpo humano e encontra-se localizado na orelha média."},{"question":"এই অনুচ্ছেদের জন্য একটি ধারাবাহিকতা লিখুন :লুৎফা তাহের ১৯৪৭ সালের ৩১ জুলাই তৎকালীন পূর্ব পাকিস্তানের ময়মনসিংহ জেলার কিশোরগঞ্জে জন্মগ্রহণ করেন। বাংলাদেশের মুক্তিযুদ্ধে","answer":"১১ নং সেক্টরের সেক্টর কমান্ডার কর্নেল আবু তাহের বীর উত্তম তার স্বামী। তার তিন সন্তান - কন্যা জয়া তাহের, পুত্র আবু কায়সার যিশু এবং পুত্র মিশু।"},{"question":"Çocuğa verilen nafaka hangi durumlarda kesilir?","answer":"Çocuğa Verilen Nafaka Hangi Durumlarda Kesilir? Çocuk için ödenen tarafa türüne “iştirak nafakası” adı verilir. Çocuğun velayetinin değişmesi, nafaka yükümlüsünün ölmesi ya da çocuğun 18 yaşını doldurması hallerinde iştirak nafakası yükümlülüğü sona erer."},{"question":"¿Cuál es un significado adicional cuando se usa la palabra \\"primo\\"? Aparentemente es cualquier objeto que puede, esencialmente de manera única, descomponerse en sus componentes primos. ¿Me puedes dar algo de contexto? ","answer":"El concepto de número primo es tan importante que se ha generalizado de diferentes maneras en varias ramas de las matemáticas. Generalmente, \\"primo\\" indica minimalidad o indecomponibilidad, en un sentido apropiado. Por ejemplo, el campo primo es el subcampo más pequeño de un campo F que contiene tanto 0 como 1. Es Q o el campo finito con elementos p, de donde proviene el nombre. A menudo un segundo significado adicional es el uso de la palabra primo, es decir, que cualquier objeto puede, esencialmente de manera única, descomponerse en sus componentes primos. Por ejemplo, en la teoría del nudo, un nudo primo es un nudo que es indescomponible en el sentido de que no puede ser escrito como la suma de dos nudos no triviales. Cualquier nudo puede ser expresado únicamente como una suma conectada de nudos primos. Los modelos Prime y los Prime 3-manifolds son otros ejemplos de este tipo."},{"question":"Ki laa ti waa ṣeyi si, awọn Fulani tun pa agbẹ mẹta sinu oko l’Ọwọ","answer":"Lẹyin bii ọjọ mẹrin pere ti wọn pa awọn meji sinu igbo ọba l’Ọwọ, awọn agbẹ mẹta mi-in lawọn Fulani darandaran tun yinbọn pa labule kan ti wọn n pe ni Ijugbere, nijọba ibilẹ Ọwọ, yii kan naa lọjọ Abamẹta, Satide, ọsẹ to kọja.Oludamọran agba fun gomina lori eto ọgbin, Akin Olotu, lo fidi iṣẹlẹ yii mulẹ fawọn oniroyin kan lọjọ Aiku, Sannde, ọsẹ ta a wa yii.O ni ipaniyan atawọn iwa ọdaran mi-in to n waye lemọ lemọ ninu igbo ọba to jẹ tipinlẹ Ondo lati ọwọ awọn Fulani ti fidi ohun to ṣokunfa bi Gomina Rotimi Akeredolu ṣe fofin de wọn ninu igbo ọba mulẹ.O ni ṣe lo yẹ kí gbogbo awọn to n sọrọ ta ko igbesẹ naa dọwọ boju pẹlu atilẹyin ti wọn n ṣe fawọn onisẹẹbi ọhun.Gomina Akeredolu la gbọ pe o ti fi ofin to rọ mọ kiko ẹran jẹ oko oloko sọwọ sile-igbimọ aṣofin ipinlẹ Ondo lọsẹ to kọja.Arakunrin ni ijọba oun ti ṣetan lati kọ awọn ibudo igbalode tawọn Fulani yoo ti maa kẹran jẹ oko wọn ní gbogbo ìjọba ibilẹ mejidinlogun to wa nipinlẹ Ondo.Bakan naa ni gomina ọhun tun fọwọ si rira ogun ọkọ fun awọn ẹsọ Amọtẹkun ki iṣẹ aabo ti wọn n ṣe ba a le rọrun si i."},{"question":"બીમારીની રજા ની વિનંતી કરતો પત્ર તમારા સુપરવાઈઝર ને લખો.","answer":"વિષય: એક દિવસ માટે બીમારીની રજા ની વિનંતીઆદરણીય [સુપરવાઈઝર/મેનેજરનું નામ],હું તમને  આ પત્ર લખી રહ્યો છું કે હું અસ્વસ્થ અનુભવું છું અને આવતીકાલે, [તારીખ] ઓફિસમાં આવી શકીશ નહીં. ડોક્ટરે મને આરામ કરવા અને સ્વસ્થ થવા માટે એક દિવસની રજા લેવાની સલાહ આપી છે. તેથી, હું એક દિવસ માટે બીમારીની રજાની વિનંતી કરવા માંગુ છું.આના કારણે પડતી અસુવિધા માટે હું દિલગીર છું અને તમને ખાતરી આપું છું કે હું મારા સહકર્મીઓ પરની અસર ઘટાડવા અને મારી ગેરહાજરી દરમિયાન સરળ કાર્યપ્રવાહ સુનિશ્ચિત કરવા માટે દરેક પ્રયાસ કરીશ. જો કોઈ તાકીદની બાબતો હોય જેના પર મારું ધ્યાન જરૂરી હોય તો હું ઈમેલ દ્વારા ઉપલબ્ધ હોઈશ.કૃપા કરીને મને જણાવો કે આ માંદગી રજા વિનંતી માટે કોઈ ચોક્કસ દસ્તાવેજો અથવા ઔપચારિકતાઓ જરૂરી છે, અને હું તેને તરત જ પ્રદાન કરીશ. હું મારી ગેરહાજરી વિશે મારી ટીમના સભ્યોને પણ જાણ કરીશ અને કામની પ્રગતિમાં કોઈ વિક્ષેપ ન આવે તેની ખાતરી કરવા માટે કોઈપણ બાકી કાર્યો અથવા પ્રોજેક્ટ્સ સોંપીશ.હું કામ પર નિયમિત હાજરી જાળવવાનું મહત્વ સમજું છું, અને હું પાછા ફર્યા પછી કોઈપણ બાકી કામ પૂર્ણ કરવાની અથવા ખોવાયેલા સમયની ભરપાઈ કરવાની ખાતરી કરીશ.તમારી સમજણ અને સમર્થન બદલ આભાર. હું આ બાબત પર તમારું ધ્યાન અને મારી વિનંતી પર તમારી વિચારણાની પ્રશંસા કરું છું. જો તમને કોઈ વધુ સૂચનાઓ અથવા માહિતીની જરૂર હોય, તો કૃપા કરીને મને જણાવવામાં અચકાશો નહીં.મારી ગેરહાજરીમાં તમને અને ટીમને ઉત્પાદક દિવસની શુભેચ્છા.તમારો વિશ્વાસુ,[તમારું નામ][તમારી સ્થિતિ/વિભાગ][સંપર્ક માહિતી]"},{"question":"Apakah kelebihan pendidikan maya dan pembelajaran atas talian? ","answer":"Antara kelebihan pendidikan maya dan pembelajaran atas talian adalah:1. Meningkatkan kemahiran teknologi 2. Penyampaian ilmu yang interaktif dan mudah 3. Membuka peluang pendidikan jarak jauh tanpa batasan 4. Mengurangkan kos perbelanjaan 5. Waktu pembelajaran yang fleksibel 6. Suasana pembelajaran yang kondusif"},{"question":"Sheeg nabi Adam waxa lgu dhex abuuray?","answer":"Waxa lagu dhex abuuray Janada. "},{"question":"إقرأ المقال التالي:إن لم تستخدم مولدًا من قبل أو لم تستخدمه منذ وقت طويل فمن المهم أن تقرأ كل التعليمات وإرشادات السلامة الواردة في كُتيب التعليمات المرفق مع المولد. قبل بدء المولد، استغل بضع دقائق لقراءة المعلومات التي يوفرها المُصَنِّع من أجل ضمان تشغيله بأمان. خزن كُتيب إرشادات السلامة مع المولد حتى تجدها بسهولة وقت الحاجة. يَصدر عن المولدات الكثيرُ من الحرارة والضوضاء والعوادم الخطرة، لذا اترك المولد في الخارج في مكان جاف بعيدًا عن أي شيء مسافة 90 سنتيمترًا، وعن أي أبواب أو نوافذ مفتوحة مسافةً لا تقل عند 6 أمتار. ينبغي أن يتوفر في المولد مقياس للوقود؛ اقرأه لتتأكد أن الخزان ممتلئ كفايةً قبل تشغيله وأضف مزيدًا من الوقود إن اقتضى الأمر. تحتاج المولدات إلى الزيت لتشحيم الأجزاء المتحركة. متبعًا إرشادات دليل المستخدم، تفقد مستوى الزيت في المولد قبل تشغيله وأضف بعض الزيت (فقط من النوع الذي يحدده المُصَنِّع) إن اقتضى الأمر. يسحب المولدُ النقال الهواءَ كجزء من عملية الاحتراق لإنتاج الكهرباء وينقيه المرشحُ بحبس ما فيه من أتربة وشوائب. تفحص المرشح دائمًا قبل استخدام المولد، فإن كان مسدودًا أو متسخًا فنظفه أو استبدله متبعًا إرشادات دليل المستخدم. للمولد مفتاح يتحكم في إنتاجه للطاقة. تأكد أن ذاك المفتاح مغلق قبل التشغيل. يتحكم ذاك الصمام في تدفق الوقود للمحرك، والذي يحتاجه المولد ليدور منتجًا طاقةً كهربية. لا تشغل صمام الوقود إلا إن كنت على وشك تشغيل المولد. مستخدمًا مفتاح التشغيل (START)، أدر المولد. امنحه عدة دقائق ليسخن ثم ضع مفتاح الدائرة الكهربية في وضع التشغيل (ON)، مع ملاحظة أنه يفضل أن تقرأ الإرشادات لتعلم كم من الوقت يتطلبه المولد ليسخن. تسمح معظم المولدات بتوصيل الأجهزة الإلكترونية بها مباشرةً، أو استخدم سلك توصيل ملائمًا وليكن متينًا يتحمل الجهد العالي وبه وصلة أرضية. أطفئه إن لم تعد تحتاجه أو إن احتجت إلى إمداده بالوقود. أغلق الدائرة الكهربية أولًا ثم أطفئه باستخدام مفتاحه، وأخيرًا أغلق صمام الوقود. تتحدد كمية الوقود التي يمكنك تخزينها بواسطة كل من القانون واعتبارات الأمان والمساحة المتاحة. حاول أن تُبقي بالجوار كميةً كافيةً من الوقود لإمداد المولد قدر حاجتك إليه.  ارجع إلى دليل المستخدم لتعلم كم من الوقت يعمل المولد على خزان وقود واحد؛ يساعدك ذلك على تقدير كمية الوقود التي يجب تخزينها. لا تستخدم إلا نوع الوقود الذي ينصح به.أكتب ملخص عن المقال السابق باللغة العربية:","answer":"اقرأ دليل المستخدم. ضع المولد في مكان ملائم. تفقد مستوى الوقود. تفقد مستوى الزيت. افحص مرشح الهواء. أغلق الدائرة الكهربية للمولد. شغل صمام الوقود. شغل المولد. وصل أجهزتك الكهربائية بالمولد. أطفئ المولد. خزن كميةً كافيةً من الوقود. أطفئ المحرك ودعه يبرد قبل تزويده بالوقود. افحص المولد دوريًا."},{"question":"Hãy viết một đoạn văn ít nhất 200 chữ dựa trên nội dung được nói tới trong câu sau: Tuyển futsal Việt Nam triệu tập 23 cầu thủ chuẩn bị cho giải Châu Á","answer":"Ông Giustozzi Diego Raul sinh năm 1978, là chiến lược gia nổi tiếng người Argentina, từng đưa Argentina World Cup 2016. Đây cũng kỳ futsal World Cup lần đầu tiên trong lịch sử của tuyển futsal Việt Nam, khi đó được dẫn dắt bởi huấn luyện viên Bruno Garcia Formoso người Tây Ban Nha và đã xuất sắc lọt vào tới vòng 1/8. Bên cạnh chức vô địch FIFA Futsal World Cup 2016, ông Giustozzi Diego Raul còn ghi dấu ấn khi cùng Argentina giành HCB đại hội thể thao Nam Mỹ 2014, đánh bại Brazil ở giải tứ hùng sau đó và đăng quang tại giải Continental Cup lần thứ 3. Ở cấp câu lạc bộ, chiến lược gia này cũng từng đưa ElPozo Murcia (Tây Ban Nha) về nhì giải Châu Âu mùa 2019-2020. Với những thành tích ấn tượng trong sự nghiệp cầm quân tại các sân chơi lớn của futsal thế giới, huấn luyện viên Giustozzi Diego Raul được kỳ vọng sẽ mang đến làn gió mới cho tuyển futsal Việt Nam, trước mắt là thi đấu thật tốt tại vòng chung kết futsal Châu Á 2022, sau đó là hướng tới mục tiêu cạnh tranh suất dự World Cup 2024. Do mới tiếp quản tuyển futsal Việt Nam nên có thể thấy tân huấn luyện viên trưởng Giustozzi Diego Raul đã niềm tin vào lực lượng các cầu thủ do các cộng sự trong ban huấn luyện giới thiệu, trong đó đa phần là những gương mặt dạn dày kinh nghiệm như thủ thành Hồ Văn Ý, Trần Văn Vũ, Khổng Đình Hùng, Phạm Đức Hòa, Ala Lê Quốc Nam, Trần Thái Huy, Nguyễn Minh Trí,… Ngoài ra có thể kể đến một số gương mặt trẻ xuất sắc như Nguyễn Văn Hiếu, Châu Đoàn Phát, Nhan Gia Hưng… Theo kế hoạch, tuyển futsal Việt Nam sẽ tập luyện tại Nhà thi đấu Thái Sơn Nam Quận 8 từ ngày 1.8 đến ngày 8.9.2022. Sau đó, thầy trò ông Giustozzi Diego Raul sẽ sang Thái Lan tham dự giải futsal quốc tế từ ngày 9.9 đến 17.9.2022. Tại giải đấu này, tuyển futsal Việt Nam sẽ có những trận thử lửa với các đối thủ rất chất lượng gồm: Iran, Morocco, Phần Lan, Angola và chủ nhà Thái Lan. Kết thúc giải futsal quốc tế tại Thái Lan, tuyển futsal Việt Nam sẽ trở về nước để tiếp tục hoàn thiện khâu chuẩn bị cuối cùng trước khi di chuyển sang Kuwait vào ngày 24.9 để tham dự vòng chung kết futsal Châu Á 2022, nơi mà tuyển futsal Việt Nam sẽ gặp Hàn Quốc, Saudi Arabia và đương kim á quân Nhật Bản tại vòng bảng."},{"question":"A ko ni i yọ owo iranwọ lori epo bẹntiroolu lai ṣepade pẹlu ẹgbẹ oṣiṣẹ-Ijọba Apapọ","answer":"Lati ma mu inira ba awọn araalu ni ijọba apapọ fi ni aọn ko ti i ni yọwọ lori owo iranwọ epo bẹntiroolu, bo tilẹ jẹ pe ofin tuntun ti Buhari ṣẹṣẹ buwọ lu lori ọrọ epo bẹntiroolu (PIB) faaye gba eleyii. Wọn ni lati ma fi ara ni araalu lawọn ko fi ni i mu eleyii ṣe loju ẹsẹ.Minisita kekere lori ọrọ epo bẹntiroolu nilẹ wa, Timpere Sylva lo sọrọ yii di mimọ. O ni ọgọjọ Naira ti wọn n ta epo bẹntiroolu naa ni wọn yoo ṣi maa ta a.Minisita yii ni awọn mọ inira ti fifi owo kun owo epo lasiko yii yoo mu ba araalu, awọn si fẹẹ ṣepade pẹlu ẹgbẹ oṣiṣẹ lati le ṣaṣaro lori bi ofin yii yoo ṣe ṣiṣẹ, ti awọn yoo si ti mojuto anwọn ọna to le gba fẹẹ mu inira ba araalu."},{"question":"ماهو الجيولوجيا ؟","answer":"علم الارض."},{"question":"सचिन तेंदुलकर ","answer":"सचिन तेंदुलकर भारतीय क्रिकेटको महान खेलाडी हुन्। उहाँ भारतका मुंबईमा १९७३ मा जन्मेका हुन्। तेंदुलकरले अपनी क्रिकेट करियरलाई अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय स्तरमा एक सफलतापूर्वक समाप्त गरेका छन्।तेंदुलकरले बारह वर्षको आयुमा अपनो प्रथम अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय क्रिकेट खेलका लागि भारतका टिममा प्रवेश गरेका थिए। उनको पहिलो एकदिवसीय अंतर्राष्ट्रिय खेल १८८९ मा होटलवान्स ट्रॉफी खेलमा हुँदो थियो।तेंदुलकरले अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय क्रिकेटमा अद्वितीय रेकर्डहरू स्थापित गरेका छन्। उहाँले अन्तर्राष्ट्रिय वनदिवसीय क्रिकेटमा १०० शतकहरूको रेकर्ड साथै सबै फोरमेटमा एकदिवसीय क्रिकेटमा सबैभन्दा धेरै अंतर्राष्ट्रिय रनहरूको रेकर्ड स्थापना गरेका छन्।तेंदुलकरले विश्वकप र विश्व टेस्ट चैम्पियनशिपमा बारम्बार भारतको ध्येयमा सहयोग गर्ने भूमिका खेलेका थ"},{"question":"请用简洁的语言回答以下问题：问题：人类学的主要研究方法有哪些？","answer":"答案：人类学的主要研究方法包括田野调查、参与观察、访谈、文献研究等。"},{"question":"Slutför den här frasen: Angela James, född 22 december 1964 i Toronto, Ontario, är en kanadensisk före detta ishockeyforward. James var Kanadas mest dominerande spelare under 1970- och 1980-talen, och kallades \\"damhockeyns Wayne Gretzky\\". Hon gjorde 34 poäng på 20 matcher i de fyra första VM-turneringarna, 1990, 1992,","answer":"1994 och 1997."},{"question":"No contexto do futebol, defina, de maneira concisa, o termo \\"Pênalti\\".","answer":"Pênalti é uma cobrança direta ao gol, concedida quando ocorre uma falta dentro da grande área sobre o time que ataca, de modo que o time atacante é recompensado com uma chance de bater ao gol sem barreira, apenas com o goleiro."},{"question":"مەحوی لە کوێ لە دایک بوو؟ ","answer":"سلێمانی "},{"question":"Qual é a capital da Argentina?","answer":"A capital da Argentina é Buenos Aires."},{"question":"Σε ποιο σημαντικό γεγονός αναφέρεται το κείμενο: Η Οξυά (παλαιότερα γνωστή ως Βλάτσι, Μπλάτσι, Μπλάτση ή Μπλάτζα και (1902-1905), Βουλγαρικά: Българска Блаца (στην κορύφωση των γεγονότων προετοιμασίας της εξέγερσης του Ίλιντεν (1902-1903)), είναι ορεινό χωριό του νομού Καστοριάς. Είναι χτισμένη σε υψόμετρο 1.200 μέτρων στις πλαγιές του Βέρνου (Βιτσίου) και είναι ένα από τα ορεινότερα χωριά της Μακεδονίας. Μέχρι το 2010 υπάγονταν στον Δήμο Βιτσίου, ενώ από τον Ιανουάριο του 2011 ανήκει στο Δήμο Καστοριάς.","answer":"Η πόλη Οξυά."},{"question":"We zoeken de op een na langste rivier van Europa. Ze ontspringt in Duitsland als samenvloeiing van 3 andere rivieren, en mondt na 2829 kilometer uit in de zwarte zee aan de grens van Oekraïne en Roemenië, en doorkruist onderweg maar liefst 11 landen. Welke rivier zoeken we?","answer":"Donau "},{"question":"(Ngokumangala) Sanibonani Sonto, kwenzenjani? Wafika nabantuboMthetho?Ungethuki Nkosikazi. Mina ngingumseshi uNhleko. Kasizile ngobubi.Sidinga usizo lwakho nje, esethemba ukuthi sizoluthola.(Esathukile) Mina nginguMaNsibande. Kwenzenjani?Siyadabuka ukukwazisa ukuthi uMfundisi uZondo uhlaselwe,utholakale edutshuliwe, njengamanje ulimele kakhulu esibhedlela.(Ethwala izandla ekhanda) Hawu! Hawu! Ngomfundisi Nkosi yamiwoneni nje, kubani?(Ngezwi elinozwela) Nathi sizwe ubuhlungu nkosikazi. Impelasiyadabuka, sizwelana nani.(Esula izinyembezi emehlweni.) Kodwa ngoMfundisi pho!Nami ivele nje yangethusa le ndaba ntombi.Hawu! Kodwa ubangiswani uMfundisi? Kanti banjani abantuemhlabeni bakithi? Bambulala ebe enzeni nje uMfundisi?Kusolakala sengathi kumayelana nemali ngoba kukhona etholakeleendlini lapho edutshulelwe khona uMfundisi.Washo ngabona, kade befuna imali yomnikelo. Kodwa beyazelaphingoba indaba yemali ibiphakathi kwethu sobathathu?E, ngizodinga usizo lwakho-ke dadewethu. (Ekhipha ibhukwana.)Ngingakubuza imibuzo embalwa?Yebo, ayikho inkinga.Umgcine nini uMfundisi?Izolo ntambama.Bekungaba ngubani isikhathi?(Elokhu esula izinyembezi.) Bese ligamanxile ihora lesikhombisa.Ingabe ukhona yini umuntu enimgibelisile endleleni?Cha, impela akekho.Kuyiqiniso ukuthi ngenkathi nigcinana nobathathu benikade nibalaimali yomnikelo negcine ihambe noMfundisi?Yebo kuyiqiniso.1. Ngokwalesi siqeshana uzokwenzani uNhleko emzini kaMaNsibande? ","answer":"Wayezophenya icala lokudutshulwa koMfundisi.  ukuhlaselwa komfundisi."},{"question":"Phát biểu nào sau đây đúng?A. – 10 ∈ N B.  – 10 ∈ ZC. – 10 ∉ ZD. – 10 ∈ N* ","answer":"Lời giảiTa có: – 10 là số nguyên và không phải là số tự nhiên nên – 10 ∈ Z, – 10 ∉ N, – 10 ∉ N* . Chọn đáp án B. "},{"question":"নিম্নলিখিত অনুচ্ছেদ সংক্ষিপ্ত করুন :স্পেনে একজনের করোনা ভাইরাস পরিক্ষার জন্য নমুনা সংগ্রহ করা হচ্ছেদেশটির স্বাস্থ্য মন্ত্রণালয় বলছে, এই তথ্য তারা ইউরোপীয় ইউনিয়নভুক্ত দেশগুলোর সাথে শেয়ার করবে। মন্ত্রী সালভাদর ইলা বলেছেন, এই তালিকা সাধারণ জনগণ এবং চাকরিদাতাদের কাছে উন্মুক্ত করা যাবে না।  তিনি বলেন এই ভাইরাসকে পরাজিত করার উপায় হল \\"আমাদের যত বেশি জনকে টিকা দেয়া হবে ততই ভালো\\"। করোনাভাইরাসের কারণে ইউরোপের দেশগুলোর মধ্যে স্পেন অন্যতম ক্ষতিগ্রস্ত একটি দেশ। দেশটিতে এখন ফাইজারের টিকা দেয়া শুরু করেছে। গত সপ্তাহেই ইইউ সদস্য দেশগুলোর জন্য অনুমোদন দেয়া হয়েছে। সোমবার লা সেক্সটা টেলিভিশনে দেয়া সাক্ষাতকারে মি. ইলা জোর দিয়ে বলেন টিকা দান বাধ্যতামূলক না। তিনি বলেন, \\"যেটা করা হবে সেটা হল একটা নিবন্ধন করা। আমরা আমাদের ইউরোপিয়ান পার্টনারের সাথে শেয়ার করবো যে এইসব মানুষদের টিকা নেয়ার প্রস্তাব দেয়া হয়েছিল কিন্তু তারা সেটা গ্রহণ করেনি।\\" \\"এটা জনসম্মুখে প্রকাশ করার জন্য কোন তথ্য-প্রমাণ না। সবটাই করা হবে তথ্য রক্ষার প্রতি পূর্ণাঙ্গ শ্রদ্ধা রেখে সেটা করা হবে।\\" তিনি আরো বলেন \\" যাদের কে প্রস্তাব দেয়া হয়েছিল এবং তারা সেটা যেকোন কারণেই হোক ফিরিয়ে দিয়েছে সেটা নিবন্ধনে উল্লেখ থাকবে। সবশেষ হিসেব অনুযায়ী, বর্তমান স্পেনের প্রায় ২৮ শতাংশ নাগরিকরা টিকা নিতে চান না। নভেম্বরে এই অনুপাত ছিল ৪৭%। অণূবিক্ষণ যন্ত্রে করোনাভাইরাস দেখতে অনেকটা এরকমসোমবার তিনি আরো মন্তব্য করেন যারা টিকা নিতে চান তাদের সাথে আঞ্চলিক কর্তৃপক্ষ যোগাযোগ করবে। \\"যারা টিকা নিতে চান না আমরা মনে করি এটা একটা ভুল সিদ্ধান্ত কিন্তু তারপরেও এটা তাদের অধিকার। আমরা এই বিভ্রান্তি দুর করার চেষ্টা করছি। টিকা দেয়ার ফলে জীবন রক্ষা হবে\\"।  সোমবারেই স্পেনে কোভিড-১৯ এ মারা যাওয়ার সংখ্যা ৫০ হাজার ছুঁয়েছে। মহামারির সময়ে দেশটি ১৮ লক্ষের বেশি মানুষ আক্রান্ত হয়েছে বলে নিবন্ধন করে। স্পেনে রাত ১১টা থেকে সকাল ৬টা পর্যন্ত দেশজুড়ে কারফিউ চালু রয়েছে যেটা চলবে মে মাসের শুরু পর্যন্ত। অনেক স্থানে মানুষজনকে শুধুমাত্র কাজ করতে, ওষুধ কিনতে এবং বৃদ্ধ ও শিশুদের যত্ন নেয়ার জন্য বের হতে দেয়া হচ্ছে। আঞ্চলিক নেতারা কারফিউ এর সময় পরিবর্তন করতে পারবেন, এমনকি সীমান্ত বন্ধ করে দিতে পারবেন। বিবিসি বাংলায় আরো পড়ুন:নিজেকে আক্রান্ত মনে হলে কী করবেন, কোথায় যাবেন?","answer":"যারা করোনাভাইরাসের টিকা নিতে অনিচ্ছা প্রকাশ করছে স্পেন তাদের নাম নিবন্ধন করছে।"},{"question":"رشحلى بعض الكتب اللى ممكن اقراها و انا مواريش حاجة.","answer":"فكرة عظيمة. القراية ف وقت الفراغ أحسن استثمار. اتمنى الترشيحات دي تعجبك:1. جزيرة الكنز: دي رواية مشهورة جداً لروبرت لويس ستيفنسون عن كنز ضائع.2. الخيميائى: رواية ممتعة كتبها باولو كويلو و فيها مغازى كتير3. سلسلة هارى بوتر: كتب هارى بوتر من أنجح السلاسل ف التاريخ و بتحكى عن مدرسة لتعليم السحر."},{"question":"Soalan: Mana satu ayat yang tidak masuk akal? Pilihan: - Ayat A: \\"Piranha adalah ikan yang sangat lembut\\". - Ayat B: \\"Piranha adalah ikan yang sangat ganas\\".  Huraikan.","answer":"Piranha mempunyai rahang dan gigi yang kuat dan oleh itu tidak lembut. Jawapannya ialah ayat A."},{"question":"Địa danh nào được xem đệ nhất phong cảnh của Quảng Ngãi?","answer":"Thiên Ấn có tục danh là núi Hó, từ xưa được xem là đệ nhất phong cảnh của tỉnh Quảng Ngãi với mỹ danh \\"Thiên Ấn niêm hà\\", tức ấn trời đóng trên sông. Sông ở đây là sông Trà Khúc, con sông lớn nhất tỉnh. Thiên Ấn là tên một ngọn núi nằm ở tả ngạn sông Trà Khúc, về phía hạ lưu, cách thành phố Quảng Ngãi chừng 3 km về hướng đông bắc, thuộc địa phận thị trấn Sơn Tịnh, huyện Sơn Tịnh. Núi cao 106 mét, trông từ bốn phía đều tựa hình thang cân. "},{"question":"السؤال: من هو ساعي رسول الله؟","answer":"الإجابة: عمرو بن أمية الضمري رضي الله عنه"},{"question":"Apakah maksud \\"bagai asal selamat ke seberang, biar bergantung di ekor buaya\\"?","answer":"Sangat memerlukan pertolongan, apa pun bentuk pertolongan akan diterima"},{"question":"«  Inona ny marina ? Fanontaniana efa namakivaky siekla maro ity ; ary efa nandalo, ka niadian-kevitra teo anoloan’ny hendry sy ny lalin-tsaina hatry ny ela, nefa tsy mbola misy valiny feno mahalaza azy tanteraka… Ny firenena sambatra sy miadana indrindra dia ny firenena mampanjaka ny fahamarinana. Hiadana ny tokantrano raha samy manao ny marina ny fianakaviana. Tsy hisy ny ahiahy ; ho foana ny hala-tety, hehena ny manorisory. » Inona ny lohahevitr’io lahatsoratra ambony io ?","answer":"Ny lohahevitr’io lahatsoratra io dia ny tombotsoa azo avy amin’ny fanaovana ny marina."},{"question":"コスプレのコスとは何の略？","answer":"コスチュームです。"},{"question":"खालील श्लोकाचा सोप्या मराठीत अर्थ सांगा श्लोक:आतां वंदीन वेदमाता । श्रीशारदा ब्रह्मसुता ।शब्दमूल वाग्देवता । माहं माया ॥ १॥","answer":"अर्थ:मी आता वेदांची जननी, ब्रह्मदेवांची कन्या, शब्दब्रह्माची उत्पत्ती जिच्यापासून झाली त्या वाग्‌देवतारूपी महामायेला, श्रीशारदेला वंदन करतो. (१)"},{"question":"ગુજરાત ના પ્રાગ મહેલની વિશેષતાઓ શું હતી?","answer":"પ્રાગ મહેલ ની વિશેષતાઓ નીચે પ્રમાણેની છે:મુખ્ય ખંડ, જેની દિવાલ પર પશુઓના મસાલા ભરેલા માથા લટકાવ્યા છે.દરબાર ખંડ, જેમાં તૂટેલાં ઝુમ્મર અને પ્રતિમઓ છે.કોરીન્થીયન થાંભલા.યુરોપીયન વનસ્પતિઓ અને પ્રાણીઓના કોતરકામ વાળું જાળી કામ.મહેલના પ્રાંગણમાં પાછળના ભાગે આવેલું નાનકડું મંદિર જેમાં સુંદર નક્શીકામ કરેલા પત્થરો જડેલા છે."},{"question":"上手と得意はどう違うのかとよく聞かれます。どう説明したらいいでしょうか。","answer":"初級の学習者によく聞かれる質問に「得意」と「上手」はどう違うのか、というものがあります。得意や苦手がそれがよくできるという「本人の意識」を表し、上手や下手はその技術の良し悪しを客観的に言い表していると言えます。△　私は料理が上手です。→ ○　私は料理が得意です。○　私は料理が下手です。　○　私は料理が苦手です。△　メアリーさんは料理が得意です(だそうです）○　メアリーさんは料理が上手です。△　メアリーさんは料理が苦手です(だそうです）○　メアリーさんは料理が下手です。他人のことを言うときには「得意」、「上手」ともに用いることが可能ですが、「上手」を使った方がほめている感じがしますね。自分の技能（サッカー、バスケなどのスポーツ、ギターやピアノ、日本語や料理）について述べるときは「得意」を使うことが多いですね。「私は料理が上手です」は文法的には問題はありませんが、ちょっと厚かましい感じがしますね。また「メアリーさんは料理が下手です」も文法的には問題ありませんが、相手への配慮からあまり使わないことが多いでしょう。余談となりますがこのように日本語では社会的な配慮が言葉の使い方に大きく影響します。レッスンの中で気になる表現がある場合は、何が原因なのか考えてみるとよいでしょう。"},{"question":"Apakah maksud 'pandai mengambil otak di dalam kepala, tiada diketahui tuan tubuh'? Berilah satu contoh ayat untuknya.","answer":"Ia bermaksud bijak berkata-kata Contoh ayat: Pak cik Mat dipilih mewakili pihak keluarga lelaki untuk berunding tentang perkahwinan Zakaria dengan Azlina kerana dia pandai mengambil otak di dalam kepala, tiada diketahui tuan tubuh."},{"question":"Hoàn thiện đoạn văn sau với nội dung có liên quan tới đoạn văn dưới đây: Hồi cuối năm 2021, trang chính chức của ĐH New South Wales, Australia đăng tải thông tin chúc mừng TS Vinh Nguyễn (hay còn gọi là TS Nguyễn Thành Vinh) được phong hàm phó giáo sư. Anh là gương mặt quen thuộc với khán giả Việt khi đảm nhiệm vai Nam trong phim Phía trước là bầu trời'' đồng thời gây ấn tượng với ngôi vị á quân tại Đường lên đỉnh Olympia mùa đầu tiên 2000. Thành Vinh còn đại diện ghi danh người Việt ở nhiều giải thưởng danh giá hàng đầu thế giới. Năm 2000, Nguyễn Thành Vinh đại diện ngôi trường giàu truyền thống hiếu học THPT chuyên Lam Sơn, Thanh Hoá - tham gia cuộc thi Đường lên đỉnh Olympia năm thứ nhất và xuất sắc về nhì với số điểm 250 tại trận chung kết. Dù không giành được vòng nguyệt quế nhưng sau đó anh vẫn được chính phủ Australia cấp học bổng du học tại Sydney. Anh theo đuổi ngành hoá học công nghiệp ở Đại học New South Wales. Sau đó, Thành Vinh trở thành TS hoá học hữu cơ nhờ sự hướng dẫn của GS Michael Sherburn, tại Đại học Quốc gia Australia, Canberra. Tại thời điểm đó, Thành Vinh được cho là một trong những tiến sĩ trẻ tuổi nhất của Việt Nam ở nước ngoài. Chuyên ngành nghiên cứu chính của anh là các phương pháp tổng hợp mới để nghiên cứu ứng dụng sản phẩm tự nhiên, tổng hợp vào mô hình phân phối thuốc. Năm 2010, sau khi hoàn thành nghiên cứu sinh, anh làm việc về hoá học hữu cơ trong nhóm của GS Dieter Enders tại Viện Hóa học Hữu cơ, thuộc Đại học RWTH Aachen, nhờ học bổng sau tiến sĩ Alexander von Humboldt. Năm 2013, anh đảm nhận vị trí giảng viên trường Hoá học tại Đại học Curtin (Perth, Australia). 5 năm sau, vị tiến sĩ người Việt được phong chức giáo viên cao cấp. Cùng năm đó, anh được nhận Học bổng tương lai. Đây là chương trình hỗ trợ nghiên cứu trong các lĩnh vực có tầm quan trọng quốc gia bằng cách tài trợ cho nhà nghiên cứu nổi bật ưu đãi để thực hiện các nghiên cứu của họ tại Australia. Những người được nhận là một trong những nhà nghiên cứu sáng giá nhất ở Australia. Một năm sau đó, anh tiếp tục nhận tài trợ Dự án Khám phá của Hội đồng Nghiên cứu Australia trị","answer":"giá 420.000 USD cho giai đoạn 2020-2022 để thực hiện nghiên cứu các phương pháp tổng hợp mới. Trước đó PGS.TS gốc Việt còn từng giành được một loạt các giải thưởng về lĩnh vực nghiên cứu đang theo đuổi như: Giải thưởng Tạp chí Hóa học Thieme 2014 danh giá, do ban biên tập của Synlett-Synthesis-Synfact lựa chọn, vì thành tích xuất sắc trong vai trò là một nhà nghiên cứu đầu sự nghiệp; Là nhà báo hoá học hữu cơ người Việt duy nhất được trao giải thưởng nghiên cứu Discovery Early Career Research Award (DECRA) do Hội đồng Nghiên cứu Australia tài trợ; Được Bộ phận Hoá học Hữu cơ của Viện Hoá học Hoàng gia Australia (RACI) trao tặng Học bổng Athel Beckwith... Trên website của mình, Thành Vinh chia sẻ, bản thân từng đi vòng quanh Australia vào năm 2017 để trình bày các kết quả nghiên cứu gần đây của nhóm tại các trường đại học và trung tâm nghiên cứu. Ngoài các giải thưởng danh giá, Á quân của Đường lên đỉnh Olympia mùa đầu tiên còn có nhiều công bố quốc tế uy tín nhờ nghiên cứu giá trị thực hiện độc lập hoặc viết chung với các thành viên trong nhóm. Chia sẻ trên truyền thông, đạo diễn Đỗ Thanh Hải cho biết đã quen Thành Vinh khi làm chương trình Gặp nhau cuối năm. Khi biết Thành Vinh từ Thanh Hoá lên Hà Nội chuẩn bị thi Olympia, đạo diễn đến tìm gặp để ''nhắm'' cho vai Nam. Theo vị đạo diễn này, Nam phải là gương mặt tri thức và Thành Vinh là người phù hợp. Dù chưa từng học một lớp diễn xuất nào song Thành Vinh vẫn diễn tròn vai cậu sinh viên ''mọt sách'', thông minh và trầm tính. Trong phim, vì túng quẫn, Nam đã lấy trộm xe của người bạn cùng xóm trọ mới chuyển đến nhưng sau đó đã trả lại vì áy náy. Vì sợ lộ tẩy, cậu đã dại dột cắt tay tự tử nhưng được mọi người trong xóm trọ phát hiện đưa đi bệnh viện. Nam còn được khán giả nhớ đến bởi tình cảm khó gọi tên với nhân vật Trà. Trong khi những sinh viên xóm dị nghị về cô gái này nhưng Nam bất chấp cùng ăn, đi chơi, xem tivi và tâm sự với người mà cậu gọi là ''chị''. Giao lưu trong chương trình Cuộc sống thường ngày của VTV vào năm 2014, Thành Vinh chia sẻ: \\"Một trong những cảnh quay khó nhất của tôi là cảnh Nam khóc sau khi ăn trộm xe đạp, rời xóm trọ ra đi và gặp chị Thương - chị cả của xóm trọ. Thật sự tôi chưa từng khóc trong tình huống tương tự như thế nên thấy rất khó. Giải pháp của đạo diễn Đỗ Thanh Hải là dùng thuốc nhỏ mắt\\". Với Thành Vinh, đóng phim là trải nghiệm thú vị của tuổi trẻ và còn khó hơn việc leo đỉnh Olympia. Tổng hợp"},{"question":"මෙම වර්ණ ප්‍රාථමික හෝ ප්‍රාථමික නොවන ලෙස වර්ග කරන්න: රතු, නිල්, කොළ, තැඹිලි, කහ, සුදු, නිල්, රෝස, කළු, සුදු, දුඹුරු.","answer":"රතු, නිල් සහ කහ මූලික වර්ණ වේ. කොළ, තැඹිලි, සුදු, නිල්, රෝස, කළු, සුදු සහ දුඹුරු ප්‍රාථමික වර්ණ නොවේ."},{"question":"Ako ay gawa sa ladrilyo, at ang mga tao ay naninirahan sa akin. Ano ako?","answer":"Ako ay isang bahay."},{"question":"Ananan’ny olona fahefana ve ny lahatra?","answer":"Tsia,tsy ananan’ny olona fahefana ny lahatra."},{"question":"Parehas ra ba ang gangis sa grasshoppers?","answer":"Ang grasshopper o tapuri maalaan na perahas sa gangis. Apan ang gangis mas taas ang antena kumpara sa tapuri na mas mubo. Pareho silang ilhan na “mukanta” pamaagi sa pag bag-id sa duha ka parte są ilang lawas. Ang gangis mukanta pamaagi sa pag bag-id sa ilang mga pako. Samtang ang tapuri mukanta pamaagi sa pag bag-id sa ilang mga tag-as na paa sa likod ngadto sa ilang mga pako. "},{"question":"Ijọba Ọṣun fẹẹ bẹrẹ iforukọsilẹ fawọn Fulani darandaran","answer":"Ijọba ipinlẹ Ọṣun ti kede imurasilẹ rẹ lati ṣe akọsilẹ iye awọn Fulani darandaran ti wọn n gbe nipinlẹ naa, ti wọn yoo si ka wọn lẹyọkọọkan.Igbesẹ yii, gẹgẹ bijọba ṣe wi, ni yoo fi aaye silẹ lati mọ nipa awọn Fulani darandaran ti wọn n gbe ninu ilu kọọkan, ti yoo si jẹ ki alaafia ati irẹpọ le wa laarin awọn ẹya Fulani/Bororo atawọn Yoruba olohun ọgbin.Lẹyin ipade alaafia ti awọn igbimọ to n ri si ibagbepọ alaafia laarin awọn Fulani/Bororo pẹlu awọn agbẹ ṣe pẹlu awọn adari ẹya Fulani ati Bororo ti wọn n pe ni Seriki, eleyii to waye ninu ọgba ileeṣẹ to n ri si ipese ounjẹ ati ọrọ ọgbin ni Abere, ni wọn ti fẹnuko bayii.Nigba to n ba awọn oniroyin sọrọ, alaga igbimọ naa, Ọnarebu Mudaṣiru Toogun, sọ pe o pọn dandan lati mọ, ati lati ni, akọsilẹ to peye lori awọn atọhunrinwa ti wọn n gbe ninu ipinlẹ Ọṣun.Toogun ni eleyii yoo ran ijọba lọwọ lati le dena wahala to n fojoojumọ waye lori ọrọ eto aabo nipasẹ aikiyesi bi awọn eeyan ṣe n wọle nigba gbogbo.O fi kun ọrọ rẹ pe akọsilẹ naa yoo ran ijọba lọwọ lati mọ awọn nnkan amayedẹrun ti wọn yoo pese fun lilo awọn Fulani ati Bororo ti wọn n gbe nipinlẹ Ọṣun.Bakan naa lo gboṣuba fun awọn Seriki ọhun fun ifọwọsowọpọ wọn pẹlu ijọba Gomina Adegboyega Oyetọla, o si fi da wọn loju pe gomina ko ni i dẹkun wiwa alaafia laarin awọn agbẹ atawọn Fulani/Bororo.Lati le ya epo kuro lara alikaama, Toogun sọ pe laipẹ nijọba yoo pin kaadi idanimọ fun gbogbo awọn Fulani darandaran atawọn Bororo, bẹẹ ni awọn agbofinro yoo maa duro wamuwamu lẹnuubode kọọkan lati maa kiyesi awọn ti wọn ba n wọle.Ninu ọrọ rẹ, Seriki Fulani nipinlẹ Ọṣun, Alhaji Ibrahim Babatunde, fi da ijọba loju pe awọn fara mọ gbogbo agbekalẹ ijọba lati le mu ki alaafia tubọ maa jọba laarin wọn atawọn agbẹ ẹya Yoruba.O ni awọn eeyan oun yoo tubọ maa gbe lalaafia pẹlu awọn olugbe ilu kọọkan ti wọn wa, o si rọ ijọba lati tubọ maa ṣugbaa awọn loorekoore."},{"question":"Gwam gwam gwam: Gwam otere nzụ baa ọhịa? ","answer":"Azịza:Ọkpọ (ike) ụgụ.Nke a bụ maka na ọ n'acha nzụ nzụ. "},{"question":"Vienintelis Lietuvoje krepšinio muziejus veikia ne Kaune ar Vilniuje, bet nedideliame mieste šiaurės Lietuvoje. Kaip vadinasi tas miestas? Šio miesto krepšinio komanda vadinasi \\"Delikatesas\\" ir 2021 m. NKL reguliariajame sezone užėmė 13 vietą.","answer":"Pirmasis šalyje krepšinio muziejus įkurtas 2009 m. gegužės 30 d. Joniškyje. Muziejaus lankytojai gali susipažinti su Joniškio ir Lietuvos krepšinio istorija. Daug informacijos apie 1937 m. Rygoje ir 1939 m. Kaune vykusius Europos II ir III krepšinio čempionatus. Krepšinio muziejus turi įsigijęs Latvijos Respublikos Prezidento Karlio Ulmanio, Lietuvos Respublikos Prezidento Antano Smetonos dovanų, skirtų 1937 m., 1939 m. Europos krepšinio čempionams – Lietuvos krepšininkams, kopijas. Sienas puošia geriausių šalies krepšininkų nuotraukos bei pelnyti medaliai. Čia galima pamatyti 2003 m. Europos krepšinio čempionate Švedijoje Lietuvos krepšinio rinktinės iškovotą aukso medalį, 2007 m. Europos čempionato Ispanijoje ir 2010 metais pasaulio krepšinio čempionate Turkijoje laimėtus bronzos medalius."},{"question":"Ułóż pytanie do podanej odpowiedzi: San Francisco znajduje się Kalifornii.","answer":"Oto pytanie do powyższej odpowiedzi: W jakim stanie USA położone jest San Francisco?"},{"question":"\\"කලියුග කාලය\\" යනු කුමක් ද?\\"මෝහිනී\\" යනු කවුද?දන්න කෙනෙක් කියා දෙන්න.","answer":"කලියුගය:පුරාණ නමැති වෛදික සාහිත්‍යයට අනුව, පැරණි භාරතීයයන් මානව චිත්තයෙහි ක්‍රමික අවනතිය යුග වශයෙන් කොටස් හතරකට බෙදා දක්වා තිබේ. ( හතරැස් කොටුවක් කොටස් හතරකට බෙදා 1,2,3,4 වශයෙන් කොටස් 4 මේ යුග හතරට වෙන් කර ඇත.)1. කෘත යුගය:සියල්ල සම්පූර්ණ කර අවසානය යන අදහස යි.2. ත්‍රේතා යුගය: ඉහත කී කොටුවල කොටස් 3ක් සම්පූර්ණ ය. ( මේ යුගයේ දී මානසික සංවර්ධනයෙහි එක් කොටසක් අවසන්ය, තුනක් ඉතිරි ව ඇත යනුයි.3. ද්වාපර යුගය: ඉහත කී කොටුවලින් කොටස් දෙකක් සම්පූර්ණ ය. දෙකොටසක් හිස් ය. ද්වාපර වූයේ ඒ අරුතිනි.4. කලි යුගය: මේ යුගයේ දී එක කොටසක වත් සම්පූර්ණ වීමක් නැත. ඒ නිසා සියල්ල ම කිලිටි ය යන අරුතින් \\"කලි\\" යන්න භාවිත කර ඇත.කලි යුගය හැර සෙසු යුගයන්හි දී ශ්‍රැති, ස්මෘති, පුරාණ සහ වෛදික ක්‍රම භාවිතයෙන් මිනිසාගේ චතුර් වර්ග සම්පත්තිය ( අර්ථ, ධර්ම, කාම, මෝක්ෂ) ලබා ගත යුතු බවත්, කලියුග කාලයේ දී ආගම මාර්ගයෙන් පමණක් විමුක්තිය ලබා ගත හැකි බවත් සඳහන්ය.මේ හැරුණු විට, විෂ්ණු පුරාණයට අනුව විෂ්ණුගේ කාල සීමාව අවසන් වී ස්වර්ගයට ගිය පසු කලි නමැති රෞද්‍ර යක්ෂණිය පොළොවට බැස්සා ය. ඇයගේ බලය යටතේ පවත්නා කාලය කලියුගය බවත් එය සම්පුර්ණයෙන් ම මිනිසාගේ පිරිහීම ඇති කරවන බවත් සඳහන් වේ.තන්ත්‍ර සාහිත්‍යයට අනුව, ඉහත කී චතුර් වර්ග සම්පත්තිය ලබා ගැනීමට, කලියුගයේ දී හැකි වන්නේ වෛදික යුගයන්ගෙන් නො ව, ආගමික තන්ත්‍රවලින් බව මහානිර්වාණ නමැති තන්ත්‍රයෙහි සඳහන් වන බව කියැවේ.මූලාශ්‍රයය: සංස්කෘත සාහිත්‍යය, ජී.එස්.බී. සේනානායක, ඇම්.ඩී.ගුණසේන සහ සමාගම, කොළඹ, 1960 ( දෙවන සංස්.)"},{"question":"Anu-ano ang mga lalawigan sa MIMAROPA?","answer":"Ang mga lalawigan ng MIMAROPA o Rehiyon IV-B ay Mindoro, Marinduque, Romblon at Palawan. Binubuo ng unang dalawang letra ng bawat lalawigan ang pangalan ng rehiyon. Matatagpuan sa Luzon ang rehiyong ito."},{"question":"اكتب مقالة على أساس هذا \\"خيط إبرةك حول الملابس من الداخل للخارج أو إلى الجانب الخطأ. استخدم جسم منحني كدليل. خياطة عبر الحفرة بتروح في اتجاه واحد. نسج الخيط أو الخيط من خلال الغرز. ربط عقدة لتثبيت الخيط أو نسجها من خلال بضع مرات أخرى. \\"  المادة:","answer":". ابدأ بتخيط الإبرة بخيطك أو خيوطك المتطابقة. خيط الخيط أو الخيط من خلال عين الإبرة، وبعدين اسحب الخيط أو الخيط من خلاله بحيث يكون معظم الخيط على جانب واحد والجانب التاني عنده بضعة بوصات (حوالي 5 سم). امسك الإبرة في العين لتمنع الخيط من أن ينفصل أثناء الخياطة. خذي في الاعتبار إنك هتحتاجين خيط أو خيط أقل أو أكثر حسب حجم الحفرة. على سبيل المثال، قد تتطلب فتحة صغيرة حوالي 12 (30.5 سم) فقط من الخيط أو الخيط، في حين قد تتطلب فتحة كبيرة 24 (61 سم) لتغطيتها. خيط الإبرة بخيط أو خيط أكتر من اللي بتظن إنك هتحتاجة. بيعتمد حجم الإبرة اللي بتستخدمه على المنتج ونوع الخيط اللي بتستخدمه. استخدم إبرة مع عين كبيرة كفاية لتناسب خيطك. من المهم تعمل على جانب مشروعك اللي مش هيكون مرئي. لو قطعتك قطعة ملابس، فقلبي الملابس رأساً على عقب. لو كان غرضك قطعة قماش مسطحة، زي بطانية أو مفرش طاولة، فقلبه على الجانب الخطأ. لضمان أن ملابسك وأشياءك التانية تبقي على شكلها الطبيعي وتمتد، فهي فكرة جيدة أن تستخدم شيء منحني كدليل، والمعروف أيضاً باسم فطر الدرنينغ. تقدر تشتري فطر دارنينغ من محلات الحرف اليدوية، أو ببساطة تستخدم حاجه من بيتك. على سبيل المثال، ممكن تستخدم مصباح كهربائي عادي كدليل لتخفيف الجوارب، أو يمكنك استخدام منحنى وعاء كبير كدليل لتخفيف سترة أو بطانية. بالنسبة لبعض المواد، مثل منديلات القماش ومناشف الطاولة، قد يكون استخدام حلقة التطريز خيار أفضل. ادخل الإبرة حوالي 1،3 سم قبل بداية الثقب و خياطة 1،3 سم ورا الثقب. بعدين كرر الخياطة دي بتمشي في الاتجاه المعاكس. احرصي على خياطة 1⁄2  (1.3 سم) بعد حواف الحفرة على كلا الجانبين علشان تتأكد من تغطية الحفرة بشكل كويس. لا تسحب الخيط أو الخيط عشان تشد الغرز. عمل كده هيسبب التجاعيد. الهدف هو استخدام جسمك المنحني أو توتر حلقة التطريز كدليل لضمان أن التجاعيد ستختلط مع بقية القماش. بعد ما تغطي الحفرة كلها مرة واحدة بخيوط بتتجه في اتجاه واحد، لازم تنسج من خلال هذه الخيوط لتشكيل شبكة. ادخل الإبرة تحت الخياطة الأولى على طرف واحد متجه عمودي للخياطة. بعد كده، نسج الخيط أو الخيط فوق الخياطة التالية. استمر لنهاية الخياطة وبعدين ارجع في الاتجاه المعاكس. مش سحب على الغرز المنسوجة كمان. ده هيسبب التجاعيد. استمر في استخدام حلقة الفطر أو التطريز بتاعك كدليل. حاول إنشاء نفس ضيق النسيج مثل الثوب اللي بتنسجه. على سبيل المثال ، لو كنت بتخيط خيط فضفاض ، فستحتاج أن تكون الغرز متباعدة إلى حد ما. لو كنت بتخيط خيط ضيق، فستحتاج الخياطة تكون ضيقة. لما تنتهي من النسيج من خلال الجولة الأولى من الغرز ، يمكنك تأمين الخيط أو الخيط لإنهاء التشويش. احكم الخيط عن طريق ربط عقدة من خلال الغرزة الأخيرة، أو عن طريق نسج الخيط من خلال العنصر بضع مرات تانية. لو قررت تعمل عقدة، احرصي على ما تسحبش الخيط عشان ما تخلصي بتعثر. كمان، احرصي على ربط العقدة بحيث تكون في الداخل أو الجانب الخاطئ من حاجتك. خذي بعين الاعتبار إن العقدة ممكن تكون مش مريحة في الجزء السفلي من جوز الجوارب، فمن الأفضل أن تنسج من خلال بضع مرات إضافية بدلًا من ذلك. ده هيبقى كفاية عشان يبقى الدرنينج في مكانه."},{"question":"Susi pinter sekolahe amarga sinaune ...Terusno ukara ing mdhuwur iki:A. ArangB. SregepC. KesedJawaban:","answer":"Jawaban: B. Sregep"},{"question":"Sheeg magaca Abwaankii allifay Riwaayaddii “Xuud baa laqay jacaylkii\\"?","answer":" Waxaa allifay Maxamuud Cabdulaahi Sangub"},{"question":"Qual time carioca tem um mundial de clubes?","answer":"O time carioca que tem um título de Campeonato Mundial de Clubes da FIFA é o Flamengo. O Flamengo venceu o Mundial em 1981 ao derrotar o Liverpool na final."},{"question":"Ολοκλήρωσε το κείμενο: Κατά τη διάρκεια της Ιουλιανής Επανάστασης","answer":"του 1830, η πλατεία έγινε η σκηνή της αντιπαράθεσης μεταξύ των εξεγερμένων και του στρατού."},{"question":"Yalı Ataköy kaç daire?","answer":"Özyazıcı İnşaat'ın TOKİ arsa ihalesinde satın aldığı Ataköy sahil şeridindeki 72 bin 864 metrekarelik arazisi üzerine kurulan Yalı Ataköy projesi 16 katlı 5 bloktan meydana geliyor. 215 bin metrekare inşaat alanına sahip olan projede 512 konut yer alıyor. Projede konutların yanı sıra 78 ticari ünite de bulunuyor."},{"question":"تاسو لاندې حالت لرئ: \\"زه هڅه کوم چې خپلې کیلي ومومئ. زما په یاد دي چې زه یوازې دوه ساعته دمخه خپلې کوټې ته تللی وم او هغه زما په جیب کې وو.\\"دې پوښتنې ته ځواب ووایه \\"زما کیلي چیرته دي؟\\" د لاندې اشارې په پام کې نیولو سره \\"زه د یوې شیبې لپاره د ملګري لیدو لپاره لاړم\\"","answer":"ما شاید دوی زما د ملګري په اپارتمان کې هیر کړي."},{"question":"كمل الفقرة:وطرح التقرير لكاتبيه -روبرت أرمسترونغ وإيثان وو- العديد من التساؤلات عما إذا كانت هذه المتاعب ستتوقف عند \\"البعض\\" أم لا، وما إذا كانت الشركات ذات التمويل الهش ستتجه نحو الإفلاس أو إعادة الهيكلة؟ أم أننا نتجه نحو أزمة ائتمانية ضخمة إلى الحد الذي قد يتسبب في","answer":"انهيار اقتصادي على نطاق واسع. وقد أشار التقرير أيضًا إلى تأثيرات هذه التحديات على العمال والفئات الاقتصادية الضعيفة، حيث قد يزيد معدل البطالة ويتسارع تدهور الأوضاع المالية للعديد من الأفراد. يبدو أن التوترات الاقتصادية تتسارع، مما يجعل الحاجة إلى استراتيجيات اقتصادية فعّالة وتحفيزية أكثر أهمية من أي وقت مضى."},{"question":"Жылын төө кылуу","answer":"Өтө манчыркап калуу, кокурайып, өөдөсүнүп, башкаларды тоготпой калуу, текеберленүү. Менден кыйын ким бар деп, пейил күтүп калуу. Бул «жылды төө кылуу» жөнүндө мындай уламыш бар. Жан-жаныбарлар чогулуп келе жаткан жылды тосуп чыгышат. Ар кимиси биринчи көрүп, алдыңкылардан болууга тырышат. Ал жаныбарлардын ичинен төө: «Менден бийик ким бар? Мен эле биринчи көрөт эмесминби»,- деп манчыркап, кокурайып мойнун сoзуп келе турган жаңы жыл жакты карап турат. Чычкан да кыбырап жылды тосот. Ал амал кылып, акырын төөнүн жонуна чыгат. Акырын жөрмөлөп отуруп, төөнүн кулагынын учуна барып отурат. Кокурайган аңкоо төө байкабай калат. Бардык жаныбарлар тирмээ карап, жылды эң биринчи көргүсү келет. Төө манчыркап, эрдин шалпайтып карап турат. Келе жаткан жаңы жылды төөнүн кулагынын учунда турган чычкан биринчи көрүп: «Тигине, жаңы жыл келди тигине»,- деп көрсөтөт. Ошентип, манчыркаган төө биринчи көрбөй, чычкан көрүп жар салат. Мына ушундан улам төөчө манчыркап, өөдөсүнгөн адамдан «Жылыңды төө кылба!» деген накыл сөз жасалган имиш."},{"question":"7x7=?","answer":"7x7=49"},{"question":"   வினா கல்லணை அணையில் சர் ஆர்தர் காட்டன் பங்களிப்பு குறித்து விளக்குக.","answer":" விடைஇந்திய நீர் பாசனத்தின் தந்தை என அறியப்படும் சர் ஆர்தர் காட்டன் என்ற ஆங்கில பொறியாளர் கல்லணையை பல ஆண்டுகாலம் ஆராய்ந்தார்.கல்லணை பலகாலம் மணல் மேடாகி நீரோட்டம் தடைப்பட்டது. ஒருங்கிணைந்த தஞ்சை மாவட்டம் தொடர்ச்சியாக வெள்ளத்தாலும், வறட்சியாலும் வளமை குன்றியது. இந்த சூழலில் 1829 இல் காவிரி பாசன பகுதி தனி பொறுப்பாளராக ஆங்கிலேய அரசால் சர் ஆர்தர் காட்டன் நியமிக்கப்பட்டார்.இவர்தான் பயனற்று இருந்த கல்லணையில் தைரியமாக சிறு சிறு பகுதியாய் பிரித்து எடுத்து மணல் போக்கிகளை அமைத்தார். அப்போது, கல்லணைக்கு அமைக்கப்பட்ட அடித்தளத்தை ஆராய்ந்த அவர் பழந்தமிழரின் அணை கட்டும் திறனையும் பாசன மேலாண்மையையும் உலகுக்கு எடுத்துக் கூறினார். கல்லணைக்கு கிரான்ட் அணைகட் என்ற பெயரையும் சூட்டினார்."},{"question":"Hãy hoàn thiện đoạn văn sau: Giao lộ thời gian số 3 với cuộc gặp gỡ giữa nhạc sĩ Đức Huy và Thịnh Suy là cuộc đối thoại giữa hai người đàn ông thuộc hai thế hệ về chuyện tình yêu. Cả hai cho thấy ngôn ngữ của tình yêu ở thời kỳ nào cũng có màu sắc giống nhau - sự dâng hiến và trong sáng. Đức Huy - nhạc sĩ của những bản tình ca - dành cho chàng nghệ sĩ trẻ nhiều lời ngợi khen về tư chất và phong cách âm nhạc. Theo Đức Huy, Thịnh Suy có sự giản dị và chân thành cũng như tươi trẻ trong các sáng tác của mình. Mở đầu chương trình, ê-kíp sản xuất chiêu đãi khán giả bằng ca khúc triệu view \\"Một đêm say\\" của Thịnh Suy, được anh chàng viết khi mới 19 tuổi qua giọng hát của Đức Huy. Đây cũng là lần đầu tiên, nhạc sĩ nổi tiếng hát một ca khúc của tác giả khác. Nếu nhắm mắt lại thưởng thức, người nghe dường như thấy Đức Huy giống như gã trai trẻ đang hát bản tình ca mời gọi cô gái của mình bằng thứ tình cảm nồng say dịu ngọt. Ở tuổi 75, Đức Huy vẫn tràn trề nhựa sống. Ông cho biết bản thân cảm thấy rất hưng phấn khi thể hiện nhạc phẩm này bởi ông dường như được trẻ lại rất nhiều. Khi được mời tham gia cùng Thịnh Suy trong \\"Giao lộ thời gian\\", Đức Huy thú nhận ông nhìn thấy hình bóng tuổi trẻ của mình trong Thịnh Suy. Còn nam ca sĩ trẻ lại cho biết khi được hát và đứng chung sân khấu với thần tượng là một may mắn quá \\"bự\\" với anh. Chàng nghệ sĩ trẻ đã cover hit \\"Yêu em dài lâu\\" của nhạc sĩ Đức Huy, thậm chí kết hợp một đoạn điệp khúc \\"Chuyện rằng\\" của chính anh. Sự kết hợp cho thấy giữa hai thế hệ có một điểm chung về âm nhạc, những ca từ giản dị, không quá trau chuốt nhưng lại thấm đẫm nhân văn và quan điểm thẳng thắn về tình yêu. Trước màn trình diễn của Thịnh Suy, Đức Huy không chỉ hài lòng mà còn ngợi khen sự thật thà, chân chất của chàng trai. Thịnh Suy còn hát tiếp bản hit \\"Đường xa ướt mưa\\" của Đức Huy, liêu trai như chính giọng hát của anh nhưng có sự rộn ràng của tuổi trẻ cùng một bản phối mới của Dương Cầm. Ngay sau phần trình bày thành công hai bản hit của Đức Huy, anh chàng tiết lộ về tên của mình. Anh lý giải Thịnh Suy có nghĩa là sự cân bằng. Trong cuộc đời sẽ có lúc buồn tủi và thất bại nên ngoài tên thật của mình là Thịnh, nhạc sĩ underground gắn chữ Suy vào nghệ danh. Đồng tình với quan điểm của Thịnh Suy, Đức Huy nói: \\"Không có trái thì làm sao có phải, không có bóng tối","answer":"thì đâu có ánh sáng. Với một người trẻ như Thịnh Suy, tôi cảm thấy đáng trân trọng vì lối suy nghĩ sâu sắc như vậy. Với ảnh hưởng không nhỏ, Thịnh Suy góp tiếng nói với những bạn trẻ, không ai có hạnh phúc mãi mãi được. Trong hành trình sống của mình sẽ có những buồn đau. Được - mất trong cuộc đời là giống nhau và phải vui với những điều như thế\\". Cuộc đối thoại của hai nghệ sĩ đã tạo cảm hứng cho host, MC Liêu Hà Trinh. Cô tiếc nuối vì không mang giấy bút để lên ý tưởng viết một cuốn sách với về sự đối lập nhau trong cuộc đời. Bản mashup \\"Và tôi cũng yêu em\\" (Đức Huy) - \\"Tình yêu màu xanh lá\\" (Thịnh Suy) với cái tên \\"Và tôi cũng yêu màu xanh lá\\" được nhạc sĩ Dương Cầm phối khí và dàn dựng càng rút ngắn khoảng cách thế hệ giữa hai khách mời. Nói về bản mashup này, Thịnh Suy cho biết mình và nhạc sĩ Đức Huy có sự gần gũi bởi cái nhìn về một tình yêu trong trẻo, không màu mè. Nghe bản mashup, người nghe sẽ có cảm giác giống như vừa thức dậy đón một buổi sáng trong lành giữa cây lá, chim muông vậy. Ở phần Hit vượt thời gian, Đức Huy thể hiện \\"Một tình yêu\\" và \\"Tình tính tang cây đàn ghita\\" của mình. Với ca khúc thứ hai, Đức Huy tâm sự bài hát được ông ấp ủ viết trong 20 năm và phải mất 5 năm để viết vì biết rằng ca khúc sẽ ở lại bên mình mãi mãi. Thông qua ca khúc, nhạc sĩ muốn truyền tải thông điệp rằng dù đời sống có lúc rớt xuống vực sâu, nếu bản thân sống tích cực hòa điệu với thiên nhiên và bạn bè, đồng nghiệp, sẽ thấy cuộc sống ý nghĩa và còn có cơ hội để sống tốt hơn. Ngoài ra, trong chương trình, ông cũng dành tặng khán giả một ca khúc xúc động viết về mẹ. Bài ru nhớ mẹ ầu ơ ví dầu là tác phẩm viết về mẹ cùng những hình ảnh của tuổi thơ. Ca khúc có sự kết nối giữa âm nhạc miền Bắc và điệu ru miền Nam là thủ pháp nhạc sĩ dùng để tri ân đến những bà mẹ Việt Nam. Tham gia Giao lộ thời gian, Thịnh Suy chờ đợi vào sự tươi mới trong lần xuất hiện này, không chỉ nhẹ nhàng như phong cách vốn có của anh mà còn có thêm sự sôi động khi trong bản phối với âm thanh của trống và một vài nhạc cụ khác. Hai ca khúc được Thịnh Suy trình bày là \\"Tiny Love\\" và \\"Thắc mắc\\" tiếp tục chinh phục người nghe và khiến khán giả như được cuốn vào sự sôi động và trăn trở cùng chàng nghệ sĩ trẻ. Kết thúc Giao lộ thời gian số 3, nhạc sĩ Đức Huy và Thịnh Suy song ca \\"Lemon Tree\\" của Fool's Garden cùng lời nhắn nhủ dành cho khán giả khi đối diện với những điều tồi tệ. Đức Huy nói: \\"Sau Covid -19, người ta rơi vào trầm cảm và sa sút tinh thần, đặc biệt là người trẻ. Thông qua bài hát cùng ý nghĩa của nó, các nghệ sĩ muốn nhắn nhủ với khán giả rằng cuộc sống vẫn đang vận hành bình thường, có lúc này, lúc kia. Nếu đắm chìm trong nỗi buồn, tự nhốt mình trong bế tắc sẽ không thấy vui. Tốt nhất là ra đường, ngắm nhìn cuộc sống, trò chuyện với người này, người kia để thấy ồ cuộc đời vẫn ổn đấy chứ\\". Dù không phải sáng tác của hai nghệ sĩ, ca khúc \\"Lemon Tree\\" đã thể hiện trọn vẹn nhiệm vụ kết thúc show diễn với tinh thần lạc quan như chính âm nhạc và con người của Đức Huy và Thịnh Suy. Và qua đó, ê-kíp sản xuất muốn gửi gắm lời nhắn âm nhạc có thể chữa lành nhiều vết thương, giúp người ta yêu đời và nhìn về tương lai tốt đẹp./."},{"question":"ගොඩබිම වේගයෙන්ම දිවිය හැකි සත්වයා කවුරුන්ද?","answer":"චීටා"},{"question":"لدي مقال طويل، هلي يمكنك تلخيصه؟ يمكن أن يؤدي تثبيت الكثير من التطبيقات على جهاز آي باد مع مرور الوقت إلى استهلاك الكثير من المساحة التخزينية المحدودة لجهاز آي باد. الألعاب أحد أكثر العناصر استهلاكًا للمساحة التخزينية حيث تستهلك الكثير من الألعاب في عصرنا الحالي مساحة تتجاوز 1 جيجابايت ويؤدي حذف هذه الألعاب والتطبيقات الأخرى التي لم تعد تستخدمها إلى تحرير مساحة تخزينية أكثر مما تتخيل.  يمكنك بالطبع حذف التطبيقات من الشاشة الرئيسية لجهازك، ولكننا سنعرض عليك طريقة فرز التطبيقات المثبتة وفق حجمها والاطلاع على المساحة التي يستهلكها كل تطبيق. لا تقلق بشأن فقد حق الوصول إلى التطبيقات التي تحذفها من جهازك حيث يتم تخزين كل تنزيلاتك مع معرّف أبل لتتمكن من إعادة تثبيت أي تطبيق، سواءً أكان مجانيًا أو مدفوعًا، في أي وقت من خلال متجر التطبيقات. يمكنك استخدام برنامج آي تيونز لنسخ كل المستندات والبيانات المصاحبة لأي تطبيق ترغب  بحذفه من جهاز آي باد، علمًا بأن تفعيل خاصية حفظ نسخ آي كلاود الاحتياطية إلى حفظ نسخة احتياطية من بياناتك على حساب آي كلاود تلقائيًا.   يمكن أن تستغرق عملية التحميل بضع لحظات. سيؤدي ذلك إلى إظهار المساحة التخزينية التي تستهلكها البيانات المرافقة للتطبيق. انقر بعد ذلك على خيار \\"حذف التطبيق\\" مجددًا لتأكيد رغبتك بحذف التطبيق وكل المستندات والبيانات المرافقة له. يمكنك تحرير مساحة تخزينية كبيرة عن طريق حذف التطبيقات غير المستخدمة بشكل منتظم..","answer":"نعم بالتأكيد. هذا تلخيص للمقال السابق:- افهم سبب احتياجك لحذف التطبيقات القديمة.- افتح تطبيق الإعدادات ثم انقر على خيار الإعدادات العامة.- انقر على خيار \\"الاستخدام\\" ثم انقر على خيار \\"إدارة الذاكرة التخزينية\\" في قسم \\"الذاكرة التخزينية\\".- انتظر لحين تحميل قائمة التطبيقات.- انقر على تطبيق لم تعد تستخدمه.- انقر على خيار حذف التطبيق.- كرّر العملية مع كل التطبيقات غير المستخدمة."},{"question":"Odpowiedz na pytanie: W którym roku zakończyła się II wojna światowa?","answer":"Odpowiedź: rok 1945 oznaczał koniec II wojny światowej i upadek nazistowskich Niemiec i Cesarstwa Japonii."},{"question":"Burburkii dimoqraadiyada somaaliya9- FARAGELINTII DIINTA IYO DILKII CULIMADA","answer":"Burburkii dimoqraadiyada somaaliya9- FARAGELINTII DIINTA IYO DILKII CULIMADADadka soomalida waxey ahaayen dad diinta islaamka ku soo gaartey si aan dhib badan loo gala kulmin,culimo diinta fidisa ayaa soo gaarey dhulka soomalidu degto waxeyna la kulmeen soo dhaweyn iyo gacmo furan waxaana u suura gashey iney baraan diinta islaamka, marba kooxo culimo ah oo ka yimi dhinaca carabta ayaa soo gaari jirey somaliya, waxeyna tegi jireen magaalooyinka iyo tuulooyinka waxaana wax ka bartey dad Somali ah oo iyagiina bilaabey iney u faaideyaan walaalohoodakale waxaana la gaarey in dhulka soomalida oo dhan la gaarsiiyo, culimada soomalidana magaalo kasta oo ay tagto waa laga soo dhoweyn jirey, xoolona waa la siin jirey,  meel ay caruurta quraanka ku baraana waa loo oodi jirey, macalinkaas wuxuu noqon jirey shaqsiga ugu qiimo badan oo la sharfo,  degaankaas dadka waaweyn wey ka faaiideysan jireen xaga su,aalaha diinta iyo waxbarashada diintaislaamka. Diinta islaamku soomaaliya waxay ka noqotey diinta keliya ee dadku qaataan kuna niyad furnaayeen, waagaas wax dowladihi ma jirin dadku iyagaa diintooda ilaashan jirey, markii meel cusub la dego waxey dadku marka hore ka bilaabi jireen dugsi quraan iyo mowlac lagu tukudo salaada,dadkuna wax bixinta ma aheyn amar qof waliba isagaa jeclaa in aan looga hormarin wax bixin hadii uu heysto. Markii mudo la ahaa waxaa biloowdey halganki gobanimadoonka culimada soomaliyeed qeyb weyn ayey ka qaateen waayo iyagaa ahaa isku xirka dadka iyo aqoonta waayo wey socon jireen isgaarsiin iyagaa ahaa, ilaa xoriyada la qaatey dadku sidaa ayey ku socdeen, markii la qaatey xoriyada dowladiina dhalatey arintii sidii ayey ku wadeen culimadu waxeyna ahayeen kuwo sidii loo ixtiraamo, qof kastoo sommali ahi caruurtiisa markuu gaaro 5 sano wuxuu geyn jirey dugsi quraanka laga barto. "},{"question":"Maxaa ka mid ah caynabinta heerarka bulshada Soomaalida?","answer":"Caynabinta heerarka bulshada Soomaalida waxay ku jiraan heerarka qiiro, wadaadnimo, isku dhafan, iyo horumarka dhaqanka bulshada."},{"question":"من اسماء الله السميع فما معنى هذا الاسم؟","answer":"السميع هو من أسماء الله الحسنى ،ومعناه :سمعه لجميع الأصوات الظاهرة والباطنة الخفية والجلية، وإحاطته التامة بها، ومعناه أيضًا: سمع الإجابة منه للسائلين والداعين والعابدين فيجيبهم ويثيبهم، ومنه قوله:  الْحَمْدُ لِلَّهِ الَّذِي وَهَبَ لِي عَلَى الْكِبَرِ إِسْمَاعِيلَ وَإِسْحَاقَ إِنَّ رَبِّي لَسَمِيعُ الدُّعَاءِ   سورة إبراهيم:39 وقول المصلي سَمِعَ اللهُ لِمَن حمِده أي استجاب. ورد اسم الله السميع في القرآن الكريم خمسًا وأربعين مرة، اقترن في أكثر من ثلاثين منها بالعليم ،كما اقترن في عشرة مواضع بالبصير، وجاء مقترناً بالقريب مرة واحدة."},{"question":"Jasmin Savoy Brown","answer":"Jasmin Savoy Brown jẹ́ òṣèrébìnrin ọmọ orilẹ-èdè Amẹ́ríkà. Ó ṣeré nínú fíìmù HBO tí àpèlé rẹ̀ jẹ́ The Leftovers (2015–2017), eré ABC tí àpèlé rẹ̀ jẹ́ For the People (2018–2019), àti eré Showtime tí àpèlé rẹ̀ jẹ́ Yellowjackets (2021–present). Ó tún ṣeré nínú àwọn fíìmù bi Sound of Violence (2021), Scream (2022) àti Scream VI (2023).Wọ́n bí Brown sí ìlú Alameda, California, wọ́n sì to dàgbà ní ìlú Springfield, Oregon. Nígbà tí ó jẹ́ ọmọ ọdún merin, Brown kópa nínú orin kan ní ilé ìjọsìn tí ó ń lọ, èyí sì mú kí ó ní ìfẹ́ sí eré ṣíṣe. Bí ó ti ń dàgbà, ó kópa nínú ọ̀pọ̀lọpọ̀ orin àti eré. Lẹ́yìn ìgbà tí ó parí ìwé mẹ́fà, ó kó lọ sí Portland, Oregon láti lépa àlá rẹ̀ nínú eré ṣíṣe."},{"question":"Su’aal: Sheeg Magaalada Ugu Qadiimsan Caalamka?","answer":"Jawaab: Magaalada Caalamka Ugu Qadiimsan Waa Magadala Arriixa Waxay-Na Ku Taalaa Dalka Falastiin."},{"question":"కింద ఇచ్చిన వాక్యాన్ని వ్యతిరేకార్థక వాక్యంగా రాయండివర్తకులు ఓడలలో ప్రయాణమౌతారు.","answer":"వర్తకులు ఓడలలో ప్రయాణము కారు."},{"question":"Beqil ma mbind mii:Waaye ñi gëm te def jëf yu sell [Farataak Sunna] ñooña ñoo di ñay dugg Àjjana, dañu fay béel.","answer":"Mbind mi jub a ngi nii:Waaye ñi gëm te def jëf yu sell [Farataa'k Sunna] ñooña ñoo di ña'y dugg Àjjana, da ñu fa'y béel."},{"question":"次のタイトルに基づいて、このトピックに関する記事を書きなさい： 日本の文化「人形浄瑠璃文楽」を習う若い人がいない","answer":"「人形浄瑠璃文楽」は人形を使った劇で、三味線の音楽と一緒に話を伝えます。江戸時代に大阪で始まりました。ユネスコの無形文化遺産になっています。劇を行う人の多くは、大阪にある国立文楽劇場で2年研修を受けて、人形の動かし方や三味線などを習います。研修を受けることができる人は23歳以下の男性で、毎年4月に研修が始まります。しかし、今年は研修を受ける人が1人もいません。研修が始まってからの50年で初めてです。研修の申し込みは毎年2月までですが、今年は研修を受けたい人を今も集めています。国立文楽劇場の人は「1人もいなくてとても残念です。若い人に『人形浄瑠璃文楽』をもっと知ってほしいです」と話しました。"},{"question":"ഇനിപ്പറയുന്നവരിൽ ആരാണ് യുഎസ് പ്രസിഡന്റുമാർ, ഹോളിവുഡ് അഭിനേതാക്കൾ: ജിമ്മി കാർട്ടർ, ജോർജ്ജ് വാഷിംഗ്ടൺ, ഡെൻസൽ വാഷിംഗ്ടൺ, ഡാനിയൽ ഡേ ലൂയിസ്, എബ്രഹാം ലിങ്കൺ, റൊണാൾഡ് റീഗൻ.","answer":"പ്രസിഡന്റുമാർ: ജോർജ്ജ് വാഷിംഗ്ടൺ, ജിമ്മി കാർട്ടർ, എബ്രഹാം ലിങ്കൺ, റൊണാൾഡ് റീഗൻ. ഹോളിവുഡ് അഭിനേതാക്കൾ: ഡാനിയൽ ഡേ ലൂയിസ്, ഡെൻസൽ വാഷിംഗ്ടൺ, പ്രസിഡന്റാകുന്നതിന് മുമ്പ് ഒരു നടനായിരുന്ന റൊണാൾഡ് റീഗൻ."},{"question":"Berikan penerangan ringkas tentang Demam Zika dalam ayat-ayat yang tidak melebihi 220 patah perkataan. ","answer":"Demam Zika, juga dikenali sebagai penyakit virus Zika, merupakan penyakit yang disebabkan oleh virus Zika. Simptomnya serupa dengan demam denggi. Kebanyakan daripada kes demam ini (60–80%) tidak menunjukkan simptom. Apabila ada simptom, ia biasanya termasuk demam, mata merah, sakit sendi, sakit kepala, dan ruam makulopapular. Secara amnya, simptom adalah tidak teruk dan berlanjutan selama kurang daripada tujuh hari. Setakat tahun 2015, kematian tidak berlaku semasa jangkitan awal. Jangkitan sudah dikaitkan dengan sindrom Guillain-Barré.Demam Zika umumnya merebak melalui gigitan nyamuk jenis Aedes. Ia juga mungkin boleh merebak melalui hubungan seks dan pemindahan darah. Penyakit ini boleh tersebar melalui ibu-ke-anak di dalam rahim dan menyebabkan mikrosefali. Diagnosis dilakukan dengan menguji darah, air kencing, atau air liur untuk RNA virus apabila seseorang itu sakit.Pencegahan penyakit ini melibatkan pengurangan gigitan nyamuk di kawasan yang penyakit ini tercetus. Usaha pencegahan termasuk penggunaan penghalau serangga, menutup sebahagian besar badan dengan pakaian, kelambu, dan memastikan tiada air bertakung kerana ia menjadi tempat pembiakan nyamuk. Tiada vaksin yang berkesan. Pegawai kesihatan Brazil mengesyorkan pada tahun 2015 supaya ibu bapa menangguhkan kehamilan disebabkan wabak ini dan adalah disarankan kepada wanita yang hamil tidak berkunjung ke kawasan tempat wabak ini sedang menular. Walaupun tiada rawatan yang khusus, paracetamol (acetaminophen) dapat membantu melegakan simptom. Kemasukan ke hospital sangat jarang diperlukan."},{"question":"Бир эсептен - бул туруктуу сөз айкашынын мааниси кандай?","answer":"Бир эсептен - бул туруктуу сөз айкашынын мааниси: бул жагынан, мындайча алганда. Мисалы: Бир эсептен бул да туура, антпесе эл өз билгенин кылбайбы."},{"question":"Awooda daawada wax manooga sheegi kartaa .","answer":"Awoodda waxtarka daawooyinka markii la is barbardhigayo kuma xirno cabbirka ku dul qoran ama inta milligram ay tahay, waxaa laga yaabaa daawo 1mg ah inay ka awood badan tahay daawo 100mg ah. Arintaani ma ahan mid badanaa bulshadu fahansan tahay.#Tusaale: Qof qaata daawo dhiig-kar oo 100 mg ah haddii ay u shaqeyn wayso, kadibne dhakhtarka ugu badalo daawo dhiig-kar kale oo 5 mg, waxaa laga yaabaa in bukaankaasi aamino inaysan daawada wax u tari doonin ama uusanba qaadan maadaama ay ka cabbir yar tahay tii hore.Sidoo kale qof cudurka macaanka ku cusub yahay haddii loo qoro daawo 500mg, waxaa laga yabaa inuu dhaho, dhakhtar ii qor mid cabbir yar oo 5 ama 10 ah, maadaama cudurka igu cusub yahay.Waxyaabahaasi waxaa looga hortagi karaa in bukaanka la wacyi galiyo, lana fahansiiyo awoodda waxtareed ee daawada, afka qalaadne lagu dhaho \\"Drug Potency\\". Mahadsanidiin. "},{"question":"Предложение 1: Для Huffington Post Highline, Роберт и Ребекка Мерсер позже написали о влиянии Вики на выборы 2016 года. Чарли Роуз недавно взял у нее интервью на эту статью. Второе предложение: В Huffington Post Highline Вики недавно написала о влиянии Роберта и Ребекки Мерсер на выборы 2016 года. Позже Чарли Роуз взял у нее интервью на эту статью. Вопрос: Есть ли в предложении 1 и 2 одно и то же значение? - Да или нет?","answer":"Нет."},{"question":"මිනිස් සිරුරේ ඇති කුඩාම අස්ථිය කුමක්ද?","answer":"මිනිස් සිරුරේ ඇති කුඩාම සහ සැහැල්ලුම අස්ථිය වනුයේ මැද කණේ ඇති ‘ධරණකය’ අස්ථිය වේ. ධරණකය යනු මිනිසාගේ සහ අනෙකුත් ක්ෂීරපායී සත්වයින්ගේ කණේ පිහිටි, ඇතුල් කණට ශබ්දය සන්නයනය කරන්නා වූ අස්ථියයි. උඩහලු හැඩැති මෙම අස්ථිය මැද කණේ පිහිටි කුඩා  අස්ථි 3නෙන් 1කි. ධරණකය කම්පන ලබා ගන්නේ ආංශික වශයෙන් සම්බන්ධ වූ නිඝාතියෙනි. පසුව කම්පන අණ්ඩාකාර කවුලුව තෙක් සම්ප්‍රේශනය කරනු ලබයි. එය නිඝාතියට සමාන්තර වශයෙන් පිහිටයි."},{"question":"Jawab soalan rumit ini: Rumah menara apakah yang berhampiran Aberchirder, Aberdeenshire yang diwarisi oleh David Gregory?","answer":"Kastil Kinnairdy"},{"question":"Unsa ang resulta kung ipuno ans 2 sa 7?","answer":"Ang resulta kay 9. "},{"question":"Tuliskan satu karangan keperihalan tentang sambutan Hari Kanak-Kanak. ","answer":"Pada hari Ahad yang lalu, sekolah saya telah mengadakan sambutan Hari Kanak-kanak di sekolah. Tujuan sambutan ini diadakan adalah untuk meraikan kanak-kanak yang bakal menjadi  pemimpin pada suatu hari nanti.            Pada awal pagi, murid-murid dan guru-guru berkumpul di dewan sekolah dengan perasaan yang gembira. Kami menyanyikan lagu Bangsa Johor, Negaraku dan lagu sekolah dengan penuh semangat. Selepas itu, kami mendengar ucapan yang disampaikan oleh guru besar. Dalam ucapannya, beliau menasihati kami agar belajar dengan bersungguh-sungguhnya supaya mendapat keputusan yang cemerlang dalam peperiksaan.          Murid-murid membuat persembahan yang menarik di atas pentas. Antaranya ialah yoyo Cina, tarian, nyanyian, silap mata dan lain-lain lagi. Para penonton bersorak-sorai sambil bertepuk tangan dengan gemuruhnya kerana persembahan-persembahan itu sungguh hebat dan menarik. Selepas itu, majlis penyampaian hadiah diadakan bagi tokoh murid. Setiap murid juga menerima hadiah Hari Kanak-kanak daripada pihak sekolah.           Pada pukul 10.30 pagi, kami pun masuk ke kelas masing-masing. Setiap kelas mengadakan jamuan. Murid-murid membawa pelbagai jenis makanan dan minuman dari rumah masing-masing. Guru-guru datang ke kelas untuk menikmati makanan dan minuman yang sedap. Kami juga makan aiskrim yang sedap untuk menghilangkan dahaga kerana cuaca sungguh panas.           Selepas itu, kami bermain pelbagai jenis permainan bersama guru-guru dengan seronoknya di dalam kelas untuk menghiburkan hati kami. Cikgu Goh juga mengambil gambar kami dengan menggunakan telefon pintarnya yang canggih untuk dijadikan kenangan yang manis. Kami juga berbual-bual bersama guru-guru dengan mesranya untuk mengeratkan hubungan antara satu sama lain.         Pada pukul 12.50 tengah hari, semua murid pun pulang ke rumah masing-masing. Saya berasa gembira kerana dapat menyambut Hari Kanak-kanak di sekolah. Saya berharap agar Hari Kanak-kanak ini akan diadakan lagi pada tahun hadapan."},{"question":"Àrún èrànkòrónà ọdún 2019","answer":"Àrùn èrànkòrónà ọdún 2019 (tàbí ní èdè gẹ̀ẹ́sì bíi Coronavirus disease 2019, COVID-19) jẹ́ àrún àkóràn kan tí èràn àrọ́lù àìsàn ìmín olóró gbígboró, èràn kòrónà irú 2 (SARS-CoV-2) ń mú wá. Àrùn náà kọ́kọ́ jẹ́ dídámọ̀ ní December 2019 ní Wuhan, ní China, tó sì ti ràn ká gbogbo àgbáyé láti ìgbà náà pẹ̀lú ajakale-arun kaakiriaye erankorona odun 2019-2020. Nínú àwọn ami-aisan rẹ̀ tó wọ́pọ̀ ni iba, ikọ́, àti àìlèmín balẹ̀. Àwọn àmì àìsàn míràn tún lè jẹ́ irora, híha kelebe, igbe olomi, ikanra ona-ofun, ainlegbo oorun, ati irora ikun. Botileje pe opo alaisan arun yi ni ami-aisan to loworo, awon miran le ni eran edo ati ikuna patapata opolopo ifun-ara. Titi di ojo 3 April 2020, iye awon alaisan COVID-19 ti a mo lagbaye je 1,040,000, iye awon alaisi je 55,100 deaths.Iye awon ti ara won ti ya je 221,000."},{"question":"Aşure kolesterolü yükseltir mi?","answer":"Kalp-damar sağlığını korurAşureye konan tüm besinler bitkisel kaynaklı olduğu için doymuş yağ oranı çok düşüktür ve kolesterol içermez."},{"question":"A: ර යන්න, ර රා රැ රෑ ආදි වශයෙන්  ස්වර ගැන්වීමේ දී යෙදෙන රෘ රෲ අක්ෂර දෙකෙහි ආවශ්‍යකතාව පිළිබඳ අදහසක් දක්වන්න.B: රෘ රෲ යනුවෙන් යෙදීම අවශ්‍ය වන වචන නැත.ලෟ ලෳ භාවිතයක් ද නැත.සමහර ව්‍යංජන සෑම ස්වරයක් සමඟ ම සංයෝග නොවේ. ඞ ව්‍යංජනය කිසි ම ස්වරයක් සමඟ උච්චාරණය නොවේ.A: බලන්ගොඩ ආනන්ද මෛත්‍රෙය මහනාහිමයන්ගේ සරල සංස්කෘත ශික්ෂකය පොතේ රෘ රෲ නැත. නමුත් ලෘ ලෲ දක්වා ඇත.","answer":"B: සංස්කෘතයේ ලෘ සහ ලෲ ඇති. මා කීවේ ලෘ නොව ලෟ ගැන ය."},{"question":"මාර්ගස්ථ මගී ප්‍රවාහන අධිකාරිය මෙහි \\"මාර්ගස්ථ\\"වචනය අනවශ්‍යයි නේද?","answer":"මෙහි වරදක් නෑ. මොකද මෙම අධ්කාරිය කටයුතු කරන්නේ මහා මාර්ගවල ධාවනය වන බස් රථ සේවා සඳහා  පමණක් වීම නිසා."},{"question":" Аксолотль деген эмне ?","answer":" Аксолотль (зоол.) — аксолотль; куйруктуу амфибия — амбистоманын  личинкасы.  "},{"question":"Đọc đoạn văn sau và đưa ra một tiêu đề phụ hợp với nội dung: Chương trình Bạn muốn hẹn hò tập 816 vừa lên sóng cùng Quyền Linh và Ngọc Lan mai mối cho Trương Quang Mau (43 tuổi), đang làm cho một công ty xây dựng ở quận 7 và Phùng Thị Thu (40 tuổi), hiện buôn bán tự do ở Thủ Đức. Theo chia sẻ, đàng trai từng trải qua một cuộc hôn nhân hơn 18 năm, đã có con 6 tuổi. Anh tâm sự sau khi mình lên TP.HCM làm ăn thì vợ chồng trục trặc dẫn đến ly hôn. Điều đó khiến Quang Mau buồn bã suốt 3 năm liền. Thậm chí có khoảng thời gian anh không ăn uống gì được, chỉ hút thuốc. Khi kể câu chuyện của mình tại chương trình, người đàn ông vẫn còn ngậm ngùi. Trước hoàn cảnh của Quang Mau, hai MC liên tục gửi lời an ủi, động viên anh phải vui vẻ, phấn chấn để bắt đầu một cuộc sống mới. \\"Hy vọng người phụ nữ mới sẽ giúp anh lấy lại giấc ngủ, giúp cho anh bớt buồn, bớt hút thuốc lại nha\\", Ngọc Lan nhắn nhủ. Về phía Phùng Thị Thu, cô một mình bươn chải nuôi 2 con suốt 11 năm qua sau khi chồng qua đời. Cô chia sẻ: \\"Khi ấy tôi mới 29 tuổi. Mình có hai thằng con trai nên cũng cố ở vậy nuôi các con trưởng thành. Nay đứa lớn 19 tuổi, đứa nhỏ được 16 tuổi rồi\\". Khi được hỏi về hình mẫu, người phụ nữ tâm sự mình chỉ cần một người có thể đồng cảm, biết san sẻ công việc và chăm lo cho các con. Điều quan trọng nhất cô cần là người đó yêu thương mình thật lòng. \\"Tôi không thích đàn ông cờ bạc, hút thuốc\\", cô nói. Trước chia sẻ này, Quyền Linh lo lắng cho đàng trai: \\"Chết rồi, bên kia ngày một gói thuốc. Biết làm sao giờ\\". Sau những thông tin ban đầu, Quyền Linh và Ngọc Lan mở rào cho cặp đôi được trực tiếp gặp mặt nhau. Trong cuộc trò chuyện, khi Quang Mau bày tỏ mong muốn đàng gái về quê mình sống nếu tiến xa hơn, Phùng Thị Thu thẳng thắn: \\"Em không quan trọng người quê ở đâu nhưng người đó phải định hướng sinh sống và làm việc ở TP.HCM. Em không thể về quê theo anh được, còn anh theo em được thì tốt\\". Tiếp đó, cả hai cũng chia sẻ với nhau về định hướng tương lai, cuộc sống nếu về chung một nhà. Họ còn trao nhau những câu hát tình cảm trước khi đến với quyết định. Tuy nhiên, sau quá trình hẹn hò và tìm hiểu, chỉ có Quang Mau bấm nút hẹn hò, còn Phùng Thị Thu từ chối đối phương. Trước tình huống này, Quyền Linh chia sẻ anh rất tiếc dù từ đầu đã biết đàng gái sẽ quyết định như vậy. \\"Nhưng trong lòng Linh vẫn ước, vẫn mong rằng nó sẽ khác. Nhưng cuối cùng nó vẫn diễn ra đúng như những gì mình suy nghĩ. Sẽ có người bấm nút cho chị, cũng sẽ có người bấm nút cho anh ấy. Đừng lo nhé, nửa mảnh ghép còn lại sẽ có ở đâu đó trong cuộc sống này. Đến lúc nào đó, nó sẽ ghép đúng vào chúng ta\\", nam MC nhắn nhủ.","answer":"\\"Tìm Kiếm Tình Yêu: Cuộc Hẹn Hò Đầy Cảm Xúc\\""},{"question":"Aphrodite weMelos ane zita rakakurumbira - chii?","answer":"Aphrodite weMelos, chivezwa chekare chechiGiriki chinozivikanwawo seVenus de Milo, chivezwa chine mukurumbira chinoratidza mwarikadzi Aphrodite (kana kuti Venus mungano dzechiRoma). Ichi chifananidzo chemarble nderimwe remabasa anonyanya kufarirwa uye anozivikanwa ehunyanzvi hwekare. Chinofungidzirwa kuti chakasikwa pakati pa130 ne100 BCE uye chakawanikwa pachitsuwa cheMelos kuGreece muna 1820. Chifananidzo ichi chinopembererwa nokuda kworunako rwacho runoyevedza uye chinomiririra mwarikadzi worudo norunako."},{"question":"19 වන ශතවර්ෂයේදී, බහුජාතික සමාගම්වල සංවර්ධනය සඳහා පතල් කැණීම ඉටු කළ වැදගත් කාර්යභාරය කුමක්ද?","answer":"රන්, රිදී, තඹ සහ තෙල් කැණීම 19 වැනි සියවසේ ප්‍රධාන කටයුත්තක් විය. රියෝ ටින්ටෝ සමාගම වැනි ජාත්‍යන්තර පතල් සමාගම් ප්‍රමුඛ විය. බ්‍රිතාන්‍ය දකුණු අප්‍රිකානු සමාගම සහ ඩි බියර්ස් වැනි ව්‍යවසායන් සමඟ සිසිල් රෝඩ්ස් ගෝලීය දියමන්ති වෙළඳපොළ පාලනය කිරීමේ කාර්යභාරයක් ඉටු කළේය."},{"question":"xbox ကို ဘယ်သူ တီထွင်ခဲ့တာလဲ။","answer":"Xbox ကို developer နှင့် engineers အဖွဲ့တစ်ဖွဲ့မှ တီထွင်ခဲ့ပြီး Kevin Bachus၊ Ted Hase နှင့် Otto Berkes တို့ပါဝင်သည်။ သူတို့အဖွဲ့၏ခေါင်းဆောင်မှာ ထိုအချိန်က Microsoft မှ အမေရိကန်အင်ဂျင်နီယာနှင့် ဗီဒီယိုဂိမ်းဒီဇိုင်နာ Seamus Blackley ဖြစ်သည်။"},{"question":"I've always wondered: ఆర్మూర్ పట్టణ వైశాల్యం ఎంత? about ఆర్మూరు.Snippet: ఆర్మూరు పురపాలక సంఘము 2006 లో స్థాపించబడింది. దీనిని మూడవ గ్రేడ్గా విభజించారు. ఈ పట్టణంలో మొత్తం 23 వార్డులు ఉన్నాయి. దీని అధికార పరిధి 26.07km2 (10.07sqmi).[3]","answer":"26.07km"},{"question":"一间牢房中关着两个犯人,其中一个因偷窃要关一年,另一个是抢劫杀人犯,却只关两个月,为什么","answer":"答案：再过两个月杀人犯就要被枪决了"},{"question":"Hãy đặt một tiêu đề phù hợp với đoạn văn sau: Viện KSND TP Hà Nội vừa hoàn tất cáo trạng truy tố bị can Đoàn Phương Anh (SN 1988, ở Khu đô thị Time City, phường Mai Động, quận Hoàng Mai, Hà Nội) về tội cưỡng đoạt tài sản, theo quy định tại Điều 170 BLHS. Theo cáo trạng, Phương Anh có chồng và hai con, nhưng đã ly hôn. Tháng 10/2017, Phương Anh quen biết anh P.N.A (SN 1985) là Tổng Giám đốc một công ty kinh doanh trong lĩnh vực xây dựng, bất động sản và có quan hệ tình cảm. Đầu năm 2018, anh P.N.A ly hôn vợ và thuê nhà sống chung như vợ chồng với Phương Anh tại khu đô thị Time City. Trong thời gian chung sống với nhau, mối quan hệ giữa anh P.N.A và Phương Anh bắt đầu rạn nứt khi Phương Anh hay ghen tuông vô cớ. Về phía anh P.N.A cũng có những lời lẽ xúc phạm và đánh Phương Anh.  Sau nhiều ngày thường xuyên xảy ra mâu thuẫn, ngày 13/2/2021, anh P.N.A muốn chấm dứt mối quan hệ tình cảm với Phương Anh nên chuyển đến sống một mình tại chung cư khác. Vì không muốn chia tay người tình nên Phương Anh đã nhờ nhiều người can thiệp để anh P.N.A quay lại, nhưng anh này một mực từ chối. Bức xúc với người tình, Phương Anh đã buộc anh P.N.A phải bồi thường cho chị ta những tổn thất về thể chất và tinh thần thì mới đồng ý chấm dứt quan hệ tình cảm. Ngày 19/2/2021, anh P.N.A và Phương Anh thống nhất lập biên bản thỏa thuận chia tay với nội dung, khi nào có điều kiện anh P.N.A sẽ mua cho Phương Anh một căn hộ tại khu đô thị Times City, trị giá khoảng 5 tỷ đồng, mở một cửa hàng thời trang trị giá khoảng 1 tỷ đồng, và lập sổ tiết kiệm cho Phương Anh với số tiền 2 tỷ đồng. Ở chiều ngược lại, Phương Anh không được làm phiền anh P.N.A và quan hệ tình ái trước đây chấm dứt. Do dịch bệnh COVID-19, anh P.N.A không làm việc để có tiền đưa cho Phương Anh nên chưa thực hiện đúng thỏa thuận. Từ tháng 5/2021 đến ngày 2/11/2021, Phương Anh liên tục gọi điện thoại từ số máy của chị ta đến điện thoại của anh P.N.A, đồng thời sử dụng các thông tin, hình ảnh về đời tư không lành mạnh của Phương Anh với anh P.N.A gửi cho nhiều người là bạn bè, đồng nghiệp và đối tác làm ăn của anh P.N.A nhằm uy hiếp, tạo áp lực buộc anh P.N.A sợ ảnh hưởng mà phải đến gặp, trả cho Phương Anh tổng số tiền hơn 13,5 tỷ đồng. Trước những hình ảnh nhạy cảm mà Phương Anh gửi, anh P.N.A lo sợ ảnh hưởng đến uy tín, danh dự và công việc làm ăn nên đã phải gặp Phương Anh để thỏa thuận về việc bảo mật thông tin đời tư của mình. Ngày 22/10/2021, anh P.N.A đã chuyển cho Phương Anh số tiền 250 triệu đồng.   Ngày 2/11/2021, khi Phương Anh tiếp tục nhận số tiền 400 triệu đồng từ anh P.N.A tại một ngân hàng ở đường Điện Biên Phủ (phường Cửa Nam, quận Ba Đình, Hà Nội) thì bị cơ quan Công an phát hiện và bắt giữ. Quá trình điều tra, ngày 11/5/2022, gia đình của Phương Anh đã trực tiếp trả cho anh P.N.A số tiền 250 triệu đồng. Ngày 16/6/2022, anh P.N.A đã nhận lại số tiền hơn 400 triệu đồng. Tổng số tiền anh P.N.A đã nhận lại là hơn 650 triệu đồng. Đến nay, anh P.N.A không yêu cầu Phương Anh phải bồi thường về dân sự và đề nghị cơ quan tố tụng xem xét giảm nhẹ hình phạt cho Phương Anh trong quá trình xét xử.  Quá trình điều tra, Phương Anh đã khai nhận hành vi phạm tội của mình như cáo trạng đã xác định. Nguồn: https://cand.com.vn/Ban-tin-113/dung-anh-nong-tong-tien-nguoi-tinh-hon-13-5-ty-dong-i662351/Nguồn: https://cand.com.vn/Ban-tin-113/dung-anh-nong-tong-tien-nguoi-tinh-hon-13-5-ty-dong-i662351/ ","answer":"Dùng ảnh \\"nóng\\" tống tiền người tình hơn 13,5 tỷ đồng"},{"question":"\\"વિકાસનો સફર\\" નામ ની બાળવાર્તા .","answer":"\\"વિકાસનો સફર\\" અહેવાલ એક છોકરો હતો જે ગામના એક છોકરાના પરિવારમાં જન્મેલો હતો. તેમના પિતાએ પ્રતિષ્ઠાનો મોટો મૂદો રાખ્યો હતો અને તેમનો સમાજમાં ગૌરવ છેડતા રહ્યાં.અહેવાલનો દિલ વિજયભરવાનો ઇચ્છુક રહ્યો. પરંતુ, તેમના ગામના કેટલાક લોકો તેની અસફળતાને ચીંઘડાવવાનો પ્રયાસ કરી રહ્યાં. બધી બધી પરીક્ષાઓમાં અહેવાલ સફળ રહ્યો હતો, પરંતુ તેમના દિલમાં એક અનામોલ ખોટું છેડી રહ્યું.એકદિવસ, એક ગુરુકુલમાં અહેવાલને એક મુખ્ય પ્રાધિકૃત સાથે મળી. પ્રાધિકૃતે તેમને તેના દિલના ખોટામાં પરિચિત કરવાનો સમય લેવાનો નિર્ણય કર્યો. તેમને સહેજે કહ્યું, \\"તારી યોજનાઓ શક્તિશાળી છે, પરંતુ તારા દિલની સાથે સાથે વર્તન પણ કરવું જોઈએ.\\"પરંતુ, અહેવાલનો દિલ જોઈએ એવું નથી. તેમનો અહંકાર અને ઈર્ષ્યાને તેમને અવગણવાનો સમય આવ્યો. પરંતુ, પછીથી તેમનો દિલ બદલવાનો શરૂ થયો. તેમને અવગણવાનો અને સહેનોનો સમય મળ્યો. પ્રતિષ્ઠાની મોટાઈ છોડવાનો પ્રયાસ કરી રહ્યો અને તેમને સફળતા મળી."},{"question":"18 ay asgari borçlanma kaç para?","answer":"540 gün (18 ay) askerlik borçlanması bedeli 2023 yılı için en az 57 bin 6462,08 TL olacak. Doğum borçlanması; 1 çocuk için 720 gün (2 yıl) doğum borçlanması bedeli 2023 yılı için en az 76 bin 861,44 TL olacak. 2 çocuk için 1.440 gün (4 yıl) doğum borçlanması bedeli 2023 yılı için en az 153 bin 722,9 TL olacak."},{"question":"ਖਿਡਾਰੀ ਨੇ ਲਗਾਤਾਰ ਪੰਜ ਖੇਡਾਂ ਜਿੱਤੀਆਂ। | ਨਤੀਜੇ ਵਜੋਂ ਕੀ ਹੋਇਆ? ਚੋਣ 1 : ਉਸਦੇ ਵਿਰੋਧੀ ਨੇ ਉਸ 'ਤੇ ਧੋਖਾਧੜੀ ਦਾ ਦੋਸ਼ ਲਾਇਆ। ਚੋਣ 2 : ਉਸ ਦੇ ਵਿਰੋਧੀ ਨੂੰ ਉਸ ਲਈ ਬੁਰਾ ਲੱਗਿਆ। ","answer":"ਚੋਣ 1 : ਉਸਦੇ ਵਿਰੋਧੀ ਨੇ ਉਸ 'ਤੇ ਧੋਖਾਧੜੀ ਦਾ ਦੋਸ਼ ਲਾਇਆ।"},{"question":"පහත ප්‍රස්තාව පිරුළේ අර්ථය කුමක්ද?\\"අපායට ගියත් කලින් යා යුතුයි\\"","answer":"මෙම ප්‍රස්තාව පිරුළේ අර්ථය වන්නේ \\"කුමන කටයුත්තකදී වුවද ප්‍රමාද නොවී අප්‍රමාද විය යුතු බව\\" යන්නය."},{"question":"Generate a headline for the following text: Sumbata na iya zama abu mai kyau na bayyana soyayya, amma ko kun san a duk lokacin da kuka sumbaci abokin tarayyar ku, me kuke bayarwa? Wani lokaci mu mutane muna tunanin ƙara dankon ƙauna ne da soyayya, amma kuma akwai abin da watakila ba mu fahimta ba... ta hanyar sumbata, muna yaɗa ƙwayoyin cuta da dama. Ko da yake ba lallai ya zama haka ba, tsarin yadda aka halicci baki yana da rikitarwa kuma yana iya adana nau'ikan ƙwayoyin cuta har 700 waɗanda za su iya rayuwa. Siffar tsarin bakin yana bai wa yawu damar samar da matsakaicin zafin jiki da kuma wadataccen abinci mai gina jiki, don haka wannan yanayin yana taimaka wa ƙwayoyin cuta su hayayyafa da girma. Tun da bakin ya cika da ƙwayoyin cuta, a bayyane yake cewa za mu iya watsa waɗannan ƙwayoyin idan muka yi sumba. Gaskiyar ita ce, a cewar wani binciken da ɗalibai a Netherlands suka yi, yana yiwuwa idan ka sumbaci wani na tsawon daƙiƙa 10 a rana, za ka iya yada ƙwayoyin cuta har miliyan 80. Kwayar cutar da ke cikin baki sunanta 'microbiota' wacce dama can take baki tun daga haihuwa. Tana canzawa dangane da abin da muke ci, ko magani ne ko a'a, muna da tsabta ko kuma muna shan sigari. Shekarunmu da yanayin kwayoyin halitta suna shafar tsarin waɗannan 'microbiota'. Duk da wannan, ƙwayoyin halittar da ke zaune a bakin ɗan adam suna da fa'idoji da yawa. Mafi yawa dai shi ne yana taimakawa wajen hana ƙwayoyin cuta samuwa, yana tallafawa garkuwar jiki da tsarin narkewar abinci tare da daidaita hawan jini. Waɗannan ƙwayoyin cuta suna rayuwa tare kuma a sassa daban -daban na baki, kuma suna hada abin da ake kira 'biofilms'. Suna mannewa da bangon wurare daban-daban a cikin baki musamman a kan wani bangare da ake ce wa ''substrate'' saboda haka suna samun kariya daga sindarai  kamar na 'antibodies' da ke aiki da garkuwar jiki. Ire -iren wadannan kwayoyin cuta suna farawa ne daga hakora, dasashi ko harshe. A wasu wuraren kamar kumatu, babu lokacin da za a samar da waɗannan 'biofilms' saboda sabunta ƙwayoyin 'mucosa' yana faruwa cikin sauri. Kusan kowane bangare na baki yana dauke da isashshen oxygen da yanayi na sinadaran abinci, yanayin da ke sa tarin kwayoyin cuta ya sauya a kai a kai. Irin wannan kwayoyin cuta ba iri ɗaya ba ko da a haƙori ɗaya ne, amma ɗayan yana gaba da bayan hakori ɗaya. Wannan bambancin yana da girma sosai don haka 'microbiota' na harshenku na iya zama kamar baƙo ga hakoran ku. Kusancin da ake buƙata yayin sumbata ya na taimakawa ko ba da damar ƙwayoyin cuta su tashi daga baki ɗaya zuwa wani. Za mu iya kawar da yawancinsu ba tare da mun sani ba. Damar kwayoyin cuta su rayu a baki ya danganta ne da yadda za su dace da inda suke. Bugu da kari, tsarin garkuwar jiki, ba ya taimakawa wajen sauƙaƙe shi, tun da miyau na haduwa da kwayoyin 'antibody' da ake kira IgA, wanda majina ke samarwa, wanda ke ƙoƙarin hana hulɗa da ƙwayoyin cuta. A takaice, mutanen da ke da gibi a tsarin haƙoransu a cikin baki, ba su da yawan wadannan 'antibodies' din ba. Don haka, lokacin da kuka sumbaci mutum, kuna karɓar ƙwayoyin cuta da yawa daga mutumin da kuke sumbata, yawancin waɗannan ƙwayoyin suna shiga cikin hanji kai tsaye. Amma wasu suna mannewa a baki. Tasirin wannan shi ne yana da wuya ƙwayoyin cuta su zauna a baki bayan sumba, amma dole ne ku yi hankali saboda akwai ƙwayoyin cuta waɗanda ba su isa su ɓoye ta cikin 'microbiota' ba. 'Biofilm' da ƙwayoyin cuta ke samarwa a hakora ana ce masa murufin haƙori a cikin harshe na yau da kullun. Wani lokaci yana da wuyar kawar da shi. Kwayoyin cuta suna amfani da sukari a cikin abinci kuma suna samar da sinadarai masu yawa. Wannan yanayin yana sa sindarain da ke lullube a kan hakori mai suna enamel ɗin haƙora ya lalace kuma ya haifar da lalacewar haƙora. Don haka shan sukari yana da alaƙa kai tsaye da lalacewar haƙora ko ramukan cikin hakori. Wannan ba sabon abu ba ne. Bisa bayanan da aka tattara, an samu ƙaruwa sosai a lalacewar haƙora, bayan an cire haraji kan sukari a Ingila, kuma wannan ya zama ruwan dare. Daya daga cikin kwayoyin da aka gano yana haifar da mafi yawan matsaloli sunanata 'Streptococcus mutans' da wani nau'i na Lactobacillus. Idan ba a cire kurajen ko kumburin daga hakoran ba, zai haifar da kumburi a dasashi kuma ya haddasa wata cuta da ake kira 'periodontitis'. A gefe guda kuma, kada mu manta cewa ƙwayoyin cuta da yawa na wannan nau'in 'microbiota' a cikin baki suna da alaƙa da halitosis (mummunan warin baki da tarin ƙwayoyin cuta ke haifarwa). Waɗannan ƙwayoyin cuta galibi suna rayuwa cikin harshe kuma suna samar da abubuwan da ke motsa ƙona sinadarin protein. Don haka, tsafta tana da mahimmanci wajen rage kamuwa da cututtuka na baki. Ta hanyar goge bayan kowane abinci, yana taimakawa cire fim ɗin biofilm daga ƙyallen haƙora da ƙwayoyin cuta. Bugu da ƙari, yayin da kuke goge hakora, kuna jawo ƙwayoyin cuta waɗanda ke buƙatar iskar oxygen don su girma, wanda abu ne mai kyau. Ya kamata ku yi buroshi da wanke harshenku. Ku ji daɗin rayuwa ... kuma ku rarraba 'microbiota' Gabaɗaya, ma'auratan da ke cikin ingantacciyar soyayya suna samun kansu da ƙwayoyin cuta iri ɗaya ko masu kama da na juna. Suna kara sumbatar juna, suna kara ba junansu kwayoyin cuta da kuma kwayoyin cutar suna kara kamanceceniya. Wannan na iya zama abin jan hankali ga masoya, amma yana da nasa illolin. Lokaci na tafiya, mutanen da ke fama da cututtukan baki na iya yada wa matansu ko mazansu cututtukan. A halin yanzu, ana ci gaba da bincike don samar da wani abu da za a sanya rika sanya wa a baki don taimakawa hana lalacewar haƙora. Wani binciken da aka yi a baya a Valencia, ya nuna cewa yana da sakamako mai kyau. Sumba tana taimakawa wajen samar da soyayya mai ƙarfi, tana motsa rai kuma ta na ƙara ƙarfin soyayya tsakanin masoyayya. La'akari da duk abin da muka gani a cikin wannan maƙala, ana ba ku shawarar ku yi taka-tsan-tsan wajen zaɓar  wanda za ku iya kulla alaƙa da shi da musanya 'microbes'.","answer":"Sure, here's a headline for the given text - Waɗanne ƙwayoyin cuta muke watsawa yayin da muke sumbata?"},{"question":"Quel est le premier élément du tableau périodique ?","answer":"Le premier élément du tableau périodique est l’hydrogène. Il est représenté par le symbole « H » et porte le numéro atomique 1. L'hydrogène est l'élément le plus simple et le plus abondant de l'univers."},{"question":"24, 21, 18, ….. అంకశ్రేణిలో ఋణపదము అయ్యే మొదటి పదము ఏది ?","answer":"ఇచ్చిన అంకశ్రేడిని కొనసాగించగా24, 21, 18, 15, 12, 9, 6, 3, 0, – 3, ……మొదటి ఋణ పదం a10 = -3"},{"question":"請回答這個問題：美國文化中的「第五大道」是指什麼？","answer":"答案：第五大道是紐約市曼哈頓上的一條著名街道，被認為是世界上最昂貴和最繁華的購物區之一。這裡有許多高級時尚品牌、奢侈品店和世界知名的建築物，是遊客和購物者的熱門目的地。"},{"question":"ప్రశ్న : మగధ బలమైన రాజ్యంగా ఆవిర్భవించడానికి తోడ్పడిన సహజ వనరుల పాత్రను ప్రశంసించుము.","answer":"మగధ రాజ్యం గంగానదికి ఇరువైపులా విస్తరించి ఉందని మీరు గమనించి ఉంటారు. నదులు, భూములను సారవంతం చేస్తాయి. గృహపతులు తమ భూములను సులభంగా సాగు చేసుకొనేవారు. నదుల మీద సరకు రవాణా చేసేవారు. సైనికులను తరిలించేవారు. మగధలోని కొంత ప్రాంతంలో అడవులున్నాయి. ఈ అడవుల నుంచి ఏనుగులను పట్టుకొని యుద్ధాలలో పోరాడటానికి వాటికి శిక్షణ ఇచ్చేవారు. అడవుల నుంచి లభించే కలపతో కోటలు, రాజభవనాలు, రథాలను నిర్మించటానికి ఉపయోగించేవారు. మగధ రాజ్యంలోని దక్షిణ ప్రాంతంలో ఇనుప ఖనిజ నిక్షేపాలు ఉండేవి. వాటిని ఉపయోగించి ఆయుధాలు తయారు చేసేవారు. వీటన్నింటి కారణంగా మగధ రాజ్యం బలమైన రాజ్యంగా ఎదిగింది. మొదటి రాజైన బింబిసారుడు, అతని కుమారుడు అజాత శత్రువు మగధను బలమైన రాజ్యంగా తీర్చిదిద్దారు. ఈ రాజు కోట నుండి విధంగా సహజ వనరులు మగధను బలమైన రాజ్యంగా ఆవిర్భవించటానికి బయలుదేరుట తోడ్పడినాయి."},{"question":"Phép cộng các số nguyên có tính chất nào sau đây?A. Giao hoán     B. Kết hợpC. Cộng với số 0     D. Tất cả các đáp án trên","answer":"Chọn đáp án D.Tính chất của phép cộng các số nguyên: giao hoán, kết hợp, cộng với số 0, cộng với số đối. Vậy đáp án A, B, C đúng nên D là đáp án chính xác nhất."},{"question":"Tohizo izao ohabolana izao :   \\"Raha tonga tokoa ny tokoa  _\\".","answer":" \\"Raha tonga tokoa ny tokoa dia lavitra ny lainga\\"."},{"question":"Trả lời câu hỏi sau: a) Hãy viết các ước của 7 và các ước của 8. Tìm ƯCLN(7, 8).b) Hai số 7 và 8 có nguyên tố cùng nhau hay không? Vì sao?c) Tìm BCNN(7, 8). So sánh bội chung nhỏ nhất với tích hai số 7 và 8.","answer":"a) + Để tìm các ước của 7 ta lấy 7 lần lượt chia cho các số tự nhiên từ 1 đến 7, các phép chia hết là: 7 : 1 = 7; 7 : 7 = 1Do đó: các ước của 7 là: 1; 7 + Để tìm các ước của 8 ta lấy 8 lần lượt chia cho các số tự nhiên từ 1 đến 8, các phép chia hết là: 8 : 1 = 8; 8 : 2 = 4; 8 : 4 = 2; 8 : 8 = 1.Các ước của 8 là: 1; 2; 4; 8.+ Từ đó suy ra ƯC(7, 8) = 1 nên ƯCLN(7, 8) = 1.b) Hai số 7 và 8 không có nguyên tố chung nào ngoài 1. Điều này có nghĩa là chúng không có nguyên tố cùng nhau. c) Ta có: 7 = 7^1; 8 = 2^3Các thừa số nguyên tố chung và riêng là 7 và 2 với số mũ cao nhất lần lượt là 1 và 3.Do đó BCNN(7, 8) = 7^1 . 2^3 = 56 Mà 7 . 8 = 56Hay ta nói bội chung nhỏ nhất của hai số nguyên tố cùng nhau 7 và 8 chính bằng tích của hai số 7 và 8. "},{"question":"Who is the current Prime Minister of England?","answer":"The current Prime Minister of England is Rishi Sunak, who has been serving as the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom and the Leader of the Conservative Party since 25 October 2022. Before becoming Prime Minister, Sunak held the position of Chancellor of the Exchequer from 13 February 2020 to 5 July 2022. Sunak is the first British Asian to hold the office of Prime Minister. He has outlined his key priorities for the year 2023 in a speech on 4 January 2023, as noted on the official website of the UK government."},{"question":"ఆవరణ సంబంధ విధులను కొనసాగించడం కోసం తీసుకోవలసిన చర్యలను గురించి రాయండి.","answer":"వాతావరణానికి ఎలాంటి నష్టం కలిగించకుండా, వ్యర్ధ పదార్థ వనరులను తగ్గించే, వనరుల సంరక్షణను దృష్టిలో పెట్టుకునే తయారీ పద్ధతుల ద్వారా తయారయ్యే ఉత్పత్తులను ఎంచుకోవాలి.కృత్రిమ ఎరువుల, కీటకనాశకాల వినియోగం లేని పద్ధతులలో తయారయిన ఉత్పత్తులను ఎన్నుకోవాలి.వినియోగాన్ని, వ్యర్ధపదార్థాల ఉత్పత్తిని తగించాలి.పునర్వినియోగానికి సంబంధించిన ఇందన వనరులు ఉపయోగాన్ని బలపరచాలి.సైకిల్ లేదా నడక ప్రజారవాణా వ్యవస్థను వాడటం ద్వారా సహజ వనరులను రక్షించడం, కాలుష్యాన్ని తగ్గించడం, ఆరోగ్య సంబంధ లాభాలను ఆస్వాదించుట.సామూహిక ఉద్యానవనాల ఏర్పాటు, మొక్కనాటే కార్యక్రమములో పాల్గొనుట.కీటక నాశకాల ఉపయోగం తగ్గించి, సహజకీటక నాశకాలను వాడటం.ఉద్యాన వనాలలో స్థానిక మొక్కలను పెంచడం, వన్య ప్రాణులకు ఆవాసాన్ని ఏర్పరచడం."},{"question":"Escreva 5 palavras com acentos.","answer":"Com certeza! 5 palavras com acentos são:CaminhãoLâmpadaSímboloHábilRomântico"},{"question":"Lidokain lokal anestezik midir?","answer":"İki önemli lokal anestezik yaygın olarak kullanılır: prokain (novokain) ve lidokain (ksilokain)."},{"question":"' මුහුණ ' කියලා ලියන හරි විදිය මේක නේද . 'මුහුන' මේක වැරැද්ද දන්න කෙනෙක් කියනවද?","answer":"වර්තමානයේ යෙදෙන 'මුහුණු' යන්න 10 සියවසේ සෙල්ලිපිවල 'මුහුණ්' වශයෙන් යෙදී ඇති බව දැක්වේ. නමුත්, මාතෘ භාෂාගත වචනයකින් බිඳී ආ බවට සාධක හමු නො වීය. මෘතෘ භාෂාවල යෙදෙන්නේ මුඛය වශයෙනි.මිශ්‍ර කරන දෙය යන අරුත ඇති 'මුහුන්' යනුවෙන් පදයක් ඇති නිසා මුහුන යි යෙදිය නොහැකිය."},{"question":"Inona no niseho teto Madagasikara ny 18 jona 2002?","answer":"Ny 18 jona 2002 dia nitsangana ny governemanta Sylla faharoa, nahitana ministra natolotr’i Ratsiraka miisa 5, araka ny fifanarahana Dakar II. Nanafaingana ny fankatoavana iraisampirenena ny fitondrana Ravalomanana izany ary maro tokoa ireo ambasadaoro vaovao (Etazonia, Japon, Ostralia, Shina, sns.) nanatitra ny taratasy fanendrena azy tamin’ny filoha malagasy nanodidina ny andron’ny 26 jona, fetim-pirenena malagasy. Ny masoivoho anglisy sy alemana ary ny filoha maorisianina moa dia nanatrika ny matso natao teo Mahamasina ny tamin’ny 26 jona. Hita amin’izany rehetra izany fa henjakenjana ny fifandraisan’iI Marc Ravalomanana tamin’ny Frantsay, izay fantatra fa nanohana an-dRatsiraka tamin’ny fifidianana natao tamin’ny taona 2001. Nihanalefaka anefa izany fifandraisan’ny Frantsay tamin’ny fitondrana malagasy izany rehefa nandresy tamin’ny fifidianana solombavambahoaka frantsay ny UMP, ary nony indray tonga teo amin’ny toeran’ny Praiministra i Jean-Pierre Raffarin. Misy koa no milaza fa ny asaambadika nataon’ny Federasiona Protestanta Malagasy any Frantsa no nahatonga izany fihatsaran’ny fifandraisana izany. "},{"question":"Inona no ilazana ny toerana fatorian'ny omby?","answer":"Fahitra  na vala no ilazana ny toerana ametrahana sy fatorian'ny omby."},{"question":"ഈ ഖണ്ഡിക ഏത് പ്രധാന സംഭവത്തെക്കുറിച്ചാണ്: ബ്രിട്ടീഷുകാർ തൂക്കിലേറ്റിയ വിപ്ലവകാരിയായ ഇന്ത്യൻ സ്വാതന്ത്ര്യ സമര സേനാനിയായിരുന്നു സൂര്യ സെൻ(1894–1934). 1930 ലെ ചിറ്റഗോങ് ആയുധപ്പുര ആക്രമണക്കേസിലെ നായകനായിരുന്നു.","answer":"ചിറ്റഗോങ് ആയുധപ്പുര നായകനായിരുന്ന സൂര്യ സെന്നിനെ കുറിച്ചുള്ളതാണ്. "},{"question":"Ọrọ apara ati ẹtan ni bawọn kan ṣe n sọ pe Naijiria ko le pin si wẹwẹ-Atiku Abubakar","answer":"Igbakeji aarẹ orileede wa tẹlẹ ri, Alaaji Atiku Abubakar, ti sọ pe ọrọ apara nla ati ẹtan ni bawọn kan ṣe n sọ pe Naijiria ko le pin si wẹwẹ, tabi pe dandan ni ki orileede naa wa lodidi, sibẹ to jẹ awọn nnkan to le fọ Naijiria yanga lo n ṣẹlẹ lojoojumọ, o ni ko si majiiki kan ninu iṣọkan orileede wa.Atiku sọrọ yii l’Ọjọbọ, Tọsidee yii, l’Abuja, olu-ilu ilẹ wa, ni gbọngan Shehu Musa Yar’Adua Center, nibi ti wọn ti n ko iwe tuntun kan jade bii ọmọ tuntun. Akọle iwe naa ni ‘Remaking Nigeria: Sixty Years, Sixty Voices,’ eyi ti Onkọwe Chido Onumah kọ nipa Naijiria.Iwe naa ṣakojọpọ awọn ọkan-o-jọkan aboyun ọrọ ati ero aritọkasi tawọn eeyan nla nla ti sọ nipa Naijiria, latigba ti orileede naa ti gba ominira lọdun 1960, ati ojuutu si awọn iṣoro to n koju ilẹ wa.Gẹgẹ bii alaga ayẹyẹ naa, Atiku ni o yẹ kawọn ọmọ Naijiria kẹkọọ arikọgbọn lara Aarẹ Mohammadu Buhari, to jẹ ero ati igbesẹ to n fa ipinya niṣakoso rẹ n gbe lọpọ igba.“O maa n pa mi lẹrin-in nigba tawọn eeyan ba n sọ pe iṣọkan Naijiria ko le fọ, dandan ni ki Naijiria wa lodidi, o si maa wa bẹẹ ni, ta lo sọ fun wọn bẹẹ? Wọn n sọrọ iṣọkan, ṣugbọn wọn n huwa ipinya, iṣọkan waa di ahẹrẹpẹ.Ko si nnkan kan ninu ajọṣepọ Naijiria to wa titi lae. Ẹnikan o le sọ pe ọran-anyan ni igbeyawo oun nigba ti ọrọ oun ati iyawo tabi ọkọ ẹ ko ba wọ mọ, to jẹ ojoojumọ ni wọn o gbọ ara wọn ye, igba wo nigbeyawo naa o ni i tuka.”Lori iṣoro eto aabo to mẹhẹ, Atiku ni pẹlu bii nnkan ṣe n lọ yii, ko sigba tawọn janduku agbebọn ko ni i di ẹgbẹ tijọba fọwọ si, tawọn gan-an maa lorukọ lọdọ ijọba.“Ta lo lero pe orileede wa le waa di ojuko ati ibuba fawọn ajinigbe atawọn janduku loriṣiiriṣii, debii pe wọn maa sọ iwakiwa wọn di okoowo nla mọ wa lọwọ, bo ṣe ri yii?Ijọba ti faaye gba awọn eeyan-keeyan yii lati maa jaye ori wọn falala debii pe ko le ya ẹnikẹni lẹnu mọ ti wọn ba lawọn fẹẹ forukọ silẹ lọjọ ijọba (Corporate Affairs Commission) tabi lọdọ ajọ olokoowo ilẹ wa (Nigerian Stock Exchange).Lọdun marun-un sẹyin, ko siṣoro lọna Abuja si Kaduna, ko si ogun nilẹ Ibo, ko si sẹni to ronu kan Amọtẹkun ki aabo le wa nilẹ Yoruba.”Alaaji Abubakar ni awọn eeyan ilẹ Hausa naa jẹbi lori ọrọ yii, tori wọn o ṣakiyesi bawọn janduku ṣe rọ lọ sinu papa Sahara to wa lagbegbe wọn, latari adagun omi Chad to gbẹ."},{"question":"Эки колун куушуруу","answer":"1. Кечирим суроо, сурануу, алдына түшүү, өтүнүү, өтүнүч кылуу.Эки колун куушуруп өзү келиптир, кечирели.2. Баш ийүү, багынуу.Өз эрктери менен бизге эки колун куушурушту."},{"question":"Manana an'ity teny nakorontana ity ianao:\\"kkaapao\\"Vinavinao ilay teny rehefa alamina.","answer":"Rehefa alamina ilay teny dia manome hoe \\"kapoaka\\"."},{"question":"काझीरंगा राष्ट्रीय पार्क कोठे आहे? ","answer":"उत्तर : काझीरंगा हे राष्ट्रीय पार्क आसाम येथे आहे "},{"question":"බෙංගාල බොක්ක කලාපයේ මීළඟට ඇතිවන සුළි කුණාටුව සඳහා  ලැබීමට නියමිත නම කුමක්ද ?","answer":"අන්තිමටම මම බලන විට මො චා  සයික්ලෝන් එක තමයි අන්තිම සයික්ලෝන් එක  බෙංගාල බොක්කේ හට ගැනුණු. එය මුලින්ම ආරම්භ වුනේ 2023 මැ යි 9."},{"question":"Inona no anaran'ny hetsika fanoherana ny fanjanahantany frantsay tao Madagasikara?","answer":"Ny hetsika fanoherana ny fanjanahantany frantsay dia fantatra amin'ny anarana hoe \\"Fikomiana tamin'ny 1947\\"."},{"question":"Is Asia a continent","answer":"yes"}]`),S={name:"App",components:{PoemCard:B},data(){return{searchQuery:"",visibleCount:6,poemsData:M,isLoading:!1}},computed:{filteredPoems(){return this.searchQuery.trim()?this.poemsData.filter(e=>{const a=this.searchQuery.toLowerCase();return e.question.toLowerCase().includes(a)||e.answer.toLowerCase().includes(a)}).slice(0,this.visibleCount):this.poemsData.slice(0,this.visibleCount)},hasMorePoems(){return this.visibleCount<this.poemsData.length}},methods:{async loadMore(){this.isLoading=!0,await new Promise(e=>setTimeout(e,1e3)),this.visibleCount+=6,this.isLoading=!1}}},C={class:"search-container"},I={class:"card-container"},P=["disabled"],K={key:0},H={key:1};function D(e,a,s,m,t,u){const k=y("PoemCard");return i(),o("section",null,[a[3]||(a[3]=n("div",{class:"top-banner"},[n("div",{class:"top-banner-title"},[n("div",{class:"top-banner-title-text"},"🤔 AI effective tips collection 🧠")])],-1)),n("div",C,[a[2]||(a[2]=n("span",{class:"search-icon"},null,-1)),b(n("input",{type:"text",class:"search-input","onUpdate:modelValue":a[0]||(a[0]=r=>t.searchQuery=r),placeholder:"Search..."},null,512),[[c,t.searchQuery]])]),n("div",I,[(i(!0),o(w,null,p(u.filteredPoems,(r,d)=>(i(),f(k,{key:d,poem:r},null,8,["poem"]))),128))]),u.hasMorePoems?(i(),o("button",{key:0,class:"load-more-button",disabled:t.isLoading,onClick:a[1]||(a[1]=(...r)=>u.loadMore&&u.loadMore(...r))},[t.isLoading?(i(),o("span",H,"Loading...")):(i(),o("span",K,"See more"))],8,P)):j("",!0)])}const L=g(S,[["render",D],["__scopeId","data-v-e8ae68a9"]]),E=JSON.parse('{"title":"","description":"","frontmatter":{"page":true},"headers":[],"relativePath":"chatai/3.md","filePath":"chatai/3.md"}'),O={name:"chatai/3.md"},V=Object.assign(O,{setup(e){return(a,s)=>(i(),o("div",null,[v(L)]))}});export{E as __pageData,V as default};
